Liberty

John Stuart Mill

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between square brackets in normal-sized type.
First launched: March 2005 Last amended: April 2008
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Chapter 1: Introduction     1
Chapter 2: Liberty of thought and discussion     10
Chapter 3: Individuality—one of the elements of well-being     36
Chapter 4: The limits to the authority of society over the individual     49
Chapter 5: Applications     61
     ·Free trade·........... 62
     ·Selling poisons·.......... 62
     ·Selling alcohol·........... 64
     ·Prostitution and gambling·.......... 65
     ·Dissuasion·............ 66
     ·Contracts—slavery·........... 67

     Liberty John Stuart Mill

     ·Contracts—marriage·........ 68
     ·Power of husbands over wives·........... 68
     ·Bringing up children·........ 69
     ·Having children·.......... 71
     ·Size of government·.......... 72

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

Chapter 1: Introduction

The subject of this essay is not the so-called ‘liberty of the will’ that is unfortunately opposed to the misnamed doctrine of philosophical necessity; ·i.e. I shan’t be writing about anything like the issue between free-will and determinism·. My topic is

•civil or •social liberty—the nature and limits of the power that society can legitimately exercise over the individual.

This question is seldom posed, and almost never discussed, in general terms. Yet it lurks behind many of the practical controversies of our day, profoundly influencing them, and is likely soon to make itself recognized as the vital question of the future. This isn’t a new issue; indeed, it has in a certain sense divided mankind almost from the remotest ages; but in the stage of progress into which the more civilized parts of humanity have now entered, it comes up under new conditions and needs a different and more fundamental treatment.

The struggle between liberty and authority is the most conspicuous feature of the parts of history of which we have the oldest records, particularly in the histories of Greece, Rome, and England. But in olden times this contest was between subjects (or some classes of them) and the government. By ‘liberty’ was meant protection against the tyranny of the political rulers. Except in some of the democratic governments of Greece, the rulers were seen as inevitably being antagonists of the people whom they ruled. The rulers consisted of a single governing person or a governing tribe or caste •who derived their authority from inheritance or conquest, or at any rate didn’t have it through the consent of the governed, and •whose supremacy men didn’t risk challenging (and perhaps didn’t want to challenge), whatever precautions might be taken against its being used oppressively. Their power was regarded as necessary, but also as highly dangerous because it was a weapon that they would try to use against their subjects as much as against external enemies. To prevent the weaker members of the community from being preyed on by innumerable vultures, there needed to be a predator stronger than the rest, whose job was to keep the vultures down. But as the •king of the vultures would be just as intent on preying on the flock as would any of the •minor predators, the subjects had to be in a perpetual attitude of defence against his beak and claws. So the aim of patriots was to set •limits to the power that the ruler should be allowed to have over the community; and this •limitation was what they meant by ‘liberty’. They tried to get it in two ways. •First, by getting certain political ‘liberties’ or ‘rights’ to be recognized; if the ruler were to infringe these, that would be regarded as a breach of duty, and specific resistance or general rebellion would be regarded as justifiable. •A second procedure—generally a later one—was to establish constitutional checks according to which some of the governing power’s more important acts required the consent of the community or of a body of some sort supposed to represent the community’s interests. In most European countries the ruling power was compelled, more or less, to submit to •the first of these kinds of limitation. Not so with •the second; and the principal objective of the lovers of liberty everywhere came to be getting this ·constitutional limit on the rulers’ power· or, when they already had it to some extent, achieving it more completely. And so long as mankind were content to fight off one enemy with help from

1

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

another ·enemy·, and to be ruled by a master on condition that they had a fairly effective guarantee against his tyranny, they didn’t try for anything more than this.

But a time came in the progress of human affairs when men stopped thinking it to be a necessity of nature that their governors should be an independent power with interests opposed to their own. It appeared to them much better that the various officers of the state should be their appointees, their delegates, who could be called back from office at the people’s pleasure. Only in that way, it seemed, could people be completely assured that the powers of government would never be misused to their disadvantage. This new demand to have •rulers who were elected and temporary became the prominent aim of the democratic party, wherever any such party existed, and to a large extent it replaced the previous efforts to limit the power of rulers. As the struggle proceeded for making the ruling power come from the periodical choice of the ruled, some people started to think that too much importance had been attached to limiting the power itself. The thought was this:

Limitations on the power of government is something to be used against rulers whose interests are habitually opposed to those of the people. What we now want is for the rulers to be identified with the people, for their interests and decisions to be the interests and decisions of the nation. The nation doesn’t need to be protected against its own will! There is no fear of its tyrannizing over itself. As long as the rulers are responsible to the nation and easily removable by it, it can afford to trust them with power.... The rulers’ power is simply the nation’s own power, concentrated and in a form convenient for use.

This way of thinking, or perhaps rather of feeling, was common among the last generation of European liberalism, and apparently it still predominates in Europe outside Britain. Those who admit any limit to what may be done by a government (setting aside governments that they think oughtn’t to exist) stand out as brilliant exceptions among the political thinkers of continental Europe. A similar attitude might by now have been prevalent in our own country, if the circumstances that for a time encouraged it hadn’t changed.

But in political and philosophical theories, as well as in persons, success reveals faults and weaknesses that failure might have hidden from view. The notion that the people needn’t limit their power over themselves might seem axiomatic at a time when democratic government was only dreamed of, or read about as having existed in the distant past. And that notion wasn’t inevitably disturbed by such temporary aberrations as those of the French Revolution, the worst of which were the work of a few usurpers—·people who grabbed power without being entitled to it·—and which in any case didn’t come from the permanent working of institutions among the people but from a sudden explosion against monarchical and aristocratic despotism. In time, however, a democratic republic came to occupy a large part of the earth’s surface, and made itself felt as one of the most powerful members of the community of nations; and elected and responsible government became subject to the scrutiny and criticisms that any great existing fact is likely to draw on itself. It was now seen that such phrases as ‘self-government’, and ‘the people’s power over themselves’ don’t express the true state of the case. The ‘people’ who exercise the power aren’t always the ones over whom it is exercised, and the ‘self-government’ spoken of is the government not of •each by himself but of •each by all the rest. The will of the people in practice means the will of

the •most numerous or the •most active part of the people;

2

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

that is,

the •majority, or •those who get themselves to be accepted as the majority.

So ‘the people’ may desire to oppress some of their number; and precautions are as much needed against this as against any other abuse of power. Thus, the limitation of government’s power of over individuals loses none of its importance when the holders of power are regularly accountable to the community, i.e. to the strongest party in it. This view of things recommends itself equally to •the intelligence of thinkers and to •the desires of the important groups in European society to whose real or supposed interests democracy is adverse; so it has had no difficulty in establishing itself, and in political theorizing ‘the tyranny of the majority’ is now generally included among the evils that society should guard against.

Like other tyrannies, the tyranny of the majority was at first feared primarily as something that would operate through the acts of the public authorities, and this is how the man in the street still sees it. But thoughtful people saw that •society itself can be the tyrant—society collectively tyrannizing over individuals within it—and that •this kind of tyranny isn’t restricted to what society can do through the acts of its political government. Society can and does enforce its own commands; and if it issues wrong commands instead of right, or any commands on matters that it oughtn’t to meddle with at all, it practises a social tyranny that is more formidable than many kinds of political oppression. Although it isn’t usually upheld by such extreme penalties, it leaves fewer means of escape, penetrating much more deeply into the details of life and enslaving the soul itself. So protection against the tyranny of government isn’t enough; there needs to be protection also against the tyranny of prevailing opinion and feeling; against the tendency of society to turn its own ideas and practices into rules of conduct, and impose them—by means other than legal penalties—on those who dissent from them; to hamper the development and if possible to prevent the formation of any individuality that isn’t in harmony with its ways.... There is a limit to how far collective opinion can legitimately interfere with individual independence; and finding and defending that limit is as indispensable to a good condition of human affairs as is protection against political despotism.

But though this proposition isn’t likely to be disputed in general terms, the practical question of where to place the limit—how to make the right adjustment between individual independence and social control—is a subject on which nearly all the work remains to be done. Everything that makes life worth living for anyone depends on restraints being put on the actions of other people. So some rules of conduct must be imposed—in the first place by law, and secondarily by ·public· opinion on many things that aren’t fit subjects for law to work on. What should these rules be? That is the principal question in human affairs; but with a few obvious exceptions it is one of the questions that least progress has been made in resolving. It hasn’t been answered in the same way in any two historical periods, and hardly ever in two countries ·in the same period·; and the answer of one period or country is a source of amazement to another. Yet the people in any given country at any given time don’t see any problem here; it’s as though they believed that mankind had always been agreed on what the rules should be. The rules that hold in their society appear to them to be self-evident and self-justifying. This almost universal illusion is one example of the magical influence of custom.... The effect of custom in preventing any doubts concerning the rules of conduct that mankind impose on one another is made all the more complete by the fact that

3

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

this isn’t something that is generally considered to call for reasons—whether to be given by one person to others or by a person to himself. People are accustomed to believe that on topics like this their feelings are better than reasons, and make it unnecessary to have reasons. (And some who like to think of themselves as philosophers have encouraged them in this.) The practical principle that leads them to their opinions on how human beings should behave is the feeling in each person’s mind that everybody should be required to act as he, and those who feel as he does, would like them to act. Of course no-one admits to himself that his standard of judgment is what he likes; but when an opinion on how people should behave isn’t supported by reasons, it can count only as one person’s preference; and if ‘reasons’ are given, and turn out to be a mere appeal to a similar preference felt by other people, it is still only many people’s liking instead of one person’s. To an ordinary man, however, his own preference (with other people sharing it) is not only a perfectly satisfactory reason but is the only reason he has for most of his notions of morality, taste, or propriety—except for notions that are explicitly written in his religious creed, and even that is something he interprets mainly in the light of his personal preferences.

So men’s opinions about what is praiseworthy or blamable are affected by all the various causes that influence •their wishes concerning the conduct of others, and these causes are as numerous as those that influence •their wishes on any other subject. It may be any of these:

their reason,

their prejudices or superstitions,

their social feelings,

their antisocial feelings—envy or jealousy, arrogance or contempt,

their desires or fears for themselves—their legitimate or illegitimate self-interest.

The last of these is the commonest.

In any country that has a dominant class, a large portion of the morality of the country emanates from that class—from its interests and its feelings of class superiority. The morality between Spartans and slave-warriors, between planters and negroes, between monarchs and subjects, between nobles and peasants, between men and women, has mostly been created by these class interests and feelings: and the sentiments thus generated react back on the moral feelings of the members of the dominant class in their relations among themselves. [In Mill’s time, ‘sentiment’ could mean ‘feeling’ or ‘opinion’.] On the other hand, where a class has lost its dominant position, or where its dominance is unpopular, the prevailing moral sentiments frequently show the marks of an impatient dislike of superiority.

Rules of conduct—both •positive and •negative—that have been enforced by law or opinion have also been influenced by mankind’s servile attitude towards the supposed •likes or •dislikes of their worldly masters or of their gods. This servility is essentially selfish, but it isn’t hypocrisy: it gives rise to perfectly genuine sentiments of abhorrence, such as have made men burn magicians and heretics.

Along with so many baser influences, the general and obvious interests of society have of course had a share—a large share—in the direction of the moral sentiments. But they have played this role not so much

4

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

by serving directly as reasons ·for this or that moral view·

as by

causing various likes and dislikes ·which lead to this or that moral view·.

And other likes and dislikes—ones having little or nothing to do with the interests of society—have made themselves felt in the establishment of moralities with quite as much force as the former ones.

The likes and dislikes of society, or of some powerful part of it, are thus the main thing that has in practice determined the rules that societies have laid down for general observance under the penalties of law or opinion. And those who have been ahead of society in thought and feeling have generally not attacked this state of things in •principle, however much they may have clashed with some of its •details. They have been busier inquiring into what things society ought to like or dislike than in questioning whether society’s likes or dislikes should be a law for individuals. They have tried to alter the feelings of mankind on the particular points on which they were themselves heretical—·i.e. out of step with society·—rather than making common cause in defence of freedom with heretics generally.

The only case in which the higher ground has been •taken on principle and •maintained with consistency by more than a few individuals is that of religious belief. And this is instructive in many ways, partly because it provides a most striking instance of the fallibility of what is called the ‘moral sense’. ·It really is the moral sense that is involved·, for the religious hatred felt by a sincere bigot is one of the most unambiguous cases of moral feeling. Those who first broke the yoke of what called itself the ‘universal church’ were in general no more willing to permit difference of religious opinion than was that church itself. [This refers to the first protestants and to the Roman Catholic Church.] But when the heat of the conflict was over, without giving a complete victory to any party, and each church or sect saw that the most it could hope for was to keep possession of the ground it already occupied, minorities were compelled to plead to those whom they could not convert for permission to differ; they had to do this because they saw that they had no chance of becoming majorities. So it is on this battle-field, and hardly anywhere else, that the rights of the individual against society have been asserted on broad grounds of principle, with the claim of society to exercise authority over dissentients being openly challenged. The great writers to whom the world owes what religious liberty it possesses have mostly asserted freedom of conscience as a right that can’t be taken away, and totally denied that a human being is accountable to others for his religious belief. Yet so natural to mankind is intolerance in whatever they really care about that religious freedom has hardly anywhere existed in practice, except where religious indifference—which dislikes having its peace disturbed by theological quarrels—has added its weight to the scale ·on the side of tolerance·. In the minds of almost all religious persons, even in the most tolerant countries, the duty of toleration is admitted with unspoken reservations:

•One person will put up with dissent in matters of church government, but not of dogma.

•Another can tolerate anyone except a Roman catholic or a unitarian.

•A third tolerates everyone who believes in revealed religion ·but not those whose religious beliefs are based on arguments and evidence rather than on revelation·.

•A few extend their charity a little further, but won’t tolerate those who don’t believe in a God and in a

5

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

future state.

Wherever the sentiment of the majority is still genuine and intense, it is found not to have weakened much its claim to be obeyed.

Because of the peculiar circumstances of English political history, though the yoke of •opinion here may be heavier than it is in most other countries of Europe, our yoke of •law is lighter. Here there is considerable resentment of direct interference with private conduct by the legislative or the executive power; though this comes not so much from any •proper respect for the independence of the individual as from the lingering habit of •seeing the government as representing an opposite interest to that of the public. The majority haven’t yet learned to feel the power of the government as being their power, or its opinions as being their opinions. When they do so, individual liberty will probably be as vulnerable to invasion from the government as it already is from public opinion. But up to now there has been a considerable amount of feeling ready to be brought into action against any attempt by the law to control individuals in respects in which they haven’t been controlled by it in the past. This happens with very little careful thought about whether or not the matter is within the legitimate sphere of legal control; so that the feeling against government interference, highly beneficial as it is on the whole, may be quite as often misplaced as well grounded in the particular instances of its application.

There is, in fact, no recognized principle that is generally used to decide whether a given item of government interference is proper. People decide ·in individual cases· according to their personal preferences. Some, whenever they see any good to be done or evil to be remedied, are willing for the government to do something about it, while others would rather put up with almost any amount of social evil than add one to the areas of human life that are subject to governmental control. And men align themselves on one side or the other in any particular case according to

•this general direction (·for or against governmental control·) of their sentiments, or to

•how much they feel their own interests to be involved in the matter in question, or to

•whether they think that the government would settle the matter in the way they prefer;

but very rarely on the basis of

•any firm, considered opinion concerning what things are fit to be done by a government.

And it seems to me that because of this absence of rule or principle, one side is wrong as often as the other; the interference of government is with about equal frequency improperly supported and improperly condemned.

The object of this Essay is to assert one very simple principle and to argue that it should absolutely govern how society deals with its individual members in matters involving compulsion and control, whether through physical force in the form of legal penalties or through the moral coercion of public opinion. The principle is this:

The only end for which people are entitled, individually or collectively, to interfere with the liberty of action of any of their number is self-protection. The only purpose for which power can be rightfully exercised over any member of a civilized community, against his will, is to prevent harm to others.

The person’s own good, whether physical or moral, isn’t a sufficient ground ·for interference with his conduct·. He cannot rightfully be compelled to do (not do) something because doing it (not doing it) •would be better for him, •would make him happier, •would be wise (in the opinions of others), or •would be right. These are good reasons for

6

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

protesting to him, reasoning with him, persuading him, or begging him, but not for compelling him or giving him a hard time if he acts otherwise. To justify that—·i.e. to justify compulsion or punishment·—the conduct from which it is desired to deter him must be likely to bring harm to someone else. The only part of anyone’s conduct for which he is answerable to society is the part that concerns others. In the part that concerns himself alone he is entitled to absolute independence. Over himself, over his own body and mind, the individual is sovereign.

I hardly need say that this doctrine is meant to apply only to human beings when they have reached the age of maturity. We aren’t speaking of children, or of young persons below the age that the law fixes as that of manhood or womanhood. Those who still need to be taken care of by others must be protected against their own actions as well as against external injury. For the same reason, we may leave out of consideration those backward states of society in which the race itself may be considered as not yet adult. The early difficulties in the way of spontaneous progress are so great that there is seldom any choice of means for overcoming them; and a ruler full of the spirit of improvement may legitimately use any means that will attain an end that perhaps can’t be reached otherwise. Despotism is a legitimate form of government in dealing with barbarians, provided that •it aims at improving things and •it uses means that actually do bring improvement. Liberty, as a principle, doesn’t apply to any state of affairs before mankind have become capable of being improved by free and equal discussion. Until then, there is nothing for them but implicit obedience to an Akbar or a Charlemagne, if they are so fortunate as to find one—·i.e. to find a despot so wise·. But in all the nations with which we need to concern ourselves here, the people long ago became able to be guided to self-improvement by conviction or persuasion; and once that stage has been reached, compulsion—whether direct physical compulsion or compulsion through penalties for non-compliance—is no longer admissible as a means to their own good, and is justifiable only for the security of others.

It might seem easier for me to defend my position if I took this stance:

‘It is just objectively abstractly right that people should be free; never mind what the consequences of their freedom are.’

But I don’t argue in that way, because I hold that the ultimate appeal on all ethical questions is to utility—i.e. to ‘what the consequences are’. However, it must be utility in the broadest sense, based on the permanent interests of man as a progressive being. Those interests, I contend, make it all right to subject individual spontaneity to external control only in respect to those actions of each individual that concern the interests of other people. If anyone does something harmful to others, there is a prima facie case for punishing him—either by law or, where legal penalties are not safely applicable, by general disapproval. There are also many positive acts for the benefit of others that an individual may rightfully be compelled to perform:

to give evidence in a court of justice,

to do his fair share in the defence of his country, or

any other joint work necessary to the interests of the society whose protection he enjoys;

and to perform certain acts of individual beneficence. For example, a man may rightfully be held to account by society for not saving a fellow-creature’s life, or not protecting a defenceless person against ill-treatment, in situations where it was obviously his duty to do this. A person may cause harm to others not only by his •actions but by his •inaction, and either way he is justly accountable to them for the harm.

7

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

The •latter case, it is true, requires a much more cautious exercise of compulsion than the •former. To make someone answerable for doing harm to others is the rule; to make him answerable for not preventing harm is, comparatively speaking, the exception. Yet there are many cases clear enough and serious enough to justify that exception. In everything concerning the external relations of the individual, he is legally answerable to those whose interests are concerned, and if necessary to society as their protector. There are often good reasons for not holding him to that responsibility; but these reasons must arise from special features of the case: either

•it is a kind of case where he is likely to act better when left to himself than when controlled in any way that society could control him; or

•the attempt to exercise control would have bad effects greater than those that it would prevent.

When such reasons as these rule out the enforcement of responsibility, the person’s own conscience should move into the vacant judgment-seat and protect those interests of others that have no external protection; judging himself all the more severely because the case doesn’t admit of his being made accountable to the judgment of his fellow-creatures.

But there is a sphere of action in which the interests of society, as distinct from those of the individual, are involved only indirectly if they are involved at all: it is the sphere containing all the part of the individual’s life and conduct that affects only himself, or affects others but only with their free, voluntary, and undeceived consent and participation. When I say ‘affects only himself’ I am talking about the direct and immediate effects of his conduct. ·This has to be stipulated·, for whatever affects himself may affect others through himself. (Conduct may be objected to on that ground; I’ll consider this later.)

So this is the appropriate region of human liberty. ·I map it as containing three provinces·. (1) The inward domain of consciousness, demanding •liberty of conscience in the broadest sense, •liberty of thought and feeling, absolute •freedom of opinion and sentiment on all subjects, practical or theoretical, scientific, moral, or theological, and •liberty of expressing and publishing opinions. This last may seem to belong under a different principle, since it involves conduct of an individual that affects other people; but it can’t in practice be separated from the liberty of thought—it is almost as important as the latter and rests in great part on the same reasons. (2) Liberty of •tastes and pursuits, of •shaping our life to suit our own character, of •doing what we like....—all this without hindrance from our fellow-creatures, so long as what we do doesn’t harm them even though they may think our conduct foolish, perverse, or wrong. (3) Following from the first two domains of liberty, there is the liberty, within the same limits, •of individuals to come together, their freedom to unite for any purpose not involving harm to others—always supposing that the people in question are of full age and aren’t being forced or deceived.

No society in which these liberties are not •mainly respected is free, whatever form of government it has; and none is completely free in which they don’t exist •absolute and unqualified. The only freedom that deserves the name is the freedom to pursue our own good in our own way, so long as we don’t try to deprive others of their good or hinder their efforts to obtain it. Each is the proper guardian of his own health of body, mind, and spirit. Mankind gain more from allowing each other to live in the way that seems good to themselves than they would from compelling each to live in the way that seems good to the rest.

This doctrine is far from new, and it may strike some as a mere truism; but in fact there is no doctrine that stands

8

Liberty John Stuart Mill 1: Introduction

more directly opposed to the general tendency of existing opinion and practice! Society has put as much effort into trying (according to its lights) to compel people to conform to its notions of •personal excellence as into trying to compel them to conform to its notions of •social excellence. The ancient commonwealths thought (and the ancient philosophers agreed) that every part of private conduct could rightly be regulated by public authority, on the ground that the state’s welfare involved the whole bodily and mental discipline of every one of its citizens. This way of thinking may have been admissible in small republics surrounded by powerful enemies, in constant peril of being pulled down by foreign attack or internal upheavals, so that even a short period of relaxation and leaving the people to themselves might easily be fatal—so easily that they couldn’t afford to wait for the beneficial permanent effects of freedom. In the modern world two factors have prevented the law from interfering so greatly in the details of private life: •the greater size of political communities, and above all •the separation between the spiritual and temporal authority, ·i.e. between church and state·, which placed the direction of men’s consciences in other hands than those that controlled their worldly affairs. But the engines of moral ·as distinct from political· repression that have been wielded against divergence from the prevailing opinion ·and attitudes· have put less energy into this with regard to •social matters than with regard to •·personal, private·, self-regarding conduct. A reason for this is that religion, which is the most powerful of the elements that have contributed to forming moral feeling, has almost always been governed either by •the ambition of a hierarchy, seeking control over every department of human conduct, or by the •spirit of puritanism. ·But that isn’t the whole story, for· some of the modern reformers who have placed themselves in strongest opposition to the religions of the past have been right up there with the churches and sects in their assertion of the right to spiritual domination. A prime example is M. Comte, whose social system as set out in his Système de Politique Positive aims at establishing (though by moral more than by legal pressures) a despotism of society over the individual that surpasses anything contemplated in the political ideal of the most rigid disciplinarian among the ancient philosophers!

Apart from the special views of individual thinkers, there is also in the world at large an increasing inclination to stretch unduly the powers of society over the individual, both through the force of opinion and even through that of legislation; and because the tendency of all the changes taking place in the world is to strengthen society and lessen the power of the individual, this encroachment isn’t one of the evils that tend spontaneously to disappear, but on the contrary is one of the evils that tend to grow more and more formidable. Mankind have some disposition, whether as rulers or as fellow-citizens, to impose their own opinions and inclinations as a rule of conduct on others; this disposition is so energetically supported by some of the best and by some of the worst feelings in human nature that it is hardly ever kept under restraint by anything except lack of power; and the power ·of societies· is not declining but growing; so unless a strong barrier of moral conviction can be raised against the mischief ·of unwarranted interference with individual liberty·, we must expect—given the way the world is—to see it increase.

It will be convenient for the argument, if instead of plunging immediately into the general thesis we confine ourselves at first to a single branch of it—a branch on which the ·general· principle here stated is to some extent recognized by current opinions. This one branch is the liberty of thought, from which it is impossible to separate the related

9

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

liberty of speaking and of writing. These liberties form a considerable part of the political morality of all countries that profess religious toleration and free institutions, but the philosophical and practical grounds on which they rest are perhaps not as familiar to people in general, or as thoroughly grasped even by many of the leaders of opinion, as might have been expected. Those grounds, when rightly understood, also apply to other divisions of our subject, and a thorough consideration of this part of the question will be found to be the best introduction to the remainder. So I hope you’ll forgive me if nothing that I am about to say is new to you, as I embark on yet one more discussion of something that has often been discussed over the past three centuries.

Chapter 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

It is to be hoped that there is no longer any need to defend the ‘liberty of the press’ as one of the protections against corrupt or tyrannical government. No argument, we may suppose, can now be needed for this:

No legislature or executive whose interests aren’t exactly the same as the people’s should be allowed •to tell them what to believe or •to decide what doctrines or arguments they shall be allowed to hear.

This aspect of the ‘liberty’ issue has been so often and so triumphantly enforced by previous writers that there is no need for me to make a special point of it here. Though the law of England regarding the press is as servile today as it was three hundred years ago, there is little danger of its being actually enforced against political discussion, except during some temporary panic when fear of revolt drives ministers and judges from their proper course.^1 Generally speaking, it

^1 These words had hardly been written when the Government’s Press Prosecutions of 1858 took place—as though intended to emphatically contradict me. Still, that ill-judged interference with the liberty of public discussion hasn’t induced me to alter a single word in the text, nor has it at all weakened my conviction that except in moments of panic the era of pains and penalties for political discussion has in our own country passed away. For one thing, the prosecutions were not persisted in; for another, they were never strictly speaking political prosecutions. The offence charged was not that of •criticizing institutions or rulers or their acts, but rather of •circulating what was deemed an immoral doctrine, namely the lawfulness of tyrannicide.

If the arguments of my present chapter have any validity, there ought to exist the fullest liberty of proclaiming and discussing—as a matter of ethical conviction—any doctrine, however immoral it may be considered. So it isn’t relevant here to consider whether the doctrine of tyrannicide is immoral. I shall content myself with ·making three points·. (1) This subject has always been one of the open questions of morals. (2) When a private citizen strikes down a criminal who has raised himself above the law and thus placed himself beyond the reach of legal punishment or control, this has been regarded by whole nations and by some of the best and wisest of men not as a crime but as an act of exalted virtue. (3) Such an act, whether it be right or wrong, is not of the nature of •assassination but rather of •civil war. In a particular case, it may be proper to punish someone for inciting others else to it, but only if an overt act has followed, and at least a probable connection can be established between the act and the incitement. Even then the only government entitled to punish such attacks is the one that has been attacked.

10

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

isn’t likely that the government in a constitutional country, whether or not it is completely answerable to the people, will often try to control the expression of opinion—except when by doing so it expresses the general intolerance of the public. Let us suppose, therefore, that the government is entirely in harmony with the people, and never thinks of coercing anyone except in ways that it thinks the people want. But I deny the right of the people to exercise such coercion, whether directly or through their government. The power ·of coercion· itself is illegitimate. The best government has no more right to it than the worst. It is at least as noxious when exerted •in accordance with public opinion as when it is exerted •in opposition to it. If all mankind minus one were of one opinion, and that one had the contrary opinion, mankind would be no more justified in silencing that one person than he would be in silencing them if he could. ·You might think that silencing only one couldn’t be so very wrong, but that is mistaken, and here is why·. If an opinion were a personal possession of no value except to the person who has it, so that being obstructed in the enjoyment of it was simply a private injury, it would make some difference whether the harm was inflicted on only a few persons or on many. But the special wrongness of silencing the expression of an opinion is that it is robbing

•·not one individual, but· the human race,

•posterity as well as the present generation,

•those who dissent from the opinion as well as those who hold it.

Indeed, those who dissent are wronged more than those who agree. •If the opinion in question is right, they are robbed of the opportunity of exchanging error for truth; and •if it is wrong, they lose a benefit that is almost as great, namely the clearer perception and livelier impression of truth that would come from its collision with error.

We need to consider these two cases separately; each has a distinct branch of the argument corresponding to it. We can never be sure that the opinion we are trying to suppress is false; and even if we were sure of its falsity it would still be wrong to suppress it. [The first branch is dealt with right away; discussion of the second starts on page 22.]

First: the opinion the authorities are trying to suppress may be true. Those who want to suppress it will deny its truth, of course; but they aren’t infallible. They have no authority to decide the question for all mankind, and exclude every other person from the means of judging. To refuse a hearing to an opinion because they are sure that it is false is to assume that their certainty is the same thing as absolute certainty—·i.e. that their being sure that P is the same as its being certainly true that P·. All silencing of discussion is an assumption of infallibility, which is a good argument for condemning it; many people have used this argument, but it’s none the worse for that.

Unfortunately for the good sense of mankind, the fact that people are fallible doesn’t carry nearly as much weight in practice as it is allowed to carry in theory. Everyone knows perfectly well that he is fallible, but few •think it necessary to take any precautions against their own fallibility, or •allow that the errors to which they admit they are liable might include some opinion of which they feel very certain. Absolute monarchs, or others accustomed to unlimited deference, usually feel this complete confidence in their own opinions on nearly all subjects. People who lack the disadvantages of monarchs and thus sometimes hear their opinions disputed, and have some experience of being set right when they are wrong, have the same unbounded confidence only in such of their opinions as are shared by all around them, or by those to whom they habitually defer. For the less confidence someone has in his own individual

11

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

judgment, the more he relies, with complete trust, on the infallibility of ‘the world’ in general. And •the world, to each individual, means •the part of it that he comes into contact with: his party, his sect, his church, his class of society. By comparison ·with most people·, a man may be called almost liberal and large-minded if to him ‘the world’ ·on which he bases his most confident opinions· is anything as comprehensive as his own country or the times in which he lives. The faith he has in this collective authority isn’t at all shaken by his being aware that other ages, countries, sects, churches, classes, and parties have thought—and even now think—the exact reverse of what he does. He bestows on his own ‘world’ the responsibility for being in the right against the dissentient ‘worlds’ of other people. It doesn’t bother him that mere accident has decided which of these numerous ‘worlds’ is the one he relies on: that the causes that make him an Anglican in London would have made him a Buddhist or a Confucian in Peking. Yet it is as evident in itself as any amount of argument can make it that ages are no more infallible than individuals, because every age has held many opinions that subsequent ages deemed to be not only false but absurd; and it is as certain that many opinions •now generally accepted •will be rejected by future ages as it is that many that •have been generally accepted are •now rejected.

An objection that is likely to be made to this argument runs somewhat as follows:

There is no greater assumption of infallibility in forbidding the propagation of error than there is in anything else done by public authority on its own judgment and responsibility. Judgment is given to men to be used. Because it may be used erroneously, are men to be told that they oughtn’t to use it at all? To prohibit something they think to be pernicious is not •to claim exemption from error, but •to perform their duty to act, fallible though they are, on their conscientious convictions. If we were never to act on our opinions because they may be wrong, we would leave all our interests uncared for and all our duties unperformed. An objection that applies to all conduct can’t be a valid objection to any conduct in particular. Governments and individuals have a duty to form the truest opinions they can; to form them carefully, and never impose them on others unless they are quite sure of being right. But when they are sure, it is not conscientiousness but cowardice to shrink from acting on their opinions, and to allow doctrines that they honestly think dangerous to the welfare of mankind—either in this life or in another—to be scattered abroad without restraint, just because other people in less enlightened times have persecuted opinions that are now believed to be true! Let us take care not to make the same mistake; but governments and nations have made mistakes in other things that are not denied to be fit subjects for the exercise of authority, such as imposing bad taxes and making unjust wars. Ought we therefore to impose no taxes, and whatever the provocation to make no wars? Men and governments must act to the best of their ability. There’s no such thing as absolute certainty, but there is assurance sufficient for the purposes of human life. We may—we must—assume our opinion to be true for the guidance of our own conduct; and that’s all we are assuming when we forbid bad men to pervert society by spreading opinions that we regard as false and pernicious.

I answer: No, it is assuming very much more than that. There is the greatest difference between •presuming an opinion to be true because, with every opportunity for

12

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

contesting it, it hasn’t been refuted, and •assuming its truth as a basis for not permitting its refutation. Complete liberty of contradicting and disproving our opinion is the very condition that justifies us in assuming its truth for purposes of action; and on no other terms can a human being have any rational assurance of being right.

Look at the history of •what people have believed; or look at the ordinary •conduct of human life. Why are each of these no worse than they are? It is certainly not because of the inherent force of the human understanding! Take any proposition that isn’t self-evident: for every person who is capable of judging it, there are ninety-nine others who aren’t; and the ‘capability’ of that one person is only comparative; for the majority of the eminent men of every past generation held many opinions now known to be erroneous, and did or approved many things that no-one would now defend. Well, then, why is it that there is on the whole a preponderance among mankind of •rational opinions and •rational conduct? If there really is this preponderance—and there must be, unless human affairs are and always were in an almost desperate state—it is owing to the fact that the errors of the human mind can be corrected. This quality of the human mind is the source of everything worthy of respect in man, whether as a thinking or as a moral being. He is capable of correcting his mistakes by discussion and experience. Not by experience alone: there must be discussion, to show how experience is to be interpreted. Wrong opinions and practices gradually give way to fact and argument; but facts and arguments can’t have any effect on the mind unless they are brought before it. Very few facts are able to tell their own story, without comments to bring out their meaning. So: because the whole strength and value of human judgment depends on a single property, namely that it can be set right when it is wrong, it can be relied on only when the means of setting it right are kept constantly at hand. Consider someone whose judgment really is deserving of confidence—how has it become so? Through his conducting himself as follows:

•He has kept his mind open to criticism of his opinions and conduct.

•He has made it his practice to listen to all that could be said against him, to profit by as much of it as was sound, and expound to himself—and sometimes to others—the fallacy of what was fallacious.

•He has felt that the only way for a human to approach knowing the whole of a subject is by hearing what can be said about it by persons of every variety of opinion, and studying all the ways in which it can be looked at by every kind of mind.

No wise man ever acquired his wisdom in any way but this; and the human intellect isn’t built to become wise in any other manner. The steady habit of correcting and completing his own opinion by comparing it with those of others, so far from causing doubt and hesitation in acting on the opinion, is the only stable foundation for a sound reliance on it. Knowing everything that can, at least obviously, be said against him, and having taken up his position against those who disagree, knowing that he has looked for objections and difficulties instead of avoiding them, and has shut out no light that can be thrown on the subject from any direction—he has a right to think his judgment better than that of any person or crowd of them that hasn’t gone through a similar process.

It is not too much to require that what the wisest of mankind, those who are best entitled to trust their own judgment, find necessary to warrant their relying on it, should be submitted to by that miscellaneous collection of a few wise and many foolish individuals called ‘the public’.

13

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

[That sentence is exactly as Mill wrote it.] The most intolerant of churches, the Roman Catholic church, even at the canonization of a saint, admits and patiently listens to a ‘devil’s advocate’. The holiest of men, it seems, can’t be admitted to posthumous honours until all that the devil could say against him is known and weighed. Even Newton’s physics—if we weren’t permitted to question it, mankind couldn’t feel as completely sure of its truth as they now do. The beliefs that we have most justification for have as their only safeguard a standing invitation to the whole world to ·try to· prove them unfounded. If that challenge isn’t accepted, or is accepted and the attempt fails, we are still far from certainty; but we have done the best that the existing state of human reason admits of; we have neglected nothing that could give the truth a chance of reaching us. If the challenge continues to stand, we can hope that if there is a better truth it will be found when the human mind is capable of receiving it; and in the meantime we may rely on having attained as close an approach to truth as is possible in our own day. That is how much certainty a fallible being can get, and that is the only way to get it.

It’s strange that men should admit the validity of the arguments for free discussion, but object to their being ‘pushed to an extreme’, not seeing that unless the reasons are good for an extreme case they aren’t good for any case. Strange that they should imagine that they aren’t assuming infallibility when they acknowledge •that there should be free discussion on all subjects that can possibly be doubtful, but think •that some particular principle or doctrine—·this being the ‘extreme’ case·—ought not to be questioned because it is so certain (meaning that it is certain because they are certain!). If we call any proposition certain while there is anyone who would deny its certainty if permitted (but who isn’t permitted), we’re assuming that we and those who agree with us are the judges of certainty—judges who don’t hear the other side.

In the present age—which has been described as ‘destitute of faith, but terrified of scepticism’—people feel sure not so much that •their opinions are true as that •they wouldn’t know what to do without them. So the claims of an opinion to be protected from public attack are based less on its truth than on its importance to society. This is alleged:

Some beliefs are so useful, indeed indispensable, to our well-being that governments have as much of a duty to uphold them as to protect any other of the interests of society. With that kind of necessity, on matters that are directly in the government’s line of duty, something less than infallibility may permit and even oblige governments to act on their own opinion, confirmed by the general opinion of mankind.

Something else that is also often argued, and still oftener thought, is this:

Only bad men would want to weaken these beneficial beliefs; and there can’t be anything wrong in restraining bad men, and in prohibiting something that only bad men would want to do.

This way of thinking tries to justify restraints on discussion not through the •truth of doctrines but through their •usefulness; and it hopes in that way to avoid having to claim to be an infallible judge of opinions. But those who are content with this don’t see that they have merely shifted the assumption of infallibility from one point to another. The usefulness of an opinion is itself a matter of opinion, and is as disputable—as open to discussion and as much in need of it—as is the opinion itself. Deciding that an opinion is dangerous, just like deciding that it is false, requires an infallible judge of opinions unless the condemned opinion has a full opportunity to defend itself. ‘Well, the heretic

14

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

may be allowed to maintain that his opinion is useful, or harmless, though he is forbidden to maintain its truth.’ That won’t do, because the truth of an opinion is part of its usefulness. If we want to know whether it is desirable that a proposition be believed, can we possibly exclude the question of whether it is true? No belief that is contrary to truth can be really useful: this is the opinion not of bad men but of the best men. When a good man is accused of denying some doctrine that he is told is useful but which he believes is false, can he be prevented from urging that false doctrines can never be useful? Those who are on the side of publicly accepted opinions never fail to take advantage of this plea; you don’t find them handling the question of utility as if it could be completely sifted out from the question of truth; on the contrary, they hold that the doctrine ·they are protecting· is indispensable precisely because it is ‘the truth’. There can be no fair discussion of usefulness if such a vital argument can be employed on one side of the debate but not on the other. And in practice when law or public feeling doesn’t permit the •truth of an opinion to be disputed, it is just as intolerant of a denial of its •usefulness....

In order to illustrate more fully the badness of denying a hearing to opinions because we have condemned them, I should tie the discussion to a concrete case; and I freely choose the cases that are least favourable to me—ones where the argument against freedom of opinion, both on the score of truth and on that of utility, is considered the strongest. Let the opinions in question be •the belief in a God and in life after death, or •any of the commonly accepted doctrines of morality. Fighting the battle on that ground gives a great advantage to an unfair opponent, who will be sure to say:

Are these the doctrines that you regard as not certain enough to deserve be taken under the protection of law? Is the belief in a God one of the opinions that (according to you) one can’t feel sure of without assuming that one is infallible?

(Indeed, many who have no desire to be unfair will say this internally.) Allow me to point out that what I call an ‘assumption of infallibility’ is not •feeling sure of a doctrine but rather •undertaking to decide that question for others, without letting them hear what can be said on the contrary side. And I denounce and deplore this claim just as much if it is put forth on the side of my own most solemn convictions. However sure someone is not only of the •falsity of an opinion but also of its •pernicious consequences, and even (to adopt expressions that I altogether condemn) of its •immorality and impiety, if that private judgment leads him to prevent the opinion from being heard to defend itself he assumes infallibility—even if his judgment is backed by the public judgment of his country or his contemporaries. And so far from •the assumption ·of infallibility· being less objectionable or less dangerous because the opinion is called immoral or impious, it is precisely with those opinions that the assumption is most fatal. It is on exactly those matters that the men of one generation commit the dreadful mistakes that arouse astonishment and horror in later generations. It is among them that we find the memorable historical instances where the arm of the law has been employed to root out the •best men and the •noblest doctrines; with deplorable success as regards the •men, though some of the •doctrines survived and (ironically) were later invoked in defence of similar conduct towards those who dissented from them or from their accepted interpretation.

Mankind can hardly be too often reminded that there was once a man named Socrates who came into a memorable collision with the legal authorities and public opinion of his time ·and place·. Born in an age and country abounding in individual greatness, this man has been reported to us. by

15

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

those who best knew both him and his times, as the most virtuous man then alive. And we know him as the head and exemplary model for all subsequent teachers of virtue, the source of the lofty inspiration of •Plato and of the judicious utilitarianism of •Aristotle (‘the master of those who know’, ·as Dante called him·), the •two sources of ethical and of all other philosophy. This acknowledged master of all the eminent thinkers who have since lived—a man whose fame, still growing after more than two thousand years, nearly outweighs all the other names that make his native city illustrious—was judicially convicted and put to death by his countrymen for impiety and immorality. •Impiety in denying the gods recognized by the state (indeed his accuser said that Socrates didn’t believe in any gods). •Immorality in being, through his doctrines and instructions, a ‘corrupter of youth’. We have every ground for believing that the tribunal honestly found him guilty, and condemned to death as a criminal the man who was probably the best man who had ever lived up to that time.

After the condemnation of Socrates, mention of most other instances of ‘justice’ gone wrong would be an anticlimax, the one exception being the event that took place on Calvary rather more than eighteen hundred years ago. The man who left on the memory of those who witnessed his life and conversation such an impression of his moral grandeur that eighteen subsequent centuries have done homage to him as God in person was ignominiously put to death... as what? As a blasphemer! Men didn’t merely mistake their benefactor; they mistook him for the exact opposite of what he was, treating him as that monster of impiety that they are now held to be because of how they treated him. The feelings that mankind now have regarding these lamentable dealings ·with Socrates and with Jesus·, especially the latter of the two, make them extremely unjust in their judgment of those who put the two death. These seem not to have been bad men—not worse than men most commonly are, but rather the contrary; men who possessed a full or perhaps over-full measure of the religious, moral, and patriotic feelings of their time and people; just the kind of men who at any time—ours included—have every chance of passing through life blameless and respected. [In the background of the next bit is this from Matthew 26: 64-5: ‘Jesus said.... “Hereafter shall ye see the son of man sitting on the right hand of power, and coming in the clouds of heaven.” Then the high priest tore his clothes, saying: “He hath spoken blasphemy; what further need have we of witnesses?”’.] The high-priest who tore his garments when he heard the words that according to all the ideas of his country constituted the blackest guilt was probably quite as sincere in his horror and indignation as are the general run of respectable and pious men now in the religious and moral sentiments they proclaim; and most of those who now shudder at the high-priest’s conduct, if they had lived in his time and been born Jews, would have acted precisely as he did. Orthodox Christians who are tempted to think that those who stoned to death the first martyrs must have been worse men than they themselves are ought to remember that one of those persecutors was St. Paul.

Let me add one more example, the most striking of all, if the •impressiveness of an error is measured by the •wisdom and virtue of the person who falls into it! If anyone in a position of power ever had grounds for thinking himself the best and most enlightened among his contemporaries it was the Emperor Marcus Aurelius. Absolute monarch of the whole civilized world, he preserved through life not only the most untainted justice but also—less to be expected from his Stoic upbringing—the tenderest heart. The few failings that are attributed to him were all on the side of leniency; and his writings, the highest ethical product of the

16

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

ancient mind, differ little if at all from the most characteristic teachings of Christ. This man, a better Christian than almost any of the ostensibly Christian sovereigns who have since reigned, persecuted Christianity. (In calling Marcus Aurelius ‘Christian’, I mean that in every sense of the word except the one having to do with the acceptance of dogmas.) Placed at the summit of all the previous attainments of humanity, with an open and free intellect and a character that led him to embody in his moral writings the Christian ideal, he nevertheless failed to see that Christianity was going to be a good and not an evil to the world.... He knew that existing society was in a deplorable state. But such as it was, he saw or thought he saw that it was held together and prevented from being worse by belief in and reverence for the accepted gods. As a ruler of mankind, with a deep sense of his duty to the world, he thought it his duty not to allow society to fall to pieces; and he didn’t see how, if its existing ties were removed, any others could be formed to pull it back together. The new religion openly aimed at dissolving the existing ties; so it seemed to him that either it was his duty to adopt that religion or it was his duty to suppress it. Well, then, •the theology of Christianity didn’t appear to him true or of divine origin, •this strange history of a crucified God was not credible to him, and •a system that purported to be based on something he found so wholly unbelievable couldn’t be foreseen to be an agency for renewal (which is what it has turned out to be, on balance). For these reasons this gentlest and most lovable of philosophers and rulers, acting on a solemn sense of duty, authorized the persecution of Christianity. To my mind this is one of the most tragic facts in all history. It is bitter to think of how different the Christianity of the world might have been if the Christian faith had been adopted as the religion of the ·Roman· empire under the auspices of Marcus Aurelius instead of those of Constantine. But in fairness to him and to the truth it must be admitted that any plea that can be urged for punishing anti-Christian teaching ·today· was available to Marcus Aurelius for punishing the propagation of Christianity. No Christian more firmly believes that atheism is false and tends to the dissolution of society than Marcus Aurelius believed the same things of Christianity—he who might have been thought more capable of appreciating it than anyone else then alive. To anyone who approves of punishment for spreading opinions, I say:

Unless you flatter yourself that you are a wiser and better man than Marcus Aurelius, more deeply informed about the wisdom of your time and more elevated in your intellect above it, more earnest in your search for truth, or more single-minded in your devotion to it when you find it—you should abstain from that assumption of the joint infallibility of yourself and the multitude which the great Antoninus [= Marcus Aurelius] made with such unfortunate results.

Some of the enemies of religious freedom are aware that they can’t defend the use of punishment for restraining irreligious opinions by any argument that won’t also justify Marcus Antoninus; and when they are hard pressed they accept this consequence and say, with Dr. Johnson, that the persecutors of Christianity were in the right. They say that persecution is an ordeal through which truth ought to pass, and always passes successfully, legal penalties being ultimately •powerless against truth but sometimes beneficially •effective against mischievous errors. This form of the argument for religious intolerance is remarkable enough to deserve scrutiny.

A theory that maintains that truth may justifiably be persecuted because persecution can’t possibly do it any harm cannot be accused of deliberate hostility to the reception of

17

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

•new truths; but we can’t congratulate it on the generosity of its treatment of the •persons through whom such truths have been brought to mankind! To reveal to the world something that deeply concerns it and that it didn’t previously know, to show the world that it had been mistaken on some vital point of worldly or spiritual concern, is as important a service as a human being can render to his fellow-creatures; and in certain cases, such as in those of the early Christians and of the leaders of the Reformation, Dr. Johnson and his fellow-believers think it to have been the most precious gift that could be bestowed on mankind. That the authors of such splendid benefits should be repaid by martyrdom, that they should be ‘rewarded’ by being treated as the vilest of criminals, is not on this theory a deplorable error and misfortune for which humanity should mourn in sackcloth and ashes, but rather is the normal and justifiable state of things. According to this doctrine, the propounder of a new truth should stand (like the proposer of a new law in the legislature of ancient Locris) with a halter around his neck, to be instantly tightened if the public assembly, after hearing his reasons, doesn’t immediately adopt his proposition. People who defend this way of treating benefactors evidently don’t set much value on the benefit! I think that this view of the subject is mostly confined to the sort of persons who think that new truths may have been desirable once but that we have had enough of them now!

Anyway, the dictum that truth always triumphs over persecution is one of those pleasant falsehoods that men repeat after one another until they become ‘common knowledge’, but which all experience refutes. History teems with instances of truth put down by persecution. Even if not suppressed forever, it can be thrown back for centuries. To speak only of religious opinions: the Reformation broke out at least twenty times before Luther, and was put down. [Mill names seven reformist individuals or groups before Luther, all ‘put down’.] Even after the era of Luther, wherever persecution was persisted in it was successful. In Spain, Italy, Flanders, the Austrian empire, protestantism was rooted out; and it would probably have been rooted out in England too if Queen Mary had lived ·longer· or Queen Elizabeth had died ·sooner·. Persecution has always succeeded except where the heretics were too strong a party to be effectively persecuted. No reasonable person can doubt that Christianity could have been wiped out in the Roman empire. It spread and became predominant because the persecutions were intermittent, lasting for only a short time and separated by long intervals of almost undisturbed ·Christian· propagandizing. It is a piece of idle sentimentality that truth as such has an inherent power, lacked by error, of prevailing against the dungeon and the stake. Men are not more zealous for truth than they often are for error, and a sufficient application of legal or even of social penalties will generally succeed in stopping the propagation of either. The real advantage that truth has is just this: when an opinion is true, it may be extinguished once or many times, but through the centuries there will generally be found persons to rediscover it, until some one of its reappearances comes at a time when circumstances are favourable to its escaping persecution until it has made enough headway to withstand all subsequent attempts to suppress it.

This will be said: ‘We don’t now put to death the introducers of new opinions; we aren’t like our ancestors who slew the prophets; we even build monuments to them.’ It is true that we no longer put heretics to death; and even against the most obnoxious opinions modern feeling probably wouldn’t tolerate punishments severe enough to wipe them out. But let us not flatter ourselves that we are now free from the stain even of legal persecution. Penalties for opinions, or

18

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

at least for expressing them, still exist by law; and even today their enforcement is not so rare as to make it at all incredible that they may some day be revived in full force. In the year 1857—·only two years before this Essay was first published·—an unfortunate man was sentenced to twenty-one months imprisonment for uttering and writing on a gate some offensive words concerning Christianity. (This happened at the summer assizes of the county of Cornwall. The man is said to be of unexceptionable conduct in every aspect of life.) [Mill gives the name and date for this and each of the other three cases he next mentions.] Less than a month later, at the Old Bailey, two people on two separate occasions were rejected as jurymen, and one of them was grossly insulted by the judge and by one of the lawyers, because they honestly declared that they had no theological beliefs. A third person, a foreigner, was for the same reason denied justice against a thief. This refusal of remedy was based on the legal doctrine that a person cannot be allowed to give evidence in a court of justice if he doesn’t proclaim a belief in a god (any god will do) and in a life after death. This doctrine is equivalent to declaring such a person to be an outlaw, someone excluded from the protection of the courts; it implies not only that •he may be robbed or assaulted with impunity if no-one but himself or people who think as he does are present, but also that •anyone else may be robbed or assaulted with impunity if the proof of the crime depends on his evidence. The underlying assumption here is that someone’s oath is worthless if he doesn’t believe in a life after death. Someone who believes this must be very ignorant of history, since it is historically true that a large proportion of unbelievers in all ages have been people of distinguished integrity and honour. This proposition wouldn’t be maintained by anyone who had the slightest conception how many of those persons who stand in greatest repute with the world, both for virtues and for attainments, are well known (at least to their intimates) to be unbelievers. Furthermore, the rule is suicidal! It cuts away its own foundation: on the claim that atheists must be liars, it accepts the testimony of all •atheists who are willing to lie, and rejects only •those who brave the disgrace of publicly owning to a detested creed rather than affirming a falsehood. A rule thus self-convicted of absurdity so far as regards its professed purpose can be kept in force only as a badge of hatred, a relic of persecution. And it is a very strange persecution, because what qualifies one for undergoing it is clearly proving that one doesn’t deserve it! The rule and the theory behind it are almost as insulting to believers as to unbelievers. For if he who doesn’t believe in a future state necessarily lies, it follows that those who do believe are prevented from lying—if indeed they are—only by the fear of hell....

These, indeed, are merely rags and remnants of persecution, and may be thought to be not so much •an indication of the wish to persecute as •an example of that very frequent infirmity of English minds, which makes them take a preposterous pleasure in the assertion of a bad principle when they are no longer bad enough to want to carry it really into practice. But unfortunately the state of the public mind doesn’t give us a guarantee that the suspension of worse forms of legal persecution, which has lasted for about one generation, will continue. At this time the quiet surface of routine is ruffled as often by attempts to revive past evils as it is by attempts to introduce new benefits. What is boasted of at the present time as the •revival of religion is always, in narrow and undeveloped minds, at least as much the •revival of bigotry; and where there is the strongest permanent leaven of intolerance in the feelings of a people—as there always is in the middle classes of this country—it doesn’t take much to provoke them into actively persecuting those whom they have

19

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

never ceased to regard as proper objects of persecution.^2

For it is this—it is •men’s opinions and feelings concerning those who disown the beliefs •they deem important—that stops this country from being a place of freedom of thought. For a long time past, the chief harm done by legal penalties has been ·merely· to strengthen the social stigma. It is the social stigma that is really effective. It is so effective that in England people are less likely to profess opinions that are under the ban of •society than are people in other countries to profess opinions that involve a risk of •judicial punishment. For those who aren’t wealthy enough to do without the good will of other people, social pressures are as effective as law in suppressing unpopular opinions; being imprisoned is no worse than being excluded from the means of earning a living. Those who have a secure income—enough to live on—and who don’t want any favours from men in power, or from bodies of men, or from the public, have nothing to fear from openly declaring their opinions except being ill thought of and ill spoken of—and they don’t have to be very heroic to be able to bear that! There is no room for any appeal for pity on behalf of such people. But though we don’t now inflict as much harm as we used to on those who think differently from us, it may be that we do ourselves as much harm as ever by our treatment of them. Socrates was put to death, but the Socratic philosophy rose like the sun in the skies and spread its illumination over the whole intellectual firmament. Christians were thrown to the lions, but the Christian Church grew up as a stately and spreading tree, towering over the older and less vigorous growths and stifling them by its shade. Our merely social intolerance doesn’t kill anyone, and doesn’t root out any opinions; but it does induce men to disguise their opinions or to abstain from actively trying to spread them. With us, heretical opinions don’t noticeably gain or lose ground in each decade or generation; they never blaze out far and wide, but continue to smoulder in the narrow circles of thoughtful and studious people among whom they originate, without ever spreading any light—whether true or deceptive—on the general affairs of mankind. This maintains a state of affairs that is very satisfactory to some minds, because it keeps all prevailing opinions outwardly undisturbed, without the unpleasant process of fining or imprisoning anybody, and without absolutely forbidding the exercise of reason by dissentients who are afflicted with the malady of thought!

^2 Ample warning can be drawn from the way in which, on the occasion of the Sepoy insurrection ·in India·, the general display of the worst parts of our national character included a large infusion of the passions of a persecutor. The ravings of fanatics or charlatans from the pulpit may be unworthy of notice; but the heads of the Evangelical party have announced as their principle for the government of Hindus and Moslems that only schools in which the bible is taught should be supported by public money, implying that public employment should be given only to real or pretended Christians. An Under-Secretary of State, in a speech delivered to his constituents....in 1857, is reported to have said:

The British Government’s toleration of the Indians’ faith, the superstition that they called ‘religion’, has had the effect of holding back the ascendancy of the British name, and preventing the salutary growth of Christianity.... Toleration is the great corner-stone of the religious liberties of this country; but don’t let them abuse that precious word toleration. As I understand it, it means the complete liberty to all, freedom of worship, among Christians who worship on the same foundation. It means toleration of all sects and denominations of Christians who believe in the one mediation, ·that is, in the mediating role of Jesus Christ·.

The ‘superstition’ in question is the faith of a hundred million British subjects! I want to call attention to the fact that a man who has been deemed fit to fill a high office in the government of this country....maintains that those who don’t believe in the divinity of Christ are all beyond the pale of toleration. Who, after this imbecilic display, can go on thinking that religious persecution has passed away, never to return?

20

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

This is a convenient plan for having peace in the intellectual world, and keeping things ticking along in very much the way they do already. But the price paid for this sort of intellectual pacification is the sacrifice of the entire moral courage of the human mind. A state of affairs in which

a large portion of the most active and inquiring intellects find it advisable to keep to themselves the genuine principles and grounds of their convictions, and try in their public statements to fit as much as they can of their own conclusions to premises that they have silently rejected,

can’t send forth people with the open fearless characters and logical consistent intellects that once adorned the thinking world. The sort of men it can be expected to produce are either mere conformers to commonplace ideas or time-servers [roughly = ‘crowd-pleasers’] for truth whose arguments on all great subjects are meant for their hearers and are not the arguments that convinced them. Those who avoid both of these roles do so by narrowing their thoughts and interests •to things that can be spoken of without getting into the territory of principles—i.e. •to small practical matters that would come right by themselves if only the minds of mankind were strengthened and enlarged, and won’t ever be made really right until that happens. ·The irony of this is that· in behaving like that they abandon the very thing that would strengthen and enlarge men’s minds, namely free and daring intellectual inquiry into the highest subjects.

If you regard this reticence on the part of heretics as no bad thing, consider this:

A consequence of their reticence is that there is never any fair and thorough discussion of heretical opinions; and ones that couldn’t survive such a discussion, though they may be prevented from spreading, don’t disappear.

But the worst harm done by banning all inquiry that doesn’t end in orthodox conclusions is not •to the minds of heretics but •to those who aren’t heretics, and whose whole mental development is cramped, and their reason intimidated, by the fear of ·coming to accept what turns out to be· heresy. Who can calculate what the world loses in the multitude of promising intellects combined with timid characters—people who don’t dare to follow out any bold, vigorous, independent train of thought for fear that it will land them in something that might be thought irreligious or immoral? Among them we may occasionally see some man of deep conscientiousness, and subtle and refined understanding, who spends his life fine-tuning his faith with an intellect that he can’t silence, exhausting the resources of ingenuity in an attempt to reconcile the promptings of •his conscience and reason with •orthodoxy, perhaps never succeeding in doing so. No-one can be a great thinker if he doesn’t recognize that his first duty as a thinker is to follow his intellect to whatever conclusions it may lead to. Someone who with due study and preparation thinks for himself does more to advance the truth, even in his errors, than is done by the true opinions of those who hold them only because they don’t allow themselves to think. Not that it is primarily—let alone solely—•to form great thinkers that freedom of thought is required. On the contrary, it is even more indispensable for enabling average human beings to reach the highest mental level they are capable of. There have been, and may again be, great •individual thinkers in a general atmosphere of mental slavery. But there never was and never will be, in that atmosphere, an intellectually active •people. Where any people—·the populace of any country·—has temporarily moved towards being intellectually active, that has been because the fear of unorthodox theorizing was temporarily suspended. Where ·on the other hand· there is a silent

21

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

understanding that principles aren’t to be disputed—where the discussion of the greatest questions that can occupy humanity is considered to be closed—we can’t hope to find the generally high level of mental activity that has made some periods of history so remarkable. Whenever the big subjects—the ones large and important enough to kindle enthusiasm—were protected from controversy, the mind of the populace wasn’t stirred up from its foundations, with even persons of the most ordinary intellect being pushed into something of the dignity of thinking beings. We had an example ·of such a push· in the condition of Europe in the period immediately following the Reformation; another, though limited to continental Europe and to a more cultivated class, in the theorizing movement of the second half of the eighteenth century; and a third, of still briefer duration, in the intellectual fermentation of Germany during the period influenced by Goethe and Fichte. These periods differed widely in what particular opinions they developed; but they had this in common: during all three the yoke of authority was broken. In each period, an old mental despotism had been thrown off and no new one had yet taken its place. The push given at these three periods has made Europe what it now is. Every single improvement that has taken place in the human mind or in human institutions can be clearly traced back to one or other of them. For some time now it has seemed that all three of those pushes are just about exhausted; and we can’t expect a fresh start until we again assert our mental freedom.

Let us now pass to the second branch of the argument [this refers to the dichotomy mentioned on page 11.] Dismissing the thought of falsehood in the publicly accepted opinions, let us assume them to be true; and ·on that basis· let us look into the value of how they are likely to be held, given that their truth is not freely and openly discussed, pro and con. However unwilling a person who has a strong opinion may be to admit that his opinion might be false, he ought to be moved by this thought: however true it may be, if it isn’t fully, frequently and fearlessly discussed, it will be held as a dead dogma rather than as a living truth.

There are people (fortunately not quite as many as there used to be) who will be satisfied if you assent undoubtingly to something that they think is true, even if you have no knowledge whatever of the grounds for the belief in question and couldn’t defend it decently against the most superficial objections. When such people get their creed to be taught as authoritative, they naturally think that no good and some harm will come from allowing it to be questioned. Where their influence is dominant, they make it nearly impossible for the publicly accepted opinion to be rejected •wisely and considerately. It may still be rejected •rashly and ignorantly; for it is seldom possible to shut off discussion entirely, and once discussion gets started, beliefs that are held as creeds rather than being based on reasons are apt to give way before the slightest semblance of an argument. Set aside that possibility, and take the case where the true opinion remains in the person’s mind, but sits there as a prejudice, a belief that owes nothing to argument and isn’t vulnerable to argument—this isn’t the way truth ought to be held by a rational being! This is not knowing the truth. Truth when accepted in that way is merely one more superstition, accidentally clinging to words that enunciate a ·genuine· truth.

Protestants at least don’t deny that the intellect and judgment of mankind ought to be cultivated [= ‘helped to grow and flourish’]. If this is to be done, what more appropriate method is there than for the person to employ his intellect and judgment on the things that concern him so much that it is considered necessary for him to hold opinions on them?

22

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

If the cultivation of the understanding consists in one thing more than in another, it is surely in learning the grounds of one’s own opinions. When people believe •something on a topic on which it is highly important to believe rightly, they ought to be able to defend •it at least against the common objections. This may be said:

Let them be taught what the grounds are for their opinions. Just because they never hear the opinions being disputed it doesn’t follow that they are merely parroting them. Persons who learn geometry don’t simply commit the theorems to memory, but understand and remember the demonstrations; and it would be absurd to say that they remain ignorant of the grounds of geometrical truths because they never hear anyone deny them and try to disprove them.

Undoubtedly; and such teaching suffices in a subject like mathematics, where there is nothing at all to be said on the wrong side of the question. That’s what is special about the evidentness of mathematical truths: all the argument is on one side. There are no objections, and no answers to objections. But on every subject on which difference of opinion is possible, the truth depends on a balance to be struck between two sets of conflicting reasons. Even in natural science there is always some other explanation possible of the same facts; some theory with •the earth at the centre instead of the sun, some theory explaining combustion in terms of •phlogiston rather than of oxygen; and it has to be shown why •that other theory can’t be the true one. Until this is shown and we know how it is shown, we don’t understand the grounds for accepting the theory that we do accept. But when we turn to infinitely more complicated subjects—to morals, religion, politics, social relations, and the business of life—three quarters of the arguments for every controversial opinion consist in dispelling the appearances that favour some opinion different from it. The second-greatest of the ancient orators has left it on record that he always studied his adversary’s case as intensely as he did his own, if not even more so. What Cicero (·the orator in question·) practised as the means of success in the law courts should be imitated by anyone who studies any subject in order to arrive at the truth. He who knows only his own side of the case doesn’t know much about it. His reasons may be good, and no-one may have been able to refute them; but if he is equally unable to refute the reasons on the opposite side, and doesn’t even know what they are, he has no ground for preferring either opinion. The rational position for him would be to suspend judgment, and if he doesn’t settle for that, he is either •being led by authority or •doing what most people do, which is to adopt the side to which he feels most strongly drawn. It isn’t enough that he should hear the arguments of opponents from his own teachers, presented in their way and accompanied by what they offer as refutations. That isn’t the way to do justice to the ·opposing· arguments, or to bring them into real contact with his own mind. He must be able to hear them from people who actually believe them, defend them in earnest, and do their very best for them. If he doesn’t know them in their most plausible and persuasive form, and doesn’t feel the whole force of the difficulty that the true view of the subject—·his view·—has to encounter and dispose of, he will never really possess the portion of truth that meets and removes that difficulty. Ninety-nine per cent of what are called ‘educated’ men are in this condition, even of those who can argue fluently for their opinions. Perhaps their conclusion is true, but it might be false for all they know ·to the contrary·. They haven’t put themselves in the mental position of those who think differently from them, and considered what such opponents may have to say; and consequently they don’t in any proper

23

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

sense of the word know the doctrine that they themselves proclaim. They don’t know the parts of it that explain and justify the rest. They don’t know the considerations showing that an apparent theoretical conflict can be reconciled, or that of two apparently strong reasons one and not the other ought to be preferred. They are strangers to all •that part of the truth that tips the balance and decides how a completely informed mind should judge; and •that won’t ever be really known except by those who have attended equally and impartially to both sides, and tried to see the reasons for both in the strongest light. This discipline is essential to a real understanding of moral and human subjects—so much so that if any important truth doesn’t have any opponents we must imagine them and supply them with the strongest arguments that the most skillful prosecutor can come up with.

To lessen the force of these considerations, an enemy of free discussion might say this:

There is no need for mankind in general to know and understand all that can be said against or for their opinions by philosophers and theologians. There is no need for common people to be able to expose all the misstatements or fallacies of an ingenious opponent. It is enough if there is always somebody capable of answering them, so that anything that is likely to mislead uneducated persons will be refuted. Simple minds, having been taught the obvious grounds of the truths they have learned, may trust to authority for the rest. They are aware that they have neither knowledge nor talent to resolve every difficulty that can be raised, and can feel secure in the thought that all the difficulties that have been •raised have been (or can be) •answered by those who are specially trained for that task.

What I am up against here are people who don’t demand that •belief in a truth should be accompanied by much •understanding of it. Well, for purposes of argument I shall concede to them that the above line of thought is right—I’ll let them have as much of it as they could possibly claim. Even with that much conceded, the argument for free discussion is in no way weakened. For even this doctrine acknowledges that mankind ought to have a rational assurance that all objections have been satisfactorily answered; and how can they be answered if they haven’t been uttered? Also, how can an answer be known to be satisfactory if the objectors have no opportunity to show that it is not? If not •the public, then at least •the philosophers and theologians who are to resolve the difficulties must become familiar with them in their most challenging form; and this can’t happen unless the difficulties are freely stated and placed in the most advantageous light that they are capable of. The Catholic Church has its own way of dealing with this embarrassing problem. It makes a sweeping distinction between •those who can be permitted to receive its doctrines through becoming convinced of them and •those who must take them on trust. Neither group is allowed any choice as to what they will accept; but the clergy—or such of them as can be fully trusted—are allowed and even encouraged to make themselves acquainted with the arguments of opponents, in order to answer them; so they are permitted to read heretical books. Lay people may not do this without special permission, which is hard to obtain. This system recognizes that it is beneficial for •teachers to know the enemy’s case, but finds a way of combining this with a denial of such knowledge to •the rest of the world—thus giving to the élite more mental culture than it allows to the mass, though not more mental freedom! By this device it succeeds in obtaining the kind of mental superiority that its purposes require; for

24

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

although culture without freedom never made a large and liberal mind, it can make a clever advocate of a cause. But in protestant countries this resource isn’t available, because protestants hold, at least in theory, that the responsibility for the choice of a religion must be borne by each person for himself, and can’t be passed off onto teachers. Besides, in the present state of the world, it is practically impossible that writings that are read by the instructed can be kept from the uninstructed. If mankind’s teachers are to be know all that they ought to know, everything must be free to be written and published without restraint.

Here is something that might be thought:

When the publicly accepted opinions are true, if the harm done by the absence of free discussion of them were merely that men are left ignorant of the grounds of those opinions, this may be an intellectual evil but it isn’t a moral one; it doesn’t affect the value of the opinions so far as their influence on character is concerned.

In fact, however, the absence of discussion leads men to forget not only the •grounds for an opinion but too often also its •meaning. The words in which it is expressed cease to suggest ideas, or suggest only a small portion of the ideas they were originally used to communicate. Instead of a vivid conception and a living belief, there remain only a few phrases learned by heart; or if any part of the meaning is retained it is only the shell and husk of it, the finer essence being lost. This fact fills a great chapter in human history—one that cannot be too earnestly studied and meditated on.

It is illustrated in the experience of almost all ethical doctrines and religious creeds. They are all full of meaning and vitality to those who originate them, and to their immediate disciples. As long as a doctrine or creed is struggling for ascendancy over other creeds, its meaning continues to be felt as strongly as—and perhaps even more strongly than—it was at the outset. Eventually either •it prevails and becomes the general opinion or •its progress stops, in which case it keeps possession of the ground it has gained but doesn’t spread any further. When either of these results has become apparent, controversy about the doctrine slackens and gradually dies away. The doctrine has taken its place as a publicly accepted opinion or as one of the recognized sects or divisions of opinion; most of its present adherents have inherited it rather than being convinced of it by reasons, and they don’t give much thought to the idea of anyone’s being converted from their doctrine to some other, because such conversions happen so rarely. At first they were constantly on the alert, either to defend themselves against the world or to bring the world over to their side; but now they have subsided into a passive state in which they •don’t (if they can help it) listen to arguments against their creed, and •don’t trouble dissentients (if there are any) with arguments in its favour. It is usually at about this stage in its history that the doctrine starts to lose its living power. We often hear the teachers of all creeds lamenting the difficulty of keeping up in the minds of believers a lively awareness of the truth to which they pay lip-service, so that the truth may penetrate their feelings and acquire a real mastery over their conduct. No such difficulty is complained of while the creed is still fighting for its existence; at that stage even the weaker combatants know and feel •what they are fighting for and •how it differs from other doctrines. And at that same stage in any creed’s existence, a good many people may be found who have brought its fundamental principles to bear on all the forms of thought, have weighed and considered them in all their important bearings, and have experienced the full effect on their characters which belief in that creed ought to produce in a mind thoroughly saturated with it.

25

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

But when the creed has come to be hereditary, and to be accepted passively rather than actively—when the mind is no longer as compelled as it once was to exercise its vital powers on the questions that its belief presents to it—there’s a progressive tendency to forget all of the belief except the words expressing it, or to give it a dull and lethargic assent, as though by taking it on trust one freed oneself from any need to make it real in one’s mind, or to test it by personal experience; until it comes to have almost no connection with the person’s inner life. Then there are the cases, so frequent these days as almost to form the majority, in which the creed remains as it were outside the mind, like a hard shell protecting it against anything else that might be directed to the higher parts of our nature; manifesting its power by not letting any fresh and living conviction get in, but itself doing nothing for the mind or heart except standing guard over them to keep them vacant.

Doctrines that are intrinsically fitted to make the deepest impression on the mind can remain in it as dead beliefs, without being ever becoming real in the imagination, the feelings, or the understanding; and an example of the extent to which this can happen is provided by the manner in which the majority of believers hold the doctrines of Christianity. By ‘Christianity’ I here mean what is counted as such by all churches and sects—the maxims and injunctions contained in the New Testament. These are regarded as sacred and accepted as laws by all professing Christians, and yet hardly one Christian in a thousand guides or tests his individual conduct by reference to them. The standard to which he (·the typical Christian·) does refer his conduct is the custom of his nation, his class, or the members of his church. So he has on one hand

a collection of ethical maxims which he believes to have been delivered to him by infallible wisdom as rules for him to govern himself by,

and on the other

a set of everyday judgments and practices, which

•go a certain distance with some of those maxims,

•go a shorter distance with others, •stand in direct opposition to some, and •are—at the bottom line—a compromise between the Christian creed and the interests and suggestions of worldly life.

He pays lip-service to the first of these standards, but the one he actually steers by is the second. All Christians believe •that the blessed are the poor and humble and those who are ill-used by the world; •that it is easier for a camel to pass through the eye of a needle than for a rich man to enter the kingdom of heaven; •that they should not judge lest they be judged; •that they should never swear; •that they should love their neighbour as themselves; •that if someone takes their cloak they should give him their coat also; •that they should take no thought for what the next day will bring; •that if they want to be perfect they should sell all their belongings and give the proceeds of the sale to the poor. They aren’t insincere when they say they believe these things. They do believe them in the way that people ‘believe’ what they have always heard praised and never heard discussed. But in the sense of ‘belief’ that refers to the living belief that regulates conduct, they believe these doctrines up to the point where it is usual to act on them, and no further. The doctrines—taken whole, as undivided lumps—·have two recognised uses·: •to throw at opponents, and •to put forward (when possible) as the reasons for things people do that they think are praiseworthy. But if you reminded them (·i.e. typical Christians·) that the maxims require an infinity of things that they never even think of doing, all you would achieve is being classified with those very unpopular characters who claim to be better than other people. The doctrines have no hold on ordinary

26

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

believers—they aren’t a power in their minds. The believers •have an habitual respect for the sound of them, but •have no feeling that spreads from the words to the meanings, forcing the mind to take them in and make the believer’s conduct conform to the formula. When it’s a question of how to behave, the believer looks around for Mr. A and Mr. B to tell him how far to go in obeying Christ.

We can be sure that with the early Christians the situation was very different from this. If it had then been the way it is now, Christianity would never have expanded from an obscure sect of the despised Hebrews into the religion of the Roman empire. When their enemies said ‘See how these Christians love one another’ (a remark not likely to be made by anybody now), they assuredly had a much livelier sense of the meaning of their creed than they have ever had since. This ·lack of lively inner conviction on the part of most Christians· is probably the main reason why Christianity now makes so little progress in extending its domain, and after eighteen centuries is still mostly confined to Europeans and the descendants of Europeans. Even with strictly religious people who are much in earnest about their doctrines and attach much more meaning to them than do people in general, it commonly happens that this comparatively active religious component in their minds comes from •Calvin or •Knox or some such person much nearer in character to themselves. The sayings of •Christ sit passively in their minds, producing hardly any effect beyond what is caused by merely listening to such amiable and bland words. No doubt there are •many reasons why doctrines that are the badge of one particular sect retain more of their vitality than do ones that are common to all recognized sects, and why teachers take more trouble to keep the meaning of the former alive; but •one reason certainly is that a doctrine that is special to one particular sect is more questioned, and has to be oftener defended against open opponents. Both teachers and learners go to sleep at their post when there is no enemy to be guarded against.

The same thing holds true, generally speaking, of all traditional doctrines—not just those of morals and religion, but also doctrines about what it is prudent to do and how to go about living your life. All languages and literatures are full of general observations on life—what it is, and how to live it—observations that everybody knows, that everybody repeats or hears and agrees to, that are accepted as truisms, but which most people don’t really know the meaning of until experience, generally of a painful kind, makes it a reality to them. It often happens that someone suffering from an unforeseen misfortune or disappointment calls to mind some proverb or common saying that has been familiar to him all his life, and that would have saved him from the calamity if he had ever felt its meaning as he does now. There are indeed reasons for this other than the absence of discussion: there are many truths whose full meaning can’t be realized—·made real in the mind·—until personal experience has brought it home. But even with these, much more of the meaning would have been understood, and what was understood would have been far more deeply impressed on the mind, if the man had been accustomed to hear it argued pro and con by people who did understand it. The fatal tendency of mankind to give up thinking about something when it is no longer doubtful is the cause of half their errors. A contemporary author has well spoken of ‘the deep slumber of a decided opinion’.

You might ask:

Is the absence of unanimity required for •true knowledge? Is it the case that for any part of mankind to realize the truth some other part must persist in error? Does a belief stop being real and living as soon as it is generally accepted—and is a proposition

27

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

never thoroughly understood and felt unless some doubt about it remains? As soon as mankind have unanimously accepted a truth, does the truth perish within them? It has always been thought that the highest aim and best result of improved intelligence is to unite mankind increasingly in the acknowledgment of all important truths; does this intelligence last only as long as it hasn’t achieved its aim? Do the fruits of conquest perish because of the very completeness of the victory?

I affirm no such thing. As mankind improve, the number of doctrines that are no longer disputed or doubted will be constantly on the increase; and the well-being of mankind could almost be measured by the number and importance of the truths that have reached the point of being uncontested. The ending of serious controversy on one question after another is a necessary aspect of the consolidation of opinion; and such consolidation is as healthy in the case of true opinions as it is dangerous and poisonous when the opinions are wrong. But although this gradual lessening of the area of diversity of opinion is ‘necessary’ in both senses of the term—being at once inevitable and absolutely needed—it doesn’t follow that all its consequences are beneficial. The need to explain a truth to its opponents or to defend it against them is an important aid to the intelligent and living grasp of it; and the loss of that aid is a disadvantage in its being universally recognized ·and thus having no opponents·. It isn’t enough to outweigh the benefit of universal recognition of a truth, but still it’s a real drawback. Where this advantage can no longer be had, I would like to see the teachers of mankind trying to provide a substitute for it—some device for making the difficulties of the question as vivid in the learner’s consciousness as if they were being urged by someone trying hard to convert him to an opposing position.

But instead of looking for ways to do this, the teachers have lost the instructive devices they formerly had. The Socratic dialectics [= inquiry through argument and counter-argument], so splendidly exemplified in the dialogues of Plato, were a device of the sort I am recommending. They were essentially a negative discussion of the great questions of philosophy and life, directed with enormous skill to convincing someone who had merely •adopted the commonplaces of publicly accepted opinion that he didn’t •understand the subject, and didn’t yet attach any definite meaning to the doctrines he proclaimed; so that in becoming aware of his ignorance the pupil might be put on the way to attaining a stable belief, resting on a clear grasp both of the meaning of doctrines and of the grounds for them. The formal debates in the universities of the middle ages had a somewhat similar purpose. They were intended to ensure that the pupil understood his own opinion and the opinion opposed to it, and could enforce the grounds of the one and refute those of the other. (The two understandings—of the two opposing opinions—of course go hand in hand.) These •mediaeval debates had indeed an incurable defect, namely that the premises appealed to were taken from authority and not from reason; and they were nothing like as good a discipline for the mind as were •the powerful dialectics that shaped the intellects of Socrates’ companions; but the modern mind owes far more to •both than it is generally willing to admit, and the present methods of education contain nothing that replaces either of them in the slightest. A person who gets all his instruction from teachers or books, even if he resists the continual temptation to settle for cramming [= ‘intensive unreflective last-minute study in preparation for an exam’], is under no compulsion to hear both sides; with the result that it is quite unusual, even among thinkers, for someone to know both sides; and the weakest part of what everybody says

28

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

in defence of his own opinion is what he has prepared as a reply to opponents. It is currently fashionable to belittle negative logic—the kind that points out weaknesses in theory or errors in practice, without establishing positive truths. Such negative criticism would indeed be a pretty poor •final result, but as a •means to attaining any positive knowledge or belief worthy of the name it is enormously valuable; and until people are again systematically trained in it there will be few great thinkers, and a low average level of intellect, in all branches of learning and research except mathematics and the physical sciences. On any other subject a person’s opinions deserve the name of ‘knowledge’ only to the extent that he has—either on his own initiative or forced to it by others—gone through the same mental process that would have been required of him in carrying on an active controversy with opponents. When we don’t have controversy, it is sorely missed and difficult to create artificially; so how absurd it is—how worse than absurd—to deprive oneself of it when it occurs spontaneously! If there are people who dispute a publicly accepted opinion, or who will dispute it if not prevented by law or social pressure, let us thank them for it, open our minds to listen to them, and rejoice that someone will do for us what we otherwise would have to do for ourselves, with much greater labour. (Or, anyway, what we otherwise ought to do if we have any regard for the certainty or the vitality of our convictions.)

There is yet another powerful reason why diversity of opinion can be advantageous—a reason that will hold good until mankind advances to an intellectual level that at present seems incalculably far off. We have so far considered only two possibilities: that •the publicly accepted opinion is false, and therefore some other opinion is true; and that •the publicly accepted opinion is true, but a conflict with the opposite error is essential to a clear grasp and deep feeling of its truth. However, there is a commoner case than either of these, namely: •the conflicting doctrines....share the truth between them, and the minority opinion is needed to provide the remainder of the truth, of which the publicly accepted doctrine captures only a part. On matters other than plain empirical fact, popular opinions are often true but are seldom or never the whole truth. They are a part of the truth—sometimes a large part, sometimes a small—but exaggerated, distorted, and torn apart from other truths that ought to accompany them and set limits to them. Minority opinions, on the other hand, are generally some of these suppressed and neglected truths, bursting the bonds that kept them down and either •seeking reconciliation with the truth contained in the common opinion or •confronting it as enemies and setting themselves up as the whole truth. The latter case has always been the most frequent, because in the human mind one-sidedness has always been the rule and many-sidedness the exception. Hence, even in •revolutions of opinion one part of the truth usually sets while another rises [the comparison is with the setting and rising of the sun in the daily •revolutions of the earth]. Even progress, which ought to add truth to truth, usually only substitutes one partial and incomplete truth for another; and any improvement this brings comes mainly from the fact that the new fragment of truth is more wanted, better suited to the needs of the time, than was the one it displaces. Even when a prevailing opinion is basically true, it will be so partial that every ·rival· opinion that embodies some part of the truth that the other omits ought to be considered precious, no matter how much error and confusion it blends in with its portion of truth. No reasonable person will be indignant because those who force on our notice truths that we would otherwise have overlooked do themselves overlook some of the truths that we see. Rather, a reasonable person will think that so long as

29

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

popular truth is one-sided, it is more desirable than regrettable that unpopular truth should have one-sided defenders too, because they—the one-sided ones—are usually the most energetic and the most likely to compel reluctant attention to the fragment of wisdom that they proclaim as if it were the whole.

Consider how things stood in the eighteenth century:

Nearly all educated people and all the uneducated people who were led by them were lost in admiration of what is called ‘civilization’, and of the marvels of modern science, literature, and philosophy. Greatly exaggerating the unlikeness between the men of modern times and those of ancient times, they cherished the belief that the differences were entirely in their favour.

What a salutary shock they received when the paradoxes of Rousseau exploded like bombshells in their midst! Rousseau’s views broke up the compact mass of one-sided opinion, and forced its elements to recombine in a better form and with additional ingredients. It’s not that the generally accepted opinions were on the whole further from the truth than Rousseau’s were; on the contrary, they were nearer to it, containing more positive truth and very much less error. Nevertheless Rousseau’s doctrine contained a considerable amount of exactly those truths that were lacking from the general opinion; these truths floated down the stream of opinion, and are the deposit that was left behind when the flood subsided. •The superior worth of simplicity of life, •the enervating and demoralizing effect of the constraints and clutter and hypocrisies of artificial society, are •ideas that have never been entirely absent from cultivated minds since Rousseau wrote; and in time they will produce their due effect, though at present they have as much need to be asserted as they ever did—and asserted by deeds, because words on this subject have nearly exhausted their power.

Another example: In politics it is almost a commonplace that a healthy state of political life requires that there be a party of •order or stability and a party of •progress or reform, until one or other of them enlarges its mental grasp enough to become a party equally of •order and of •progress, knowing what is fit to be preserved and what ought to be swept away. Each of these ways of thinking

gets its usefulness from the deficiencies of the other,

but also to a great extent

is kept sane and reasonable by the opposition of the other.

Consider the standing antagonisms of practical life, including: democracy vs. aristocracy, property vs. equality, co-operation vs. competition, luxury vs. abstinence, sociality vs. individuality, liberty vs. discipline, and so on. Unless opinions favourable to each side of each of these are expressed with equal freedom and pressed and defended with equal talent and energy, there is no chance of both the conflicting elements obtaining their due; one scale is sure to go up and the other down. In the great practical concerns of life, truth is very much a matter of reconciling and combining opposites—so much so that few people have minds that are capacious and impartial enough to make the adjustment anything like correctly, so that it has to be made by the rough process of a struggle between combatants fighting under hostile banners. With any of the great open questions I have listed, if either of the two rival opinions has a better claim than the other to be (not merely tolerated but) encouraged and countenanced, it is the one that happens to be the minority opinion at a given time and place. That is the one that for the time being represents the neglected interests, the aspect of human well-being that is in danger of obtaining less than its share. I am aware that in this country

30

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

now there is no intolerance of differences of opinion on most of these topics. I bring them forward just as unquestionable examples of the universal fact that in the existing state of the human intellect the only chance of fair play for all sides of the truth is through diversity of opinion. Even when the world is almost unanimous on some subject and is right about it, people who disagree—if there are any to be found—probably have something to say for themselves that is worth hearing, and truth would lose something by their silence.

It may be objected:

But some publicly accepted principles, especially on the highest and most vital subjects, are more than half-truths. Christian morality, for instance, is the whole truth on that subject and anyone who teaches a morality that varies from it is wholly in error.

This is in practice the most important of all the cases, so it none can be better for testing the general maxim. But before pronouncing on what Christian morality is or is not, it would be desirable to decide what ‘Christian morality’ means. If it means the morality of the New Testament, I am surprised that anyone who knows about it from the book itself can suppose that it was announced or intended as a complete doctrine of morals. The gospel always refers to a pre-existing morality, and confines its precepts to matters in respect of which that morality was to be corrected or superseded by a wider and higher one. Also, these precepts are expressed in extremely general terms, and often can’t possibly be interpreted literally; they have the impressiveness of poetry or eloquence rather than the precision of legislation. It has never been possible to extract a body of ethical doctrine from this without eking it out from •the Old Testament, that is, from •a system that is elaborate enough but in many respects barbarous, and intended only for a barbarous people. St. Paul, a declared enemy to this Judaic mode of interpreting the doctrine of his master and of filling in the gaps in it, also assumes a pre-existing morality ·but a different one·, namely that of the Greeks and Romans; and his advice to Christians is largely a system of coming to terms with that, even to the extent of seeming to endorse slavery. What is called ‘Christian morality’, but should rather be termed ‘theological morality’, was not the work of Christ or the apostles, but is of much later origin. It was gradually built up by the Catholic Church of the first five centuries, and though moderns and protestants don’t automatically accept it as authoritative, they have modified it much less than might have been expected. For the most part, indeed, they have contented themselves with •cutting off the parts that had been added to it in the middle ages and •replacing those by fresh additions selected according to the character and tendencies of the sect in question. I would be the last person to deny that mankind owes a great debt to this morality and to its early teachers; but I don’t hesitate to say that in many important respects it is incomplete and one-sided, and that human affairs would have been in a worse condition than they now are if it hadn’t been that ideas and feelings from outside this morality contributed to the formation of European life and character. Christian morality (so called) has all the marks of a reaction; it is to a large extent protest against paganism. Its ideal is

•innocence rather than nobleness, and

•abstinence from evil rather than energetic pursuit of good.

And this means that its ideal is

•negative rather than positive, and

•passive rather than active.

It has been well said that in its precepts ‘thou shalt not’ predominates unduly over ‘thou shalt’. In its horror of the pleasures of the senses it made an idol of asceticism,

31

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

which has been gradually trimmed down into a mere idol of rule-following. In holding out the hope of heaven and the threat of hell as the official and appropriate motives for a virtuous life, this morality falls far below the best of the ancients, and does what it can to make human morality essentially selfish, by disconnecting each man’s feelings of duty from the •interests of his fellow-creatures except so far as a •self-interested inducement is offered to him for attending to them. It is essentially a doctrine of passive obedience; it teaches obedience to all established governmental authorities; not that they are to be actively obeyed when they command something that •religion forbids, but they aren’t to be resisted—let alone rebelled against—for any amount of wrong to •ourselves. And while in the morality of the best pagan nations there’s a place for •duty to the state—a disproportionate place, even, infringing on the just liberty of the individual—in purely Christian ethics •that grand department of duty is scarcely noticed or acknowledged. [Mill’s point is that Christian ethics enjoins obedience to the state, but not self-directed positive service to the state.] It is in the Koran, not the New Testament, that we read the maxim ‘A ruler who appoints any man to an office when there is in his dominions another man better qualified for it sins against God and against the state.’ What little recognition the idea of •obligation to the public obtains in modern morality is derived from Greek and Roman sources, not from Christian ones; just as in the morality of private life whatever there is in the way of magnanimity, high-mindedness, personal dignity, even the sense of honour, is derived from the purely human and not the religious part of our education, and never could have grown out of a standard of ethics in which the only officially recognized value is that of obedience.

I fully concede that there could be forms of Christian ethics that were free of these defects, and that Christian ethics could be made consistent with the many requisites of a complete moral doctrine that it doesn’t actually contain. And I would say this even more strenuously about the doctrines and precepts of Christ himself. I believe that the sayings of Christ •are everything they were apparently •intended to be; that they can be reconciled with anything that a comprehensive morality requires; that everything that is excellent in ethics can be brought within their scope with no more violence to their language than has been done to it by all who have tried to deduce from them any practical system of conduct whatever. But it is quite consistent with this to believe that the sayings of Christ contain only a part of the truth and weren’t meant to contain more; that many essential elements of the highest morality

•aren’t provided for (or intended to be provided for) in the recorded sayings of the founder of Christianity, and

•have been entirely thrown aside in the system of ethics that the Christian church has erected on the basis of those sayings.

So I think it a great error to persist in trying to find in Christian doctrine the complete rule for our guidance which its author intended that doctrine to •endorse and •enforce but only partially to •provide. I also believe that this narrow theory is becoming a grave practical evil, detracting greatly from the value of the moral training and instruction that so many well-meaning people are now at last working to promote. These people try to form minds on an exclusively religious pattern, discarding those non-religious standards that used to coexist with and supplement Christian ethics, receiving some of its spirit and giving it some of theirs. I greatly fear that this will result—that it is now resulting—in a low, abject, servile type of character, one that may submit itself to what it thinks is the Supreme Will but can’t •rise to

32

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

or •feel for the conception of Supreme Goodness. The moral regeneration of mankind, I believe, will require that Christian ethics exist side by side with other ethical principles that can’t be developed from exclusively Christian sources. The Christian system is no exception to the rule that in an imperfect state of the human mind the interests of truth require a diversity of opinions. It isn’t necessary that in starting to attend to moral truths not contained in Christianity men should ignore any of the ones it does contain. Such prejudice or oversight, when it occurs, is altogether bad. Still, we can’t hope to avoid it altogether, and it must be regarded as the price to be paid for an incalculable good. When one part of the truth is claimed to be the whole of it, this must and ought to be protested against; and if the protestors’ sense of the unfairness of this makes them unjust in their turn, this one-sidedness may be lamented just as the other was. But it must be tolerated. If Christians want to teach unbelievers to be fair to Christianity, they should themselves be fair to unbelief. Much of the noblest and most valuable moral teaching has been the work not only of men who didn’t know the Christian faith but also of men who knew and rejected it; anyone who has the most ordinary acquaintance with literary history knows this; running away from it can’t do the truth any service.

I don’t claim that the most unlimited use of freedom in expressing all possible opinions would put an end to the evils of religious or philosophical sectarianism. Every truth that men with limited minds are in earnest about is sure to be •asserted, •taught, and in many ways even •acted on as if no other truth existed in the world, or anyway none that could limit or restrict the first. All opinions tend to become sectarian, and I admit that very free discussion is not a cure for this. Indeed, discussion heightens and worsens sectarianism; truth that ought to be seen may be rejected all the more violently because it is proclaimed by people regarded ·by the sectarians· as opponents. But it is not on the impassioned partisan, but rather on the calmer and more disinterested [= ‘not self -interested’] bystander, that this collision of opinions has a healthy effect. The really threatening evil is not •the violent conflict between parts of the truth, but •the quiet suppression of half of it. When people are forced to listen to both sides, there are grounds for hope; it’s when they attend to only one side that errors harden into prejudices, and truth itself stops acting like truth because it comes to be exaggerated into falsehood. Very few people have the mental capacity to

sit in intelligent judgment between two sides of a question, of which only one is represented by an advocate.

·Because of the scarcity of people with that skill·, truth has no chance except to the extent that every side of it, every opinion that embodies any fraction of it, has advocates who can get themselves listened to.

I have argued that freedom of opinion, and freedom of the expression of opinion, are needed for the mental well-being of mankind (on which all other kinds of well-being depend). I now briefly repeat my four distinct reasons for this view. 1 An opinion that is compelled to silence may, for all we can certainly know, be true. To deny this is to assume our own infallibility. 2 Even when the silenced opinion is an error, it can and very commonly does contain a portion of the truth; and since the general or prevailing opinion on any topic is rarely if ever the whole truth ·about it·, it is only through the collision of conflicting opinions that the remainder of the truth has any chance of being supplied. Thirdly, even if the publicly accepted opinion is not only true but is the whole truth ·on the subject in question·, unless it is vigorously and earnestly disputed most of those who accept it will have it

33

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

in the manner ·merely· of a prejudice, with little grasp or sense of what its rational grounds are. And also (this being my fourth argument), the meaning of the doctrine itself will be in danger of being lost or weakened, and deprived of its vital effect on character and conduct. It will become a mere formal pronouncement, effective not in doing any good but only in cluttering up the ground and preventing the growth of any real and heartfelt conviction from reason or personal experience.

Before leaving the topic of freedom of opinion, I should discuss the view that the free expression of all opinions should be permitted on condition that the expression is temperate and doesn’t exceed the bounds of fair discussion. How are these supposed bounds to be fixed? Is the criterion that the bounds have been passed if those whose opinion is attacked are offended? ·That would be useless, because· experience shows that offence is given whenever the attack is telling and powerful, and that every opponent who pushes them hard and whom they find it difficult to answer appears to them (if he shows any strong feeling on the subject) to be an intemperate opponent. This fixing of the boundaries to temperateness could be discussed at length, and it is an important consideration from a practical point of view; but ·I shan’t pursue it any further on its own, because· it merges into a more fundamental objection ·to the demand for temperateness in debate·. Undoubtedly the manner of asserting an opinion, even a true one, may be very objectionable and may rightly be severely criticized. But the principal offences of this kind—·i.e. offences in the manner of conducting a debate·—are such that it is usually impossible to convict the offender unless he accidentally gives himself away. The most serious of them is to argue invalidly, to suppress facts or arguments, to misstate the elements of the case, or misrepresent the opposite opinion. But all this is continually done—often to an extreme—in perfect good faith by people who aren’t regarded as ignorant or incompetent (and in many other respects may not be ignorant or incompetent); so that there are seldom adequate grounds for a conscientious accusation of morally culpable misrepresentation; and still less could the law presume to interfere with this kind of misconduct in controversy. As for what is commonly meant by ‘intemperate’ discussion, namely invective, sarcasm, personal insults, and the like: the denunciation of these weapons ·of debate· would deserve more sympathy if it were ever proposed to forbid them equally to both sides; but ·in practice· it is desired to restrain the use of them only against the prevailing opinion. Against the unprevailing opinion they may not only be used without general disapproval but will be likely to lead to the person’s being praised for his honest zeal and righteous indignation. Yet the harm that is done by these ·weapons of debate· is greatest when they are used against the comparatively defenceless; and whatever unfair advantage an opinion can get from being defended in this way goes almost exclusively to publicly accepted opinions. The worst offence of this kind that can be committed by a controversialist is to brand those who hold the contrary opinion as bad and immoral men. Those who hold some unpopular opinion are especially vulnerable to slander of this sort, because usually they are few and uninfluential, and nobody else feels much interest in seeing justice done to them. But from the nature of the case they can’t use this weapon against defenders of a prevailing opinion: it wouldn’t be safe for them to use it, and anyway it wouldn’t achieve anything for them and would merely reflect back on their own cause. In general, opinions contrary to those that are commonly accepted can obtain a hearing only by carefully moderate language and the most cautious avoidance of unnecessary offence, from which they hardly

34

Liberty John Stuart Mill 2: Liberty of thought and discussion

ever deviate even slightly without losing ground; whereas unmeasured abuse employed on the side of the prevailing opinion really does deter people from proclaiming contrary opinions and from listening to those who proclaim them. In the interests of truth and justice, therefore, it is far more important to restrain this employment of abusive language than the other; for example, if we had to choose, there would be much more need to discourage offensive attacks on unbelief than offensive attacks on religion. But it is obvious that •law and •authority have no business restraining either of them. And here is what •opinion should do, ·i.e. what we should all do·. We ought to base our verdict on the circumstances of the individual case, condemning anyone—on either side of the argument—whose mode of advocacy shows lack of candour, or malignity, bigotry or intolerance of feeling. But we shouldn’t infer these vices from the side that a person takes ·in the debate·, even if it is the opposite side to our own. And we should give deserved honour to everyone, whatever opinion he may hold, who has the •calmness to see and the •honesty to state what his opponents and their opinions really are, exaggerating nothing to their discredit and keeping back nothing that might be thought to count in their favour. This is the real morality of public discussion; and even if it is often violated, I am happy to think that there are many controversialists who to a great extent observe it and even more who conscientiously try to do so.

35

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

Chapter 3: Individuality—one of the elements of well-being

I have presented •the reasons that make it imperative that human beings should be free to form opinions and to express them openly, and •the pernicious consequences to the intellectual nature of man (and through that to his moral nature) unless this freedom is either granted or claimed in spite of being prohibited. Now let us see whether those same reasons don’t require that men should be free to act on their opinions—to carry them out in their lives, without physical or moral hindrance from their fellow-men, so long as they are acting at their own risk and peril. This last proviso is of course indispensable. No-one claims that actions should be as free as opinions. On the contrary, even opinions lose their immunity when the circumstances in which they are expressed are such that merely expressing them is a positive incitement to some harmful act. The opinion that corn-dealers are starvers of the poor ought to be allowed to pass freely when it is simply presented to the world in print; but someone can justly be punished for announcing it orally or passing it out on a placard to an excited mob that has gathered in front of a corn-dealer’s house. (Another example might be the opinion that private property is robbery.) Acts of any kind that harm others without justifiable cause may be—and in the more important cases absolutely must be—brought under control, either by adverse opinion or (when necessary) by active interference. The liberty of the individual must be limited by this:

He must not adversely affect other people.

[Mill’s actual words: ‘He must not make himself a nuisance to other people.’] But if he refrains from interfering with others in things that are their own concern, and merely acts according to his own inclination and judgment in things that concern himself, he should be freely allowed to put his opinions into practice at his own cost; and the reasons for this are the very ones that show that opinion should be free:

•mankind are not infallible;

•their truths are mostly only half-truths;

•uniformity of opinion is not desirable unless it results from the fullest and freest comparison of opposite opinions;

•diversity ·of opinion· is a good thing, not a bad one, until mankind become much more able than at present to recognize all sides of the truth.

These principles apply as much to men’s conduct as to their opinions. Just as it is useful that while mankind are imperfect there should be different opinions, so is it that •there should be different experiments in living; that •different kinds of personal character should be given free scope as long as they don’t injure others; and that •the value of different ways of life should tried out in practice when anyone wants to try them. It is desirable, in short, that in matters that don’t primarily concern others individuality should assert itself. When a person’s conduct is ruled not by his character but by the traditions or customs of others, one of the principal ingredients of human happiness—and the chief ingredient of individual and social progress—is lacking.

The greatest difficulty one meets in maintaining this principle doesn’t come from •people’s views about the means to an acknowledged end, but from •their indifference to the end in question. If it were ·generally· felt

that the free development of individuality is a leading essential of well-being; that it isn’t merely something that comes along with all that we mean by the terms

36

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

‘civilization’, ‘instruction’, ‘education’ and ‘culture’, but is itself a necessary part and precondition of all those things,

there would be no danger of liberty’s being undervalued, and no great difficult about settling the boundaries between it and social control. The trouble is that in the thinking of most people individual spontaneity is hardly recognized as having any intrinsic value, or as deserving any respect on its own account. The majority are satisfied with the ways of mankind as they now are (·of course·, for it is they who make them what they are!), and they can’t understand why those ways shouldn’t be good enough for everybody. As for moral and social reformers—·who by definition are not satisfied with the ways of mankind as they now are·—the majority of them don’t have spontaneity as any part of their ideal; rather, they look on it with resentment, as a troublesome and perhaps rebellious obstruction to the general acceptance of what these reformers themselves think would be best for mankind. Wilhelm von Humboldt, so eminent both for his learning and as a politician, based one of his works on the thesis that

•the end of man, or that which is prescribed by the eternal or immutable dictates of reason and not suggested by vague and transient desires, is the highest and most harmonious development of his powers to a complete and consistent whole;

that therefore,

•that towards which every human being must ceaselessly direct his efforts, and on which especially those who design to influence their fellow-men must ever keep their eyes, is the individuality of power and development;

that •for this two things are needed, ‘freedom, and a variety of situations’; and that •from the combination of these arise ‘individual vigour and great diversity’, which combine themselves in ‘originality’ [Wilhelm von Humboldt, The Sphere and Duties of Government]. Few people outside Germany even understood what he meant!

And yet, although most people are unaccustomed to a doctrine like that of von Humboldt, and surprised to find anyone attaching so high a value to individuality, one has to think that the issue—·the difference between the majority view and von Humboldt’s·—can only be one of degree. •·Looking at it from one side·: No-one’s idea of excellence in conduct is that people should do absolutely nothing but copy one another. No-one would assert that people ought not to put into their way of life, and into their handling of their affairs, any mark whatever of their own judgment or of their own individual character. •On the other hand, it would be absurd to ·value individuality so absolutely as to· claim that people ought to live as if nothing whatever had been known in the world before they came into it; as if experience so far had done nothing towards showing that one way of life or course of conduct is preferable to another. Nobody denies that people should be taught and trained in youth so that they can know what has been learned from human experience and can benefit from it. But when a human being has arrived at the maturity of his faculties, it is his privilege—and indeed his proper role—to use and interpret experience in his own way. It is for him to find out what part of recorded experience is properly applicable to his own circumstances and character. The traditions and customs of other people provide some evidence of what their experience has taught them—evidence that has some weight, and thus has a claim to his deference. But ·there are three reasons for not giving it the final decision about how he should live his life·. In the first place, •those people’s experience may be too narrow, or they may not have interpreted it

37

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

rightly. Secondly, •their interpretation of their experience may be correct but unsuitable to him. Customs are made for customary circumstances and customary character; and his circumstances or his character may be uncustomary. Thirdly, •even when the customs are good in themselves and are suitable to him, still ·he ought not· to conform to custom as such, ·because that· doesn’t educate or develop in him any of the qualities that are the distinctive endowment of a human being. The human faculties of perception, judgment, discriminative feeling, mental activity, and even moral preference are exercised only in making choices. He who does something because it is the custom doesn’t make a choice. He gains no practice either in seeing what is best or in wanting it. Like our muscular powers, our mental and moral powers are improved only by being used. You don’t bring your faculties into play by •doing something merely because others do it, any more than by •believing something only because others believe it. If the reasons for an opinion are not conclusive in your way of thinking, your reason can’t be strengthened by your adopting the opinion, and is likely instead to be weakened; and if the reasons for acting in a certain way are not in harmony with your feelings and character, acting in that way is contributing towards making your feelings and character inert and slack rather than active and energetic. (I am here setting aside cases where personal affections or the rights of others come into the picture.)

He who lets the world (or his own portion of it) choose his plan of life for him doesn’t need any faculty other than the ape-like ability to imitate. He who chooses his plan for himself employs all his faculties. He must use

observation to see,

reasoning and judgment to foresee,

activity to gather materials for decision,

discrimination to decide,

and, when he has decided,

firmness and self-control to keep to his deliberate decision.

And how much he requires and uses these abilities depends directly on how much of his conduct is determined according to his own judgment and feelings. He might be guided in some good path, and kept out of harm’s way, without any of these things. But ·in that case· what will be his comparative worth as a human being? It really does matter not only what men do but also what sort of men they are that do it. Among the works of man that human life is rightly employed in perfecting and beautifying, surely the most important is man himself. Supposing it were possible to get houses built, corn grown, battles fought, cases tried, and even churches erected and prayers said, by machinery—by automatons in human form—it would be a considerable loss to accept automatons in exchange for men and women, even the men and women who at present inhabit the more civilized parts of the world, who are poor specimens of what nature can and will produce. Human nature is not a machine to be built on the basis of a blueprint, and set to do exactly the work prescribed for it; rather, it is a tree that needs to grow and develop itself on all sides, according to the tendency of the inward forces that make it a living thing.

It will probably be conceded that it is desirable for people to exercise their understandings, and that an intelligent following of custom or even occasionally an intelligent deviation from custom is better than following custom in a blind and mechanical way. To a certain extent it is admitted that our •understanding should be our own. But there isn’t the same willingness to admit that our •desires and impulses should likewise be our own, or to admit that it is anything but a peril and a snare to possess impulses of our own, unless they are extremely weak. Yet desires and impulses

38

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

are as much a part of a perfect human being as beliefs and restraints. Strong impulses are perilous only when they aren’t properly balanced—i.e. when one set of aims and inclinations is developed into strength while others that ought to coexist with them remain weak and inactive. Men act badly not because their desires are strong but because their consciences are weak. There is no natural connection between strong impulses and a weak conscience. The natural connection is the other way. [Those two sentences are as Mill wrote them. Perhaps he means that strong impulses tend to produce not weak consciences but strong ones.] To say that •one person’s desires and feelings are stronger and more various than those of someone else is merely to say that •he has more of the raw material of human nature, and is therefore capable perhaps of more evil but certainly of more good. Strong impulses are but another name for energy. Energy can be turned to bad uses, but more good can always come from an energetic nature than from a slack and impassive one. Those who have most natural feeling are always those whose cultivated feelings—·the ones developed through education, experience, and thought·—can also be made the strongest. The •strong susceptibilities that make personal impulses vivid and powerful are also the source of the most passionate love of virtue and the sternest self-control. Society does its duty and protects its interests by developing •these, not by rejecting the stuff of which heroes are made because it doesn’t know how to make them! A person whose desires and impulses are his own—expressing his own nature as it has been developed and modified by his own culture—is said to have a character. (One whose desires and impulses are not his own doesn’t have a character, any more than a steam-engine does.) If the impulses are not only his but are strong, and are under the control of a strong will, then he has an energetic character. If you think that individuality of desires and impulses shouldn’t be encouraged to unfold itself, you must maintain that society doesn’t need strong natures—that it isn’t the better for containing many people who have much character—and that a high average level of energy is not desirable.

In some early states of society, these forces ·of high-level individual energy· were too far ahead of society’s power at that time to discipline and control them. There was a time when the element of spontaneity and individuality was excessive, and social forces had a hard struggle with it. The difficulty then was to induce men with strong bodies or minds to obey any rules that required them to control their impulses. To overcome this difficulty, law and discipline behaved like the Popes in their struggle against the Emperors: they asserted a power over the whole man, claiming to control all his life in order to control his character, which society hadn’t found any other sufficient means of binding. But society now has the upper hand over individuality; and the danger that threatens human nature is not too much but too little in the way of personal impulses and preferences. Things have vastly changed since the time when the passions of those who were strong (through their rank or position, or through their personal qualities) were in a state of habitual rebellion against laws and ordinances, and had to be strictly held down so that people within their reach might enjoy a little security. In our times, from the highest class of society down to the lowest, everyone lives as though under the eye of a hostile and dreaded censorship. Not only in what concerns others but in what concerns only themselves, the individual or the family don’t ask themselves:

what do I prefer? or

what would suit my character and disposition? or

what would allow the best and highest in me to have fair play, and enable it to grow and thrive?

39

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

They ask themselves:

what is suitable to my position?

what is usually done by people in my position and economic level?

or (worse still)

what is usually done by people whose position and circumstances are superior to mine?

I don’t mean that they choose what is customary in preference to what suits their own inclination. It doesn’t occur to them to have any inclination except to do what is customary. Thus the mind itself is bent under the yoke. Even in what people do for pleasure, conformity is the first thing they think of; they like in crowds [think of this as on a par with ‘they walk in crowds’]; they exercise choice only among things that are commonly done; they shun peculiarity of taste and eccentricity of conduct as much as they shun crimes. Eventually, by not following their own nature they come to have no nature to follow: their human capacities are withered and starved; they become incapable of any strong wishes or natural pleasures, and are generally without either •opinions or •feelings that are home-grown and properly theirs. Now is this the desirable condition of human nature?

It is so on the Calvinistic theory. According to it:

The one great offence of man is self-will. Obedience contains all the good of which humanity is capable. You have no choice; you must do this and nothing else; ‘whatever isn’t a duty is a sin’. Human nature is radically corrupt, so there is no redemption for anyone until human nature is killed within him.

To someone who holds this theory of life,

there is nothing wrong with crushing out any of the human faculties, capacities, and susceptibilities. The only capacity man needs is a capacity to surrender himself to the will of God; and if he uses any of •his faculties for any purpose but to obey that supposed will more effectively, he is better without •them.

That is the theory of Calvinism; and it is held in a milder form by many who don’t consider themselves Calvinists. The mildness consists in a less ascetic interpretation to the alleged will of God. They hold that it is his will that mankind should gratify some of their inclinations; not of course in the way they themselves prefer, but in the way of obedience—i.e. in a way prescribed to them by authority, and therefore inevitably the same for all. ·The crucial point about this ‘milder’ form of Calvinism is that it still doesn’t allow for individuality of character·.

In some such insidious [= ‘sneaky’] form as this, there is at present a strong tendency to ·adopt· this narrow theory of life and the pinched and hidebound type of human character that it favours. No doubt many people sincerely think that human beings thus cramped and dwarfed are as their maker designed them to be; just as many have thought that trees with all their lower branches removed or clipped into figures of animals are much finer than in their natural state. But if it is any part of religion to believe that man was made by a good Being, it is more consistent with that faith to believe •that this Being gave humans all their faculties to be developed and unfolded, not rooted out and incinerated, and •that he takes delight in every advance his creatures make towards the ideal of which they are capable, every increase in their ability to understand, to act, or to enjoy. According to the Calvinistic conception of humanity, we had our nature bestowed on us purely in order to have it stamped out. There is a different ideal of human excellence from that. ‘Pagan self-assertion’ is one of the elements of human worth, as well as ‘Christian self-denial’ (I take the phrases from John Sterling’s Essays). There is a •Greek ideal of self-development, which the Platonic and Christian

40

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

ideal of self-government blends with but does not supersede. It may be better to be a John Knox than an Alcibiades, but it is better to be a •Pericles than either; and if we had a Pericles today, he would have about him every good that John Knox had.

The way to make •human beings become something noble and beautiful to see and think about is not by wearing down into uniformity all that is individual in them but rather by cultivating it and enabling it to grow, within the limits imposed by the rights and interests of others.... And that is also the way to make •human life become rich, diversified, and animating, furnishing more abundant nourishment for high thoughts and elevating feelings, and strengthening the tie that binds every individual to the ·human· race by making the race infinitely better worth belonging to. The more each person develops his individuality, the more valuable he becomes to himself, and thus the more capable of being valuable to others. There is a greater fullness of life about his own existence, and when there is more life in the units there is more in the mass that is composed of them. There has to be as much compression ·of the mass· as is necessary to prevent the stronger specimens of human nature from encroaching on the rights of others, but there is ample compensation for this even from the point of view of human development. The means of development that the individual loses by being prevented from gratifying his inclinations at the expense of others is chiefly obtained at the expense of the development of other people, ·so that this lessening of his development may produce an over-all gain in human development·. And even for himself there is ·really no net loss, because· what is suppressed in him in the interests of others is balanced by the better development of the social part of his nature, which is made possible by the restraint put on the selfish part. Being held to rigid rules of justice for the sake of others develops the feelings and capacities that aim at the good of others. But being restrained in things that don’t affect their good—restrained merely by their displeasure—develops nothing valuable except such force of character as may develop in •resisting the restraint. If the restraint is •accepted, it dulls and blunts the person’s whole nature. To give any fair play to the nature of each person, it is essential that different people should be allowed to lead different lives. Historical periods have been noteworthy to posterity in proportion to how widely they have allowed this. Even despotism doesn’t produce its worst effects so long as individuality exists under it; and whatever crushes individuality is despotism, whatever name it is given and whether it claims to be enforcing the will of God or the commands of men.

Having said that individuality is the same thing as development, and that the cultivation of individuality is the only thing that does or can produce well-developed human beings, I might here close the argument. For what more or better can be said of any condition of human affairs than that it brings human beings themselves nearer to the best they can be? or what worse can be said of any obstruction to good than that it prevents this? Doubtless, however, these considerations won’t be enough to convince those who most need convincing. So I need also to show that these developed human beings are of some use to undeveloped ones—to point out, to those who don’t want liberty and wouldn’t avail themselves of it ·if they could·, that they may be rewarded in some way they can understand for freely allowing other people to make use of liberty.

In the first place, then, I suggest that those who don’t want liberty might possibly learn something from the exercise of liberty by those who do want it. No-one will deny that originality is a valuable element in human affairs.

41

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

There is always need for people not only •to discover new truths and point out when a former truth is true no longer, but also •to start new practices and to set the example of more enlightened conduct and of better taste and sense in human life. Someone who denied this would have to think that the world has already attained perfection in all its ways and practices! Admittedly, not everyone is able to provide this benefit; there are few people—a small fragment of the whole of mankind—whose experiments ·in living·, if adopted by others, would be likely to be an improvement on established practice. But these few are the salt of the earth; without them, human life would become a stagnant pool. I’m talking not only about the ones who introduce good things that didn’t exist before, but also about those who keep alive the good things that already exist. If there were nothing new to be done, would human intellect cease to be necessary? Would it be a reason why those who do the old things should forget why they are done, and do them like cattle rather than like human beings? There is only too great a tendency for even the best beliefs and practices to degenerate into •something mechanical; and unless there were a succession of people whose ever-recurring originality prevents the grounds of those beliefs and practices from becoming merely traditional, such •dead matter wouldn’t survive the smallest jolt from anything really alive, and there would be no reason why civilization shouldn’t die out as did the Byzantine Empire. It’s true that persons of genius are and probably always will be a small minority; but in order to have them we must preserve the soil in which they grow. [In Mill’s time, ‘genius’ meant something like ‘high intelligence combined with creative imagination’—something like what it means today, but not quite as strong.] Genius can breathe freely only in an atmosphere of freedom. Persons of genius are by definition more individual than other people—and therefore less able to squeeze themselves, without being harmed, into any of the small number of moulds that society provides in order to save its members the trouble of forming their own character. If out of timidity they consent to be forced into one of these moulds, and to let all that part of themselves that can’t expand under the pressure remain unexpanded, society won’t gain much from their genius. If they are of a strong character and break their fetters, they become a target for the society that hasn’t succeeded in reducing them to something commonplace, to point at with solemn warning as ‘wild’, ‘erratic’, and so on; like complaining against the Niagara river because it doesn’t flow smoothly between its banks like a Dutch canal.

When I insist so emphatically on the importance of genius, and the need to allow it to unfold itself freely both in thought and in practice, I’m well aware •that no-one will deny this position in theory, and also •that almost everyone is really totally indifferent to it. People think genius a fine thing if it enables a man to write an exciting poem or paint a picture. But in the true sense of ‘genius’, that of originality in thought and action, though no-one says that it isn’t a thing to be admired, most people secretly think they can do very well without it. This, alas, is too natural to be wondered at. Originality is the one thing that unoriginal minds cannot feel the use of. They can’t see what it is to do for them—how could they? If they could see what it would do for them it wouldn’t be originality. The first thing that originality has to do for them is to open their eyes; and if they got their eyes fully open, they too would have a chance of being original. Meanwhile, recollecting that nothing was ever yet done that someone didn’t do first, and that all good things that exist are the fruits of originality, let them—·the unoriginal people·—•be modest enough to believe that there is something still left for originality to accomplish,

42

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

and •assure themselves that the less conscious they are of their lack of originality the greater is their need for it.

In sober truth, whatever may be said or even done to honour real or supposed mental superiority, the general tendency of things throughout the world is to render mediocrity the dominant power among mankind. In ancient history, in the middle ages, and to a lessening extent through the long transition from feudal times to the present, the individual was a power in himself; and if he had either great talents or a high social position he was a considerable power. These days individuals are lost in the crowd. In politics it almost goes without saying that public opinion now rules the world. The only power that deserves the name is that of the masses, and of governments when they act out the tendencies and instincts of the masses. This is as true in the •moral and social relations of private life as in •public transactions. Those whose opinions go by the name of ‘public opinion’ are not the same sort of public in every country: in America they are the whole white population, in England chiefly the middle class. But they are always a mass, that is to say, collective mediocrity. And a still greater novelty of the present age is this: the mass don’t now take their opinions from dignitaries in church or state, from recognized leaders, or from books. Their thinking is done for them by men much like themselves, addressing them or speaking in their name on the spur of the moment, through the newspapers. I’m not complaining of all this. I don’t assert that anything better is generally compatible with the present low state of the human mind. But that doesn’t stop the government of mediocrity from being mediocre government. No government by democracy or a numerous aristocracy, either in its political acts or in the opinions, qualities, and tone of mind [Mill’s phrase] that it encourages, ever did or could rise above mediocrity, except in so far as the all-powerful •Many have let themselves be guided (which in their best times they always have done) by the advice and influence of a more highly gifted and instructed •One or •Few. All wise or noble things are and must be started by individuals; generally by some one individual. The honour and glory of the average man is that he is capable of following that start, that he can respond internally to wise and noble things and be led to them with his eyes open. I am not endorsing the sort of ‘hero-worship’ that applauds the strong man of genius for forcibly taking over the government of the world and making it do his bidding in spite of itself. All he is entitled to is freedom to point out the way. The power of compelling others to follow it is not only inconsistent with the freedom and development of everyone else but is also corrupting to the strong man himself. However, at a time when the opinions of masses of merely average men have become or are becoming the dominant power, it does seem that what is needed as a counter-weight and corrective to that tendency is more and more conspicuous individuality on the part of those who stand at the higher levels of thought. It is especially in these circumstances that exceptional individuals, instead of being deterred, should be encouraged to act differently from the mass. At other times there was no advantage in their doing so, unless they acted not only differently but better. In the present age the mere example of non-conformity, the mere refusal to bend the knee to custom, is itself a service ·even if the way of life it leads to is not better than than that of the mass but only different from it·. Precisely because the tyranny of ·public· opinion works so as to make eccentricity a fault, it is desirable, in order to break through that tyranny, that people should be eccentric. There has always been plenty of eccentricity when and where there has been plenty of strength of character; and the amount of eccentricity in a society has generally been proportional to the amount

43

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

of genius, mental vigour, and moral courage the society contained. That so few now dare to be eccentric marks the chief danger of the time.

I have said that it is important to give the freest possible scope to •uncustomary things, so that in due course some of these may turn out to be fit to be converted into •customs. But independence of action and disregard of custom don’t deserve encouragement only because they may lead to better ways of action and customs more worthy of general adoption; and people of decided mental superiority are not the only ones with a just claim to carry on their lives in their own way. There is no reason why all human lives should be constructed on some one pattern or some small number of patterns. If a person has even a moderate amount of common sense and experience, his own way of planning his way of life is the best, not because it is the best in itself but because it is his own way. Human beings are not like sheep; and even sheep aren’t indistinguishably alike. A man can’t get a coat or a pair of boots to fit him unless they are either made to his measure or he has a whole warehouse full or coats or boots to choose from. Well, is it easier to fit him with a life than with a coat? Are human beings more like one another in their whole physical and spiritual make-up than in the shape of their feet? If it were only that people differ in their tastes, that would be reason enough for not trying to fit them all into one mould. But different people also need different conditions for their spiritual development; they can’t all exist healthily in the same •moral atmosphere and climate any more than all plants can flourish in the same •physical climate. The very things that help one person to develop his higher nature hinder another from doing so. A way of life that is a healthy excitement to one person, keeping all his faculties of action and enjoyment in their best order, is to another a distracting burden that suspends or crushes all his inner life. Such are the differences among human beings in their sources of pleasure, their susceptibilities to pain, and the operation on them of different physical and moral forces, that unless there is a corresponding variety in their ways of life they won’t get their fair share of happiness and won’t rise to the mental, moral, and aesthetic level that they are naturally capable of. Why then should tolerance, as far as the public attitude is concerned, extend only to tastes and ways of life that have to be accepted because so many people have them? Nowhere (except in some monastic institutions) is diversity of taste entirely unrecognized: a person may without blame either like or dislike rowing, or smoking, or music, or athletic exercises, or chess, or cards, or study, because those who like each of these things are too numerous to suppress, and so are those who dislike them. But the man—and still more the woman—who can be accused either of doing ‘what nobody does’ or of not doing ‘what everybody does’ is criticized as much as if he or she had committed some serious moral offence. You need to have a title, or some other badge of rank or of support from by people of rank, if you’re to be able to indulge somewhat in the luxury of doing as you like without harm to your reputation. To indulge somewhat, I repeat; for someone who allows himself much of that indulgence—·that permission to differ·—runs the risk of something worse than verbal criticism; they are in danger of being committed as lunatics and of having their property taken from them and given to their relations. [At this point Mill has a long footnote which is here raised into the main text.]
START OF THE LONG FOOTNOTE
There is something both contemptible and frightful in the sort of evidence on the basis of which, in recent years, any person can be judicially declared unfit to manage his affairs; and after his death his will can be set aside (if his estate is large

44

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

enough to pay the expenses of litigation—which are charged against the estate). All the minute details of his daily life are pried into, and if something is found that looks even slightly out of the ordinary, as seen through the medium of the perceiving and describing faculties of the lowest of the low, it is laid before the jury as evidence of insanity. This move often meets with success, because the jurors are little if at all less vulgar and ignorant than the witnesses, while the judges, with that extraordinary ignorance of human nature and human life that continually astonishes us in English lawyers, often help to mislead them. These trials speak volumes about the state of feeling and opinion among ordinary uneducated people with regard to human liberty. So far from setting any value on individuality—so far from respecting the right of each individual to act (where others aren’t concerned) in •the way that seems good to his own judgment and inclinations—judges and juries can’t even conceive that a sane person could want •such freedom. In bygone days, when it was proposed to burn atheists, charitable people used to suggest putting them into a mad-house instead. It wouldn’t be surprising to see this done now, with the doers applauding themselves for treating these unfortunates in such a humane and Christian manner instead of persecuting them on behalf of religion—while also silently deriving satisfaction from the atheists’ getting what they deserve!
END OF FOOTNOTE
One characteristic of the present direction of public opinion is especially calculated to make it intolerant of any notable signs of individuality. The general average of mankind are moderate—·middling·—not only in intellect but also in inclinations: they •haven’t any tastes or wishes strong enough to incline them to do anything unusual, so they don’t understand those who •have, and classify all such people with the wild and intemperate whom they are accustomed to look down on. Combine this general fact with the supposition that a strong movement has started towards the improvement of morals, and it is obvious what we have to expect! Well, in these days such a movement has started: much has actually been brought about in the way of increased regularity of conduct and discouragement of excesses; and there is a widespread sense of •philanthropy—for the moral and prudential improvement of our fellow-creatures there is no more inviting field than •that. These tendencies of the times cause the public to be more disposed than at almost any earlier time to prescribe general rules of conduct and try to make everyone conform to the approved standard. And that standard—whether stated or silently understood—is to desire nothing strongly. Its ideal of character is to be without any notable character, to maim by compression (like a Chinese lady’s foot) every part of human nature that stands out prominently, and tends to make the person noticeably dissimilar in outline to commonplace humanity.

As usually happens with ideals that exclude half of what is desirable, the present standard for approval produces only an inferior imitation of the other half. Instead of

•great energies guided by •vigorous reason, and

•strong feelings strongly controlled by a •conscientious will,

its result is weak feelings and weak energies, and just because they are weak they can be kept in outward conformity to the rules without any strength either of will or of reason.... There is now scarcely any outlet for energy in this country except business. The energy expended in that may still be regarded as considerable. What little is left over from business is spent on some hobby—it may be a useful hobby, even a philanthropic one, but it is always some one thing, and generally a small thing. The greatness of England is now all collective: we are all individually small, and seem

45

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

to be capable of great things only through our habit of combining; and with this state of affairs our moral and religious philanthropists are perfectly contented. But it was men of a different type from this that made England what it has been, and men of a different type will be needed to prevent England’s decline.

The despotism of custom is everywhere the permanent blockage to human advancement, because it never loses its hostility to the disposition to aim at something better than what is customary, a disposition that is called—depending on the circumstances—the spirit of •liberty, or the spirit of •progress or of •improvement. ·These three are not exactly the same, and I shall say a little about how they inter-relate·.The spirit of improvement isn’t always a spirit of liberty, for it may aim at forcing improvements on an unwilling people; and when the spirit of liberty resists such attempts it becomes, in that place and for a while, an ally of the opponents of ‘improvement’. But the only unfailing and permanent source of improvement is liberty, since through liberty there are as many possible independent centres of improvement as there are individuals. The progressive principle can be the love of liberty or the love of improvement; and either way it is antagonistic to the sway of custom, involving at least emancipation from that yoke; and what is of most interest in the history of mankind is this contest between improvement and custom. Most parts of the world have no history properly so-called, because in them the despotism of custom is complete. This is the case over the whole east. No-one there thinks of resisting the argument from custom, except perhaps some tyrant intoxicated with power. And we see the result. Those nations must once have had originality: they didn’t spring up out of the ground populous, literate, and skilled in many of the arts of life; they made themselves like that, and at that time were the greatest and most powerful nations in the world. What are they now? The subjects or dependents of ·Europeans·—tribes •whose forefathers wandered in the forests when theirs had magnificent palaces and gorgeous temples, but •who ·subsequently had the good fortune that among them· custom shared its power with liberty and progress. It seems that a people may be progressive for a certain length of time and then stop. When does it stop? When it ceases to possess individuality. If a similar change comes over the nations of Europe, it won’t have exactly the same shape ·as in the east·, because the despotism of custom with which the European nations are threatened is not precisely stationariness. It forbids singularity, but it doesn’t rule out change, provided we all change together. We have discarded the fixed costumes of our forefathers; everyone must still dress like other people, but the fashion may change once or twice a year. In this way we take care that when there is change it is for the sake of change, and not from any idea of beauty or convenience; for the same idea of beauty or convenience would not strike all the world at the same moment and be simultaneously thrown aside by everyone at another moment, ·and so to give any power to ideas of beauty or convenience would be a threat to uniformity·. But we are progressive as well as changeable: we continually make new inventions in mechanical things, and keep them until they are superseded by something better; we are eager for improvement in politics, in education, even in morals, though our idea of moral improvement chiefly consists in persuading or forcing other people to be as good as we are. It isn’t •progress that we object to; on the contrary, we flatter ourselves that we are the most progressive people who ever lived. It is •individuality that we war against: we would think we had done wonders if we had made ourselves all alike, forgetting that

46

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

one person’s unlikeness to another is generally what first draws the attention of either of them to the imperfection of his own type and the superiority of the other, or the possibility of combining the advantages of both so as to produce something better than either.

We have a warning example in China—a nation of much talent, and even much wisdom in some respects. This is due to China’s rare good fortune in having been provided at an early period with a particularly good set of customs that were partly the work of men to whom even the most enlightened European must grant the title of sages and philosophers (with certain limitations). The Chinese are remarkable, too, in the excellence of their apparatus for •implanting (as far as possible) the best wisdom they have in every mind in the community, and •seeing to it that those who have acquired the most of that wisdom occupy the positions of honour and power. Surely—·you might think·—the people who did this have discovered the secret of human progressiveness, and must have kept themselves steadily at the head of the movement of the world. On the contrary, they have become stationary—have remained so for thousands of years—and if they are ever to be further improved it must be by foreigners. They have succeeded beyond all hope in doing what English philanthropists are so industriously working at, namely making a people all alike, all governing their thoughts and conduct by the same maxims and rules; and these—·the Chinese people of today·—are the fruits of that success. The modern régime of public opinion is an unorganized version of what the Chinese educational and political systems have in an organized form; and unless individuality can successfully assert itself against this yoke, Europe, despite its noble antecedents and its professed Christianity, will tend to become another China.

What is it that has so far preserved Europe from this fate? What has made the European family of nations an •improving rather than a •stationary portion of mankind? It’s not that they are more excellent than the Chinese; when excellence exists it is an effect of improvement, not a cause. Rather, it is the remarkable diversity of character and culture among the Europeans. Individuals, classes, and nations have been extremely unlike one another; they have set out on a great variety of paths, each leading to something valuable; and although at every period those who travelled in different paths have been intolerant of one another, and each would have thought it an excellent thing if all the rest could have been compelled to travel his road, their attempts to block each other’s development have rarely had any permanent success, and each has in time had to put up with receiving the good which the others have offered! Europe’s progressive and many-sided development is due, in my judgment, wholly to this plurality of paths. But it is already starting to have less of this benefit. It is decidedly advancing towards the Chinese ‘ideal’ of making all people alike. M. de Tocqueville, in his last important work, remarks how much more the Frenchmen of the present day resemble one another than did those even of the last generation. The same remark might be made of Englishmen in a far greater degree. In a passage I have already quoted, Wilhelm von Humboldt points out two things as required for human development because they are required to make people unlike one another—namely, •freedom and •variety of situations. The second of these is diminishing day by day in this country. The circumstances that surround different classes and individuals, and shape their characters, are daily becoming more assimilated ·to one another·. Formerly, different ranks, neighbourhoods, trades, professions lived in what might be called different worlds; at present to a great degree they inhabit the same

47

Liberty John Stuart Mill 3: Individuality

world. Comparatively speaking, they now read the same things, listen to the same things, see the same things, go to the same places, have their hopes and fears directed to the same objects, have the same rights and liberties, and the same means of asserting them. Great as are the differences of position that remain, they are nothing compared with the differences that have gone. And the assimilation still goes on. All the political changes of the day promote it, since they all tend to raise the low and to lower the high. Every extension of education promotes it, because education brings people under common influences and gives them access to the general stock of facts and sentiments. Improvements in the means of communication promote it by bringing the inhabitants of distant places into personal contact, and keeping up a rapid flow of changes of residence between one place and another. The increase in commerce and manufacture promotes it by •spreading more widely the advantages of comfortable circumstances, and by •opening all objects of ambition—even the highest—to general competition, so that the desire to rise is no longer a mark of a particular class but of all classes. A force that is even more powerful than all these in bringing about a general similarity among mankind is the way public opinion, in this and other free countries, completely dominates the state. There used to be various social eminences which enabled persons entrenched on them to disregard the opinion of the multitude, but they have gradually become levelled. The very idea of resisting the will of the public, when they are positively known to have a will, disappears more and more from the minds of practical politicians. So there stops being any social support for non-conformity—any substantive social power that is itself opposed to the dominance of numbers, and has a concern for taking under its protection opinions and tendencies that are at odds with those of the public.

The combination of all these causes forms so great a mass of influences hostile to •individuality that it is hard to see how •it can stand its ground. It will do so with increasing difficulty unless the intelligent part of the public can be made to feel its value—to see that it is good that there should be differences, even if not for the better, indeed even if it sometimes seems to them to be for the worse. If the claims of individuality are ever to be asserted, the time is now, when the enforced assimilation is still far from complete. It is only in the earlier stages that any defence can be successfully mounted against the attack. The demand that all other people shall resemble ourselves grows by what it feeds on. If there is no resistance until life is reduced nearly to one uniform type, all variations from that type will come to be considered impious, immoral, even monstrous and contrary to nature. When mankind spend some time without seeing diversity, they quickly become unable even to conceive it.

48

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

Chapter 4: The limits to the authority of society over the individual

What, then, is the rightful limit to the sovereignty of the individual over himself? Where does the authority of society begin? How much of human life should be assigned to individuality, and how much to society?

Each will receive its proper share if each has that which more particularly concerns it. To individuality should belong the part of life in which it is chiefly the individual that is interested; to society, the part which chiefly interests society. [Here and throughout, your being ‘interested in’ something means that your interests are involved in it; this is not ‘interested in’ as the opposite of ‘bored by’.]

Though society is not founded on a contract, and though no good purpose is served by inventing a contract in order to infer social obligations from it, everyone who receives the protection of society owes society something in return for this benefit, and the sheer fact that they have a society makes it indispensable that each should be bound to conform to a certain line of conduct towards the rest. This conduct consists ·in two things·.

(1 Not harming the interests of one another; or, rather, not harming certain ·particular· interests which ought to be classified (by explicit law or tacit understanding) as rights.

(2) Doing one’s share (to be fixed by some fair principle) of the labours and sacrifices incurred for defending the society or its members from injury and harassment.

Society is justified in enforcing these conditions at the expense of those who try to avoid fulfilling them. Nor is this all that society may do. The acts of an individual may be hurtful to others, or lacking in proper consideration for their welfare, without going so far as violating any of their constituted rights. The offender may then be justly punished by opinion, though not by law. As soon as any part of a person’s conduct has a negative effect on the interests of others, society has jurisdiction over it, and the question whether or not the general welfare will be promoted by interfering with it becomes open to discussion. But there is no room for raising any such question when a person’s conduct affects the interests of no-one but himself, or needn’t affect others unless they want it to (all the persons concerned being adults with the ordinary amount of understanding). In all such cases there should be perfect freedom, legal and social, to perform the action and accept the consequences.

It would be a great misunderstanding of this doctrine to suppose that it is one of selfish indifference, claiming that human beings have no concern with each other’s behaviour and shouldn’t concern themselves about one anothers’ well-doing or well-being unless their own interests are involved. Instead of any lessening there is need for a great increase of disinterested [= ‘not self -interested’] effort to promote the good of others. But ·it is one thing to •act on one’s belief that it would be better for x himself if he didn’t do y and another to •bring legal or social pressure on him not to do y·. For persuading people to look after themselves, disinterested benevolence can find instruments other than whips and scourges, whether of the literal or the metaphorical sort. I am the last person to undervalue the self-regarding virtues; they are second in importance only to the social virtues, if not first equal with them. It is equally the business of education to cultivate both. But even education works by •conviction and persuasion as well as by •compulsion; and once the period of education is past, it is only by •conviction

49

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

and persuasion that the self-regarding virtues should be instilled into people. Human beings owe to each other help to distinguish the better from the worse, and encouragement to choose the former and avoid the latter. They should be forever stimulating each other to increased exercise of their higher faculties, and increased direction of their feelings and aims towards things and thoughts that are wise instead of foolish, elevating instead of degrading. But no one person or group is entitled to say to another adult human being that he shall not do with his life for his own benefit what he chooses to do with it. He is the person most interested in his own well-being; except in cases of strong personal attachment, the interest that anyone else can have in it is trifling compared with his own; and society’s interest in him as an individual (except with regard to his conduct toward others) is fractional and altogether indirect. ·And there is also a point about the knowledge on which interference would have to be based·. The most ordinary man or woman has means of knowledge concerning his own feelings and circumstances that immeasurably surpass those that anyone else can have. The interference of society to overrule his judgment and purposes in what affects only himself must be based ·not on knowledge about him in particular but· on general presumptions ·about people as a whole·; these general presumptions may be altogether wrong, and even when they are right they are as likely as not to be misapplied to individual cases. (Remember that the application is being made to someone by other people, who therefore don’t know much about the circumstances of the case). In this department of human affairs, therefore, individuality has its proper field of action. In the conduct of human beings towards one another, it is necessary that general rules should for the most part be observed so that people can know what to expect; but in each person’s own concerns, his individual spontaneity is entitled to free exercise. Considerations to aid his judgment, urgings to strengthen his will, may be offered to him and even pushed at him by others; but he is the final judge. Any •errors that he is likely to commit against advice and warning are far outweighed by •the evil of allowing others to constrain him to what they think to be his good.

I don’t mean that a person’s self-regarding qualities or deficiencies oughtn’t to affect how others regard him. That is neither possible nor desirable. If he is conspicuous in any of the qualities that conduce to his own good, he is to that extent a proper object of admiration. He is that much nearer to the ideal perfection of human nature. If he is grossly lacking in those qualities, a sentiment the opposite of admiration will follow. There is a degree of folly, and a degree of what may be called (though the phrase is somewhat objectionable) lowness or depravity of taste, which—though it can’t justify •harming the person who manifests it—makes him necessarily and properly the object of •distaste and in extreme cases the object of •contempt; anyone who has the opposite qualities in due strength would have to have •these feelings. Though not doing wrong to anyone ·else·, a person may so act as to compel us to judge him to be a fool or a being of some inferior kind, and to feel towards him in that way; and since this judgment and feeling are a fact that he would prefer to avoid, it is doing him a •service to warn him of it beforehand, as it would be to warn him of any other disagreeable consequence to which he is exposing himself. It would indeed be a good thing if this •service were given much more freely than the common notions of politeness at present permit, and if one person could honestly point out to another that he thinks him at fault, without being considered pushy or bad-mannered. We also have a right in various ways to act on our unfavourable opinion of anyone,

50

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

not oppressing his individuality but exercising ours. We are not bound, for example, to seek his society; we have a right to avoid it (though not to parade the avoidance), for we have a right to choose the society most acceptable to us. We have a right—and possibly even a duty—to warn others against him if we think his example or conversation likely to have a bad effect on those with whom he associates. When we have at our disposal various possibilities of giving help, we may give others the preference over him unless it is a question of helping him to improve. In these different ways a person may suffer very severe penalties at the hands of others for faults that directly concern only himself; but he suffers these penalties only as natural and spontaneous consequences of the faults themselves, not because they are purposely inflicted on him for the sake of punishment. A person who shows

rashness, obstinacy, self-conceit,

can’t live within moderate means,

can’t restrain himself from hurtful indulgences, and

pursues animal pleasures at the expense of those of feeling and intellect,

must expect to be lowered in the opinion of others, and to have a smaller share of their favourable sentiments; has no right to complain of this unless he has deserved their favour by special excellence in his social relations, thus establishing a right to help from them—a right that isn’t affected by how badly he treats himself.

What I contend for is this: with regard to the part of someone’s conduct and character that concerns his own good but doesn’t affect the interests of others in their relations with him, the only inconveniences that he should be subject to are ones that are strictly inseparable from the unfavourable judgment of others. Acts injurious to others require a totally different treatment. Encroachment on the rights of other, infliction on them of any loss or damage not justified by his own rights, falsehood or trickery in dealing with them, unfair or ungenerous use of advantages over them, even selfish abstinence from defending them against harm—these are fit objects of moral reproach and, in serious cases, of moral retribution and punishment. And not only these •acts but also the •dispositions that lead to them are strictly immoral, and are fit objects of disapproval that may rise to the level of disgust.

Cruelty of disposition, malice and ill-nature, envy (that most anti-social and odious of all passions), hypocrisy and insincerity, irritability over trifles, immoderate resentment, the love of domineering over others, the desire to gather in more than one’s share of advantages, the pride that is pleased when others fail, the egotism that thinks self and its concerns more important than everything else and decides all doubtful questions in his own favour

—these are moral vices, and constitute a bad and odious moral character. Not so the self-regarding faults previously mentioned: they are not strictly immoralities, and don’t constitute wickedness however intense they are. They may be proofs of any amount of folly or lack of personal dignity and self-respect; but they invite moral condemnation only when they involve a breach of duty to others for whose sake the individual is obliged to take care of himself. What are called duties to ourselves are not socially obligatory unless circumstances turn them into duties to others as well. The phrase ‘duty to oneself’, when it means anything more than prudence, means self-respect or self-development; and there is no ‘it’s-for-the-good-of-mankind’ reason why anyone should be held accountable to his fellow-creatures for either of them.

The distinction between •the loss of regard that a person may rightly incur through a lack of prudence or of personal

51

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

dignity and •the condemnation that is due to him for an offence against the rights of others, is not a merely verbal one. It makes a vast difference both in our feelings and in our conduct towards him, whether he displeases us in •things in which we think we have a right to control him, or displeases us in •things in which we know we haven’t. If he displeases us, we may express our distaste, and we may keep our distance from a person as well as from a thing that displeases us; but we shan’t therefore feel called on to make his life uncomfortable. We shall reflect that he already bears, or will bear, the whole penalty of his error. If he spoils his life by mismanagement, that won’t lead us to want to spoil it still further: instead of wishing to punish him, we’ll try to lighten his punishment, by showing him how to avoid or cure the evils that his conduct tends to bring on him. He may be to us an object of •pity, perhaps of •dislike, but not of •anger or •resentment; we shan’t treat him like an enemy of society; the worst we shall think ourselves justified in doing is leaving him to himself, if we don’t interfere benevolently by showing interest or concern for him. The situation is entire different if he has infringed the rules necessary for the protection of his fellow-creatures, individually or collectively. The evil consequences of his acts don’t then fall on himself but on others; and society, as the protector of all its members, must strike back at him, inflicting pain on him for the express purpose of punishment, and must take care that the pain is sufficiently severe. In this •latter case he is an offender in our court, and we are called on not only to sit in judgment on him but, in one way or another, to carry out our own sentence; whereas in the •former case it is not our role to inflict any suffering on him except what may incidentally follow from our using the same liberty in the regulation of our own affairs that we allow him in his.

Many people will deny that we can distinguish the part of a person’s life that concerns only himself from the part that concerns others. They may say:

How can any part of the conduct of a member of society be a matter of indifference to the other members? No person is an entirely isolated being; it is impossible for a person to do anything seriously or permanently hurtful to himself without harm coming at least to those closely connected with him and often far beyond them. If he injures his property, he does harm to those who directly or indirectly derived support from it, and usually lessens somewhat the general resources of the community. If he worsens his physical or mental abilities, he not only brings evil on all who depended on him for any portion of their happiness but makes himself unable to render the services that he owes to his fellow-creatures generally; perhaps becomes a burden on their affection or benevolence....
      Finally, if by his vices or follies a person does no direct harm to others, he nevertheless does do harm by the example he sets, and he ought to be compelled to control himself, for the sake of those whom the sight or knowledge of his conduct might corrupt or mislead.
      And even if the consequences of misconduct could be confined to the vicious or thoughtless individual himself, ought society to abandon to their own guidance those who are manifestly unfit for it? We all agree that children and young people should be protected against themselves; so isn’t society equally bound to protect against themselves adults who are equally incapable of self-government? If gambling, or drunkenness, or sexual licence, or idleness, or uncleanliness, are as injurious to happiness and as

52

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

great a hindrance to improvement as many or most of the acts prohibited by law, why shouldn’t the law try to put them down also (as far as practicability and social convenience allow)? And as a supplement to the unavoidable imperfections of law, oughtn’t public opinion at least to organize a powerful guard against these vices, and rigorously apply social penalties on those who are known to practise them? There is no question here of restricting individuality or blocking trials of new and original experiments in living. Nothing is being prevented except things that have been tried and condemned from the beginning of the world until now—things that experience has shown not to be useful or suitable to any person’s individuality. There must be some length of time and amount of experience after which a moral or prudential truth can be regarded as established! All that is proposed here is to prevent generation after generation from falling over the same precipice that has been fatal to their predecessors.

I fully admit that the harm a person does to himself may seriously affect (both through their sympathies and their interests) those closely connected with him, and may in a lesser degree affect society in general. When by conduct of this sort a person is led to violate a distinct and assignable obligation to one or more others, the case is no longer in self-regarding category and becomes amenable to moral condemnation in the proper sense of the term. [By an ‘assignable’ obligation, Mill means an obligation to someone in particular, as distinct from (say) an obligation to keep yourself fit in case someone or other comes to need your help. More of this at the start of the next paragraph.] For example: if through intemperance or extravagance a man becomes unable to pay his debts, or unable to support and educate his family, he is deservedly condemned and might be justly punished; but it is for the breach of duty to his family or creditors, not for the extravagance. If the resources that ought to have been devoted to them had been diverted from them for the most prudent investment, the moral culpability would have been the same.... Again, if (as often happens) a man causes grief to his family •by his addiction to bad habits, he deserves reproach for his unkindness or ingratitude; but he may deserve it just as much if he causes grief to his family •by cultivating habits that are not in themselves vicious. Someone who

fails in the consideration generally due to the interests and feelings of others, without •being compelled by some more imperative duty or •justified by allowable self-preference,

is a subject of moral disapproval for that failure, but not for •the cause of it and not for •any errors that are merely personal to himself and may have indirectly led to it. Similarly, when a person disables himself through purely self-regarding conduct from the performance of some definite duty he has towards the public, he is guilty of a social offence. No-one ought to be punished simply for being drunk, but a soldier or a policeman should be punished for being drunk on duty. In short, whenever there is definite damage, or a definite risk of damage, either to an individual or to the public, the case is taken out of the domain of liberty and placed in that of morality or law.

But with regard to the merely contingent....harm that a person causes to society by conduct that doesn’t violate any specific duty to the public or bring harm to any assignable individual except himself: this inconvenience is one that society can afford to bear for the sake of the greater good of human freedom. If adults are to be punished for not taking proper care of themselves, I would rather it were done for their own sake than done on the grounds that we are

53

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

preventing them from impairing their ability to render to society benefits that society doesn’t claim it has a right to demand! But I can’t consent to argue the point as if society had no means of bringing its weaker members up to its ordinary standard of rational conduct, except waiting till they do something irrational and then punishing them—legally or morally—for it. Society has had absolute power over them during all the early part of their existence; it has had the whole period of childhood and teen-age in which to try to make them capable of rational conduct in life. The existing ·adult· generation is master both of the training and the entire circumstances of the generation to come. Indeed it can’t make them perfectly wise and good, because it is itself so lamentably short of goodness and wisdom; and its best efforts are not always, in individual cases, its most successful ones; but it is perfectly well able to make the rising generation, as a whole, as good as itself and a little better. If society lets any considerable number of its members grow up as mere children, incapable of being acted on by rational consideration of long-term consequences, society has itself to blame for the upshot. Armed not only with •all the powers of education but also with •the dominance that the authority of a publicly accepted opinion always exercises over the minds of those who are least fitted to judge for themselves; and aided by •the natural penalties that can’t be prevented from falling on those who incur the distaste or the contempt of those who know them; let society not claim that besides all •this it needs the power to issue commands and enforce obedience in the personal concerns of individuals—concerns in which, on all principles of justice and policy, the decision ought to rest with those who will have to put up with the consequences. And nothing tends more to discredit and frustrate the better means of influencing conduct than a resort to the worse. If those whom we are trying coerce into prudence or temperance include any who are made of the same stuff as vigorous and independent characters, they will certainly rebel against the yoke. No such person will ever feel that others have a right to control him in his concerns—the kind of right that they do have to prevent him from harming them in their concerns; and it easily comes to be considered a mark of spirit and courage to fly in the face of such illegitimate authority, ostentatiously doing the exact opposite of what it commands. An example was the fashion of grossness that followed, in the time of Charles II, the fanatical moral intolerance of the puritans. With respect to what is said about the need to protect society from the bad example set for others by the vicious or the self-indulgent: it is true that a bad example may have a pernicious effect, especially the example of doing wrong to others with impunity to the wrong-doer. But we are now speaking of conduct which, while doing no wrong to others, is •supposed to do great harm to the agent himself; and I don’t see how those who believe •this can help thinking that the example must on the whole do more good than harm, because in displaying the misconduct it also displays the painful or degrading consequences which....are supposed nearly always to flow from it.

But the strongest of all the arguments against the public’s interfering with purely personal conduct is that when it does interfere the odds are that it interferes •wrongly and •in the wrong place. On questions of social morality—of duty to others—the opinion of the overruling majority is likely to be right oftener than it is wrong, because on such questions they are only required to judge how a given mode of conduct, if allowed to be practised, would affect their interests. But the opinion of a similar majority imposed as a law on the minority on questions of self-regarding conduct is quite as likely to be wrong as right; for in these cases public opinion

54

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

means at best some people’s opinion of what is good or bad for other people; while very often it doesn’t even mean that, because the public consider only their own preference and don’t pay the slightest regard to the pleasure or convenience of those whose conduct they censure. There are many who regard any conduct that they have a distaste for as an insult to themselves, and resent it as an outrage to their feelings; as a religious bigot, when accused of disregarding the religious feelings of others, has been known to reply that they disregard his feelings by persisting in their abominable worship or creed! But •a person’s feeling for his own opinion is not on a par with •the feeling of someone else who is offended at his holding it; any more than •a person’s desire to keep his purse is on a par with •a thief’s desire to take it. Someone’s taste is as much his own particular concern as is his opinion or his purse. It is easy for anyone to imagine an ideal public which leaves individuals free to choose in all matters where there are two sides to the question, and only requires them to abstain from kinds of conduct that •universal experience has condemned. But whoever saw a public that did set any such limit to its censorship? and when does the public trouble itself about •universal experience? In its interferences with personal conduct the public is seldom thinking of anything but the dreadfulness of anyone’s acting or feeling differently from itself; and this standard of judgment is what ninety percent of all moralists and moral theorists hold up to mankind as the dictate of religion and philosophy. The standard in question is thinly disguised in the hands of these people. What they openly teach is that things are right because they are right—because we feel them to be so. They tell us to search in our own minds and hearts for laws of conduct binding on ourselves and on all others. What can the poor public do but apply these instructions and make their own personal feelings of good and evil, if they are reasonably unanimous in them, obligatory on all the world?

The evil that I am pointing out here isn’t one that exists only in theory; and you may expect me to cite examples in which the public of this age and country improperly dresses up its own preferences as moral laws. I am not writing an essay on the aberrations of existing moral feeling, which is too weighty a subject to be discussed parenthetically and by way of illustration. But I do need to provide some examples, to show that the principle I maintain is of serious and practical significance, and that I am not trying to set up a barrier against imaginary evils. And it isn’t hard to show by abundant examples that one of the most universal of all human tendencies is the tendency to extend the bounds of what may be called ‘moral police’ until it encroaches on the most unquestionably legitimate liberty of the individual. ·Examples of this will occupy the remainder of the present chapter·.

As a first instance, consider the hostilities that men feel on no better grounds than that persons whose religious opinions are different from theirs don’t practise their religious observances, especially their religious abstinences. To cite a rather trivial example, nothing in the creed or practice of Christians does more to make Moslems hate them than the fact of their eating pork. There are few acts that Christians and Europeans regard with more sincere disgust than Moslems regard this particular way of satisfying hunger. It is in the first place an offence against their religion; but this doesn’t explain either the degree or the kind of their repugnance; for wine also is forbidden by their religion, and Moslems all think it is wrong to drink wine, but they don’t think it is disgusting. In contrast with that, their aversion to the flesh of the ‘unclean beast’ has that special character—like an instinctive revulsion—which the

55

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

idea of uncleanness, when once it thoroughly sinks into the feelings, seems always to excite even in those whose personal habits are anything but scrupulously clean. A remarkable example of this force of the idea of uncleanness is provided by the sentiment of religious impurity that is so intense in the Hindus. Suppose now that in a people of whom the majority were Moslems, that majority were to insist on not permitting pork to be eaten within the limits of the country. This would be nothing new in Moslem countries.^3 Would it be a legitimate exercise of the moral authority of public opinion? and if not, why not? The practice is really revolting to such a public. They also sincerely think that it is forbidden and abhorred by God. Neither could the prohibition be censured as religious persecution. It might be religious in its origin, but it wouldn’t be persecution for religion, since nobody’s religion makes it a duty to eat pork. The only tenable ground for condemning it would be that the public has no business interfering with the personal tastes and self-regarding concerns of individuals.

To come somewhat nearer home: the majority of Spaniards consider it a gross impiety, offensive in the highest degree to the supreme being, to worship him in any but the Roman Catholic way; and no other public worship is lawful on Spanish soil. The people of all Southern Europe look on a married clergy as not only irreligious, but unchaste, indecent, gross, disgusting. What do protestants think of these perfectly sincere feelings, and of the attempt to enforce them against non-Catholics? Yet, if mankind are justified in interfering with each other’s liberty in things that don’t concern the interests of others, on what principle is it possible consistently to exclude these cases? or who can blame people for wanting to suppress what they regard as a scandal in the sight of God and man?

No stronger case can be shown for prohibiting anything that is regarded as a personal immorality than is made out for suppressing these practices in the eyes of those who regard them as impieties; and unless we are willing to adopt the logic of persecutors, and to say that •we may persecute others because we are right and that •they must not persecute us because they are wrong, we must beware of admitting a principle whose application to ourselves we would resent as a gross injustice.

Those examples may be objected to, although unreasonably, as drawn from situations that couldn’t arise among us, because in this country public opinion isn’t likely to enforce abstinence from meats, or to interfere with people for worshipping, and for either marrying or not marrying, according to their creed or inclination. My next example, however, will involve an interference with liberty that we have by no means passed all danger of. Wherever the puritans have been sufficiently powerful, as in New England and in Great Britain at the time of Cromwell they have tried with considerable success to put down all public amusements and nearly all private ones—especially music, dancing, public games and other gatherings for purposes of amusement, and the theatre. In this country there are still many people whose notions

^3 The case of the Bombay Parsis is an interesting example of this. This industrious and enterprising tribe, the descendants of the Persian fire-worshippers, fled from their native country to escape the Caliphs; when they arrived in western India they were tolerated by the Hindu sovereigns on condition that they gave up eating beef. When those regions afterwards fell under the dominion of Moslem conquerors, the Parsis obtained from them a continuing tolerance on condition that they gave up eating pork. What was at first •obedience to authority became a •second nature, and the Parsis to this day abstain both from beef and pork. Though not required by their religion, this double abstinence has had time to grow into a custom of their tribe; and in the east custom is a religion.

56

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

of morality and religion condemn these recreations; and those people belong chiefly to the middle class, which is the dominant power in the present social and political condition of the kingdom, so that it is by no means impossible that people with these views may some day command a majority in parliament. How will the rest of the community like having the amusements that shall be permitted to them regulated by the religious and moral sentiments of the stricter Calvinists and Methodists? Wouldn’t they pretty abruptly tell these intrusively pious members of society to mind their own business? Well, that is precisely what should be said to every government and every public who claim that no person shall enjoy any pleasure that they think is wrong. Once the principle of that claim is admitted, no-one can reasonably object to its being acted on in the spirit of the majority, or of other dominant power in the country; and everyone must be ready to conform to the idea of a Christian commonwealth as understood by the early settlers in New England, if a religious creed similar to theirs should ever succeed in regaining its lost ground. And religions supposed to be declining often have regained lost ground!

Here is another possibility, perhaps more likely to come about than the one last mentioned. We all know that there is a strong tendency in the modern world towards a democratic constitution of society, whether or not accompanied by democratic political institutions. Let us then look at the United States, the country where this tendency is most completely realized—the country where both society and the government are most democratic. It is said that there the feeling of the majority, who find disagreeable any appearance of a more showy or costly style of living than they can hope to rival, operates as a fairly effective expense-controlling law, and that in many parts of the Union it is really difficult for a person with a very large income to find any way of spending it without being disapproved of by the people. This is said, and no doubt it is a much exaggerated account of the real facts; but the state of things it portrays is not only conceivable and possible, but is a probable result of •democratic feeling combined with •the notion that the public has a right of veto over how individuals shall spend their incomes. Add to those two the supposition of •a considerable spreading of socialist opinions, and it may become abominable in the eyes of the majority to possess more than a very little property or to have any income not earned by manual labour. Opinions similar in principle to these already prevail widely among the artisan class [= ‘the class of skilled manual workers’], and weigh oppressively on those who are especially vulnerable to the opinion of that class, namely its own members. It is known that the bad workmen who form the majority of the workers in many branches of industry are firmly of opinion that bad workmen ought to receive the same wages as good ones, and that those who have superior skill or work harder ought not to be allowed to earn more than those who haven’t and don’t. And they employ a moral police which occasionally becomes a physical one [meaning: they use moral bullying and sometimes physical force] to deter skillful workmen from receiving and employers from giving more pay for more useful service. If the public have any jurisdiction over private concerns, I can’t see that these people are at fault, or that any individual’s particular public can be blamed for asserting the same authority over his individual conduct as the general public asserts over people in general.

But setting aside suppositious cases, in our own day •gross intrusions on the liberty of private life are actually practised, •still greater ones are threatened with some expectation of success, and •opinions are presented that would give to the public an unlimited right not only to prohibit by law everything that it thinks wrong, but also, in order to get

57

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

at what it thinks wrong, to prohibit any number of things that it admits to be innocent.

Under the name of ‘preventing intemperance’ the people of one English colony and of nearly half the United States have been forbidden by law from making any use whatever of alcoholic drinks, except for medical purposes. [This refers to the so-called ‘Maine Law’ of 1815.] Prohibition of their sale, ·which is what is explicitly forbidden by law·, is and is intended to be prohibition of their use. And though the impracticability of enforcing the law has caused its repeal in several of the states that had adopted it, including the one from which it derives its name, an attempt has nevertheless been started, and is pushed with considerable zeal by many of the professed philanthropists, to agitate for a similar law in this country. The association (or ‘Alliance’ as it terms itself) which has been formed for this purpose has acquired some notoriety through the publicity given to a correspondence between its Secretary and one of the very few English public men who hold that a politician’s opinions ought to be founded on principles. Lord Stanley’s part in this correspondence should strengthen the hopes already built on him, by those who know how few of those who figure in political life have such qualities as are shown in some of his public appearances. The spokesman for the Alliance, who would ‘deeply deplore the recognition of any principle that could be wrenched around so as to justify bigotry and persecution’, points out the ‘broad and impassable barrier’ that divides such principles from those of his association. ‘All

matters relating to thought, opinion, conscience

appear to me’, he says, ‘to lie outside the sphere of legislation; all

matters pertaining to social acts and habits....

appear to me to be within that sphere.’ He doesn’t mention a third class, different from either of these, namely

acts and habits that are not social but individual;

although it is to this class, surely, that the act of drinking alcoholic liquors belongs. Selling such liquors, however, is trading, and trading is a social act. But the infringement complained of is not on the liberty of the seller but on that of the buyer and consumer; since the state might just as well •forbid him to drink wine as •purposely make it impossible for him to obtain it. The Secretary ·of the Alliance·, however, says: ‘I claim as a citizen a right to legislate whenever my social rights are invaded by the social act of another.’ Now for the definition of these ‘social rights’.

‘If anything invades my social rights, certainly the traffic in strong drink does. It destroys my primary right of security by constantly creating and stimulating social disorder. It invades my right of equality by making a profit out of the creation of misery that I am taxed to support. It impedes my right to free moral and intellectual development by surrounding my path with dangers and by weakening and demoralizing society, from which I have a right to claim mutual aid and personal relationships.’

This is a theory of ‘social rights’ the like of which has probably never before been stated clearly! It is nothing short of this: that it is my absolute social right that every other individual shall act in every respect exactly as he ought; that whoever fails in the least detail of this violates my social right and entitles me to demand that the legislature remove the grievance. So monstrous a •principle is far more dangerous than any •single interference with liberty; there is no violation of liberty that it wouldn’t justify; it acknowledges no right to any freedom whatever, except perhaps the freedom to hold opinions in secret without ever disclosing them; for the moment an opinion that I consider poisonous passes anyone’s lips it invades all the ‘social rights’ attributed to

58

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

me by the Alliance. The doctrine ascribes to all mankind a vested interest in each other’s moral, intellectual, and even physical perfection, to be defined by each claimant according to his own standard.

Another important example of illegitimate interference with the rightful liberty of the individual, not simply threatened but long since carried into triumphant effect, is legislation concerning the sabbath. Refraining from one’s usual daily occupations on one day of the week, as far as is practically possible, is no doubt a highly beneficial custom, though it is in no respect religiously binding on any except Jews. And it can’t be followed without a general consent to that effect among the classes of people with jobs to do, because if some people follow it, that compels others to do so. It may therefore be allowable and right that the law should guarantee to each person the observance by others of the custom in question, by suspending the large-scale operations of the economy on a particular day. But this justification is based on the direct interest that others have in each individual’s observance of the practice; so it doesn’t apply to the leisure-time occupations that a person chooses to engage in; nor does it hold good, in the slightest degree, for legal restrictions on amusements. It is true that the amusement of some is the day’s work of others; but the labour of a few is compensated for by the •pleasure of the many (and by the •good their recreation does for them), provided that the few freely choose their work and are free to give it up. The workers are perfectly right in thinking that if everyone worked on Sunday, seven days’ work would have to be given for six days’ wages: but so long as the great mass of employments are suspended, the small number who must still work for the enjoyment of others obtain a proportional increase of earnings; and they aren’t obliged to follow those occupations if they would rather have leisure than pay. If a further remedy is sought, it might be found in the establishment by custom of a holiday on some other day of the week for those particular classes of persons. So the only ground on which restrictions on Sunday amusements can be defended must be that they are religiously wrong; and this is a motive of legislation that never can be too earnestly protested against. ‘Injuries to the gods are the gods’ business’ [Tacitus; Mill gives it in Latin]. It remains to be proved that society or anyone acting for it has been appointed by heaven to avenge any supposed offence to God that isn’t also a wrong to our fellow-creatures. The notion that it is one man’s duty that another should be religious was the basis for all the religious persecutions ever perpetrated, and if it were right it would fully justify them. The feeling that breaks out in the repeated attempts to stop railway travel on Sunday, in the resistance to the opening of museums, and the like, doesn’t have the cruelty of •the persecutors of old, but the state of mind indicated by it is fundamentally the same as •theirs. It is a determination not to tolerate others in doing what is permitted by their religion, because it isn’t permitted by the persecutor’s religion. It is a belief that God not only abominates the act of the misbeliever but will blame us if we don’t interfere with him.

To these examples of the small regard that is commonly paid to human liberty, I can’t help adding one more: the language of downright persecution that breaks out from the press of this country whenever it feels called on to say something about the remarkable phenomenon of Mormonism. Much might be said concerning the unexpected and instructive fact that

an alleged new revelation and a religion based on it, the product of obvious fraud and not even supported by the prestige of extraordinary qualities in its founder, is believed by hundreds of thousands of people and

59

Liberty John Stuart Mill 4: Limits to society’s authority

has been made the foundation of a ·whole· society—in the age of newspapers, railways, and the electric telegraph!

What here concerns us is that this religion, like other and better ones, has its martyrs; that its prophet and founder was, for his teaching, put to death by a mob; that others of its adherents lost their lives by the same lawless violence; that they were forcibly expelled, in a body, from the territory in which they first grew up; and now that they have been chased into a solitary recess in the middle of a desert, many in this country openly declare that it would be •right (thought not •convenient) to send an expedition against them to compel them by force to conform to the opinions of other people. The item in the Mormon doctrine that chiefly arouses the hostility that thus breaks through the ordinary restraints of religious tolerance is its acceptance of polygamy. Though permitted to Moslems, Hindus, and Chinese, this seems to arouse unquenchable animosity when practised by people who speak English and claim to be some kind of Christian. No-one disapproves of this Mormon institution ·of polygamy· more deeply than I do. Far from being in any way countenanced by the principle of liberty, it is a direct infraction of that principle, being a mere riveting of the chains of one half of the community, while freeing the other half from having an obligation running the other way; and there are other reasons against it also. Still, it must be remembered that this relation is as much voluntary on the part of the women concerned in it (who may be regarded as its victims) as is the case with any other form of the marriage institution. This may seem surprising, but it has its explanation in the common ideas and customs of the world, which teach women to think of marriage as the one thing they need. That makes it intelligible that many a woman should prefer being one of several wives to not being a wife at all. Other countries are not asked to recognize such unions, or to release any portion of their inhabitants from their own laws on the grounds that they have Mormon beliefs. But when the dissentients—·the Mormons·—have

•conceded to the hostile attitudes of others far more than those others were entitled to demand,

and when they have

•left the territories where their doctrines were unacceptable, and settled in a remote corner of the earth that they have been the first to make habitable to human beings,

it’s hard to see on what principles but those of tyranny they can be prevented from living there under what laws they please, provided they commit no aggression against other nations and allow perfect freedom of departure to those who are dissatisfied with their ways. A recent writer who is in some respects a person of considerable merit proposes not a crusade but what he calls a civilizade [a war in the service not of the cross but of civilisation] against this polygamous community, to put an end to what seems to him a step backwards in civilization. To me too that is what it seems to be, but I’m not aware that any community has the right to force another to be civilized. As long as those who suffer through the bad law don’t call for help from other communities, I can’t accept that persons entirely unconnected with them ought to step in and require that a condition of things with which all who are directly involved appear to be satisfied should be put an end to because it scandalizes people some thousands of miles away, people who have no part or concern in it. Let them send missionaries, if they please, to preach against it; and let them, by any fair means (of which silencing the teachers is not one) oppose the progress of similar doctrines among their own people. If civilization has gained the upper hand over barbarism when barbarism had the world to itself,

60

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

it is absurd to claim to be afraid that barbarism, after having been fairly put down, might revive and conquer civilization. A civilization that could thus be beaten by its vanquished enemy must already have become so degenerate that neither its appointed priests and teachers nor anybody else is able to stand up for it—or anyway will take the trouble to do so. In that case, the sooner such a civilization receives notice to quit, the better! It can only go on from bad to worse until it is destroyed and regenerated (like the western part of the Roman Empire) by energetic barbarians.

Chapter 5: Applications

One would like the principles asserted in these pages to be applied consistently across all the various branches of government and morals; but there is no chance of doing that fruitfully until the principles have become more generally accepted, so that they can be the basis for a discussion of the relevant details. The few remarks I shall make on questions of detail are meant to •illustrate the principles rather than to •follow them out to their consequences. What I shall be offering are not so much •applications as •specimens of application [= ‘examples of how to go about applying’ the principles]. They may serve to clarify the meaning and the limits of the two maxims that together form the entire doctrine of this work, and to assist the judgment in holding the balance between them in the cases where it appears doubtful which of them is applicable to the case.

The principles in question are these two:

(1) The individual is not accountable to society for his actions insofar as these concern the interests of no-one but himself.

Advice, instruction, persuasion, and avoidance by other people, if they think it necessary for the individual’s own good, are the only measures by which society can justifiably express its dislike or disapproval of his conduct.

(2) The individual is accountable for such of his actions as are prejudicial to the interests of others, and he may be subjected either to social or to legal punishments if society thinks that one or the other is needed for its protection.

The first point to be made is this: Just because damage (or the probability of damage) to the interests of others is the only thing that can justify the interference of society, it doesn’t follow that it always justifies such interference. In many cases an individual in pursuing a legitimate object necessarily (and therefore legitimately) causes pain or loss to others, or gets for himself a good that someone else had had a reasonable hope of obtaining. Such oppositions of interest between individuals often arise from bad social institutions, and are unavoidable while those institutions last; others would be unavoidable under any institutions. Anyone who succeeds in an overcrowded profession or in a competitive examination—·more generally·, someone who comes ahead of someone else in any contest for something that they both want—derives benefit from his competitor’s loss, wasted effort, and disappointment. But we all agree that it is better

61

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

for the general interest of mankind that people should pursue their objectives undeterred by consequences of this sort. In other words, society doesn’t grant disappointed competitors any legal or moral right to immunity from this kind of suffering; and feels called on to interfere ·in competitive situations· only when someone has succeeded through •means that it is contrary to the general interest to permit—namely •fraud, treachery, or force.

·Free trade·

Again, trade is a social act. Someone who undertakes to sell goods of any kind to the public is doing something that affects the interests of other people and of society in general; and so his conduct does in principle come within the jurisdiction of society; which is why it used to be thought the duty of governments, in all cases that were thought important, to fix prices and regulate the processes of manufacture. But it is now recognized, though only after a long struggle, that the best way to get good products at low prices is to leave the producers and sellers perfectly free, as long as the buyers are free to get their supplies from elsewhere. This is the so-called doctrine of Free Trade. The case for it is different from the case for the principle of individual liberty defended here, but it is just as solid. Restrictions on trade, or on production for purposes of trade, are indeed restraints; and restraint as such is always bad; but the restraints ·on trade that are· in question here affect only that part of conduct that society is in principle entitled to restrain, and they are wrong purely because they don’t really produce the results they are meant to produce. So the principle of individual liberty is not involved in the doctrine of Free Trade ·itself·, nor does it come into most of the •questions that arise concerning the limits of that doctrine: for example, •how much public control is admissible to prevent fraud by adulteration; •how far sanitary precautions, or arrangements to protect people working in dangerous occupations, should be enforced on employers. Questions like these involve the liberty issue only ·in a marginal way·, through the general thesis that

leaving people to themselves is always better, other things being equal, than controlling them.

It can’t be denied that people may be legitimately controlled for ends such as the ones I have just mentioned. On the other hand, some questions relating to interference with trade are centrally questions of liberty; such as

the Maine Law mentioned above ·on page 58·,

the prohibition on importing opium into China,

the restriction of the sale of poisons;

all cases—in short, where the object of the interference is to make it hard or impossible to obtain a particular commodity. These interferences are objectionable as infringements on the liberty not of the producer or seller but of the buyer.

·Selling poisons·

One of these examples, that of the sale of poisons, raises a new question—the question of what the proper limits are of what may be called the functions of police. [As used here by Mill, ‘police’ covers any activities that are concerned with watching over society or some part of it, aiming to stop bad things—not just crimes—from happening.] How far can liberty legitimately be invaded for the prevention of crime or of accidents? It is one of the undisputed functions of government to take •precautions against crime before it has been committed, as well as to •detect and punish it afterwards. The preventive function of government, however, is far more liable to be abused at the expense of liberty than is its punitive function; for almost every part of the legitimate freedom of action of a human

62

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

being could be represented, and fairly too, as increasing the facilities for some kind of misconduct. (·Someone earns his living making hammers; now think about the crimes that can be committed using a hammer!·) Still, if a public authority or even a private person sees someone evidently preparing to commit a crime, they aren’t bound to stay out of it until the crime is committed, but may interfere to prevent it. If poisons were never bought or used for any purpose except •to commit murder, it would be right to prohibit their manufacture and sale. In fact, however, they may be wanted for •purposes that are not only innocent but useful, and restrictions can’t be imposed in •one case without operating also in •the other. Again, it is a proper part of the duty of public authority to guard against accidents. If either a public officer or anyone else saw a person starting to cross a bridge that was known to be unsafe, and there was no time to warn him of his danger, they might seize him and pull him back without any real infringement of his liberty; for liberty consists in doing what one desires, and he doesn’t desire to fall into the river. Nevertheless, when there is not a certainty of trouble but only a risk of it, no-one but the person himself can judge whether in this case he has a strong enough motive to make it worthwhile to run the risk; and so I think he ought only to be warned of the danger, not forcibly prevented from exposing himself to it. (This doesn’t apply if he is a child, or delirious, or in some state of excitement or pre-occupation that won’t let him think carefully.) Similar considerations, applied to such a question as the sale of poisons, may enable us to decide which possible kinds of regulation are contrary to principle and which are not. For example, a precaution such as labelling the drug with some word warning of its dangerous character can be enforced without violation of liberty: the buyer can’t want not to know that the stuff he has bought has poisonous qualities. But to require that in all such cases a doctor’s prescription be produced would make it sometimes impossible, and always expensive, to obtain the article for legitimate uses. The only way that I can see of putting difficulties in the way of crime committed through poison, without significantly infringing on the liberty of those who want the poisonous substance for other purposes, is to provide what Bentham has aptly called ‘preappointed evidence’. This is familiar to everyone in the case of contracts.

When a contract is entered into, it is usual and right that the law should require, as a condition of its being enforceable, that certain formalities should be observed—signatures, attestation of witnesses, and so on—so that if any dispute should later arise there will be evidence to show that the contract was really entered into, and that there was nothing in the circumstances to make it legally invalid: the effect being to throw great obstacles in the way of fictitious contracts, or contracts that wouldn’t be valid if the circumstances in which they were made became known.

Precautions of a similar nature might be enforced in the sale of articles that could be used as instruments of crime. The seller, for example, might be required to enter in a register the exact time of the sale, the name and address of the buyer, and the precise quality and quantity sold; to ask what it was wanted for, and to record the answer he received. And when there was no medical prescription, the presence of some third person might be required, to bring home to the purchaser the fact ·of what he was buying·, in case there should afterwards be reason to think it had been used for criminal purposes. Such regulations wouldn’t make it much harder •to obtain the poison, but would make it much harder •to use it improperly without detection.

63

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

·Selling alcohol·

Society’s inherent right to ward off crimes against itself by antecedent precautions suggests the obvious limitations to the maxim that purely self-regarding misconduct cannot properly be meddled with in the way of prevention or punishment. For example, drunkenness isn’t a fit subject for legislative interference; but if someone had once been convicted of an act of violence to others under the influence of drink, I think it legitimate that he should be placed under a special legal restriction, personal to himself; that if he were ever again found drunk he would be liable to a penalty, and that if when in that state he committed another offence, the punishment he would be liable to for that other offence should be increased in severity. In a person whom drunkenness excites to do harm to others, making himself drunk is a crime against others. Another example: if an idle person isn’t receiving support from the public or breaking a contract, it would be tyranny for him to be legally punished for his idleness; but if he is failing to perform his legal duties to others, as for instance to support his children, it is not tyrannical to force him to fulfil that obligation—by forced labour if no other means are available. This applies whether the source of the trouble is his idleness or some other avoidable cause.

Again, there are many acts which, being directly harmful only to the agents themselves, ought not to be legally prohibited, but which when done publicly are a violation of good manners. That brings them within the category of offences against others, and so they may rightfully be prohibited. Offences against decency come into this category, but I shan’t spend time on them, especially since they are connected only indirectly with our subject. ·Indecent actions are thought of as wrong in themselves, whether or not done publicly; but· the objection to publicness—·which is our subject·—is equally strong in the case of many actions that aren’t in themselves condemnable and aren’t thought to be so by anyone.

There is another question to which we need an answer that is consistent with the principles I have laid down. Take some case of

personal conduct that is ·generally· supposed to be blameable, but which respect for liberty prevents society from preventing or punishing, because the harm directly resulting from it falls wholly on the person himself.

The question is: if the agent is free to act like that, ought others to be equally free to advise or encourage him to do so? This question isn’t entirely easy. When someone invites someone else to act in a certain way, we can’t say that what the inviter is doing is ‘strictly his own business’. Advising or inducing someone is a social act; so we might think that it—like actions in general that affect others—is amenable to social control. But a little reflection corrects the first impression by showing that even though the case doesn’t fall strictly within the definition of individual liberty, it does fall within the scope of the reasons for the principle of individual liberty. ·Here is how·. If people must be allowed, in whatever concerns only themselves, •to act as seems best to themselves at their own peril, they must equally be free •to consult with one another about what should be done—to exchange opinions and give and receive suggestions. Whatever it is permitted to do, it must be permitted to advise to do. The question is doubtful only when the advisor gets a personal benefit from his advice, when he makes his living out of promoting what society and the state consider to be an evil.

64

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

·Prostitution and gambling·

That introduces a new element of complication, namely, the existence of classes of people whose interests are opposed to what is considered as the good of the public, and whose way of living is based on counteracting that good. Ought this to be interfered with or not? For example, •fornication [= ‘sexual intercourse outside marriage’] must be tolerated, and so must •gambling; but should a person be free to be a •pimp or to keep a •gambling-house? The case is one of those that lie on the exact boundary line between two principles, and it isn’t immediately clear which of the two it properly belongs to. There are arguments on both sides. On the side of toleration this may be said:

The fact of following something as an occupation, and living or profiting by the practice of it, can’t make criminal something that would otherwise be admissible. The act should either be consistently permitted or consistently prohibited. If the principles that we have been defending are true, society as such has no business deciding anything to be wrong that concerns only the individual. It can’t go beyond dissuasion; and one person should be as free to persuade as another to dissuade.

In opposition to this it may be contended that:

Although the public or the state are not warranted in authoritatively deciding, for purposes of repression or punishment, that a given kind of conduct affecting only the interests of the individual is good or bad, if they do regard it as bad they are fully justified in assuming that there is at least an open question about whether it is bad or not. Given just this ·very minimal· assumption, they can’t be acting wrongly in trying to exclude the influence of persuasions that are self-interested, of encouragers who can’t possibly be impartial—ones who have a direct personal interest on one side, the side the state believes to be wrong, and who admit that they have purely personal motives for promoting it. Surely nothing can be lost, no good can be sacrificed, by arranging things in such a way that individuals make their choice, whether wisely or foolishly, on their own initiative, as free as possible from the wiles of people who want to stimulate their inclinations for self-interested purposes of their own. Thus, although

the ·present· laws about gambling are utterly indefensible, and all people should be free to gamble in their own or each other’s houses, or in any place of meeting established by their own subscriptions and open only to the members and their visitors,

nevertheless public gambling-houses shouldn’t be permitted. It is true that the prohibition is never effective, and that however much tyrannical power is given to the police, gambling-houses can always be maintained under other pretences; but still they may be compelled to conduct their operations with a certain degree of secrecy and mystery, so that nobody knows anything about them but those who seek them. That is as much as society should aim at.

There is considerable force in these arguments. I shan’t venture to decide whether they are sufficient to justify the moral anomaly of punishing the accessory to an act when the agent himself is (and must be) allowed to go free—of fining or imprisoning the pimp but not the prostitute or her client, the gambling-house keeper but not the gambler. Still less ought the common operations of buying and selling to be interfered with on analogous grounds. Almost every article that is

65

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

bought and sold could be used in excess, and the sellers have a financial interest in encouraging that excess; but no argument can be based on this in favour of (for instance) the Maine Law [see page 58]; because the class of dealers in strong drinks, though they have a financial interest in their product’s being misused, are indispensably required for the sake of their legitimate use. However, the motivation these dealers have for promoting excessive use of alcohol is a real evil, and it justifies the state in imposing restrictions and requiring guarantees—ones that would be infringements of legitimate liberty if it weren’t for that justification.

·Dissuasion·

A further question: when the state regards certain conduct as contrary to the best interests of the agent, should it without forbidding that conduct nevertheless discourage it? For example, should the state take measures to make the means of drunkenness more costly, or make them harder to get by limiting the number of the places where they are sold? On this as on most other practical questions, many distinctions need to be made. To tax stimulants solely so as to make them more difficult to obtain is a measure differing only in degree from prohibiting them entirely; and it would be justifiable only if prohibition were justifiable. Every increase of cost is a prohibition to those who can’t afford the newly raised price; and to those who can afford it, the increase is a penalty inflicted on them for gratifying a particular taste. Their choice of pleasures, and their way of spending their income (after satisfying their legal and moral obligations to the state and to individuals), are their own concern and must be left to their own judgment. These considerations may seem at first sight to condemn the selection of alcohol as a special subject of taxation for purposes of revenue. But it must be remembered •that taxation for fiscal purposes is absolutely inevitable; •that in most countries a considerable part of that taxation has to be indirect; and therefore •that the state can’t help imposing penalties on the use of some articles of consumption—penalties that may prevent some people from buying such articles. So the state has a duty to consider, in the imposition of taxes, what commodities the consumers can best spare; and that points very clearly to commodities that it thinks are positively harmful when used in more than very moderate quantities. (Something that will harm people is certainly something they can spare!) So taxation of stimulants—up to the point that produces the largest amount of revenue (supposing that the state needs so much)—is not only admissible but to be approved of.

How exclusive a privilege should the sale of these commodities be? The answer depends on what purposes the restriction is intended to serve. All places where the public gather require the restraint of a police [here = ‘the restraint of enforceable rules governing how they are run’], and this is especially true of drinking-places, because offences against society are especially apt to originate there. So it is appropriate •to confine the power of selling alcoholic drinks (at least for consumption on the spot) to persons of known or vouched-for respectability of conduct; •to make whatever regulations about hours of opening and closing are needed for public surveillance; and •to withdraw the license if breaches of the peace repeatedly take place through the connivance or incapacity of the keeper of the drinking-house, or if it becomes a rendezvous for thinking up and planning offences against the law. [Mill here uses ‘connivance’ in its proper meaning, which comes from a Latin word meaning ‘to close one’s eyes’. To connive at something is to pretend not to notice it, instead of putting a stop to it as you ought to do.] I can’t think of any further restriction that would be in principle justifiable. What about limiting the

66

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

number of beer and spirit-houses so as to make them harder to get to, thus reducing the occasions of temptation? No. Not only does that expose all to an inconvenience because there are some who would make bad use of easily found drinking-houses, but also it is suited only to a state of society in which the labouring classes are openly treated as children or savages, and placed under a discipline of restraint—·like that of a child·—to fit them for future admission to the privileges of freedom. This is not the principle on which the labouring classes are said to be governed in any free country; and no-one who properly values freedom will assent to their being so governed unless this is the case:

All efforts have been exhausted to train them for freedom and govern them as freemen, and it has been definitively proved that they can only be governed as children.

The bare statement of this condition shows the absurdity of supposing that such efforts have been made in any case that needs be considered here. The institutions of this country are a mass of inconsistencies, with the result that

•we admit into our practice restraints that belong to the system of despotic government (also called ‘paternal’ government), while

•the general freedom of our institutions prevents the exercise of the amount of control that would be needed to make the restraints really effective as moral education.

·And so we get the worst of both worlds, so to speak·.

·Contracts—slavery·

I pointed out in an early part of this work that the liberty of •the individual, in matters that concern him alone, implies a corresponding liberty in •any number of individuals to regulate by mutual agreement such matters as involve them jointly and don’t involve anyone else. There is no problem about this so long as the •will of all the people in question remains unaltered; but since that •will may change, it is often necessary (even when no-one else is affected) that they should enter into engagements [= roughly ‘contracts’] with one another; and when they do, it is generally good that those engagements should be kept. Yet probably every country has laws creating some exceptions to this general rule. People are not held to engagements that violate the rights of third parties; but also it is sometimes considered a sufficient reason for releasing them from an engagement that it is harmful to themselves. In this and most other civilized countries, for example, an engagement by which a person sells himself (or allows himself to be sold) as a slave would be null and void—not enforced by law or by public opinion. The ground for thus limiting his power of voluntarily disposing of his own course of life is obvious, and is very clearly seen in this extreme case. Here it is.

The reason for not interfering with a person’s voluntary acts except for the sake of others is consideration for his liberty. His voluntary choice is evidence that what he so chooses is desirable to him, or at least endurable by him, and his good is on the whole best provided for by allowing him to pursue it in his own way. But by selling himself as a slave he abdicates his liberty; he forgoes any future use of it after that single act. He therefore defeats the very purpose that is the justification for allowing him to dispose of himself. From now on he won’t be free.... The principle of freedom can’t require that he should be free not to be free! Being allowed to give up his freedom is not freedom.

67

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

These reasons, the force of which is so conspicuous in this special case, are evidently of far wider application; yet a limit is everywhere set to them by the necessities of life, which continually require not that we should give up our freedom but that we should consent to this or that limitation of it. But the principle that demands uncontrolled freedom of action in all that concerns only the agents themselves requires that those who have become obliged to one another in things that don’t concern any third party should be able to release one another from their engagement....

·Contracts—marriage·

Baron Wilhelm von Humboldt, in the excellent Essay from which I have already quoted, asserts his view that engagements involving personal relations or services should never be legally binding beyond a limited duration of time; and that the most important of these engagements, marriage, having the special feature that its objectives are defeated unless the feelings of both the parties are in harmony with it, should require nothing more than the declared wish of either party to dissolve it. This subject is too important and too complicated to be discussed in an aside, and I touch on it only so far as I need it for purposes of illustration. This work of Baron Humboldt’s aims to be brief and very general; and that required him in this instance to settle for announcing his conclusion without discussing his reasons for it. If he had gone into the reasons, he would doubtless have recognized that the question can’t be settled on grounds as simple as those to which he confines himself. When a person, either by explicit promise or by conduct, has encouraged someone else to rely on his continuing to act in a certain way—to build expectations and plans, and to stake any part of his plan of life on that supposition—a new series of moral obligations arises on his part towards that person. They may possibly be overruled, but they can’t be ignored. Again, if the relation between two contracting parties •has had consequences for others, if it •has placed third parties in any special position or even (as in the case of marriage) •has brought third parties into existence, then both the contracting parties come to have •obligations towards those third persons; and the choice of whether to maintain the original contract must have a great effect on whether—or at least on how—those •obligations are fulfilled. It doesn’t follow—and I don’t believe—that these obligations extend to requiring the fulfilment of the contract at all costs to the happiness of the reluctant party, but they are a necessary element in the question. And even if, as von Humboldt maintains, they ought to make no difference to the •legal freedom of the parties to release themselves from the engagement (and I also hold that they oughtn’t to make much legal difference), they necessarily make a great difference to the parties’ •moral freedom. A person is ·morally· bound to take all these circumstances into account before deciding on a step that may affect such important interests of others; and if he doesn’t allow proper weight to those interests he is morally responsible for the wrong ·he does to the third parties·. I have made these obvious remarks as an aid to illustrating the general principle of liberty, and not because they are at all needed on the particular question ·of divorce·. So far from needing reminders about obligations to third parties, discussions of divorce are usually handled as though the interests of children were everything, and those of adults were nothing!

·Power of husbands over wives·

I have already remarked that because there are no recognized general principles ·governing it·, liberty is often granted

68

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

where it should be withheld, as well as withheld where it should be granted. One of the cases in which the sentiment of liberty is the strongest in modern Europe is a case where I think it is altogether misplaced. A person should be free to do as he likes in his own concerns, but he ought not to be free to do as he likes in acting for someone else under the pretext that the other person’s affairs are his affairs. The state, while it respects the liberty of each in what specially concerns himself, is •bound to maintain a vigilant control over his exercise of any power over others that it lets him have. This •obligation is almost entirely disregarded in the case of family relations, a case whose direct influence on human happiness makes it more important than all the others taken together. The almost despotic power of husbands over wives isn’t something I need to go into here, ·because it doesn’t provide an illuminating work-out for the principle of liberty. There are two reasons for this. •One is that cure for this despotism is perfectly simple·: all that is needed for the complete removal of the evil is for wives to have the same rights, and to be protected by the law in the same manner, as everyone else. •·The other is that nobody defends the power of husbands over wives by mis-applying the notion of the husbands’ liberty·: on this subject, the defenders of established injustice don’t avail themselves of the plea of liberty, but come out openly as the champions of power. It is in the case of children that misapplied notions of liberty are a real obstacle to the state’s fulfilling its duties. One would almost think that a man’s children were supposed to be literally (and not metaphorically) a part of himself, given how public opinion watches for and objects to the smallest interference of law with his absolute and exclusive •control over them. It watches over this more than over almost any interference with the father’s own •freedom of action—so much less do people value •liberty than they value •power.

·Bringing up children·

Consider, for example, the case of education. Isn’t it almost a self-evident axiom that the state should require and compel the education, up to a certain standard, of every human being who is born its citizen? Yet who is there that isn’t afraid to recognize and assert this truth? Hardly anyone indeed will deny that it is one of the most sacred duties of the parents (or, as law and usage now stand, the father!) after calling a human being into the world to give to that being an education fitting him to perform his part well in life towards others and towards himself. But while this is unanimously declared to be the father’s duty, hardly anyone in this country will listen to the suggestion that he should be obliged to perform it. Instead of his being required to make any exertion or sacrifice for securing •education to the child, it is left to his choice to accept •it or not, ·even· when it is provided at no cost to himself! It still isn’t ·generally· recognized that to bring a child into existence without •a fair prospect of being able to provide food for its body and also •instruction and training for its mind is a moral crime, both against the unfortunate offspring and against society; and that if the parent doesn’t fulfil this obligation the state ought to ensure that it is fulfilled—with the costs falling on the parent as far as possible.

If the ·government’s· duty to enforce universal education were once admitted, that would put an end to the difficulties about what the state should teach, and how it should teach. These difficulties now convert the subject into a mere battle-field for sects and parties, causing the time and labour that should have been spent on •educating to be wasted in •quarrelling about education. If the government made up its mind to require a good education for every child, it could save itself the trouble of providing one. It could leave it up to

69

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

parents to obtain the education where and how they pleased, and restrict its own involvement to •helping to pay the school fees of the poorer classes of children, and •paying the entire school expenses of those who have no-one else to pay for them. The reasonable objections that are brought against State education don’t apply to the •enforcement of education by the state; their target is the state’s taking on itself the task of •directing that education, which is a totally different thing. No-one objects more strongly than I do to the state’s being in charge of the whole or any large part of the education of the people. Everything I have said about the importance of individuality of •character, and variety in •opinions and •ways of life, applies also to variety in •education, which is of the same enormous importance as those three. A general state education is a mere contrivance for moulding people to be exactly like one another; and as the mould in which it casts them is the one that pleases the predominant power in the government, insofar as it is efficient and successful to that extent it establishes a despotism over the mind, which naturally leads to despotism over the body. And this is true whatever the predominant power may be—whether a monarch, a priesthood, an aristocracy, or the majority of the people at that time. If there is to be any education established and controlled by the state, it should be merely one among many competing experiments, carried on for the purpose of example and stimulus, to keep the others up to a certain standard of excellence.

An exception to this generalization is created when a society in general is in such a backward condition that it can’t or won’t provide for itself any proper institutions of education unless the government takes on the task. In that case, indeed, the government may accept for itself, as the lesser of two great evils, the business of schools and universities; just as it may take on the running of joint-stock companies in a country that has no system of private enterprise adequate for undertaking great works of industry.

But in general, if a country contains enough people qualified to provide education under government auspices, those same people would be able and willing to give an equally good education at private schools, given the assurance of payment that would be provided by a law making education compulsory, together with state aid to those unable to pay for themselves.

How could such a law be enforced? It would have to be through public examinations, extending to all children and beginning at an early age. An age might be fixed at which every child must be examined, to discover whether he or she could read. A child who turns out to be unable to read might be sent to school at the father’s expense, unless the father had some sufficient ground of excuse; and he might also be subjected to a moderate fine which he could if necessary pay by working it off. Once in each year the examination should be renewed, with a gradually extending range of subjects, so as to make it virtually compulsory for everyone to have and retain a certain minimum of general knowledge. Beyond that minimum, there should be voluntary examinations on all subjects, at which all who reach a certain standard of proficiency might claim a certificate. To prevent the state from exercising through these arrangements an improper influence over opinion, the knowledge required for passing an examination should, even in the higher class of examinations, be strictly confined to facts and positive [= ‘factual’] science—and of course the merely instrumental parts of knowledge, such as languages and their use. The examinations on religion, politics, or other controversial topics should depend not on the truth or falsehood of opinions ·about those topics·, but on matters

70

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

of fact—that such and such an opinion is held, on such and such grounds, by such and such authors, or schools, or churches. Under this system, the coming generation would be no worse off in regard to all controversial truths than they are at present; they would be brought up as churchmen or dissenters as they now are, the state merely taking care that they should be informed churchmen or informed dissenters. There would be nothing to hinder them from being taught religion, if their parents so chose, at the same schools where they were taught other things. All attempts by the state to bias the conclusions of its citizens on controversial subjects are evil; but the state may very properly offer to discover and certify that a person possesses the knowledge needed to make his conclusions, on any given subject, worth attending to. A student of philosophy would be the better for being able to pass an examination on both Locke and Kant, whichever of the two he takes up with, and even if he doesn’t take up with either; and there is no reasonable objection to examining an atheist on the case for Christianity, provided he isn’t required to proclaim that he accepts it. But I think that the examinations in the higher branches of knowledge should be entirely voluntary. It would give too dangerous a power to governments if they were allowed to exclude anyone from professions, even from the profession of teacher, for allegedly not being qualified. I agree with Wilhelm von Humboldt •that ·university· degrees or other public certificates of scientific or professional acquirements should be given to all who present themselves for examination and pass the test; but •that such certificates should give them no advantage over competitors other than the weight that public opinion may give to them as evidence that the person is qualified.

·Having children·

It is not only in the matter of education that misplaced notions of liberty prevent the •moral obligations of parents from being recognized and •legal obligations on them from being imposed, in matters where there are always the strongest grounds for the •former and in many cases for the •latter also. The very act of causing the existence of a human being is one of the most responsible actions [= ‘actions in which one takes on responsibilities’] in the range of human life. To undertake this responsibility—giving a life that may be either a curse or a blessing—is a crime against the offspring unless he or she will have at least the ordinary chances of a desirable existence. And in a country that is over-populated or threatened with being so, to produce more than a very small number of children is a serious offence against all who live by the pay they get for their work, because every new child threatens wage-levels by adding to the competition for work. The laws which in many countries on the European continent forbid marriage unless the parties can show that they have the means of supporting a family don’t exceed the legitimate powers of the state: and whether such laws really are advisable (which mainly depends on local circumstances and feelings), they are not objectionable as violations of liberty. Such laws are interferences by the state to prohibit a bad act—an act injurious to others, which ought to bring criticism and social stigma even when it isn’t thought advisable to add legal punishment. Yet the current ideas of liberty, which bend so easily to real infringements of the freedom of the individual in matters that concern only himself, would repel any attempt to restrain his inclinations when they will otherwise lead to lives of wretchedness and depravity for his offspring, with many evils to other people who are close enough to feel the effects of how the offspring

71

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

act. When we compare the strange •respect of mankind for liberty, with their strange •lack of respect for it, we might imagine that a man had an indispensable •right to do harm to others and •no right at all to please himself without doing harm to anyone.

·Size of government·

I have saved up till the last a large class of questions about the limits of government interference that don’t strictly belong to the subject of this Essay but are closely connected with it. These questions arise when the reasons against interference don’t turn on the principle of liberty. The question is not about •restraining the actions of individuals but about •helping them: it is asked whether the government should do or cause to be done something for their benefit, instead of leaving it to be done by themselves individually or in voluntary groups.

When government interference wouldn’t involve any infringement of liberty, it may still be objected to on either of three grounds.

(1) The first is when the thing to be done is likely to be better done by individuals than by the government. Speaking generally, no-one is as fit to conduct a business or decide how or by whom it shall be conducted as are those whose personal interests are involved in it. This principle condemns the interferences (once so common) of the legislature or the officers of government in the ordinary processes of industry. But this matter has been sufficiently enlarged on by political economists, and is not particularly related to the principles of this Essay.

(2) The second objection has more to do with our subject. In many cases, though •individuals may not on average do the particular thing as well as the officers of government would, it is nevertheless desirable that it should be done by •them as a means to their own mental education—a way of strengthening their active faculties, exercising their judgment, and giving them a familiar knowledge of the subjects with which they are thus left to deal. Though not the only reason, this is a chief reason for •jury trials in cases that aren’t political; for •free and popular local and municipal institutions; for •having industrial and philanthropic enterprises run by voluntary associations. These aren’t questions of liberty, and are connected with that subject only by remote tendencies; but they are questions of development. This is not the place to go at length into these things as parts of national education; as being indeed the special training of a citizen, the practical part of the political education of a free people, taking them out of the narrow circle of personal and family selfishness, getting them used to the wider view of joint interests, the management of joint concerns—habituating them to act from public or semi-public motives and guide their conduct by aims that unite them instead of isolating them from one another. Without these habits and powers, a free constitution can neither be worked nor preserved, as is illustrated by the too-often transitory nature of political freedom in countries where it doesn’t rest on a sufficient basis of local liberties. The management of purely local business by the localities, and of the great enterprises of industry by the union of those who voluntarily put up the money for them, is further recommended by all the advantages that I have presented as belonging to individuality of development and variety in ways of acting. Government operations tend to be everywhere alike. With individuals and voluntary associations, on the other hand, there are varied experiments and endless diversity of experience. The state can usefully •make itself a central depository of the experience resulting from many trials,

72

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

and •actively circulate and diffuse knowledge about what that experience has shown. Its business is to enable each experimenter to benefit by the experiments of others, instead of tolerating no experiments but its own.

(3) The third and most powerful reason for restricting the interference of government is the great evil of adding unnecessarily to its power. Every function added to those already exercised by the government causes its influence over hopes and fears to be more widely diffused, and increasingly converts the active and ambitious part of the public into hangers-on of the government, or of some party that aims at becoming the government. If •the roads, the railways, the banks, the insurance offices, the great joint-stock companies, the universities, and the public charities, were all branches of the government; if in addition •the municipal corporations and local boards, with all that they now do, became departments of the central administration; and if •the employees of all these different enterprises were appointed and paid by the government, and looked to the government for every promotion or pay-increase, not all the freedom of the press and democratic constitution of the legislature would make this or any other country free except in name. And the more efficiently and scientifically the administrative machinery was constructed—the more skillful the arrangements for obtaining the best qualified hands and heads with which to work it—the greater the harm it would do. In England it has recently been proposed that all the members of the government’s civil service should be selected by competitive examination, to obtain for those jobs the most intelligent and instructed persons that can be found; and much has been said and written for and against this proposal. One of the arguments most insisted on by its opponents is that a permanent official servant of the state doesn’t have good enough prospects of salary and importance to attract the highest talents, which will always be able to find a more inviting career in the professions, or in the service of companies and other public bodies. It would not have been surprising if this argument had been used by the friends of the proposition, as an answer to its principal difficulty. It is certainly strange coming from the opponents! What is urged as an •objection is ·really· the •safety-valve of the proposed system. If indeed all the high talent of the country could be drawn into the service of the government, a proposal tending to bring about that result might well cause uneasiness. If every part of the business of society that required organized co-operation or large and comprehensive views were in the hands of the government, and if government posts were always filled by the ablest men, almost all the enlarged culture and practised intelligence in the country would be concentrated in a numerous bureaucracy, to whom alone the rest of the community would look for all things: the mass of people for direction and dictation in all they had to do; able and aspiring people for personal advancement. (I said ‘almost all’. The exception would be the intelligence and ability of scientists and scholars.) The sole objects of ambition would be to be admitted into the ranks of this bureaucracy and to rise in it. Under this regime, ·government that badly needs changing will not be changed·. •The outside public doesn’t have the practical experience it needs to be qualified to criticize or check the mode of operation of the bureaucracy. And •even if the accidents of despotism or the natural working of democratic institutions occasionally raise to the summit a ruler or rulers who want to reform the government, no reform can be carried out that is contrary to the interests of the bureaucracy. That is the sad condition of the Russian empire, as is shown in the accounts of those who have had a good enough opportunity to observe it. The Czar himself is powerless against the bureaucratic body: he can send any

73

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

one of them to Siberia, but he can’t govern without them or against their will. On every decree of his they have a tacit veto, ·which they can exercise· by merely not carrying the decree into effect. In countries of more advanced civilization and of a more revolutionary spirit the public, accustomed to expect everything to be done for them by the state, or at least to do nothing for themselves without asking the state not only for permission to do it but even how it is to be done, naturally hold the state responsible for everything bad that happens to them; and when things become worse than they are willing to put up with, they rise against the government and make what is called a ‘revolution’; whereupon somebody else, with or without legitimate authority from the nation, leaps into the seat ·of power·, issues his orders to the bureaucracy, and everything goes on much as it did before—the bureaucracy being unchanged, and nobody else being capable of taking their place.

A very different scene appears among a people accustomed to transact their own business. In France a large part of the people have been engaged in military service, many having held at least the rank of noncommissioned officers; so in every popular uprising there are several persons competent to take the lead and improvise some reasonable plan of action. What the French are in •military affairs, the Americans are in every kind of •civil business: leave them without a government and every group of Americans is able to improvise one and to carry on that or any other public business with a sufficient amount of intelligence, order and decision. This is what every free people ought to be; and a people capable of this is certain to be free; it will never let itself be enslaved by any man or group of men ·who can take control only· because they are able to seize and pull the reins of the central administration. No bureaucracy can hope to make such a people as this do or undergo anything that they don’t like. But where everything is done through the bureaucracy, nothing to which the bureaucracy is really opposed can be done at all. The constitution [here = ‘governmental structure’] of such countries is an organization of the experience and practical ability of the nation into a disciplined body for the purpose of governing the rest; and the more perfect that organization is in itself, the more successful in drawing to itself and educating for its own purposes the ablest people from all ranks of the community, the more complete is the bondage of everyone—including the members of the bureaucracy. For •the governors are as much the slaves of •their organization and discipline as •the governed are slaves of •the governors. A Chinese mandarin is as much the tool and creature of a despotism as the humblest peasant. An individual Jesuit is to the utmost degree of abasement the slave of his order—·the Society of Jesus·—although the order itself exists for the collective power and importance of its members.

It should also be borne in mind that the absorption of all the principal ability of the country into the governing body is fatal, sooner or later, to the mental activity and progressiveness of the ·governing· body itself. Its members are banded together, working a system which (like all systems) has to proceed to a large extent by fixed rules; and this puts them under the constant •temptation of sinking into lazy routine, and if they occasionally desert that blinkered trudge along the same old path they have the •temptation to rush into some half-examined crudity that has struck the fancy of some leading member of the corps. And the only guard against these closely allied (though seemingly opposite) tendencies, the only stimulus that can keep the ability of the ·governing· body itself up to a high standard, is its being open to the watchful criticism of equally able people outside the body. So it is indispensable that there should be

74

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

some way, independently of the government, of having such able people and giving them the opportunities and experience necessary for a correct judgment of great practical affairs. If we •do want to have permanently a skillful and efficient body of officials, above all, a body that can come up with original ideas and is willing to adopt improvements, and if we •don’t want our bureaucracy to degenerate into a pedantocracy, this body mustn’t absorb into itself all the occupations that form and cultivate the skills required for the government of mankind.

So we have on one side •the evils ·in over-large government·, evils that are so formidable to human freedom and advancement; and on the other side •the benefits that come from the collective application of the force of society (under its recognized leaders) for removing obstacles to its well-being. ·This gives us a question of balance, the question of· how to secure as much of •the advantages of centralized power and intelligence as possible without •handing over to the government too great a proportion of the society’s activity. ·In brief·: At what point do •the evils start to predominate over •the benefits? This is one of the most difficult and complicated questions in the business of government. It is largely a question of detail, in which many and various considerations must be kept in view and no absolute rule can be laid down. But I believe that the practical principle that is needed for us to stay safe, the ideal to be kept in view, the standard by which to test all arrangements intended for overcoming the difficulty, can be expressed thus:

•the greatest dissemination of power consistent with efficiency, but

•the greatest possible centralization of information, and diffusion of it from the centre.

·Applying the former of these would give a result like that· in the New England states: all business that wouldn’t be better left to the individuals directly concerned would be distributed amongst a large number of public officials, chosen by the localities. ·And, applying the second of the two rules of thumb·, each branch of local affairs would he superintended centrally by a branch of the general government; and the superintending body would act like a lens, concentrating the variety of information and experience derived from •the conduct of that branch of public business in all the localities, from •everything analogous that is done in foreign countries, and from •the general principles of political science. This central organization should have a right to know all that is done, and a special duty to make the knowledge acquired in one place available for others. Freed from the petty prejudices and narrow views of a locality by its elevated position and wide sphere of observation, its advice would naturally carry much authority; but its actual power as a permanent institution should, in my view, be limited to compelling the local officers to obey the laws laid down for their guidance. In everything not provided for by general rules, those officers should be left to their own judgment, under responsibility to their constituents. For the violation of rules they should be answerable to the law, and the rules themselves should be •laid down by the •legislature; the •central administrative authority only •watching over whether they are obeyed and—if they are not—•appealing to the courts to enforce the law or (as the case may be) •appealing to the ·local· constituencies to dismiss the officials who haven’t acted in the spirit of the law. That is the general conception of how the Poor Law Board is intended to superintend the administrators of the Poor Rate ·in separate localities· throughout this country. Whatever powers the Board has exercised beyond this limit were right and necessary in that particular case, to cure maladministration in matters deeply affecting not merely the localities but the whole country; since no locality has a moral

75

Liberty John Stuart Mill 5: Applications

right to mismanage in such a way as to turn itself into a nest of pauperism, necessarily overflowing into other localities and worsening the moral and physical condition of the whole labouring community. The Poor Law Board has powers of administrative coercion and subordinate legislation which, owing to the state of opinion on the subject, it doesn’t use much. It is perfectly justifiable in using them in a case where the •national interest is significantly involved, but they would be wholly out of place in the supervision of •purely local interests. But a central organ of information and instruction for all the localities would be equally valuable in all branches of administration. A government can’t have too much of the kind of activity that positively aids and stimulates individual effort and development. The trouble starts when instead of arousing the activity and powers of individuals and bodies it substitutes its own activity for theirs; when, instead of informing, advising, and sometimes denouncing, it makes them work in chains or orders them to stand aside while it does their work for them. The worth of a state in the long run is the worth of the individuals composing it. A state that •dwarfs its individuals in order to •make them easier to lead will find—even if it wanted to lead for beneficial purposes—that with small men no great thing can really be accomplished. And a state that makes

•the interests of the individuals’ mental expansion and elevation

subordinate to

•having a little more administrative skill (or the semblance of it that practice gives) in the details of business

will eventually find that the perfection of machinery to which it has sacrificed everything will do no good, because of the lack of the vital power which, in order that the machine might work more smoothly, it has preferred to banish.

76

Utilitarianism

John Stuart Mill

Copyright © 2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth.
First launched: September 2005 Last amended: April 2008
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Chapter 1: General Remarks 1
Chapter 2: What utilitarianism is 4

·Higher and Lower Pleasures·...........5
·Happiness as an Aim·.....................8
·Self-Sacrifice·................................11
·Setting the Standard too High?·.....12
·Is Utilitarianism Chilly?·................13
·Utilitarianism as ‘Godless’·.............15
·Expediency·..................................15
·Time to Calculate?·.......................16
·Bad Faith·....................................17

Chapter 3: What will motivate us to obey the principle of utility? 18
Chapter 4: What sort of proof can be given for the principle of utility? 24

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill

Chapter 5: The connection between justice and utility 28

·Punishment·.....38
·Wages·............39
·Taxation·.........39

ii

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 1: General remarks

Chapter 1: General Remarks

Little progress has been made towards deciding the controversy concerning the criterion of right and wrong. Among all the facts about the present condition of human knowledge, the state of this controversy is •most unlike what might have been expected and •most indicative significant of the backward state in which theorizing on the most important subjects still lingers. That is how little progress has been made! From the dawn of philosophy the question concerning the summum bonum [Latin, = ‘the greatest good’] or, what is the same thing, concerning the foundation of morality, has

•been regarded as the main problem in speculative thought,

•occupied the most gifted intellects, and

•divided them into sects and schools, vigorously warring against one another.

And after more than two thousand years the same discussions continue! Philosophers still line up under the same opposing battle-flags, and neither thinkers nor people in general seem to be any nearer to being unanimous on the subject than when young Socrates listened to old Protagoras and asserted the theory of utilitarianism against the popular morality of the so-called ‘sophist’ (I’m assuming here that Plato’s dialogue is based on a real conversation). [Except on page 14, ‘popular’ is used in this work only to mean ‘of the people’, with no implication about being liked.]

It is true that similar confusion and uncertainty, and in some cases similar disagreements, exist concerning the basic principles of all the sciences—even including the one that is thought to be the most certain of them, namely mathematics—without doing much harm, and usually without doing any harm, to the trustworthiness of the conclusions of those sciences. This seems odd, but it can be explained: the detailed doctrines of a science usually •are not deduced from what are called its first principles and •don’t need those principles to make them evident. If this weren’t so, there would be no science more precarious, and none whose conclusions were more weakly based, than algebra. This doesn’t get any of its certainty from what are commonly taught to learners as its •elements ·or first principles·, because •these, as laid down by some of its most eminent teachers, are as full of fictions as English law and as full of mysteries as theology. The truths that are ultimately accepted as the first principles of a science are really the last results of metaphysical analysis of the basic notions that are involve in the science in question. Their relation to the science is not that of •foundations to a building but of •roots to a tree, which can do their job equally well if they are never dug down to and exposed to light. But though in science the particular truths precede the general theory, the reverse of that might be expected with a practical art such as morals or legislation. [Here an ‘art’ is any activity requiring a set of rules or techniques, and ‘practical’ means ‘having to do with human conduct’.] All action is for the sake of some end; and it seems natural to suppose that rules of action must take their whole character and colour from the end at which actions aim. When we are pursuing something, a clear and precise conception of what we are pursuing would seem to be the first thing we need, rather than being the last we are to look forward to. One would think that a test· or criterion· of right and wrong must be •the means of discovering what is right or wrong, and not •a consequence of having already discovered this.

1

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 1: General remarks

The difficulty can’t be avoided by bringing in the popular theory of a natural ·moral· faculty, a sense or instinct informing us of right and wrong. For one thing, the ‘criterion’ dispute includes a dispute about whether there is any such moral instinct. And, anyway, believers in it who have any philosophical ability have been obliged to abandon the idea that it—·the moral faculty or ‘moral sense’ or moral intuition·—picks out what is right or wrong in this or that •particular case in the way that our other senses pick up the sight or sound that is actually present ·in the •particular concrete situation·. Our moral faculty, according to all those of its friends who are entitled to count as thinkers, supplies us only with the •general principles of moral judgments; it belongs with reason and not with sense-perception; what we can expect from it are the abstract doctrines of morality, and not the perception of morality in particular concrete situations. The intuitionist school of ethics insists on the necessity of general laws just as much as does the inductive school (as we might label it). They both agree that· knowing· the morality of an individual action is not a matter of •direct perception but of the •application of a law to an individual case. The two schools mostly agree also in what moral laws they recognize; but they differ on

•what makes those moral laws evident, and

•what give them their authority.

According to the intuitionists, the principles of morals are evident a priori: if you know the meanings of the terms in which they are expressed, you’ll have to assent to them. According to the inductivists, •right and wrong are questions of observation and experience just as •truth and falsehood are. But both schools hold equally that morality must be deduced from principles; and the intuitive school affirm as strongly as the inductive does that there is a science of morals—· i.e. an organized system containing basic axioms from which the rest can be rigorously deduced·. Yet they seldom attempt to provide a list of the a priori principles that are to serve as the premises of the science; and they almost never make any effort to reduce those various principles to one first principle, one first all-purpose ground of obligation. Instead, they either •treat the ordinary precepts of morals as though they had a priori authority or •lay down as the all-purpose groundwork of those maxims some general moral principle that is much less obviously authoritative than the maxims themselves and hasn’t ever been widely accepted. Yet to support their claims there ought to be one fundamental principle or law at the root of all morality; or if there are several of them, •they should be clearly rank-ordered in relation to one another, and •there should be a self-evident principle or rule for deciding amongst them when they conflict· in a particular case·.

The lack of any clear recognition of an ultimate standard may have •corrupted the moral beliefs of mankind or made them uncertain; on the other hand, the bad effects of this deficiency may have •been moderated in practice. To determine how far things have gone in the •former way and how far in the •latter would require a complete critical survey of past and present ethical doctrine. But it wouldn’t be hard to show that whatever steadiness or consistency mankind’s moral beliefs have achieved has been mainly due to the silent influence of a standard that hasn’t been ·consciously· recognised. In the absence of an acknowledged first principle, ethics has been not so much a •guide to men in forming their moral views as a •consecration of the views they actually have; but men’s views—both for and against—are greatly influenced by what effects on their happiness they suppose things to have; and so the principle of utility—or, as Bentham eventually called it, ‘the greatest happiness principle’—has had a large share in forming the moral doctrines even of those who

2

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 1: General remarks

most scornfully reject its authority. And every school of thought admits that the influence of actions on happiness is a very significant and even predominant consideration in many of the details of morals, however unwilling they may be to allow the production of happiness as the fundamental principle of morality and the source of moral obligation. I might go much further and say that a priori moralists can’t do without utilitarian arguments (I am not talking about the ones who don’t think they need to argue at all!). It is not my present purpose to criticise these thinkers; but I can’t refrain from bringing in as an illustration a systematic treatise by one of the most illustrious of the a priori moralists, the Metaphysics of Ethics by Kant. This remarkable man, whose system of thought will long remain one of the landmarks in the history of philosophical thought, lays down in that treatise a universal first principle as the origin and ground of moral obligation:

Act in such a way that the rule on which you act could be adopted as a law by all rational beings.

But when he begins to derive any of the actual duties of morality from this principle he fails, almost grotesquely, to show that there would be any contradiction—any logical impossibility, or even any physical impossibility—in the adoption by all rational beings of the most outrageously immoral rules of conduct. All he shows is that the universal adoption of such rules would have consequences that no-one would choose to bring about.

In the present work I shall, without further discussion of the other theories, try to contribute something towards the understanding and appreciation of the Utilitarian or Happiness theory, and towards such proof as it can be given. Obviously this can’t be ‘proof’ in the ordinary and popular meaning of that word. Questions about ultimate ends can’t be settled by direct proof. You can prove something to be good only by showing that it is a means to something that is admitted without proof to be good. The art of medicine is proved to be good by its conducing to health, but how is it possible to prove that health is good? The art of music is good because (among other reasons) it produces pleasure, but what proof could be given that pleasure is good? So if it is claimed that

•there is a comprehensive formula that covers everything that is good in itself, and

•whatever else is good is not good as an end but as a means ·to something that is covered by the formula·,

the formula may be accepted or rejected but it can’t be given what is commonly called a ‘proof’. But we shouldn’t infer that its acceptance or rejection must depend on blind impulse or arbitrary choice. There is a broader meaning of the word ‘proof’ in which this question is as capable of ·being settled by· ‘proof’ as any other of the disputed questions in philosophy. The subject is within reach of the faculty of reason, which doesn’t deal with it solely by ·moral· intuitions ·such as the intuitionists believe in·. Considerations can be presented that are capable of determining the intellect either to give or withhold its assent to the doctrine; and this is equivalent to proof.

We shall examine presently what sort of thing these considerations are and how they apply to the question at hand. In doing this we shall be examining what rational grounds can be given for accepting or rejecting the utilitarian formula. But if there is to be rational acceptance or rejection, the formula should first be correctly understood. I believe that •the chief obstacle to acceptance of the utilitarian principle has been people’s very imperfect grasp of its meaning, and that if the misunderstandings of it—or even just the very gross ones—could be cleared up, the question would be greatly simplified and a large proportion of its difficulties

3

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

removed. So before I embark on the philosophical grounds that can be given for assenting to the utilitarian standard, I shall offer some illustrations of the doctrine itself; aiming to

•show more clearly what it is,

•distinguish it from what it is not, and

•dispose of such of the practical objections to it as come from or are closely connected with mistaken interpretations of its meaning.

Having thus prepared the ground, I shall afterwards try to throw as much light as I can on the question, considered as one of philosophical theory.

Chapter 2: What utilitarianism is

Some people have supposed that those who stand up for ‘utility’ as the test of right and wrong use that term in the restricted and merely colloquial sense in which ‘utility’ is opposed to pleasure. A passing remark is all that needs to be given to that ignorant blunder. [This is probably a protest against, among other things, a school-master in Dickens’s fine novel Hard Times, whose approach to education insisted on what is ‘useful’ and flatly opposed any kind of pleasure.] I owe an apology to the philosophical opponents of utilitarianism for even briefly seeming to regard them as capable of so absurd a misunderstanding. The blunder is all the more extraordinary given that another of the common charges against utilitarianism is the opposite accusation that it bases everything on pleasure (understood very crudely). One able writer has pointedly remarked that the same sort of persons, and often the very same persons, denounce the theory ‘as impracticably dry when the word “utility” precedes the word “pleasure”, and as too practicably voluptuous when the word “pleasure” precedes the word “utility”’! Those who know anything about the matter are aware that every writer from Epicurus to Bentham who maintained the theory of ‘utility’ meant by it not •something to be contrasted with pleasure but •pleasure itself together with freedom from pain; and instead of opposing the useful to the agreeable or the ornamental, they have always declared that ‘useful’ includes these among other things. Yet the common herd, including the herd of writers—not only in newspapers and magazines but in intellectually ambitious books—are perpetually falling into this shallow mistake. Having caught up the word ‘utilitarian’, while knowing nothing whatever about it but its sound, they habitually express by it keeping out or neglecting pleasure in some of its forms, such as beauty, ornament and amusement. And when the term ‘utility’ is ignorantly misused in this way, it isn’t always in criticism of utilitarianism; occasionally it occurs when utilitarianism is being complimented, the idea being that utility is something •superior to frivolity and the mere pleasures of the moment, ·whereas really it •includes them·. This perverted use is the only one in which the word ‘utility’ is popularly known, and the one from which the young are now getting their sole notion of its meaning. Those who introduced the word, but who had for many years stopped using it as a doctrinal label, may well feel

4

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

themselves called upon to resume it, if by doing so they can hope to contribute anything towards rescuing it from this utter degradation.^1

The doctrine that the basis of morals is utility, or the greatest happiness principle, holds that actions are right in proportion as they tend to promote happiness, wrong in proportion as they tend to produce the reverse of happiness. By ‘happiness’ is meant pleasure and the absence of pain; by ‘unhappiness’ is meant pain and the lack of pleasure. To give a clear view of the moral standard set up by the theory, much more needs to be said, especially about what things the doctrine includes in the ideas of pain and pleasure, and to what extent it leaves this as an open question. But these supplementary explanations don’t affect the theory of life on which this theory of morality is based—namely the thesis that

pleasure and freedom from pain are the only things that

are desirable as ends, and that

everything that is desirable at all is so either •for the

pleasure inherent in it or •as means to the promotion of pleasure and the prevention of pain.

(The utilitarian system has as many things that are desirable, in one way or the other, as any other theory of morality.)

Now, such a theory of life arouses utter dislike in many minds, including some that are among the most admirable in feeling and purpose. The view that life has (as they express it) no higher end—no better and nobler object of desire and pursuit—than pleasure they describe as utterly mean and grovelling, a doctrine worthy only of pigs. The followers of Epicurus were contemptuously compared with pigs, very early on, and modern holders of the utilitarian doctrine are occasionally subjected to equally polite comparisons by its German, French, and English opponents.

·Higher and Lower Pleasures·

When attacked in this way, the Epicureans have always answered that it is not they but their accusers who represent human nature in a degrading light, because the accusation implies that human beings are capable only of pleasures that pigs are also capable of. If this were true, there’d be no defence against the charge, but then it wouldn’t be a charge; for if the sources of pleasure were precisely the same for humans as for pigs, the rule of life that is good enough for them would be good enough for us. The comparison of the Epicurean life to that of beasts is felt as degrading precisely because a beast’s pleasures do not satisfy a human’s conceptions of happiness. Human beings have •higher faculties than the animal appetites, and once they become conscious of •them they don’t regard anything as happiness that doesn’t include •their gratification. Admittedly the Epicureans were far from faultless in drawing out the consequences of the utilitarian principle; to do this at all adequately one must include—·which they didn’t·—many Stoic and some Christian elements. But every Epicurean theory of life that we know of assigns to the •pleasures of the intellect, of the feelings and imagination and of the moral sentiments a much higher value as pleasures than

^1 I have reason to believe that I am the first person who brought the word ‘utilitarian’ into ·general· use. I didn’t invent it, but adopted it from a passing expression in Mr. Galt’s Annals of the Parish. After using it as a label for several years, he and others abandoned it because of their growing dislike for anything resembling a badge or slogan marking out a sect. But as a name for •one single opinion, not •a set of opinions—to stand for the recognition of utility as a standard, not any particular way of applying the standard—the term fills a gap in the language, and offers in many cases a convenient way of avoiding tiresome long-windedness.

5

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

to •those of mere sensation. But it must be admitted that when utilitarian writers have said that mental pleasures are better than bodily ones they have mainly based this on mental pleasures being more permanent, safer, less costly and so on—i.e. from their circumstantial advantages rather than from their intrinsic nature. And on all these points utilitarians have fully proved their case; but they could, quite consistently with their basic principle, have taken the other route—occupying the higher ground, as we might say. It is quite compatible with the principle of utility to recognise that some kinds of pleasure are more desirable and more valuable than others. In estimating· the value of· anything else, we take into account •quality as well as •quantity; it would be absurd if the value of pleasures were supposed to depend on •quantity alone.

‘What do you mean by “difference of quality in pleasures”? What, according to you, makes one pleasure •more valuable than another, merely as a pleasure, if not its being •greater in amount?’ There is only one possible answer to this.

Pleasure P1 is more desirable than pleasure P2 if: all or almost all people who have had experience of both give a decided preference to P1, irrespective of any feeling that they ought to prefer it.

If those who are competently acquainted with both these pleasures place P1 so far above P2 that •they prefer it even when they know that a greater amount of discontent will come with it, and •wouldn’t give it up in exchange for any quantity of P2 that they are capable of having, we are justified in ascribing to P1 a superiority in quality that so greatly outweighs quantity as to make quantity comparatively negligible.

Now, it is an unquestionable fact that the way of life that employs the higher faculties is strongly preferred ·to the way of life that caters only to the lower ones· by people who are equally acquainted with both and equally capable of appreciating and enjoying both. Few human creatures would agree to be changed into any of the lower animals in return for a promise of the fullest allowance of animal pleasures;

•no intelligent human being would consent to be a fool,

•no educated person would prefer to be an ignoramus,

•no person of feeling and conscience would rather be selfish and base,

even if they were convinced that the fool, the dunce or the rascal is better satisfied with his life than they are with theirs.... If they ever think they would, it is only in cases of unhappiness so extreme that to escape from it they would exchange their situation for almost any other, however undesirable they may think the other to be. Someone with higher faculties •requires more to make him happy, •is probably capable of more acute suffering, and •is certainly vulnerable to suffering at more points, than someone of an inferior type; but in spite of these drawbacks he can’t ever really wish to sink into what he feels to be a lower grade of existence. Explain this unwillingness how you please! We may attribute it to

•pride, a name that is given indiscriminately to some of the most and to some of the least admirable feelings of which human beings are capable;

•the love of liberty and personal independence (for the Stoics, that was one of the most effective means for getting people to value the higher pleasures); or

•the love of power, or the love of excitement, both of which really do play a part in it.

But the most appropriate label is a sense of dignity. All human beings have this sense in one form or another, and how strongly a person has it is roughly proportional to how well endowed he is with the higher faculties. In those who have a strong sense of dignity, their dignity is so essential

6

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

to their happiness that they couldn’t want, for more than a moment, anything that conflicts with it.

Anyone who thinks that this preference takes place at a sacrifice of happiness—anyone who denies that the superior being is, other things being anywhere near equal, happier than the inferior one—is confusing two very different ideas, those of happiness and of contentment. It is true of course that the being whose capacities of enjoyment are low has the greatest chance of having them fully satisfied ·and thus of being contented·; and a highly endowed being will always feel that any happiness that he can look for, given how the world is, is imperfect. But he can learn to bear its imperfections, if they are at all bearable; and they won’t make him envy the person who isn’t conscious of the imperfections only because he has no sense of the good that those imperfections are imperfections of—·for example, the person who isn’t bothered by the poor quality of the conducting because he doesn’t enjoy music anyway·. It is better to be a human being dissatisfied than a pig satisfied; better to be Socrates dissatisfied than a fool satisfied. And if the fool or the pig think otherwise, that is because they know only their own side of the question. The other party to the comparison knows both sides.

‘But many people who are capable of the higher pleasures do sometimes, under the influence of temptation, give preference to the lower ones.’ Yes, but this is quite compatible with their fully appreciating the intrinsic superiority of the higher. Men’s infirmity of character often leads them to choose the nearer good over the more valuable one; and they do this just as much when •it’s a choice between two bodily pleasures as when •it is between a bodily pleasure and a mental one. They pursue sensual pleasures at the expense of their health, though they are perfectly aware that health is the greater good, ·doing this because the sensual pleasures are nearer·.

‘Many people who begin with youthful enthusiasm for everything noble, as they grow old sink into laziness and selfishness.’ Yes, this is a very common change; but I don’t think that those who undergo it voluntarily choose the lower kinds of pleasures in preference to the higher. I believe that before they devote themselves exclusively to the lower pleasures they have already become incapable of the higher ones. In most people a capacity for the nobler feelings is a very tender plant that is easily killed, not only by hostile influences but by mere lack of nourishment; and in the majority of young persons it quickly dies away if their jobs and their social lives aren’t favourable to keeping that higher capacity in use. Men lose their high aspirations as they lose their intellectual tastes, because they don’t have time or opportunity for indulging them; and they addict themselves to lower pleasures not because they deliberately prefer them but because they are either •the only pleasures they can get or •the only pleasures they can still enjoy. It may be questioned whether anyone who has remained equally capable of both kinds of pleasure has ever knowingly and calmly preferred the lower kind; though throughout the centuries many people have broken down in an ineffectual attempt to have both at once.

I don’t see that there can be any appeal against this verdict of the only competent judges! On a question as to which is the better worth having of two pleasures, or which of two ways of life is the more agreeable to the feelings (apart from its moral attributes and from its consequences), the judgment of those who are qualified by knowledge of both must be admitted as final—or, if they differ among themselves, the judgment of the majority among them. And we can be encouraged to accept this judgment concerning the quality of pleasures by the fact that there is no other tribunal to appeal to even on the question of quantity. What means

7

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

do we have for deciding which is the more acute of two pains, or the more intense of two pleasurable sensations, other than the collective opinion of those who are familiar with both? ·Moving back now from quantity to quality·: there are different kinds of pain and different kinds of pleasure, and every pain is different from every pleasure. What can decide whether a particular ·kind of· pleasure is worth purchasing at the cost of a particular ·kind of· pain, if not the feelings and judgment of those who are experienced ·in both kinds·? When, therefore, those feelings and judgments declare the pleasures derived from the higher faculties to be preferable in kind, apart from the question of intensity, to those that can be enjoyed by animals that don’t have the higher faculties, their opinion on this subject too should be respected.

I have dwelt on this point because you need to understand it if you are to have a perfectly sound conception of utility or happiness, considered as the governing rule of human conduct. But you could rationally accept the utilitarian standard without having grasped ·that people who enjoy the higher pleasures are happier than those who don’t·. That’s because the utilitarian standard is not •the agent’s own greatest happiness but •the greatest amount of happiness altogether; and even if it can be doubted whether a noble character is always happier because of its nobleness, such a character certainly makes other people happier, and the world in general gains immensely from its existence. So utilitarianism would achieve its end only through the general cultivation of nobleness of character, even if

each individual got benefit only from the nobleness of others, with his own nobleness serving to reduce his own happiness.

But mere statement of this last supposition [the indented one just above] brings out its absurdity so clearly that there is no need for me to argue against it.

·Happiness as an Aim·

According to the greatest happiness principle as I have explained it, the ultimate end...., for the sake of which all other things are desirable (whether we are considering our own good or that of other people) is an existence as free as possible from pain and as rich as possible in enjoyments. This means rich in •quantity and in •quality; the test of •quality, and the rule for measuring it against •quantity, being the preferences of those who are best equipped to make the comparison—equipped, that is, by the range of their experience and by their habits of self-consciousness and self-observation. If the greatest happiness of all is (as the utilitarian opinion says it is) •the end of human action, is must also be •the standard of morality; which can therefore be defined as:

the rules and precepts for human conduct such that: the observance of them would provide the best possible guarantee of an existence such as has been described—for all mankind and, so far as the nature of things allows, for the whole sentient creation.

Against this doctrine, however, another class of objectors rise up, saying that the rational purpose of human life and action cannot be happiness in any form. For one thing, it is unattainable, they say; and they contemptuously ask ‘What right do you have to be happy?’, a question that Mr. Carlyle drives home by adding ‘What right, a short time ago, did you have even to exist?’. They also say that men can do without happiness; that all noble human beings have felt this, and couldn’t have become noble except by learning the lesson of.... renunciation. They say that thoroughly learning and submitting to that lesson is the beginning and necessary condition of all virtue.

8

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

If the first of these objections were right, it would go to the root of the matter; for if human beings can’t have any happiness, the achieving of happiness can’t be the end of morality or of any rational conduct. Still, even if human beings couldn’t be happy there might still be something to be said for the utilitarian theory, because utility includes not solely •the pursuit of happiness but also •the prevention or lessening of unhappiness; and if the •former aim is illusory there will be all the more scope for—and need of—the •latter. At any rate, that will be true so long as mankind choose to go on living, and don’t take refuge in the simultaneous act of suicide recommended under certain conditions by ·the German poet· Novalis. But when someone positively asserts that ‘It is impossible for human life to be happy’, if this isn’t something like a verbal quibble it is at least an exaggeration. If ‘happiness’ is taken to mean a continuous state of highly pleasurable excitement, it is obvious enough that this is impossible. A state of exalted pleasure lasts only moments, or—in some cases and with some interruptions—hours or days. Such an experience is the occasional •brilliant flash of enjoyment, not its •permanent and steady flame. The philosophers who have taught that happiness is the end of life were as fully aware of this as those who taunt them. The ‘happiness’ that they meant was not a life of rapture; but

a life containing some moments of rapture, a few brief pains, and many and various pleasures; a life that is much more active than passive; a life based on not expecting more from life than it is capable of providing.

A life made up of those components has always appeared worthy of the name of ‘happiness’ to those who have been fortunate enough to obtain it. And even now many people have such an existence during a considerable part of their lives. The present wretched education and wretched social arrangements are the only real hindrance to its being attainable by almost everyone. [In Mill’s day ‘education’ tended to have a broader meaning than it does today, and to cover every aspect of a young person’s upbringing.]

‘If human beings are taught to consider happiness as the end of life, they aren’t likely to be satisfied with such a moderate share of it.’ On the contrary, very many people have been satisfied with much less! There seem to be two main constituents of a satisfied life, and each of them has often been found to be, on its own, sufficient for the purpose. They are tranquillity and excitement. Many people find that when they have much tranquillity they can be content with very little pleasure; and many find that when they have much excitement they can put up with a considerable quantity of pain. It is certainly possible that a man—and even the mass of mankind—should have both tranquillity and excitement. So far from being incompatible with one another, they are natural allies: prolonging either of them is a preparation for the other, and creates a wish for it. The only people who don’t desire excitement after a restful period are those in whom laziness amounts to a vice; and the only ones who dislike the tranquillity that follows excitement—finding it •dull and bland rather than •pleasurable in proportion to the excitement that preceded it—are those whose need for excitement is a disease. When people who are fairly fortunate in their material circumstances don’t find sufficient enjoyment to make life valuable to them, this is usually because they care for nobody but themselves. If someone has neither public nor private affections, that will greatly reduce the amount of excitement his life can contain, and any excitements that he does have will sink in value as the time approaches when all selfish interests must be cut off by death. On the other hand, someone who leaves after him objects of personal affection, especially if he has developed a fellow-feeling with the interests of mankind as a whole, will

9

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

retain as lively an interest in life on the eve of his death as he had in the vigour of youth and health. Next to selfishness, the principal cause that makes life unsatisfactory is lack of mental cultivation [= ‘mental development’]. I am talking here not about minds that are cultivated as a philosopher’s is, but simply minds that have been open to the fountains of knowledge and have been given a reasonable amount of help in using their faculties. A mind that is cultivated in that sense will find inexhaustible sources of interest in everything that surrounds it—in the objects of nature, the achievements of art, the imaginations of poetry, the incidents of history, human events in the past and present as well as their prospects in the future. It is possible to become indifferent to all this, even when one hasn’t yet exhausted a thousandth part of it; but that can happen only to someone who from the beginning has had no •moral or human interest in these things, and has looked to them only to •satisfy his curiosity.

·These two prime requirements of happiness—•mental cultivation and •unselfishness—shouldn’t be thought of as possible only for a lucky few·. There is absolutely no reason in the nature of things why an amount of •mental culture sufficient to give an intelligent interest in science, poetry, art, history etc. should not be the inheritance of everyone born in a civilised country; any more than there’s any inherent necessity that any human being should be a •selfish egotist whose only feelings and cares are ones that centre on his own miserable individuality. Something far superior to this is, even now, common enough to give plenty of indication of what the human species may become. Genuine private affections and a sincere interest in the public good are possible, though to different extents, for every rightly brought up human being. In a world containing so much to interest us, so much for us to enjoy, and so much needing to be corrected and improved, everyone who has a moderate amount of these moral and intellectual requirements—·unselfishness and cultivation·—is •capable of an existence that may be called enviable; and such a person will certainly •have this enviable existence as long as

•he isn’t, because of bad laws or conditions of servitude, prevented from using the sources of happiness that are within his reach; and

•he escapes the positive evils of life—the great sources of physical and mental suffering—such as poverty, disease, and bad luck with friends and lovers (turning against him, proving to be worthless, or dying young).

So the main thrust of the problem lies in the battle against these calamities. In the present state of things, poverty and disease etc. can’t be eliminated, and often can’t even be lessened much; and it is a rare good fortune to escape such troubles entirely. Yet no-one whose opinion deserves a moment’s consideration can doubt that most of the great positive evils of the world are in themselves removable, and will (if human affairs continue to improve) eventually be reduced to something quite small. Poverty, in any sense implying suffering, could be completely extinguished by the wisdom of society combined with the good sense and generosity of individuals. Even that most stubborn of enemies, •disease, could be indefinitely reduced in scope by good physical and moral education and proper control of noxious influences [= ‘air- and water-pollution’]; while the progress of science holds out a promise of still more direct conquests over •this detestable foe. And every advance in that direction reduces the probability of events that would cut short our own lives or—more important to us—the lives of others in whom our happiness is wrapped up. As for ups and downs of fortune, and other disappointments connected with worldly circumstances, these are principally the effect of

10

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

gross foolishness, of desires that got out of control, or of bad or imperfect social institutions.

In short, all the large sources of human suffering are to a large extent—and many of them almost entirely—conquerable by human care and effort. Their removal is grievously slow, and a long succession of generations will perish in the battle before the conquest is completed and this world becomes what it easily could be if we had the will and the knowledge to make it so. Yet despite this, every mind that is sufficiently intelligent and generous to play some part (however small and inconspicuous) in the effort will draw a noble enjoyment from the contest itself—an enjoyment that he couldn’t be induced to give up by any bribe in the form of selfish indulgence.

And this leads to the right response to the objectors who say that we can, and that we should, do without happiness. It is certainly possible to do without happiness; nineteen-twentieths of mankind are compelled to do without it, even in those parts of our present world that are least deep in barbarism. And it often happens that a hero or martyr forgoes it for the sake of something that he values more than his individual happiness. But what is this ‘something’ if it isn’t the happiness of others or something required for ·their· happiness? It is noble to be capable of resigning entirely one’s own share of happiness, or the chances of it; but no-one engages in self-sacrifice just so as to engage in self-sacrifice! He must have some end or purpose. You may say: ‘The end he aims at in his self-sacrifice is not ·anyone’s· happiness; it is virtue, which is better than happiness.’ In response to this I ask: Would the sacrifice be made if the hero or martyr didn’t think it would spare others from having to make similar sacrifices? Would it be made if he thought that his renunciation of happiness for himself would produce no result for any of his fellow creatures except to make their situation like his, putting them in also in the position of persons who have renounced happiness? All honour to those who can give up for themselves the personal enjoyment of life, when by doing this they contribute worthily to increasing the amount of happiness in the world; but someone who does it, or claims to do it, for any other purpose doesn’t deserve admiration any more than does the ascetic living on top of his pillar. He may be a rousing proof of what men can do, but surely not an example of what they should do.

·Self-Sacrifice·

Only while the world is in a very imperfect state can it happen that anyone’s best chance of serving the happiness of others is through the absolute sacrifice of his own happiness; but while the world is in that imperfect state, I fully admit that the readiness to make such a sacrifice is the highest virtue that can be found in man. I would add something that may seem paradoxical: namely that in this ·present imperfect· condition of the world •the conscious ability to do without happiness gives the best prospect of bringing about such happiness as is attainable. For nothing except that •consciousness can raise a person above the chances of life by making him feel that fate and fortune—let them do their worst!—have no power to subdue him. Once he feels that, it frees him from excessive anxiety about the evils of life and lets him (like many a Stoic in the worst times of the Roman Empire) calmly develop the sources of satisfaction that are available to him, not concerning himself with the uncertainty regarding how long they will last or the certainty that they will end.

Meanwhile, let utilitarians never cease to claim that they have as much right as the Stoic or the Transcendentalist to maintain the morality of devotion to a cause as something

11

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

that belongs to them. The utilitarian morality does recognise that human beings can sacrifice their own greatest good for the good of others; it merely refuses to admit that the sacrifice is itself a good. It regards as wasted any sacrifice that doesn’t increase, or tend to increase, the sum total of happiness. The only self-renunciation that it applauds is devotion to the happiness, or to some of the means to happiness, of others....

I must again repeat something that the opponents of utilitarianism are seldom fair enough to admit, namely that the happiness that forms the utilitarian standard of what is right in conduct is not •the agent’s own happiness but •that of all concerned. As between his own happiness and that of others, utilitarianism requires him to be as strictly impartial as a disinterested and benevolent spectator. [Here and everywhere Mill uses ‘disinterested’ in its still-correct meaning = ‘not self -interested’ = ‘not swayed by any consideration of how the outcome might affect one’s own welfare’.] In the golden rule of Jesus of Nazareth we read the complete spirit of the ethics of utility. To

do as you would be done by, and to love your neighbour as yourself

constitute the ideal perfection of utilitarian morality. As the ·practical· way to get as close as possible to this ideal, ·the ethics of· utility would command two things. (1) First, laws and social arrangements should place the happiness (or what for practical purposes we may call the interest) of every individual as much as possible in harmony with the interest of the whole. (2) Education and opinion, which have such a vast power over human character, should use that power to establish in the mind of every individual an unbreakable link between •his own happiness and •the good of the whole; especially between •his own happiness and •the kinds of conduct (whether doing or allowing) that are conducive to universal happiness. If (2) is done properly, it will tend to have two results: (2a) The individual won’t be able to conceive the possibility of being personally happy while acting in ways opposed to the general good. (2b) In each individual a direct impulse to promote the general good will be one of the habitual motives of action, and the feelings connected with it will fill a large and prominent place in his sentient existence. This is the true character of the utilitarian morality. If those who attack utilitarianism see it as being like this, I don’t know •what good features of some other moralities they could possibly say that utilitarianism lacks, •what more beautiful or more elevated developments of human nature any other ethical systems can be supposed to encourage, or •what motivations for action that aren’t available to the utilitarian those other systems rely on for giving effect to their mandates.

·Setting the Standard too High?·

The objectors to utilitarianism can’t be accused of always representing it in a •discreditable light. On the contrary, objectors who have anything like a correct idea of its disinterested character sometimes find fault with utilitarianism’s standard as being •too high for humanity. To require people always to act from the •motive of promoting the general interests of society—that is demanding too much, they say. But this is to mistake the very meaning of a standard of morals, and confuse the •rule of action with the •motive for acting. It is the business of ethics to tell us what are our duties, or by what test we can know them; but no system of ethics requires that our only motive in everything we do shall be a feeling of duty; on the contrary, ninety-nine hundredths of all our actions are done from other motives, and rightly

12

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

so if the •rule of duty doesn’t condemn them. It is especially unfair to utilitarianism to object to it on the basis of this particular misunderstanding, because utilitarian moralists have gone beyond almost everyone in asserting that the motive has nothing to do with the morality of the action though it has much to do with the worth of the agent. He who saves a fellow creature from drowning does what is morally right, whether his motive is duty or the hope of being paid for his trouble; he who betrays a friend who trusts him is guilty of a crime, even if his aim is to serve another friend to whom he is under greater obligations.

Let us now look at actions that are done from the motive of duty, in direct obedience to ·the utilitarian· principle: it is a misunderstanding of the utilitarian way of thinking to conceive it as implying that people should fix their minds on anything as wide as the world or society in general. The great majority of good actions are intended not for •the benefit of the world but for parts of the good of the world, namely •the benefit of individuals. And on these occasions the thoughts of the most virtuous man need not go beyond the particular persons concerned, except to the extent that he has to assure himself that in benefiting those individuals he isn’t violating the rights (i.e. the legitimate and authorised expectations) of anyone else. According to the utilitarian ethics the object of virtue is to multiply happiness; for any person (except one in a thousand) it is only on exceptional occasions that he has it in his power to do this on an extended scale, i.e. to be a public benefactor; and it is only on these occasions that he is called upon to consider public utility; in every other case he needs to attend only to private utility, the interest or happiness of some few persons. The only people who need to concern themselves regularly about so large an object as society in general are those ·few· whose actions have an influence that extends that far. ·Thoughts about the general welfare do have a place in everyone’s moral thinking· in the case of refrainings—things that people hold off from doing, for moral reasons, though the consequences in the particular case might be beneficial. The thought in these cases is like this: ‘If I acted in that way, my action would belong to a class of actions which, if practised generally, would be generally harmful, and for that reason I ought not to perform it.’ It would be unworthy of an intelligent agent not to be consciously aware of such considerations. But the amount of regard for the public interest implied in this kind of thought is no greater than is demanded by every system of morals, for they all demand that one refrain from anything that would obviously be pernicious to society; ·so there is no basis here for a criticism of utilitarianism in particular·.

·Is Utilitarianism Chilly?·

The same considerations dispose of another reproach against the doctrine of utility, based on a still grosser misunderstanding of the purpose of a standard of morality and of the very meanings of the words ‘right’ and ‘wrong’. It is often said that utilitarianism •makes men cold and unsympathising; that it •chills their moral feelings towards individuals; that it •makes them attend only to

•the dry and hard consideration of the consequences of actions,

leaving out of their moral estimate

•the ·personal· qualities from which those actions emanate.

If this means that they don’t allow their judgment about the rightness or wrongness of an action to be influenced by their opinion of the qualities of the person who does it, this is a complaint not against •utilitarianism but against •having any standard of morality at all; for certainly no known ethical

13

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

standard declares that an action is good or bad because it is done by a good or a bad man, still less because it is done by a lovable, brave or benevolent man, or by an unfriendly, cowardly or unsympathetic one. These considerations ·of personal virtue· are relevant to how we estimate persons, not actions; and the utilitarian theory in no way conflicts with the fact that there are other things that interest us in persons besides the rightness and wrongness of their actions. The Stoics, indeed, with the paradoxical misuse of language which was part of their system and by which they tried to raise themselves to a level at which their only concern was with virtue, were fond of saying that he who has virtue has everything; that it is the virtuous man, and only the virtuous man, who is rich, is beautiful, is a king. But the utilitarian doctrine doesn’t make any such claim on behalf of the virtuous man. Utilitarians are well aware that there are other desirable possessions and qualities besides virtue, and are perfectly willing to allow to all of them their full worth. They are also aware that •a right action doesn’t necessarily indicate a virtuous character, and that •actions that are blamable often come from· personal· qualities that deserve praise. When this shows up in any particular case, it modifies utilitarian’s estimation not of the act but of the agent. They do hold that in the long run the best proof of a good character is good actions; and they firmly refuse to consider any mental disposition as good if its predominant tendency is to produce bad conduct. This, which I freely grant, makes utilitarians unpopular with many people; but this is an unpopularity that they must share with everyone who takes seriously the distinction between right and wrong; and the criticism is not one that a conscientious utilitarian need be anxious to fend off.

If the objection means only this:

Many utilitarians look on the morality of actions, as measured by the utilitarian standard, in too exclusive a manner, and don’t put enough emphasis on the other beauties of character that go towards making a human being lovable or admirable,

this may be admitted. Utilitarians who have cultivated their moral feelings but not their sympathies or their artistic perceptions do fall into this mistake; and so do all other moralists under the same conditions. What can be said in excuse of other moralists is equally available for utilitarians, namely that if one is to go wrong about this, it is better to go wrong on that side, ·rather than caring about lovability etc. and ignoring the morality of actions·. As a matter of fact, utilitarians are in this respect like the adherents of other systems: there is every imaginable degree of rigidity and of laxity in how they apply their standard ·of right and wrong·: some are puritanically rigorous, while others are as forgiving as any sinner or sentimentalist could wish! But on the whole, a doctrine that highlights the interest that mankind have in the repression and prevention of conduct that violates the moral law is likely to do as good a job as any other in turning the force of public opinion again such violations. It is true that the question ‘What does violate the moral law?’ is one on which those who recognise different standards of morality are likely now and then to differ. But ·that isn’t a point against utilitarianism·; difference of opinion on moral questions wasn’t first introduced into the world by utilitarianism! And that doctrine does supply a tangible and intelligible way—if not always an easy one—of deciding such differences.

14

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

·Utilitarianism as ‘Godless’·

It may be worthwhile to comment on a few more of the common misunderstandings of utilitarian ethics, even those that are so obvious and gross that it might appear impossible for any fair and intelligent person to fall into them. ·It might appear impossible but unfortunately it isn’t·: the crudest misunderstandings of ethical doctrines are continually met with in the deliberate writings of persons with the greatest claims both to high principle and to philosophy. That is because people—even very able ones—often take little trouble to understand the likely influence of any opinion against which they have a prejudice, and are unaware of this deliberate ignorance as a defect. We quite often hear the doctrine of utility denounced as a godless doctrine. If this mere assumption needs to be replied to at all, we may say that the question depends on what idea we have formed of the moral character of the Deity. If it is true that God desires the happiness of his creatures above all else, and that this was his purpose in creating them, then utilitarianism, far from being a godless doctrine, is the most deeply religious of them all. If the accusation is that utilitarianism doesn’t recognise the revealed will of God as the supreme law of morals, I answer that a utilitarian who believes in the perfect goodness and wisdom of God has to believe that whatever God has thought fit to reveal on the subject of morals must fulfil the requirements of utility in a supreme degree. Others besides utilitarians have held this:

The Christian revelation was intended (and is fitted) to bring into the hearts and minds of mankind a spirit that will enable them to find for themselves what is right, and incline them to do right when they have found it; rather than to tell them—except in a very general way—what it is. And we need a doctrine of ethics, carefully followed out, to know what the will of God is.

We needn’t discuss here whether this is right; because whatever aid religion—either natural or revealed—can provide to ethical investigation is as open to the utilitarian moralist as to any other. He is as entitled to cite it as God’s testimony to the usefulness or hurtfulness of a course of action as others are to cite it as pointing to a transcendental law that has no connection with usefulness or happiness.

·Expediency·

Again, utilitarianism is often slapped down as an immoral doctrine by giving it the name ‘Expediency’, and taking advantage of the common use of that term to contrast it with ‘Principle’. But when ‘expedient’ is opposed to ‘right’, it usually means what is expedient for the particular interest of the agent himself, as when a high official sacrifices the interests of his country in order to keep himself in place. When it means anything better than this, it means what is expedient for some immediate temporary purpose, while violating a rule whose observance is much more expedient. The ‘expedient’ in this sense, instead of being the same thing as the •useful, is a branch of the •hurtful. For example, telling a lie would often be expedient for escaping some temporary difficulty or getting something that would be immediately useful to ourselves or others. But (1) the principal support of all present social well-being is people’s ability to trust one another’s assertions, and the lack of that trust does more than anything else to keep back civilisation, virtue, everything on which human happiness on the largest scale depends. Therefore (2) the development in ourselves of a sensitive feeling about truthfulness is one of the most useful things that our conduct can encourage, and the weakening of

15

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

that feeling is one of the most harmful. Finally, (3) any deviation from truth—even an unintentional one—does something towards weakening the trustworthiness of human assertion. For these reasons we feel that (4) to obtain an immediate advantage by violating such an overwhelmingly expedient rule is not expedient, and that someone who acts in that way does his bit towards depriving mankind of the good, and inflicting on them the harm, involved in the greater or less reliance that they can place in each other’s word, thus acting as though he were one of mankind’s worst enemies. Yet all moralists agree that even this rule ·about telling the truth·, sacred as it is, admits of possible exceptions. The chief one is the case where the withholding of some fact from someone would save an individual (especially someone other than oneself) from great and undeserved harm, and the only way of withholding it is to lie about it. (Examples: keeping information ·about the whereabouts of a weapon· from a malefactor, keeping bad news from a person who is dangerously ill.) But in order that this exception ·to the truth-telling rule· doesn’t extend itself beyond the need for it, and has the least possible effect of weakening reliance on truth-telling, it ought to be recognised, and if possible its limits should be defined; and if the principle of utility is good for anything, it must be good for weighing these conflicting utilities against one another, and marking out the region within which one or the other dominates.

·Time to Calculate?·

Again, defenders of utility often find themselves challenged to reply to such objections as this: ‘Before acting, one doesn’t have time to calculate and weigh the effects on the general happiness of any line of conduct.’ This is just like saying: ‘Before acting, one doesn’t have time on each occasion to read through the Old and New Testaments; so it is impossible for us to guide our conduct by Christianity.’ The answer to the objection is that there has been plenty of time, namely, the whole past duration of the human species. During all that time, mankind have been learning by •experience what sorts of consequences actions are apt to have, this being something on which all the morality of life depends, as well as all the prudence [= ‘decisions about what will further one’s own interests’]. The objectors talk as if the start of this course of •experience had been put off until now, so that when some man feels tempted to meddle with the property or life of someone else he has to start at that moment considering for the first time whether murder and theft are harmful to human happiness! Even if that were how things stand, I don’t think he would find the question very puzzling....

If mankind were agreed in considering utility to be the test of morality, they would of course—it would be merely fanciful to deny it—reach some agreement about what is useful, and would arrange for their notions about this to be taught to the young and enforced by law and opinion. Any ethical standard whatever can easily be ‘shown’ to work badly if we suppose •universal idiocy to be conjoined with it! But on any hypothesis short of •that, mankind must by this time have acquired positive beliefs as to the effects of some actions on their happiness; and the beliefs that have thus come down ·to us from the experience of mankind· are the rules of morality for the people in general—and for the philosopher until he succeeds in finding something better. I admit, or rather I strongly assert, that

•philosophers might easily find something better, even now, on many subjects; that

•the accepted code of ethics is not God-given; and that

•mankind have still much to learn about how various kinds of action affect the general happiness.

16

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 2: What utilitarianism is

The corollaries from the principle of utility, like the rules of every practical art, can be improved indefinitely, and while the human mind is progressing they are constantly improving.

But to consider the intermediate rules of morality as unprovable is one thing; to pass over them entirely, trying to test each individual action directly by the first principle, is another. It is a strange notion that having a •first principle is inconsistent with having •secondary ones as well. When you tell a traveller the location of the place he wants to get to, you aren’t forbidding him to use landmarks and direction-posts along the way! The proposition that happiness is the end and aim of morality doesn’t mean that no road ought to be laid down to that goal, or that people going to it shouldn’t be advised to take one direction rather than another. Men really ought to stop talking a kind of nonsense on this subject –nonsense that they wouldn’t utter or listen to with regard to any other practically important matter. Nobody argues that the art of navigation is not based on astronomy because sailors can’t wait to calculate the Nautical Almanack. Because they are rational creatures, sailors go to sea with the calculations already done; and all rational creatures go out on the sea of life with their minds made up on the common questions of right and wrong, as well as on many of the much harder questions of wise and foolish. And we can presume that they will continue to do so long as foresight continues to be a human quality. Whatever we adopt as the fundamental principle of morality, we need subordinate principles through which to apply it; the absolute need for them is a feature of all ·moral· systems, so it doesn’t support any argument against any one system in particular. To argue solemnly in a manner that presupposes this:

No such secondary principles can be had; and mankind never did and never will draw any general conclusions from the experience of human life

is as totally absurd, I think, as anything that has been advanced in philosophical controversy.

·Bad Faith·

The remainder of the standard arguments against utilitarianism mostly consist in blaming it for •the common infirmities of human nature and •the general difficulties that trouble conscientious persons when they are shaping their course through life. We are told that a utilitarian will be apt to make his own particular case an exception to moral rules; and that when he is tempted ·to do something wrong· he will see more utility in doing it than in not doing it. But is utility the only morality that can provide us with excuses for evil doing, and means of cheating our own conscience? ·Of course not·! Such excuses are provided in abundance by •all doctrines that recognise the existence of conflicting considerations as a fact in morals; and this is recognized by every doctrine that any sane person has believed. It is the fault not •of any creed but •of the complicated nature of human affairs that rules of conduct can’t be formulated so that they require no exceptions, and hardly any kind of action can safely be stated to be either always obligatory or always condemnable.

Every ethical creed softens the rigidity of its laws by giving the morally responsible agent some •freedom to adapt his behaviour to special features of his circumstances; and under every creed, at the •opening thus made, self-deception and dishonest reasoning get in. Every moral system allows for clear cases of conflicting obligation. These are real difficulties, knotty points both in the •theory of ethics and in the •practical personal matter of living conscientiously. In practice they are overcome, more or less successfully, according to the person’s intellect and virtue; but it can’t

17

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 3: What will motivate us?

be claimed that having an ultimate standard to which conflicting rights and duties can be referred will make one less qualified to deal with them! If utility is the basic source of moral obligations, utility can be invoked to decide between obligations whose demands are incompatible. The ·utility· standard may be hard to apply, but it is better than having no standard. In other systems, the moral laws all claim independent authority, so that there’s no common umpire entitled to settle conflicts between them; when one of them is claimed to have precedence over another, the basis for this is little better than sophistry, allowing free scope for personal desires and preferences (unless the conflict is resolved by the unadmitted influence of considerations of utility). It is only in these cases of conflict between secondary principles that there is any need to appeal to first principles. In every case of moral obligation some secondary principle is involved; and if there is only one, someone who recognizes that principle can seldom be in any real doubt as to which one it is.

Chapter 3: What will motivate us to obey the principle of utility?

The question is often asked, and it is a proper question in relation to any supposed moral standard,

What is its sanction? [= ‘What is the reward for conforming to it and/or the punishment for not doing so?’]

What are the motives to obey it?

or more specifically,

What is the source of its obligation? Where does it get its binding force from?

It is a necessary part of moral philosophy to provide the answer to this question. It often takes the shape of an objection to the utilitarian morality in particular, as though it were specially applicable to that; but really it arises in regard to all standards. It arises, in fact, whenever someone is called on to adopt a standard ·that is new to him·, or to put morality on some basis on which he hasn’t been accustomed to rest it. The only morality that presents itself to the mind with the feeling of being in itself obligatory is the customary morality, the one that education and opinion have •consecrated; and when a person is asked to believe that this morality derives its obligation from some general principle around which custom has not thrown the same •halo, he finds the demand paradoxical; the supposed corollaries seem to have a more binding force than the original theorem; the superstructure seems to stand better without its supposed foundation than with it. He says to himself, ‘I feel that I am bound not to rob or murder, betray or deceive; but why am I bound to promote the general happiness? If my own happiness lies in something else, why may I not give that the preference?’

If the utilitarian philosophy’s view of the nature of the moral sense is correct, this difficulty will always present itself, until the influences that form moral character have taken the same hold of the •principle that they have taken of some of its •consequences. That will be the time when the improvement of education brings about something that Christ certainly intended should come about, namely that

18

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 3: What will motivate us?

the •feeling of unity with our fellow-creatures should be as deeply rooted in our character, and feel to us to be as completely a part of our nature as the •horror of crime is in an ordinarily well brought up young person. While we are waiting for that day to come, the difficulty has no special application to the doctrine of utility, but is inherent in every attempt to analyse morality and organize it under principles. Unless the first principle already has in men’s minds as much sacredness as any of its applications, this process always seems to deprive the applications of a part of their sanctity.

The principle of utility either has, or perfectly well could have, all the sanctions that belong to any other system of morals. Those sanctions are either external or internal. I needn’t spend long on the external sanctions. They are

the hope of favour and the fear of displeasure from •our fellow creatures or from •the ruler of the universe,

and also

whatever sympathy or affection we may have for •them, or whatever love and awe we may have towards •Him, inclining us to do ·what they want or· what He wants, independently of selfish consequences.

Obviously there is no reason why all these motives for conforming to moral principles shouldn’t attach themselves to the utilitarian morality as completely and as powerfully as to any other. Indeed, the motives that refer to our fellow creatures are sure to do so, insofar as people are intelligent enough ·to make the connection·. Here is why. Whether or not there is any basis of moral obligation other than the general happiness, men do want happiness; and however imperfect a particular person’s conduct may be, he does desire and commend all conduct by others that promotes his happiness. With regard to the religious motive: if men believe in the goodness of God (as most of them say they do), those who think that conduciveness to the general happiness is the essence of good, or even just the criterion of good, must believe that general happiness is also what God approves. So

•the whole force of external reward and punishment, whether physical or moral and whether coming from God or from our fellow men,

together with

•everything that human nature is capable of in the way of disinterested devotion to God or to man,

become available ·as sanctions· to enforce ·obedience to· the utilitarian morality, in proportion as that morality is recognised. And the more the techniques of education and general cultivation are put to work on this, the stronger the sanctions will be.

That’s enough about external sanctions. The internal sanction of duty is one and the same, whatever our standard of duty may be. It is a feeling in our own mind, a more or less intense pain that comes with violations of duty; and in properly cultivated moral natures it rises in the more serious cases into shrinking from the violation as an impossibility. When this feeling is disinterested, and connected with the pure idea of duty and not with some particular form of it or with any of the merely accessory circumstances, it is the essence of •conscience; though in •that complex phenomenon as it actually exists the simple fact ·of pure conscience· is usually all encrusted over with associated feelings derived

from sympathy,

from love and even more from fear;

from all the forms of religious feeling;

from memories of childhood and of all our past life;

from self-esteem, desire for the esteem of others, and

occasionally even self-abasement.

19

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 3: What will motivate us?

It seems to me that this extreme complicatedness is the origin of the sort of mystical character which is apt to be attributed to the idea of moral obligation and which leads people to think that the idea ·of moral obligation· can’t possibly attach itself to any objects except the ones that, by a supposed mysterious law, are found in our present experience to arouse it. Its binding force, however, consists in the existence of a mass of feeling that must be broken through in order to do what violates our standard of right; and if we do nevertheless violate that standard, the feelings will probably have to be encountered afterwards in the form of remorse. Whatever theory we have of the nature or origin of conscience, this is what it essentially consists of.

Since the ultimate sanction of all morality (external motives apart) is a subjective feeling in our own minds, I see nothing awkward for the utilitarian in the question ‘What is the sanction of the utilitarian standard?’ We can answer, ‘It is the same as of all other moral standards—namely the conscientious feelings of mankind.’ Undoubtedly this sanction has no binding force for those who don’t have the feelings it appeals to; but these people won’t be more obedient to any other moral principle than to the utilitarian one. No morality of any kind has any hold on them except through external sanctions. Meanwhile the feelings do exist, a fact in human nature; and experience shows that they are real and that they can act with great power on people in whom they have been duly developed. No reason has ever been shown why they can’t be developed to as great intensity in connection with the utilitarian rule of morals as with any other.

I realize that some people are inclined to believe that a person who sees in moral obligation

a transcendental fact, an objective reality belonging to the province of ‘things in themselves’

is likely to be more obedient to moral obligation than one who believes it to be

entirely subjective, being rooted purely in human consciousness.

But whatever a person’s opinion may be on this metaphysical point, the force he is really urged by is his own subjective feeling, and the •power of the force is exactly measured by the •strength of the feeling. No-one’s belief that

duty is an objective reality

is stronger than the belief that

God is an objective reality;

yet the belief in God, apart from the expectation of actual reward and punishment, operates on conduct only through the subjective religious feeling, and the power of the operation is proportional to the strength of the feeling. The sanction, so far as it is disinterested, is always in the mind itself; so the thought of the transcendental moralists ·I am discussing· must be this:

This sanction won’t exist in the mind unless it is believed to have its root outside the mind. If a person can say to himself ‘What is now restraining me—what is called my conscience—is only a feeling in my own mind’, he may draw the conclusion that when the feeling ceases the obligation also ceases, and that if he finds the feeling inconvenient he may disregard it and try to get rid of it.

But is this danger confined to the utilitarian morality? Does the belief that moral obligation has its seat outside the mind make the feeling of it too strong for you to get rid of it? The facts are otherwise—so much so that all moralists admit and lament how easy it is for conscience to be silenced or stifled in most people’s minds. People who never heard of the principle of utility ask themselves ‘Need I obey my conscience?’ just as often as do utilitarians. Those whose

20

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 3: What will motivate us?

conscientious feelings are so weak as to allow them to ask this question, if they answer ‘Yes’ they will do so not because •they believe in the transcendental theory but because of •the external sanctions.

It isn’t necessary for present purposes to decide whether the feeling of duty is innate or implanted [i.e. whether it is part of our natural birthright or is acquired along the way through education or whatever]. Assuming it to be innate, the question remains as to what duties the feeling naturally attaches itself to; for the philosophic supporters of the innateness theory are now agreed that ·what is given to us innately·—what we have an intuitive perception of—is the •principles of morality and not its •details. If there is anything innate in all this, I don’t see why the feeling that is innate shouldn’t be the feeling of •concern for the pleasures and pains of others. If any principle of morals is intuitively obligatory, I should say it must be •that one. If so, intuitive ·innatist· ethics would coincide with utilitarian ethics, and there would be no further quarrel between them. Even as things stand, although the intuitive moralists believe that there are other intuitive moral obligations, they do already believe that this—·the obligation to seek the welfare of others·—is one; for they all hold that a large portion of morality turns on the consideration that should be given to the interests of our fellow-creatures. So if the belief in the transcendental origin of moral obligation does give any additional force to the internal sanction, it appears to me that the utilitarian principle already has the benefit of it.

On the other hand, if the moral feelings are not innate but acquired (as I think they are), that doesn’t make them any less natural. It is natural for man to speak, to reason, to build cities, to cultivate the ground, though these are acquired abilities. The moral feelings are indeed not ‘a part of our nature’ in the sense of being detectably present in all of us; but this is a sad fact admitted by the most strenuous believers in the transcendental origin of those feelings. Like the other acquired capacities I have referred to, the moral faculty, if not a part of our nature, is a natural outgrowth from it. Like them, it can to a certain small extent spring up spontaneously and can be brought by cultivation to a high degree of development. Unfortunately, it can—by a sufficient use of external sanctions and of the force of early impressions—be cultivated in almost any direction; so that there is hardly anything so absurd or so mischievous that these influences can’t make it act on the human mind with all the authority of conscience. To doubt that the same power might be given by the same means to the principle of utility, even if it had no foundation in human nature, would be flying in the face of all experience.

But while the culture of the intellect continues, purely artificial moral associations gradually give way through the dissolving force of analysis. If this were the case:

•The feeling of duty when associated with utility seems as arbitrary ·as any of those others·;

•There is no prominent part of our make-up, no powerful class of feelings, with which that association harmonizes, making us feel it as congenial and inclining us not only to encourage it in others (for which we have abundant ·self·-interested motives), but also to value it in ourselves; in short,

•Utilitarian morality has no natural basis in our feelings,

—in that case it might well happen that this association ·of duty with utility· was analysed away, even after it had been implanted by education. But there is this basis of powerful natural sentiment; and this will constitute the strength of the utilitarian morality once general happiness is recognised as the ethical standard. This firm foundation is that of

21

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 3: What will motivate us?

the social feelings of mankind; the desire to be in unity with our fellow creatures. It is already a powerful force in human nature, and fortunately one of those that tend to be made stronger—even without being explicitly taught—by the influences of advancing civilisation. The social state is at once so natural, so necessary and so habitual to a man that, except in some unusual circumstances or an effortful thought-experiment, he never thinks of himself as anything but a member of a group; and this association becomes stronger and stronger as mankind moves further from the state of savage independence. Thus, any condition that is essential to a state of society becomes more and more an inseparable part of each person’s conception of the state of things that he is born into and that is the destiny of a human being.

Now society between human beings—except in the relation of master to slave—is obviously impossible on any other basis than that the interests of all are to be consulted. Society between •equals can only exist on the understanding that the interests of all are to be regarded •equally. And since in all states of civilisation every person except an absolute monarch has equals, everyone is obliged to live on these terms with somebody; and in every age some advance is made towards a state in which it will be impossible to live permanently with anybody except on terms of equality. In this way people grow up unable to think of a state of total disregard of other people’s interests as one they could possibly live in. They have to conceive of themselves as at least refraining from all the most harmful crimes and (if only for their own protection) living in a state of constant protest against them. They are also familiar with the fact of co-operating with others and of acting (at least for the time being) in the interests of a group rather than of themselves as individuals. So long as they are co-operating, their purposes are identified with those of others; there is at least a temporary feeling that the interests of others are their own interests. All strengthening of social ties and all healthy growth of society gives to each individual a stronger personal interest in •acting with regard for the welfare of others; and it also leads him to identify his •feelings more and more with their good, or at least with an even greater degree of concern for it in his actions. He comes, as though instinctively, to be conscious of himself as a being who pays regard to others as a matter of course. The good of others becomes to him a thing naturally and necessarily to be attended to, like any of the physical conditions of our existence. Now, however •much or little of this feeling a person has, he has the strongest motives both of ·self·-interest and of sympathy to express this feeling in his behaviour, and to do all he can to encourage it in others; and even if he has •none of it himself, it is as much in his interests as in anyone else’s that others should have it. Consequently the smallest seeds of the feeling are laid hold of and nourished by the •contagion of sympathy and the •influences of education; and a complete web of supporting association is woven around it by the powerful force of the external sanctions. [Regarding ‘contagion’: Mill means merely that through sympathy a feeling can be passed on from one person to another.]

As civilisation goes on, this way of thinking about ourselves and about human life is increasingly felt to be natural. Every step in political improvement makes it more so, by

•removing the sources of conflicts of interest, and

•removing the inequalities in legal status between individuals or classes, because of which it is still practicable to disregard the happiness of large portions of mankind.

As the human mind improves, there is a steady increase in the influences that tend to generate in each individual a

22

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 3: What will motivate us?

feeling of unity with all the rest; a feeling which in its perfect state would make him never think of or want any benefit for himself if it didn’t also involve benefits for all the rest. Now suppose this were the case:

This feeling of unity is taught as a religion. The whole force of education, of institutions and of opinion is directed—as it used to be in the case of religion—to making every person grow up from infancy surrounded on all sides both by people who have the feeling of unity, who say they have it, and who act on it.

I don’t think that anyone who can realize this conception [= ‘make it real to himself in his mind’] will have any doubts about the sufficiency of the ultimate sanction for the happiness morality. To any student of ethics who finds the realization difficult [i.e. who can’t get a real sense of what it would be like if the above scenario came true], I recommend that he get help from the second of M. Comte’s two principal works, the Traité de politique positive. I have the strongest objections to the system of politics and morals presented in that book; but I think it has more than adequately shown the possibility of

•giving to the service of humanity, even without help from a belief in God, both the psychological power and the social effectiveness of a religion; and •making it take hold of human life and colour all thought, feeling and action far more thoroughly than any religion has ever done; the danger being not that it might be insufficient but that it might be so excessive as to interfere unduly with human freedom and individuality.

This feeling ·of unity· that constitutes the binding force of the utilitarian morality on those who accept it doesn’t have to wait until....everyone has it. It’s true that in the comparatively early state of human advancement in which we now live, a person can’t feel such total sympathy with everyone else that he couldn’t do anything that would work against their interests; but even now a person in whom the social feeling is at all developed can’t bring himself to think of the rest of his fellow creatures as struggling rivals with him for the means of happiness, rivals whom he must want to see defeated in their aims so that he can succeed in his. The deeply rooted conception that every individual has of himself as a social being, even now, tends to make him feel it as one of his natural wants that his feelings and aims should harmonize with those of his fellow creatures. (If differences of opinion and of mental culture make it impossible for him to share many of their actual feelings—perhaps even make him denounce and defy those feelings—he still needs to be aware that his real aim doesn’t conflict with theirs, and that he isn’t •opposing but •promoting what they really wish for, namely their own good.) In most individuals this feeling ·of unity· is much weaker than their selfish feelings, and is often entirely lacking. But to those who have it, it bears all the marks of a natural feeling. It doesn’t present itself to their minds as •a superstition they were brought up in or •a law forced on them by the power of society, but as •an attribute that it would be bad for them to lack. This conviction is the ultimate sanction of the greatest happiness morality. It is this that •makes any mind with well-developed feelings work with rather than against the outward motives to care for others, the motives provided by what I have called ‘the external sanctions’; and when those sanctions are absent or act in an opposite direction, •constitutes in itself an internal binding force that is strong in proportion to the sensitiveness and thoughtfulness of the ·person’s· character. Apart from people whose mind is a moral blank, few could bear to lay out their course of life on the plan of paying no regard to others except in ways that would serve their own interests.

23

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 4: What proof for the principle of utility?

Chapter 4: What sort of proof can be given for the principle of utility?

I have already remarked ·on page 3· that questions of ultimate ends don’t admit of ‘proof’ in the ordinary meaning of that term. It’s true of all first principles—the first premises of our knowledge, as well as those of our conduct—that they can’t be proved by reasoning. But the first principles of our knowledge, being matters of fact, can be the subject of a direct appeal to the faculties that make judgments of fact—namely our ·outer· senses and our internal consciousness. Can an appeal be made to those same faculties on questions of practical ends [= ‘questions about what we ought to aim at’]? If not, what other faculty is used for us to know them?

Questions about ends are, in other words, questions what things are desirable. The utilitarian doctrine is that happiness is desirable as an •end, and is the only thing that is so; anything else that is desirable is only desirable as •means to that end. What should be required regarding this doctrine—what conditions must it fulfil—to justify its claim to be believed?

The only proof capable of being given that an object is visible is that people actually see it. The only proof that a sound is audible is that people hear it; and similarly with the other sources of our experience. In like manner, I apprehend, the sole evidence it is possible to produce that anything is desirable is that people do actually desire it. [This paragraph up to here is given in Mill’s exact words.] If ·happiness·, the end that the utilitarian doctrine proposes to itself, were not acknowledged in theory and in practice to be an end, nothing could ever convince any person that it was an end. No reason can be given why

•the general happiness is desirable,

except the fact that

•each person desires his own happiness, so far as he thinks it is attainable.

But this is a fact; so we have not only all the proof there could be for such a proposition, and all the proof that could possibly be demanded, that

happiness is a good, that

each person’s happiness is a good to that person, and

therefore that

general happiness is a good to the aggregate of all persons.

Happiness has made good its claim to be one of the ends of conduct, and consequently one of the criteria of morality.

But this alone doesn’t prove it to be the sole criterion. To prove that in the same way, it seems, we would have to show not only that people desire happiness but that they never desire anything else. Now it’s obvious that they do desire things that common language sharply distinguishes from happiness. For example, they desire virtue and the absence of vice, and this desire is just as real as their desire for pleasure and the absence of pain. The desire for virtue is not as universal as the desire for happiness, but it is just as authentic a fact as the other. So the opponents of the utilitarian standard think they have a right to infer that there are other ends of human action besides happiness, and that happiness is not the standard for approval and disapproval.

But does the utilitarian doctrine deny that people desire virtue, or maintain that virtue is not something to be desired? Quite the contrary! It maintains not only that virtue is to be •desired, but further that virtue is to be •desired disinterestedly, for itself. Utilitarian moralists believe that actions and dispositions are virtuous only because they

24

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 4: What proof for the principle of utility?

promote an end other than virtue; and that it is on this basis that we decide what is virtuous. But set all that aside; it is still open to the utilitarians to place virtue at the very head of the things that are good as means to the ultimate end. They also recognise as a psychological fact that an individual could regard virtue as a good in itself, without looking to any end beyond it; and they hold this:

The mind is not in a right state, not in a state consistent with utility, not in the state most conducive to the general happiness, unless it does love virtue in this manner—as something that is desirable in itself even when, in the particular case, it wouldn’t produce those other desirable consequences that it tends ·in general· to produce.

This opinion doesn’t depart in the slightest from the happiness principle. The ingredients of happiness are very various, and each of them is desirable •in itself and not merely •when considered as adding to some total. The principle of utility doesn’t mean that any given pleasure (music, for instance) and any given freedom from pain (good health, for instance) is to be looked on ·only· as a means to a collective something called ‘happiness’, and to be desired ·only· on that account. They are desired and desirable in and for themselves; besides being means to the end they are also a part of it. Well, according to the utilitarian doctrine, virtue is not naturally and originally part of the end (·happiness·) but it is capable of becoming so; and in those who unselfishly love it virtue has become so, and is desired and cherished not as a means to happiness but as a part of their happiness.

To illustrate this further, let us consider something else that is like virtue in the respect I have been discussing. That is, something of which this is true:

It was originally a means ·to something that is desired·, and if it weren’t a means to anything else it would be of no interest to anyone; but by association with what it is a means to it comes to be desired for itself, and indeed desired with the utmost intensity.

What I have in mind is money. There is nothing intrinsically more desirable about money than about any heap of glittering pebbles. Its value is solely the value of the things that it will buy; the desire for it is the desire for other things that it can lead to. Yet the love of money is not only one of the strongest moving forces of human life, but many people desire money in and for itself; the desire to have it is often stronger than the desire to use it, and goes on getting stronger even when the person is losing all the desires that point to ends to which money might be a means. So it is true to say that money is desired not for the •sake of an end but as •part of the end. From being a means to happiness it has come to be itself a principal ingredient of the individual’s conception of happiness. The same may be said of most of the great objects of human life—power, for example, or fame; except that each of these brings a certain amount of immediate pleasure, which at least seems to be naturally inherent in them, whereas nothing like that can be said about money. Still, the strongest natural attraction of power and of fame is the immense aid they give to the attainment of our other wishes; this generates a strong association between them and all our objects of desire; and that association gives to the direct desire for power or fame the intensity it often has, so that in some people it is stronger than all other desires. In these cases the means have become a part of the end, and a more important part of it than any of the things that they are means to. What was once desired as a help towards getting happiness has come to be desired for its own sake—as a part of happiness. The person is made, or thinks he would be made, happy by merely having power or fame, and is made unhappy by failure to get it. The desire for it isn’t a different

25

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 4: What proof for the principle of utility?

thing from the desire for happiness, any more than is the love of music or the desire for health. They are included in happiness. They are some of the elements of which the desire for happiness is made up. Happiness is not an abstract idea, but a concrete •whole; and these are some of its •parts. And the utilitarian standard allows and approves of their being so. Life would be a poor thing, very poorly provided with sources of happiness, if nature didn’t arrange for this way in which things that are intrinsically indifferent, but lead to or are otherwise associated with the satisfaction of our basic desires, become in themselves sources of pleasure more valuable than the basic pleasures—more permanent... and more intense.

Virtue, according to the utilitarian conception, is a good of this description. Originally the only reason for wanting it was its conduciveness to pleasure and especially to protection from pain. But this created an association ·of virtue with pleasure and absence of pain·, and through this association virtue can be felt to be a good in itself, and can be desired as such with as much intensity as any other good. The desire for virtue differs from the love of money, of power, of fame, in this: •those three can and often do make the person •noxious to the other members of the society to which he belongs, whereas the disinterested •love of virtue makes him a •blessing to them—nothing more so! And so the utilitarian standard, while it tolerates and approves those other acquired desires

•up to the point beyond which they would do more harm than good to the general happiness,

demands the cultivation of the love of virtue

•up to the greatest strength possible

because it is more important than anything else to the general happiness.

The upshot of the preceding lines of thought is that really nothing is desired except happiness. Anything that is desired otherwise than as a means to some end beyond itself (and ultimately a means to happiness) is desired as being itself a part of happiness, and it isn’t desired for itself until it has become so. Those who desire virtue for its own sake desire it either •because a person’s awareness of his virtue is a pleasure, or •because his awareness of his not being virtuous is a pain, or •for both reasons united. For the fact is that this pleasure and pain seldom exist separately, but almost always together: one person feels pleasure at the degree of virtue he has achieved, and pain at not having achieved more. If one of these gave him no pleasure, and the other no pain, he wouldn’t love or desire virtue, or would desire it only for the other benefits that it might produce for himself or for persons whom he cared for. So now we have an answer to the question: What sort of proof can be given for the principle of utility? If the opinion that I have now stated is psychologically true—if human nature is so constituted that we desire nothing that isn’t either a •part of happiness or a •means to it—we can’t have and don’t need any other proof that •these are the only desirable things. If so, happiness is the only end of human action, and the promotion of it is the test by which to judge all human conduct; from which it necessarily follows that it must be the criterion of morality, since a part is included in the whole.

Is this really so? Do human beings desire nothing for itself except that which is a pleasure to them or that whose absence is a pain? We are now confronted by a question of fact and experience, which like all such questions depends on evidence. It can only be answered by practised self-awareness and self-observation, assisted by observation of others. I believe that when these sources of evidence are consulted without any bias, they will declare that

•desiring a thing and •finding it pleasant,

26

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 4: What proof for the principle of utility?

are entirely inseparable phenomena, or rather they are two parts of the same phenomenon, and that the same is true of

•aversion to a thing and •thinking of it as painful.

Strictly speaking, they are two different ways of naming the same psychological fact; •to think of an object as desirable (unless as a means) and to think of it as pleasant are one and the same thing; and •it is a physical and metaphysical impossibility to desire anything except in proportion as the idea of it is pleasant.

This seems to me to be so obvious that I expect it will hardly be disputed. The objection that will be made is not that

desire could be ultimately directed to something other than pleasure and freedom from pain,

but that

the will is a different thing from desire; and a solidly virtuous person or any other person whose purposes are fixed carries out his purposes without any thought of the pleasure he has in contemplating them or expects to get from their fulfilment; and he persists in acting on his purposes even if these pleasures are greatly lessened by changes in his character or the weakening of his passive sensibilities (·i.e. his desires·), or are outweighed by the pains that the pursuit of his purposes may bring on him.

All this I fully admit, and have stated it elsewhere as positively and emphatically as anyone. Will is an •active phenomenon, and is a different thing from desire, which is the state of •passive sensibility. Though originally an offshoot from desire, will can in time take root and detach itself from the parent stock; so much so that in the case of an habitual purpose, instead of willing the thing because we desire it we often desire it only because we will it. But this is merely an instance of a familiar phenomenon, namely the power of habit, and isn’t at all confined to the case of virtuous actions. (1) Many indifferent things that men originally did from a motive of some sort they continue to do from habit. Sometimes this is done unconsciously, with the person becoming aware of it only after the action; at other times it is done with conscious volition, but volition that has become habitual and is put into operation by the force of habit. (2) This may be in opposition to the person’s deliberate preference, as often happens with those who have acquired habits of vicious or hurtful self-indulgence. (3) Or it may be that the habitual act of will in the individual instance is not in •contradiction to the general intention prevailing at other times but in •fulfilment of it.

That’s the case for a person of confirmed virtue, and for anyone who deliberately and consistently pursues any definite end. The distinction between will and desire, understood in this way, is an authentic and highly important psychological fact; but the fact consists solely in this—•that will, like all every other part of our make-up, is amenable to habit, and •that we can will from habit something we no longer desire for itself or desire only because we will it. It is still true that will at the beginning is entirely produced by desire—taking ‘desire’ to cover the repelling influence of pain as well as the attractive influence of pleasure. Now let us set aside the person who has a confirmed will to do right, and think about the one in whom that virtuous will is still feeble, conquerable by temptation, and not to be fully relied on; how can it be strengthened in him? Where the will to be virtuous doesn’t exist in sufficient force, how can it be implanted or awakened? Only by making the person desire virtue—by making him think of it in a pleasurable light, or of its absence in a painful one. By

•associating right-doing with pleasure or wrong-doing with pain, or by

27

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

•bringing out and impressing and bringing home to the person’s experience the pleasure naturally involved in doing right or the pain in doing wrong,

it is possible to call forth that will to be virtuous which, when it is firmly built into the person’s make-up, acts without any thought of either pleasure or pain. Will is the child of desire, and moves out of the control of its parent only to come under the control of habit. Something’s being a result of habit doesn’t count towards its being intrinsically good; and the only reason for wishing that the purpose of virtue should become independent of pleasure and pain ·by becoming habitual· is the fact that the influence of the pleasurable and painful associations that prompt virtuous behaviour can’t be depended on for unerring constancy of action until it has acquired the support of habit. Habit is the only thing that makes patterns of feeling and conduct certain; and it is because of the importance to others of being able to rely absolutely on one’s feelings and conduct, and the importance of this to oneself, that the will to do right should be made to grow into this habitual independence—·this independence from desire that is bought about by habit·. In other words, this ·virtuous· state of the will is a •means to good, not •intrinsically a good; and so it doesn’t contradict the •doctrine that nothing is a good to human beings except to the extent that it is either itself pleasurable or is a means of getting pleasure or avoiding pain. But if this •doctrine is true, the principle of utility is proved. Whether the doctrine is true must now be left to the judgment of the thoughtful reader.

Chapter 5: The connection between justice and utility

[In this chapter Mill frequently uses the word ‘sentiment’. In his usage, a ‘sentiment’ could be either belief or a feeling. That ambiguity has work to do: Mill thinks that ‘That is unjust!’ expresses the speaker’s feelings, but many of his opponents think it expresses the speaker’s belief that the action in question objectively has a certain intrinsic quality. Speaking of the ‘sentiment’ that is expressed is one way of staying neutral between the two views. The present version of the chapter uses ‘sentiment’ every time that Mill does (and only then), and uses ‘feeling’ every time that Mill does (and only then).]

Down through the ages, one of the strongest objections to the doctrine that utility or happiness is the criterion of right and wrong has been based on the idea of justice. The •powerful sentiment and •apparently clear thought that this word brings to mind, with a rapidity and certainty resembling an instinct, have seemed to the majority of thinkers to •point to an inherent quality in things, •to show that what is just must have an existence in nature as something absolute, fundamentally distinct from every variety of what is expedient. The concept of justice (they have thought) conflicts with the concept of expediency, though they commonly admit that in the long run justice and expediency go together as a matter of fact.

In the case of this moral sentiment (as of all the others) there is no necessary connection between the question of its

28

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

•origin, and the question of its •binding force. That a feeling is bestowed on us by nature doesn’t necessarily mean that we should always do what it prompts us to do. The feeling of justice might be a special instinct (·and thus bestowed by nature·) and yet need to be controlled and enlightened by a higher reason, just as all our other instincts do. If we have intellectual instincts that lead us to think in a particular way, as well as animal instincts that prompt us to act in a particular way, the intellectual ones aren’t necessarily more infallible in their sphere than the animal ones are in their sphere; just as wrong actions can be prompted by the animal instincts, wrong judgments [= ‘wrong beliefs’] may sometimes be prompted by the intellectual instincts. But although it is one thing to •believe that we have natural feelings of justice and another to •accept them as an ultimate criterion of conduct, these two opinions are very closely connected in point of fact. Mankind are always inclined to think that any •subjective feeling that they can’t explain in any other way is a revelation of some •objective reality. What we need to do now is to discover whether the reality to which the feeling of justice corresponds is one that needs to be revealed in any such special manner. That is, to discover whether

the justice or injustice of an action is a •special quality all on its own, and distinct from all the action’s other qualities,

or rather

the justice or injustice of an action is only a combination of certain of those qualities seen or thought about in a •special way.

[This is what Mill, on page 30, calls ‘the main problem’.] For the purpose of this inquiry it is practically important to consider whether

the feeling of justice and injustice is sui generis—·not a special case of something more general·—like our sensations of colour and taste (·such as something’s tasting sweet·),

or rather

the feeling of justice and injustice is a derivative feeling, formed by a combination of other feelings (·comparable with something’s tasting stale·).

It is especially important to look into this; here is why.

(1) People are usually willing enough to agree that objectively—·out there in the world·—the dictates of justice coincide with a part of the field of general expediency, ·i.e. that very often the just action is also the action that will be most expedient from the point of view of people in general·. (2) But the subjective mental feeling of justice is different from the feeling that commonly goes with simple expediency, and except in the extreme cases of expediency the feeling of justice is far more imperative in its demands. (3) So people •find it hard to see justice as only a particular kind or branch of general utility, and they •think that its greater binding force requires it to have a totally different origin.

To throw light on this question we must try to find out what it is that marks off justice, or injustice, as special. (I’ll put this in terms of injustice because justice, like many other moral attributes, is best defined by its opposite.) When actions are described as ‘unjust’, is there some one quality that is being attributed to all of them, a quality that marks them off from actions that are disapproved of but aren’t said to be ‘unjust’? If so, what quality is it? If some one common quality (or collection of qualities) is always present in everything that men customarily call ‘just’ or ‘unjust’, we can judge whether

the general laws of our emotional make-up could enable this particular quality (or combination of qualities) to summon up a sentiment with the special

29

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

character and intensity ·of the sentiment of justice or injustice·,

or whether instead

the sentiment ·of justice or injustice· can’t be explained, and must be regarded as something that nature provided independently of its other provisions.

If we find the former to be the case, we shall by answering this question have also solved the main problem. If the latter is the case, we’ll have to look for some other way of tackling the main problem.

To find the qualities that a variety of objects have in common we must start by surveying the objects themselves in the concrete [= ‘not partial descriptions of them but the objects themselves as they are in actuality, with all their qualities’]. Let us therefore turn our attention to the various ways of acting and arrangements of human affairs that are universally or ·at least· widely characterized as ‘just’ or as ‘unjust’, taking them one at a time. A great variety of things are well known to arouse the sentiments associated with those names. I shall survey ·five of· them rapidly, not trying to put them in any special order.

(1) It is usually considered unjust to deprive anyone of his personal liberty, his property, or anything else that belongs to him by law. This gives us one instance of the application of the terms ‘just’ and ‘unjust’ in a perfectly definite sense, namely: It is just to respect, and unjust to violate, the legal rights of anyone. But there are several exceptions to this, arising from the other ways in which the notions of justice and injustice come up. For example, the person who suffers the deprivation may (as they say) have ‘forfeited’ the rights that he is deprived of. I’ll return to this case soon.

(2) ·The second kind of case will come in the last sentence of this paragraph; a preliminary matter needs to be sorted out first·. The legal rights of which someone is deprived may be rights that he oughtn’t to have had in the first place, i.e. the law that gives him these rights may be a bad law. When that is so or when (which is the same thing for our purpose) it is supposed to be so, opinions will differ as to the justice or injustice of breaking that law. Some maintain that no law, however bad, ought to be disobeyed by an individual citizen; that if the citizen is to show his opposition to it, he should do so only by trying to get the law altered by those who are authorized to do that. This opinion condemns many of the most famous benefactors of mankind, and would often protect pernicious institutions against the only weapons that in the circumstances have any chance of succeeding against them. Those who have this opinion defend it on grounds of expediency, relying principally on the importance to the common interests of mankind of preserving unbroken the sentiment of submission to law. Other people hold the directly contrary opinion, namely that any law that is judged to be •bad may blamelessly be disobeyed, even if it isn’t judged to be •unjust, but only thought to be bad because inexpedient; while others would permit disobedience only to •unjust laws; while yet others say that all laws that are inexpedient are unjust, because every law imposes some restriction on the natural liberty of mankind, and this restriction is an injustice unless it is made legitimate by tending to the people’s good. Among these differences of opinion this much seems to be universally agreed:

There can be unjust laws; so law is not the ultimate criterion of justice.

A law may give one person a benefit, or impose harm on someone else, which justice condemns. But when a law is thought to be unjust, it seems always to be because it is thought to infringe somebody’s right (just as when a breach of law is unjust). Because it’s a law that is thought to infringe the person’s right, this can’t be a legal right, so it is labelled

30

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

differently and is called a ‘moral right’. So we can say that a second case of injustice consists in taking or keeping from a person something to which he has a moral right.

(3) It is universally considered just that each person should get what he deserves (whether good or evil) and unjust that someone should obtain a good or be made to undergo an evil which he doesn’t deserve. This is perhaps the clearest and most emphatic form in which the idea of justice is conceived by people in general. As it involves the notion of desert [= ‘deservingness’], the question arises, what constitutes desert? Broadly speaking, a person is understood to deserve good if he does right, and to deserve evil if he does wrong; and in a more special sense, to deserve good from those to whom he does or has done good, and to deserve evil from those to whom he does or has done evil. The injunction ‘Return good for evil’ has never been regarded as a case of the fulfilment of justice, but as one in which the claims of justice are set aside in obedience to other considerations.

(4) It is agreed to be unjust to break faith with anyone—to fail to do something we have said or clearly implied that we would do, or disappoint expectations raised by our conduct, at least if we knew we were raising them and meant to do so. Like the other obligations of justice I have already spoken of, this one isn’t regarded as absolute. Rather, it is thought of as capable of being overruled when •there is a stronger obligation of justice on the other side, or when •the other person has acted in a way that is deemed to clear us of our obligation to him and to constitute a forfeiture of the benefit that he has been led to expect.

(5) Everyone agrees that it is inconsistent with justice to be partial—to show favour or preference to one person over another in matters to which favour and preference don’t properly apply. But impartiality seems to be regarded not as a duty in itself but rather as a needed part of some other duty; for it is agreed that favour and preference are not always blameworthy, and indeed the cases where they are condemned are the exception rather than the rule. If a person could in some way favour his family or friends over strangers without violating any other duty, he would be blamed rather than applauded for not doing so. No-one thinks it unjust to choose one person in preference to another as a friend, a connection, or a companion. Where rights are concerned, impartiality is of course obligatory, but this comes from the more general obligation to give everyone what he has a right to. For example, an arbitration court must be impartial because it is bound to set aside every other consideration and award a disputed item to the one of two parties who has the right to it. In some other cases impartiality means being solely influenced by desert; as with the administering of reward and punishments by judges, teachers or parents. In yet other cases impartiality means being solely influenced by concern for the public interest, as in making a selection among candidates for a government job. In short, impartiality considered as an obligation of justice can be said to mean being influenced only by the considerations that (it is supposed) ought to influence the matter in hand, and resisting the pull of any motives that prompt to conduct different from what those considerations would dictate.

Closely allied to the idea of impartiality is that of equality, which often plays a part in one’s thought of justice and in the performance of just actions. Many people think it is the essence of justice. But in this context, even more than in any of the others, the notion of justice varies in different persons, with the variations conforming to their different notions of utility, ·i.e. of what is expedient·. Each person maintains that equality is demanded by justice except where he thinks that expediency requires inequality. The justice of giving

31

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

equal protection everyone’s rights is maintained by those who support the most outrageous inequality in what rights people have. Even in slave countries it is theoretically admitted that the rights of the slave, such as they are, ought to be as sacred as those of the master; and that a court that fails to enforce them with equal strictness is lacking in justice; while at the same time social arrangements that leave to the slave scarcely any rights to enforce are not thought unjust because they are not thought to be inexpedient. Those who think that utility requires distinctions of rank don’t think it unjust that riches and social privileges should be distributed unequally; but those who think this inequality to be inexpedient think it unjust also. Whoever thinks that government is necessary sees no injustice in whatever inequality is involved in giving to the magistrate powers not granted to other people. Even among those who hold doctrines that advocate abolishing all social distinctions, there are as many questions of justice as there are differences of opinion about expediency. Some communists consider it unjust to share out the products of the community’s work in any way except exactly equally; others think it just that those whose wants are greatest should receive most; while others hold that those who work harder or who produce more or whose services are more valuable to the community can justly claim a larger share in the division of the products. And every one of these opinions can plausibly be backed by the sense of natural justice.

Among so many different uses of the term ‘justice’ (not regarded as an ambiguous word!), it is a little difficult to get hold of the mental link which holds them together and on which the moral sentiment associated with the term essentially depends. Perhaps we may get some help with this puzzle from the history of the word, as indicated by its etymology.

In most languages, if not in all, the etymology of the word that corresponds to ‘just’ points distinctly to an origin connected with law. [Mill illustrates this with references to Latin, Greek, German and French.] I am not committing the fallacy.... of assuming that a word must still continue to mean what it originally meant. Etymology is slight evidence of what idea is now signified by the word, but it is but the very best evidence of how it arose. I don’t think there can be any doubt that the....original element in the formation of the notion of justice was ·the idea of· conformity to law. It constituted the entire idea among the Hebrews, up to the birth of Christianity; as might be expected in the case of a people whose laws tried to cover all subjects on which guidance was required, and who believed those laws to have come directly from God. But other nations (especially the Greeks and Romans), knowing that their laws had originally been made and were still being made by men, weren’t afraid to admit that those men might make bad laws; that men might lawfully do things....that would be called unjust if done by individuals without permission from the law. And so the sentiment of injustice came to be attached not to all violations of law but only to

•violations of laws that do and ought to exist,

•violations of non-existent laws that ought to exist, and

•laws themselves when they are taken to be contrary to what ought to be law.

In this way the idea of law and of laws was still predominant in the notion of justice, even when the laws actually in force ceased to be accepted as the standard of it.

It’s true that mankind consider the idea of justice and its obligations as applicable to many things that aren’t—and that nobody thinks should be—regulated by law. Nobody wants laws to interfere with all the details of private life, yet everyone agrees that in all daily conduct a person may and does show himself to be either just or unjust. But even here

32

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

the idea of the breach of what ought to be law still lingers in a modified form. It would always give us pleasure, and would chime in with our feelings about what is fit ·or appropriate or suitable·, if acts that we think unjust were punished, though we don’t always think it expedient that this should be done by the courts. We forgo that gratification because of inconveniences that it would bring. We would be glad to see just conduct enforced and injustice repressed, even in the smallest details of our lives, if we weren’t rightly afraid of trusting the officers of the law with such unlimited power over individuals. When we think that a person is bound in justice to do a thing, it is an ordinary use of language to say ‘He ought to be made to do it’. We would be gratified to see the obligation enforced by anybody who had the power to enforce it. If we see that it would be inexpedient for it to be enforced by law, we

•regret that it can’t be enforced by law,

•consider it bad that the person can get away with it, and

•try to make amends for this by subjecting the offender to a strong expression of our own and the public’s disapproval.

Thus the idea of legal constraint is still the generating idea of the notion of justice, though it goes through several changes before emerging as the notion of justice that exists in an advanced state of society.

I think that the above is a true account, as far as it goes, of the origin and development of the idea of justice. But it doesn’t yet contain anything to distinguish •that obligation from •moral obligation in general. For the truth is that the idea of penal sanction, which is the essence of law, enters not only into the conception of injustice but into the conception of any kind of wrong. Whenever we call something ‘wrong’ we mean to imply that a person ought to be punished somehow for doing it; if not by law, by the opinion of his fellow-creatures; if not by opinion, by the reproaches of his own conscience. This ·relation to the idea of enforcement by law· seems to be the real turning point of the distinction between morality and simple expediency. It is a part of the notion of duty in every one of its forms that a person may rightfully be compelled to do his duty, just as he may rightfully be compelled to pay a debt.... If we don’t think it would be all right to make a person do a certain thing, we don’t call it his ‘duty’. There may be reasons of prudence, or of the interests of other people, that count against actually using compulsion, but we clearly understand that the person himself would not be entitled to complain ·if he were compelled·. In contrast with this, there are other things that we •wish people would do, •like or admire them for doing, perhaps •dislike or despise them for not doing, but yet •admit that they are not bound to do. It is not a case of moral obligation; we don’t blame them, i.e. we don’t think that they are proper objects of punishment. It may become clear later on how we get these ideas of deserving and not deserving punishment; but I don’t think there is any ·room for· doubt •that this distinction lies at the bottom of the notions of right and wrong; •that whether we call a bit of conduct ‘wrong’ rather than using some other term of dislike or discredit depends on whether we think that the person ought to be punished for it; and whether we say it would be ‘right’ for a person to do such-and-such rather than merely that it would be desirable or praiseworthy for him to do so depends on whether we would like to see the person compelled to act in that manner rather than merely persuaded and urged to do so.

So the notion of fitness to be punished is the characteristic difference that marks off (not justice, but) •morality in general from the •remaining provinces of expediency and

33

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

worthiness; so we are still looking for the characteristic that distinguishes •justice from •other branches of morality. Now it is known that ethical writers divide moral duties into two classes, to which they give the ill-chosen labels ‘duties of perfect obligation’ and ‘duties of imperfect obligation’. The latter are duties in which, though the act is obligatory, the particular occasions of performing it are left to our choice. For example, we are bound to engage in acts of charity or beneficence, but we aren’t bound to perform them towards any definite person or at any prescribed time. In the more precise language of legal theorists, duties of perfect obligation are the •ones that create a correlative right in some person or persons; duties of imperfect obligation are the •moral obligations that don’t give rise to any right. I think it will be found that this distinction exactly coincides with the distinction between •justice and •the other obligations of morality. In my survey ·on pages 30-32· of the various common ideas about ‘justice’, the term seemed generally to involve the idea of a personal right—a claim on the part of one or more individuals, like what the law gives when it confers an ownership or other legal right. Whether the injustice consists in (1) and (2) depriving a person of something he owns, or in (4) breaking faith with him, or in (3) treating him worse than he deserves or (5) worse than other people who have no greater claims, in each case the supposition implies two things—a wrong done, and some definite person who is wronged. Injustice may also be done by treating a person better than others, but in that case some other definite people, his competitors, are wronged.

It seems to me that this feature in the case—some person’s having a right correlated with the moral obligation—constitutes the defining difference that separates •justice from •generosity or •beneficence. Justice implies something which it is not only right to do, and wrong not to do, but which some individual person can claim from us as his moral right. No-one has a moral right to our generosity or beneficence, because we are not morally bound to practise those virtues towards any given individual. It will be found with this as with every correct definition that the particular cases that seem to conflict with it are those that most confirm it. Some moralists have tried to argue that although no given individual has a right to our beneficence, mankind in general does have a right to all the good we can do them. Someone who maintains that automatically includes generosity and beneficence within the category of justice. He is obliged to say that

we owe our utmost exertions to our fellow creatures, thus assimilating those exertions to a debt;

or that

nothing less than our utmost exertions can be an adequate return for what society does for us, thus classifying the case as one of gratitude,

both of which are acknowledged cases of justice. Wherever there is a right, the case is one of justice and not of the virtue of beneficence. If you don’t draw the general line between •justice and •morality where I have drawn it, you’ll turn out to be drawing no line between them and to be merging all morality in justice.

Now that we have tried to discover the distinctive elements that make up the idea of justice, we are ready to start looking for the right answer to these questions:

•Is the feeling that accompanies the idea of justice attached to it by a special provision of nature?

•Could that feeling have grown out of the idea itself, in accordance with some known laws ·about human nature·?

If the answer to the second question is Yes, then a more particular question arises:

34

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

•Could the feeling have originated in considerations of general expediency?

Although •the sentiment itself doesn’t arise from anything that would or should be termed an idea of ‘expediency’, •whatever is moral in it does.

We have seen that the two essential ingredients in the sentiment of justice are •the desire to punish a person who has done harm, and •the knowledge or belief that there is some definite individual or individuals to whom harm has been done.

Now it appears to me that the desire to punish a person who has done harm to some individual is a spontaneous outgrowth from two sentiments that are both utterly natural, and that either are instincts or resemble instincts. They are the impulse of self-defence, and the feeling of sympathy.

It is natural to resent, and to repel or retaliate for, any harm done or attempted against ourselves or against those with whom we sympathise. We needn’t discuss the origin of this sentiment here. Whether it is an instinct or a result of intelligence, we know that it is common to all animal nature; for every animal tries to hurt those who have hurt it or its young, or who it thinks are about to do so. In this matter human beings differ from other animals in only two respects. (1) They are capable of sympathising not only with their offspring, or (like some of the more noble animals) with some superior animal who is kind to them, but with all human beings—even with all sentient beings. (2) They have a more developed intelligence, which gives a wider range to the whole of their sentiments, whether self-regarding or sympathetic. By virtue of his superior intelligence, even apart from his greater range of sympathy, a human being can understand the idea of a community of interest between himself and the human society of which he forms a part, so that any conduct that threatens the security of the society generally is threatening to his own security in particular, and calls forth his instinct (if that’s what it is) of self-defence. With that superiority of intelligence joined to the power of sympathising with human beings generally, the human being can take on board the collective idea of his tribe, his country, or mankind, in such a way that any act hurtful to them arouses his instinct of sympathy and urges him to resist.

One element in the sentiment of justice is the desire to punish. That, I think, is the natural feeling of retaliation or vengeance processed by intellect and sympathy so that it applies to the injuries....that wound us by wounding society at large. This sentiment in itself has nothing moral in it; what is moral is its being pure purely at the service of the social sympathies, so that it is aroused only when they call it up. For the natural feeling would make us resent indiscriminately whatever anyone does that is disagreeable to us; but when it is made moral by the social feeling, it acts only in ways that conform to the general good. A just person resents a hurt to society even if it isn’t directly a hurt to him, and he doesn’t resent a hurt to himself, however painful, unless it is a kind of hurt that society, as well as he himself, would want to prevent.

You might want to object against this doctrine: ‘When we feel our sentiment of justice outraged, we aren’t thinking of society at large or of any collective interest, but only of the individual case.’ Well, it is certainly common enough—though the reverse of commendable—for someone to feel resentment merely because he has suffered pain; but a person whose resentment is really a moral feeling, i.e. who considers whether an act is blamable before he allows himself to resent it, though he may not explicitly say to himself that he is standing up for the interests of society, certainly does feel that he is asserting a rule that is for the benefit of others as well as for his own benefit. If he is not feeling this—if he is

35

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

regarding the act solely as it affects him individually—he is not consciously just; he is not concerning himself about the justice of his actions. This is admitted even by anti-utilitarian moralists. When Kant (as I remarked ·on page 3·) propounds as the fundamental principle of morals ‘Act in such a way that the rule on which you act •could be adopted as a law by all rational beings’, he virtually acknowledges that the interest of mankind.... must be in the person’s mind when he is conscientiously deciding on the morality of the act. If that isn’t what Kant is getting at, he is using words without a meaning: for he couldn’t plausibly mean that a rule even of utter selfishness •couldn’t possibly be adopted by all rational beings, that there is some insuperable obstacle in the nature of things to its adoption. To give any meaning to Kant’s principle we must take it to be saying that we ought to shape our conduct by a rule that all rational beings might adopt with benefit to their collective interest.

To recapitulate: the idea of justice involves two things: a •rule of conduct, and a •sentiment that sanctions the rule. The •rule must be supposed to be common to all mankind, and intended for their good. The •sentiment is a desire that punishment may be suffered by those who infringe the rule. A third thing is also involved, namely the thought of some definite person who suffers by the infringement—someone whose rights.... are violated by it. And the sentiment of justice appears to me to be:

(1) the animal desire to repel or retaliate for a hurt or damage to oneself or to those with whom one sympathises, widened so as to include all persons—with the widening brought about by (2) the human capacity for broadened sympathy and the human conception of intelligent self-interest.

The feeling gets its •status as moral from (2), and its •unique impressiveness and psychological force from (1).

I have treated the idea of a right that the injured person has, and that the injury violates, not as a separate element in the make-up of •the idea and •the sentiment but as one of the forms in which the other two elements clothe themselves. These elements are

a hurt to some assignable person or persons, and

a demand for punishment.

An examination of our own minds, I think, will show that these two include the whole of what we mean when we speak of ‘violation of a right’. When we call something a person’s ‘right’, we mean that he has a valid claim on society to protect him in his possession of it, either by the force of law or by the force of education and opinion. If we think he has a strong enough claim, on whatever basis, to have something guaranteed to him by society, we say that he has ‘a right’ to it. If we want to prove that something does not belong to him by right, we think we have done that as soon as it is admitted that society ought not to take measures for guaranteeing that he keeps it but should leave that to chance or to his own efforts. Thus, a person is said to have a right to what he can earn in fair professional competition, because society ought not to allow anyone else to hinder him from trying to earn as much as he can in that manner. But he doesn’t have a right to three hundred pounds a year, even if that is what he happens to be earning; because society is not called on to ensure that he will earn that sum. On the other hand, if he owns ten thousand pounds worth of government bonds at three per cent, he has a right to three hundred pounds a year because society has come under an obligation to provide him with an income of that amount.

As I see it, then, for me to have a right is for me to have something that society ought to defend me in the possession of. Why ought it to do so? The only reason I can give is general utility. If that phrase doesn’t seem to convey a

36

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

good enough sense of how strong the obligation is—i.e. good enough to account for the special energy of the feeling—that’s because the make-up of the sentiment includes not only a •rational element but also an •animal element, the thirst for retaliation; and this thirst gets its intensity as well as its moral justification from the extraordinarily important and impressive kind of utility that is concerned. The ·general· interest that is involved is that of security, which everyone feels to be the most vital of all interests. All •other earthly benefits are needed by this person and not by that, and many of them can if necessary be cheerfully done without or replaced by something else; but no human being can possibly do without •security. We depend on it for all our immunity from evil. And we depend on it for the whole value of every single good that goes beyond the passing moment; because if we could be deprived of anything the next instant by whoever was at that moment stronger than ourselves, nothing could be of any worth to us except the gratification of the instant. Second only to food and drink, security is the most indispensable of all the requirements of life; and it can’t be had unless the machinery for providing it is kept running continuously. That’s why our notion of the claim we have on our fellow-creatures to join in making safe for us the very groundwork of our existence gathers feelings around it that are much more intense than those concerned in any of the more ordinary kinds of utility. They are so much more intense that this difference in •degree (as is often the case in psychology) becomes a real difference in •kind. The claim takes on the absoluteness, the apparent infinity that won’t let it be weighed against other considerations, which distinguish the feeling of right and wrong from that of ordinary expediency and inexpediency. The feelings concerned are so powerful, and we rely so absolutely on finding a responsive feeling in others (because the interests of everyone are involved) that

ought and should grow into must, and

recognised indispensability becomes moral necessity,

analogous to physical necessity and often as strongly binding a force as physical necessity is.

If that analysis or something like it is not the correct account of the notion of justice, if justice is totally independent of utility and is an independently existing standard that the mind can recognise by simply looking into itself, it’s hard to understand why that internal oracle is so ambiguous, and why so many things appear just or unjust depending on the light in which they are looked at.

We are continually being told that utility is an uncertain standard which every different person interprets differently, and that there is no safety but in the unchangeable, unerasable, unmistakable dictates of justice, which are self-evident and independent of the fluctuations of opinion. This would make one think •that there could be no controversy on questions of justice; •that if we take that for our rule—·the supposedly unmistakable dictate of justice·—the question of how to apply it to any given case could be answered with as much certainty as if it had been proved by a mathematical demonstration. This is so far from being the case that there is as much disagreement and discussion about what is •just as about what is •useful to society. It’s not just that different nations and different individuals have different notions of justice; in the mind of •one and the same individual justice isn’t some •one rule, principle or maxim, but •many, which don’t always coincide in their dictates and which the individual chooses between on the basis of some extraneous standard or of his own personal inclinations.

37

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

·Punishment·

For instance, some say that (1) it is unjust to punish anyone for the sake of setting an example for others; that punishment is just only when it is intended for the good of the sufferer himself. Others maintain the exact opposite, contending that (2) to punish adults for their own benefit is despotism and injustice, since if the matter at issue is solely their own good no-one has a right to control their own judgment of it; but that •someone may justly be punished to prevent evil to others, this being the exercise of the legitimate right of self-defence. Mr. Owen affirms that (3) is unjust to punish at all; for the criminal didn’t make his own character; his upbringing and environment have made him a criminal, and he isn’t responsible for these. All these opinions are extremely plausible; and so long as the question is argued simply as one of justice, without going down to the principles that underlie justice and are the source of its authority, I don’t see how any of these reasoners can be refuted. For in truth each of the three builds on rules of justice that are admittedly true. (1) appeals to the acknowledged injustice of

•singling out an individual and sacrificing him, without his consent, for other people’s benefit.

(2) relies on the acknowledged justice of self-defence, and the admitted injustice of

•forcing one person to conform to someone else’s notions of what is good for him.

(3) The Owenite invokes the admitted principle that

•it is unjust to punish anyone for what he cannot help.

Each ·moralist· is triumphant so long as he isn’t forced to take into consideration any maxims of justice except the one he has selected; but as soon as their different maxims are brought face to face, each disputant seems to have exactly as much to say for himself as the others have to say for themselves. No one of them can carry out his own notion of justice without trampling on some other notion of it that is equally binding.

These are difficulties; they have always been felt to be such; and many devices have been invented to get around them rather than to overcome them. As a refuge from (3) men imagined what they called ‘freedom of the will’, fancying that they couldn’t justify punishing a man whose will is in a thoroughly odious state unless prior circumstances are thought to have played no part in his coming to be in that state. A favourite device for escaping from the other difficulties has been the fiction of a contract—a contract through which at some unknown period all the members of society promised to obey the laws and consented to be punished for any disobedience to them. This contract was supposed to give to the legislators a right which it is assumed they wouldn’t otherwise have had, to punish lawbreakers either for their own good or for the good of society. This nice idea was thought to get rid of the whole difficulty and to legitimize the infliction of punishment on the strength of another accepted maxim of justice,.... namely that something isn’t unjust if it is done with the consent of the person who is supposed to be hurt by it. I need hardly remark that even if this ‘consent’ were not a mere fiction, this maxim doesn’t have greater authority than the others that it is brought in to supersede. On the contrary, it’s an instructive specimen of the loose and irregular manner in which supposed principles of justice spring up....

And when it is agreed that it is legitimate to inflict ·some ·punishment, many conflicting conceptions of justice come to light when people discuss ·what·—i.e. discuss the proper apportionment of punishments to offences. No rule on this subject recommends itself so strongly to the primitive and spontaneous sentiment of justice as the lex talionis—•an eye

38

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

for an eye and a tooth for a tooth. This principle of Jewish and Moslem law has been generally abandoned in Europe as a practical maxim, but I suspect that there is in most minds a secret hankering after it; and when retribution happens falls on an offender in that precise shape, the general feeling of satisfaction that arises shows how natural is the sentiment that endorses this •repayment in kind. For many people the test of justice in this area is that the punishment should be proportional to the offence, meaning that it should be exactly measured by the culprit’s moral guilt (whatever their standard is for measuring that). According to these people, the question

What amount of punishment is necessary to deter potential offenders from offending?

has nothing to do with the question of justice, whereas for other people that question is the whole topic. According to them, men cannot justly inflict on a fellow creature, no matter what his offences have been, any amount of suffering beyond the least that will suffice to prevent him from repeating his misconduct and others from imitating it. (Men cannot justly do this; ·they may have a different view about what God can justly do·.)

·Wages·

To take another example from a subject I have already referred to. In a co-operative industrial association, is it just or not that someone’s talent or skill should entitle him to higher pay? On the negative side of the question it is argued that whoever does his best deserves equally well, and can’t justly be put in a worse position through no fault of his own; that higher abilities already bring more than enough advantages—the admiration they arouse, the personal influence they command, and the internal sources of satisfaction that come with them—without adding to these a greater share of the world’s goods; and that society is bound in justice to •compensate the less favoured for this undeserved inequality of advantages, rather than to •make it worse. On the opposite side it is maintained that society receives more from the more efficient worker; that because his services are more useful, society owes him a larger return for them; that a greater share of the joint result is actually his work, and not to allow his claim to it is a kind of robbery; that if he is only to receive as much as others, he can only be justly required to produce as much and to give a smaller amount of time and effort in proportion to his greater efficiency. Who is to decide between these appeals to conflicting principles of justice? In this case justice has two sides to it, which can’t be brought into harmony, and the two disputants have chosen opposite sides—one looking to what it is just that •the individual should receive, the other to what it is just that •the community should give. Each from his own point of view is unanswerable; and any choice between them on grounds of justice must be perfectly arbitrary. Only social utility can decide the preference.

·Taxation·

Then consider how many and how irreconcilable are the standards of justice that people bring into discussions of....taxation. One opinion is that payment to the state should be numerically proportional to the person’s wealth. Others think that justice dictates ‘graduated taxation’, as they call it, taking a higher percentage from those who have more to spare. In the light of natural justice a strong case might be made for disregarding wealth altogether and taking the same absolute sum from everyone who could pay it—just as the subscribers to an association or a club all pay the

39

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

•same sum for the •same privileges, whether or not they can all equally afford it. Since the protection (it might be said) of law and government is provided to everyone and equally demanded by everyone, there is no injustice in making them all buy it at the same price. It is regarded as justice, not injustice, for a shop-keeper to charge to all his customers the same price for the same article, not varying the price according to their means of payment. Nobody actually advocates this doctrine, as applied to taxation, because it conflicts so strongly with man’s feelings of humanity and of social expediency; but the principle of justice it relies on is as true and as binding as any principles of justice that can be appealed to against it. Accordingly it silently influences lines of defence that are employed for other ways of assessing taxation. People feel obliged to argue that the state does more for the rich than for the poor, as a justification for its taking more from them (though really that isn’t true, for if there were no law or government the rich would be far better able to protect themselves than the poor would be, and indeed would probably succeed in making the poor their slaves). And others defer to the same-price-for-same-goods conception of justice when they maintain that all should pay an equal tax for the protection of their persons (these being of equal value to all), and an unequal tax for the protection of their property (which is unequal ·in its value·). Opponents of this proposal reply that my everything is as valuable to me as your everything is to you, ·even if you own much more than I do·. The only way of extricating ourselves from these confusions is the utilitarian way.

Well, then, is the line between the just and the expedient a merely imaginary distinction? Have mankind been deluded in thinking that justice is a more sacred thing than policy, and that policy considerations ought not to be listened to until the demands of justice have been satisfied? By no means. The account I have given of the nature and origin of the sentiment of justice recognises a real distinction. I attach importance to this justice/expediency distinction—at least as much as any of the moralists who grandly express their utter contempt for the consequences of actions as an element in their morality! While I dispute the claims of any theory that sets up an imaginary standard of justice that isn’t based on utility, I regard the justice that is based on utility as being the chief part, and incomparably the most sacred and binding part, of all morality. ‘Justice’ is a name for certain kinds of moral rules that

concern the essentials of human well-being more closely,

and therefore

are more absolutely binding,

than any other rules for the guidance of life; and the notion that we have found to be of the essence of the idea of justice—that of a right residing in an individual—implies and testifies to this more binding obligation.

The moral rules that forbid mankind to •hurt one another (remembering always to include in this the •wrongful interference with each other’s freedom) are more vital to human well-being than any maxims, however important, that merely point out the best way of managing some aspect of human affairs. They have also the special feature that they have more to do with mankind’s social feelings than anything else does. Their being observed is the only thing that preserves peace among human beings: if it weren’t for the fact that obedience to them is the rule and disobedience the exception, everyone would see everyone else as an enemy against whom he must be perpetually guarding himself. Almost equally important is the fact that these are the precepts that mankind have the strongest and the most

40

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

direct reasons to get one another to accept. By merely giving each other prudential instruction or exhortation, they may gain nothing (or think they gain nothing). Everyone has an unmistakable interest in urging on others the duty of positive beneficence, but nothing like as strong an interest ·as everyone has in urging on others the duty of justice·: a person might not need the benefits that others might give him, but he always needs them not to harm him. Thus the moralities that protect every individual from being harmed by others, either directly or by being hindered in his freedom to pursue his own good, are both •the ones that he himself has most at heart and also •the ones that he has the strongest interest in announcing and enforcing by word and deed. It is by a person’s •observance of these that we test and decide whether he is fit to exist as one of the fellowship of human beings, for •that determines whether he will be harmful to those with whom he is in contact. Now, these are the moralities that primarily make up the obligations of justice. The •most conspicuous cases of injustice—the ones that give its tone to the feeling of repugnance that characterises the sentiment—are acts of wrongful aggression, or wrongful exercise of power over someone; the •next are acts that consist in wrongfully withholding from a person something that is his due; in both cases a positive hurt is inflicted on him, in the form either of direct suffering or of the lack of some good that he had reasonable grounds, either of a physical or of a social kind, for counting on.

The same powerful motives that command us to observe these primary moralities tell us to punish the people who violate them. This calls up the impulses of •self-defence, of •defence of others and of •vengeance against such people; and for that reason retribution or evil for evil comes to be closely connected with the •sentiment of justice, and is included in everyone’s •idea of justice. Good for good is also one of the dictates of justice. This is obviously socially useful, and carries with it a natural human feeling; but it doesn’t have at first sight the obvious connection with hurt or injury that is the source of the characteristic intensity of the sentiment of justice, and is present in the most elementary cases of just and unjust. But although the connection ·with hurt or injury· is less •obvious, it is not less •real. Someone who accepts benefits and refuses to give benefits in return at a time when they are needed inflicts a real hurt, by disappointing a very natural and reasonable expectation—an expectation that he must at least tacitly have encouraged, for otherwise (in most cases) the benefits would not have been conferred ·in the first place·. The •disappointment of expectation ranks high among human evils and wrongs, as is shown in the fact that it constitutes the principal criminality of two highly immoral acts—•breach of friendship and •breach of promise. Few hurts that human beings can receive are greater, and none wound more, than when someone that a person has habitually and confidently relied on fails him in his hour of need; and few wrongs are greater than this mere withholding of good; none arouse more resentment in the suffering person or in a sympathising spectator. So the principle of giving to each what he deserves—i.e. good for good as well as evil for evil—is not only included within the idea of justice as I have defined it but is a proper object of that intensity of sentiment which leads people to put •the just higher than •the merely expedient.

Most of the •maxims of justice that are current in the world, and commonly appealed to in dealings where justice is involved, are simply ways of putting into effect the •principles of justice that I have spoken of. That

41

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

•a person is responsible only for what he has voluntarily done or could voluntarily have avoided,

•it is unjust to condemn any person without giving him a hearing,

•the punishment ought to be proportional to the offence,

and the like, are maxims intended to prevent the just principle of evil for evil from being twisted to the infliction of evil without that justification. Most of these common maxims have come into use from the practice of courts of justice, which have laid down the rules that are necessary if they are to fulfil their double function of •inflicting punishment when it is due and of •awarding to each person his right. It was only natural that they should have been led to a more complete recognition and elaboration of such rules than was likely to occur to anyone else.

The first of the judicial virtues, impartiality, is an obligation of justice partly for the reason just given—namely that it is a necessary condition of the fulfilment of the other obligations of justice. But this isn’t the only source of the high status among human obligations of the maxims of equality and impartiality—maxims that are included among the precepts of justice by the common run of people and by those who are most enlightened. From one point of view they can be seen as following from the principles I have already laid down. If it is a duty to do to each according to his deserts, returning good for good as well as repressing evil by evil, it necessarily follows that we should (when no higher duty forbids this) treat equally well all who have deserved equally well of us, and that society should treat equally well all who have deserved equally well of it—that is, who have deserved equally well period. This is the highest abstract standard of social and distributive justice. All institutions and the efforts of all virtuous citizens should be made to converge on this standard as far as possible.

But this great moral duty rests on a still deeper foundation, being a direct upshot of the first principle of morals, and not a mere logical inference from secondary or derivative doctrines. It is involved in the very meaning of utility, or the greatest happiness principle. That principle is a mere form of words with no intelligible meaning unless one person’s happiness counts for exactly as much as another’s (assuming that they are equal in degree, and with the proper allowance made for differences in kinds of happiness—·see pages 5-8 above·). Bentham’s dictum, ‘everybody to count for one, nobody for more than one’ might be written under the principle of utility as an explanatory commentary. [At this point Mill has a long footnote, which is here raised into the main text.]
·START OF THE LONG FOOTNOTE·
This implication, in the first principle of the utilitarian scheme, of perfect impartiality between persons is regarded by Mr. Herbert Spencer (in his Social Statics) as disproving utility’s claim to be a sufficient guide to right; because (he says) the principle of utility presupposes the underlying principle that everybody has an equal right to happiness. It may be more correctly described as supposing that equal amounts of happiness are equally desirable, whether felt by the same or by different persons. But this isn’t •a presupposition of the principle of utility, or •a premise that is needed in defence of the principle; rather, it is •the principle itself; for what is the principle of utility if not the proposition that that ‘happiness’ and ‘desirable’ are synonymous terms? The only underlying principle that is implied is this: the truths of arithmetic are applicable to the valuation of happiness, as of all other measurable quantities.

Mr. Spencer, in a letter on the subject of the preceding note, objects to being considered an opponent of utilitari-

42

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

anism, and says that he regards happiness as the ultimate end of morality; but he thinks that that end is only partially achievable by empirical generalisations from the observed results of conduct, and is completely achievable only by deducing from the laws of life and the conditions of existence what kinds of action necessarily tend to produce happiness and what kinds to produce unhappiness. I entirely agree with this doctrine, except for the word ‘necessarily’; and when that word is set aside, I don’t know of any modern advocate of utilitarianism who would disagree. Mr Spencer in Social Statics especially picked on Bentham. But Bentham is utterly willing to deduce the effect of actions on happiness from the laws of human nature and the universal conditions of human life; no writer is more so! He is usually accused of relying too exclusively on such deductions, and refusing to be bound by the generalisations from specific experience that Mr. Spencer thinks that utilitarians generally confine themselves to. My own opinion (and, I gather, Mr. Spencer’s) is that in ethics, as in all other branches of scientific study, what is needed to give to any general proposition the kind and degree of evidence that constitutes scientific proof is that the results of these two processes shall harmonize, each corroborating and verifying the other.
·END OF THE LONG FOOTNOTE·
Everyone’s equal claim to •happiness (in the opinion of the moralist and the legislator) involves an equal claim to all •the means to happiness, except when the maxim is limited by the inevitable conditions of human life and the general interest (which includes the interests of every individual). When such limits are set, they ought to be strictly construed [Mill’s own phrase]. Just as with every other maxim of justice, this one is far from being universally applied or thought to be applicable; on the contrary, as I have already remarked, it bends to every person’s ideas of social expediency. But whenever it is taken to be applicable at all, it is held to be something that justice dictates. All people are judged to have a right to equality of treatment, except when some recognised social expediency requires the reverse. And so it comes about that when any social inequality stops being considered expedient it comes to be considered not merely as inexpedient but as unjust. Then it appears to be so tyrannical that people are apt to wonder how it could ever have been tolerated; forgetting that they themselves may—under an equally mistaken notion of expediency—be tolerating other inequalities which, if they were corrected, would seem quite as monstrous as the one that the people have eventually learnt to condemn. The entire history of social improvement has been a series of transitions in which one custom or institution after another moves from being a supposed primary necessity of social existence into the category of a universally condemned injustice and tyranny. That is what has happened with distinctions of slaves and freemen, nobles and serfs, patricians and plebeians; and so it will be, and in part already is, with the aristocracies of colour, race, and sex.

From what I have said it appears that ‘justice’ is a name for certain moral requirements which, regarded collectively, stand higher in the scale of social utility—and are therefore more bindingly obligatory—than any others; though particular cases may occur in which some other social duty is important enough to overrule one of the general maxims of justice. Any of those maxims could be overruled in that way. Thus, to save a life it may be not merely •allowable but a •duty to steal or take by force the necessary food or medicine, or to kidnap the only qualified medical practitioner and compel him to serve. We don’t call anything ‘justice’ that isn’t a virtue; so in these cases of overruling we usually say not that •justice must give way to some other moral principle

43

Utilitarianism John Stuart Mill 5: Connecting justice and utility

but rather that what is just in ordinary cases is not just in this particular case because of that other principle, ·the one that does the overruling·. By this useful adjustment of language we enable justice to keep its character as something that can’t be overruled, and we’re spared the necessity of maintaining that injustice can sometimes be praiseworthy.

The considerations that I have brought forward seem to me to resolve the only real difficulty confronting the utilitarian theory of morals. It has always been evident that all cases of •justice are also cases of •expediency: the difference is in the special sentiment that attaches to •the former and not to •the latter. If

•this characteristic sentiment has been sufficiently accounted for; if

•there is no need to credit it with having some special origin all of its own; if

•it is simply the natural feeling of resentment, made moral by being made coextensive with the demands of social good; and if

•this feeling not only does but ought to exist in all the classes of cases to which the idea of justice corresponds;

then the idea of justice no longer presents itself as a stumbling-block to utilitarian ethics. ‘Justice’ remains the appropriate name for certain social utilities. The utilities in question •are vastly more important, and therefore more absolute and imperative, than any others are as a class (though not more so than others may be in particular cases); so they •ought to be (and naturally are) guarded by a sentiment that differs from others not only in degree but also in kind. The sentiment of justice is distinguished from the milder feeling that attaches to the mere idea of promoting human pleasure or convenience by the more definite nature of its commands and by the sterner character of its sanctions.

44

The Subjection of Women

John Stuart Mill

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between brackets in normal-sized type. The phrase ‘the subjection of women’ occurs quite often in this version, because it helps to keep things clear; in Mill’s original it hardly occurs except in the title. The chapter-titles are added in this version. So are the section-breaks and -titles; these are offered not as formal structure but only as rough guides to where new topics are launched.—As a background to this work, you should know: In 1830 at the age of 24 Mill formed an extremely close moral and intellectual friendship with Mrs Harriet Taylor; this continued, with no sexual impropriety, until her husband died in 1851, whereupon she and Mill married. She died seven years later, and the present work was written a few years after that.
First launched: November 2009

Contents

CHAPTER 1: The question can be raised 1

Reason versus ‘instinct’........ 2

Modern changes of attitude............... 5

Slavery and absolute monarchy........ 6

Natural?......... 7

Complaints......... 8

Affection.......... 9

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill

The course of history................. 10

The ‘nature’ of women................ 12

The ‘need’ for compulsion.............. 15

CHAPTER 2: The laws governing marriage 17

Judging by the best instances............ 18

The need for decisions................ 22

Would liberated women be fair?........... 23

The moral education of mankind........... 24

Property rights............ 27

CHAPTER 3: Occupations for women outside marriage 29

Women as governors................. 30

Practice versus theory................ 33

‘Nervous temperament’................ 35

The size and quality of brains............ 38

Different nations, different views.......... 39

Women in the arts and sciences........... 40

Moral differences................... 45

CHAPTER 4: What good would reform do? 47

The moral education of males............. 47

Doubling the brain pool............... 49

The moral influence of women: chivalry................ 50

The moral influence of women: charity.................. 51

The moral influence of wives on husbands............... 53

The moral effects of difference............ 55

The moral effects of inferiority............ 56

Benefits to the individual woman........... 57

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

CHAPTER 1

The question can be raised

The object of this Essay is to explain as clearly as I can the reasons for following proposition:

The principle that regulates the existing social relations between the two sexes—the legal subordination of one sex to the other—is wrong itself, and is now one of the chief obstacles to human improvement; and •it ought to be replaced by a principle of perfect equality that doesn’t allow any power or privilege on one side or disability on the other.

·For convenience I’ll call this ‘the Opinion’·. I have accepted the Opinion from the earliest time when I had any views on social political matters; and instead of being weakened or modified ·through the years· it has grown steadily stronger ·in my mind· through reflection and my experience of life.

The task I am undertaking here will be hard work.... But don’t think that the difficulty must come from the scarcity or obscurity of solid reasons for the Opinion. Rather, the difficulty is one that exists whenever something is being defended against a mass of feeling. Just because the opposing view is strongly rooted in feelings, it is ·psychologically· strengthened rather than weakened by having the weight of argument go against it. If it were accepted as a result of argument, counter-arguments might shake the solidity of the conviction; but when it rests solely on feeling, ·arguments against it don’t shake it at all·: the worse it fares in the clash of arguments, the more convinced its adherents are that their feeling must have some deeper basis that the arguments don’t reach! And while the feeling remains, it keeps erecting fresh walls of argument to repair the gaps that have been made in the old ones. And there are so many factors giving intensity and deep roots to the feelings connected with our present subject—making them more intense and deeper-rooted than the feelings that gather protectively around •other old institutions and customs—that we shouldn’t be surprised to find those feelings to be less undermined and loosened than any of the •others by the progress of the great modern spiritual and social transition; nor should we suppose that the barbarisms to which men cling longest must be less barbaric than the ones they shake off earlier.

Those who attack an almost universal opinion are faced with difficulties all the way. They have to be very lucky and unusually able if they are to get a hearing at all. It is harder for them to obtain a •trial than it is for any other litigants to obtain a •verdict. And if they do get a hearing, it subjects them to a set of logical requirements totally different from the ones imposed on other people. (1) In all other cases, the burden of proof is supposed to lie with the affirmative: if someone is accused of murder, it’s up to his accusers to prove his guilt, not for him to prove his innocence. If there’s a difference of opinion about the reality of an alleged historical event that doesn’t involve strong feelings in anyone—the Siege of Troy, for example—those who say that it did happen are expected to produce their proofs before the other side can be required to say anything; and the most they are ever required to do is to show that the evidence produced by their opponents is of no value. (2) Again, in practical matters [i.e. in moral, social and political matters] the burden of proof is supposed to be with those who are against liberty—those who contend for....•any limitation of the general freedom

1

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

of human action or •anything that denies to one person or kind of person any privilege or advantage that others have. The a priori presumption is in favour of freedom and impartiality. It is held that there should be no restraint except what is required by the general good, and that the law should....treat everyone alike except where dissimilarity of treatment is required by positive reasons of justice or of policy. [To say that there is a ‘presumption’ in favour of a practice is to say that the practice should be regarded as justifiable unless a case is made against its being so; the stronger the presumption, the stronger the counter-case has to be.]

But none of these rules of evidence will be allowed to benefit those who maintain the Opinion that I shall defend. It is useless for me to say:

Those who maintain that men have a right to command and women an obligation obey, or that men are fit for government and women unfit, are on the affirmative side of the question, and are bound to show positive evidence for their position or accept that it has been defeated.

It is equally unavailing for me to say:

Those who deny to women any freedom or privilege that is rightly allowed to men are opposing freedom and recommending partiality, so there is a double presumption against them; and they should be held to the strictest standards of proof, with the judgment going against them unless they argue successfully enough to exclude all doubt.

These would be regarded as good pleas in any ordinary case—but not in this one! Before I could hope to make any impression ·on the other side· I would be expected not only to answer everything ever said by the opposition, but to imagine everything that could be said by them.... And besides refuting all arguments for the affirmative ·anti-liberty pro-discrimination· side, I’ll be called upon for invincible positive arguments to prove a negative. And even if I could leave the opposite party with a host of unanswered arguments against them, and not a single unrefuted argument on their side, this wouldn’t be regarded as much of an achievement; because a cause supported by universal usage and by such a great weight of popular sentiment is supposed to have a presumption in its favour, superior to any conviction that an appeal to reason can produce in intellects other than those of a high class. [In Mill’s day a ‘sentiment’ could be a feeling, or a belief, or a practical attitude. In this version the word will be left unaltered. Decide for yourself what he means by each occurrence of it.]

I am not complaining about these difficulties. It would be useless to do so, because they are inevitable when one has to argue through •people’s understandings against the hostility of •their feelings and practical tendencies. I am up against

practical principles in which people have been born and bred, and which are the basis of much existing order of the world;

I can hardly expect them to

surrender at the first argumentative attack that they aren’t capable of logically resisting.

That would require them to rely on their own power of estimating arguments, and that can’t happen until the understandings of the majority of mankind are much better developed than they ever have been. So I am quarreling with my opponents not for having •too little faith in argument but for having •too much faith in custom and the general feeling.

Reason versus ‘instinct’

The eighteenth century is supposed to have regarded the reasoning elements in human nature as infallible; in reaction

2

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

against that, the nineteenth century attributes infallibility to the unreasoning elements. We have replaced the god-like status of •Reason by a god-like status for •Instinct; and we label as ‘instinct’ anything that we find in ourselves and can’t find any rational foundation for. This idolatry is infinitely more degrading than the other; of all the false worships of the present day, this one is the worst and is the main support of all the others. It probably won’t be dislodged until a sound psychology lays bare the real root of much that people now bow down to as ‘intended by Nature’ and ‘commanded by God’. As regards the present question, I shall accept....that established custom and general feelings should be regarded as conclusive against me, unless this custom and feeling can be shown to have •owed their existence down through the ages to causes other than their soundness, and to have •derived their power from the worse rather than the better parts of human nature. Let the judgment go against me unless I can show that the judge ·in this case· has been tampered with! This is a smaller concession than you might think, because proving this—·i.e. proving that there’s something bad and wrong about the causes of the feelings that oppose me·—is by far the easiest part of my task.

If a practice is very general, this sometimes creates a strong presumption that it is—or at any rate was—conducive to praiseworthy ends. This is the case when the practice was first started (or later kept up) as a means to such ends, and was based on experience of how the ends could be most effectively be achieved. If the following were the case—

•When the authority of men over women was first established, that was the result of conscientiously comparing different ways of structuring the government of society;

•various other types of social organisation were tried—the government of women over men, equality between the two, and other such mixed and divided structures of government; and

•people’s experience of those convinced them that the best arrangement for producing the happiness and well-being of both women and men was the one in which women are wholly under the rule of men, having no share at all in public concerns, and each in private being legally obliged to obey the man with whom she has associated her destiny

—if that were the case (I repeat), that would provide some evidence that when the subjection of women was first adopted it was the best (though even then the social facts that recommended it may have since then ceased to be facts). But the state of the case is in every respect the reverse of this. (1) The opinion in favour of the present system....rests on theory only, for no other system has been tried; so that experience, as contrasted with theory, can’t be claimed to have pronounced any verdict. (2) The adoption of this system of inequality never was the result of deliberation, or forethought, or any social ideas, or any notion whatever of what would be best for humanity or the good order of society. It arose simply from the fact that from the dawn of human society every woman was in a state of bondage to some man, because •she was of value to him and •she had less muscular strength than he did. Laws and political systems always begin by recognising the relations they find already existing between individuals, converting a mere physical fact into a legal right, giving it the sanction of society; their main aim is to replace

the assertion and protection of these rights by irregular and lawless conflict of physical strength

by

the assertion and protection of these same rights by public and organised means.

3

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

In this way, those who had already been compelled to obey became legally bound to obey. Slavery, at first a mere affair of force between the master and the slave, came to be governed by rules, and to be a matter of agreement among the masters: binding themselves to one another for common protection, the masters guaranteed by their collective strength the private possessions of each, including his slaves. In early times, most males were slaves, as well as all females. And many centuries passed—some of them times of high cultivation—before any thinker was bold enough to ask ‘Is it right? Is it absolutely socially necessary?’ about either of these slaveries. Gradually such thinkers did arise; and....at last the slavery of the male sex has been abolished in all the countries of Christian Europe; and....the slavery of the female sex has been gradually changed into a milder form of dependence. But this dependence, as it exists at present, is not an original institution, taking a fresh start from considerations of justice and social expediency—it is the primitive state of slavery lasting on through a series of weakenings brought about by the same causes that have softened all kinds of conduct and brought all human relations more under the control of justice and the influence of humanity. The subjection of women hasn’t lost the taint of its brutal origin. So the mere fact of its existence doesn’t create any presumption in its favour. Anyone who wants there to be a presumption in its favour had better try to get it from the fact that the subjection of women has survived, while many products of the same odious source have been done away with. And that fact is what makes the statement ‘The inequality of rights between men and women has no other source than the law of the strongest’ sound strange to ordinary ears.

That this statement should sound like a paradox is in some respects creditable to the progress of civilisation and the improvement of mankind’s moral sentiments [see note on page 2]. We now live—i.e. one or two of the world’s most advanced nations now live—in a state in which the law of the strongest seems to be entirely abandoned as the regulating principle of the world’s affairs: nobody proclaims it, and in most contexts nobody is permitted to practise it. When anyone succeeds in doing so, he disguises it through the pretence that he has some general social interest on his side. This being the apparent state of things, people flatter themselves that the rule of mere force is ended; that the law of the strongest can’t be the reason for the existence of anything that has remained in full operation down to the present time. They think: ‘However any of our present institutions may have •begun, no institution can have been •preserved into this period of advanced civilisation except by a well-grounded feeling that it fits human nature and is conducive to the general good.’ They don’t understand

•the great vitality and durability of institutions that place right on the side of might;

•how intensely they are clung to;

•how the good as well as the bad propensities and sentiments of those who have power in their hands become identified with retaining it;

•how slowly these bad institutions give way, one at a time, the weakest first. beginning with those that are least interwoven with the daily habits of life; and

•how very rarely those who have obtained legal power because they first had physical power have ever lost their hold of it until the physical power had passed over to the other side.

That shifting of the physical force didn’t happen in the case of women; and this fact, combined with all the special features of this particular case, made it certain from the outset that this branch of the system of right founded on might would be

4

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

the very last to disappear (though its most atrocious features were softened earlier than several of the others).... So it isn’t surprising that the subjection of women, as long as it doesn’t proclaim its own origin and there is no discussion bringing to light its true character, isn’t felt to jar with modern civilisation, any more than domestic slavery among the Greeks jarred with their notion of themselves as a free people.

Modern changes of attitude

The truth is that people of the present and the last two or three generations have lost all practical sense of the primitive condition of humanity. The only ones who can form any mental picture of what society was like in ancient times are the few who have •studied history or have •spent much time in parts of the world occupied by the living representatives of ages long past. People don’t now realize how entirely, in former ages, the •law of superior strength was the •rule of life, and how publicly and openly it was proclaimed. (·Note the adverbs I have chosen·. I don’t say ‘cynically’ or ‘shamelessly’, because those words imply a feeling that there was something in it to be ashamed of, and in those earlier ages only a philosopher or a saint could have room in his mind for any such notion.) History gives a cruel experience of human nature, in showing •that the regard due to the life, possessions, and entire earthly happiness of any category of people was measured precisely by what they had the power of enforcing; and •that all who in any way resisted authorities that had power, however dreadful might be the provocation, were opposed not only by the law of force but also by all other laws and all the notions of social duty; and were regarded by those whom they resisted as being guilty....of the worst of all crimes, deserving the cruellest punishments human beings could inflict. [A tiny change came about when masters found it convenient to make promises to their slaves, Mill says, but such promises were lightly regarded and not very effective. Then:] The ancient republics provided the first examples of a portion of human relations fenced around and governed by something other than the law of force; that is because they were from the outset based on some kind of agreement, or at any rate were created by a union of persons with about the same amount of power. The original •law of force remained in full operation between them and their slaves, and also (except when limited by explicit agreements) between a commonwealth and its subjects or other independent commonwealths; but still •its banishment even from such a narrow domain as that of relations among the powerful started the regeneration of human nature. It did this by giving birth to sentiments of which experience soon demonstrated the immense value, even for material interests, and which from then on only needed to be enlarged, not created. Although slaves were not part of the commonwealth, it was in the free states [Mill’s phrase] that slaves were first felt to have rights as human beings. The Stoics were, I believe, the first—except so far as the Jewish law constitutes an exception—who taught as a part of morality that men had moral obligations to their slaves. After Christianity became ascendant, no-one could ever again have been a stranger to this belief, in theory; and after the rise of the Catholic Church there were always people who stood up for it. Yet enforcing it was the hardest task that Christianity ever had to perform. For more than a thousand years the Church kept up the contest, with hardly any perceptible success. It wasn’t for lack of power over men’s minds. The Church’s power was prodigious. It could make kings and nobles hand over their most valued possessions to enrich the Church. It could make thousands of people....shut themselves up in

5

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

convents to work out their salvation by poverty, fasting, and prayer. It could send hundreds of thousands across land and sea, Europe and Asia, to give their lives for the deliverance of the Holy Sepulchre [this is a reference to the Crusades].... All this it did; but it couldn’t make men fight less with one another, or be less cruel in their tyranny over the serfs and (when they could) over ordinary citizens.... Only by the growing power of kings was an end put to fighting (except between kings or competitors for kingship); only by the growth of a wealthy and warlike bourgeoisie in the fortified towns, and of a peasant infantry that proved more powerful in battle than undisciplined knights on horseback, were some limits set to the insolent tyranny of the nobles over the bourgeoisie and peasantry. •This tyranny was persisted in until long after the oppressed had acquired enough power to be able, often, to get conspicuous revenge; and on the Continent much of •it continued up to the time of the French Revolution, though in England the earlier and better organisation of the democratic classes put an end to it sooner, by establishing equal laws and free national institutions.

Slavery and absolute monarchy

....People mostly don’t remember or bear in mind how institutions and customs that never had any basis but the law of force last on into ages and states of general opinion that would never have permitted them to be established. Less than forty years ago Englishmen could still by law hold human beings in bondage as saleable property; within the present century they could kidnap them and work them literally to death. This absolutely extreme case of the law of force, condemned ·even· by those who can tolerate almost every other form of arbitrary power....was the law of civilised and Christian England within the memory of persons now living; and in one half of Anglo-Saxon America, three or four years ago, not only did slavery exist but the slave-trade and the breeding of slaves expressly for that trade was a general practice between slave states. Yet not only was there more sentiment [see note on page 2] against it but (in England at least) less feeling or interest in favour of it than of any other of the customary abuses of force; because the motive for it was nakedly commercial, those who profited by it were a very small minority, and the natural feeling of all those who weren’t personally getting anything from it was absolute loathing.... Then consider the long duration of absolute monarchy, ·i.e. monarchy with no legal controls or limits on how the monarch can behave or what laws he can pass·. [Mill in his next sentence equates that with ‘military despotism’, presumably on the grounds that no monarch could have absolute powers if he didn’t have control of the country’s army.] In England at present almost everyone sees military despotism as a case of the law of force, having no origin or justification but that. Yet in all the other great nations of Europe it still exists, or ceased to exist only recently; and even now it is favoured by many people, especially but not exclusively by people with high social status and importance. [Mill’s point here, he explains, is that absolute monarchy has proved to be remarkably durable despite two features that might be expected to weaken it:

(1) Plenty of countries don’t have it. And at most times in history there have been spectacularly prosperous and successful countries that were governed in other ways.

(2) The immediate beneficiary of an absolute monarchy is the monarch, that one person; for everyone else this system is ‘naturally and necessarily humiliating’.

In contrast with this, the system of the subjection of women

(1) is universal; there are no vivid examples of prosperous rejections of it; and

6

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

(2) is immediately gratifying to half of the human race, namely the male half: ‘The clodhopper exercises....his share of the power equally with the highest nobleman’.

And it has a third feature that favours its survival over absolute monarchy, namely:

(3) Anyone who is empowered by the subjection of women gets power over the person who is closest to him, and...]

...everyone who desires power desires it most over those who are nearest to him, with whom his life is passed, with whom he has most concerns in common and in whom any independence of his authority is oftenest likely to interfere with his individual preferences.... Also, the possessors of the power provided by the subjection of women are better placed than any absolute monarch to prevent any uprising against the system. Every one of the subjects lives under the very eye....of one of the masters, in closer intimacy with him than with any of her fellow-subjects; with no means of combining against him, no power of even locally overmastering him; and with the strongest motives for seeking his favour and avoiding giving him offence. In struggles for political emancipation, we all know how often its champions are bought off by bribes, or daunted by terrors. In the case of women, each individual of the subject-class is in a permanent state of bribery and intimidation combined.... If ever any system of privilege and enforced subjection had its yoke tightly riveted on the necks of those who are kept down by it, this has. I haven’t yet shown that it is a wrong system: but anyone who can think about this must see that even if it is wrong it was certain to outlast all other forms of unjust authority. And when some of the grossest of the other forms still exist in many civilised countries, and have only recently been got rid of in others, it would be strange if the one that is most deeply rooted had yet been perceptibly shaken anywhere....

Natural?

Some will object that it’s not fair to compare •the government of the male sex with •the other forms of unjust power that I have discussed, because it is natural while the others are arbitrary and brought about by mere usurpation. But was there ever any domination that didn’t appear natural to those who possessed it? There was a time when the division of mankind into a small class of masters and a large class of slaves appeared, even to the most cultivated minds, to be the only natural condition of the human race! Aristotle, with his great intellect and his great contributions to the progress of human thought, held this opinion without doubt or misgiving; and his reason for it was the reason usually given for the dominion of men over women, namely that there are different natures among mankind, free natures and slave natures; that the Greeks were of a free nature, the barbarian races of Thracians and Asiatics of a slave nature. [And, Mill continues, the same was said by the slave-owners of the southern United States.] Again, the theorists of absolute monarchy have always claimed it to be the only natural form of government, descending ultimately from the authority of a father over his family,....which is older and more basic than society itself and, they contend, the most natural authority of all. Indeed the law of force itself has always seemed the most natural of all grounds for the exercise of authority—has seemed so, I mean, to those who haven’t been able to find any other basis ·for their favoured form of tyranny·. Conquering races hold it to be Nature’s own dictate that the feebler and more unwarlike races should submit to the braver and more manly, or, to put it more bluntly, that the conquered

7

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

should obey the conquerors. The smallest acquaintance with human life in the middle ages shows •how supremely natural the dominion of the feudal nobility over men of low condition appeared to the nobility themselves, and •how unnatural the conception seemed, of a person of the inferior class claiming equality with them or exercising authority over them. And it seemed almost as natural to the class held in subjection: the emancipated serfs and citizenry, even in their most vigorous struggles, never claimed a share of authority; they only demanded some limitation to the power of tyrannising over them. So true is it that ‘unnatural’ generally means only ‘uncustomary’, and that whatever is usual appears natural. The subjection of women to men is a universal custom, so any departure from it quite naturally appears unnatural!.... When people in distant parts of the world first learn anything about England, they are astonished to be told that England is under a queen; that seems to them so unnatural as to be almost incredible. To Englishmen it doesn’t seem at all unnatural, because they are used to it; but they do feel it unnatural that women should be soldiers or members of parliament. In the feudal ages, on the other hand, war and politics were not thought unnatural to women, because they were not unusual; it seemed natural that women of the privileged classes should be of manly character, inferior in nothing but bodily strength to their husbands and fathers. The independence of women seemed rather less unnatural to the Greeks than to other peoples in ancient times, because of the mythical Amazons (whom they believed to be historical), and the partial example of the women of Sparta, who, though they were •by law just as subordinate to men as the women in other Greek states, were more free •in fact; they were trained to bodily exercises in the same way as the men, giving ample proof that they were not naturally disqualified for them. There can be little doubt that Spartan experience suggested to Plato, among many other of his doctrines, that of the social and political equality of the two sexes.

Complaints

It will be said that •the rule of men over women differs from all these others in not being a rule a rule of force, •that it is accepted voluntarily, •that women don’t complain, and are consenting parties to it. Well, the first point to make is that a great number of women do not accept it. Ever since there have been women able to make their sentiments known by their writings (the only form of going-public that society permits to them), increasingly many of them have protested against their present social condition; and recently many thousands of them, headed by the most eminent women known to the public, petitioned Parliament to allow them the vote. The claim of women to be educated as well and as broadly as men as men is urged with growing intensity and with a great prospect of success; while the demand for their admission into professions and occupations that have so far been closed to them becomes more urgent every year. [Mill speaks of movements along these lines in the USA and in some European countries. Then:] We can’t possibly know how many more women there are who silently have such hopes, but there are plenty of signs of how many would have them if they weren’t so strenuously taught to repress them as improper for their sex. ·It may have occurred to you that these examples concern only certain parts or aspects of the subjection of women, not the whole thing. Nothing much follows from that, however·. No enslaved class ever asked for complete liberty at once. [The next sentence refers to a 13th-century rebel who during his brief time of power established a parliament that included representatives of the common people.] When Simon de Montfort called the representatives of the common people to

8

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

sit for the first time in Parliament, did any of them dream of demanding that such an assembly....should make and destroy ministries, and dictate to the king in affairs of State? No such thought entered into the imagination of the most ambitious of them. The nobility were already claiming such powers; the common people claimed only to be exempt from arbitrary taxation and from the gross individual oppression of the king’s officers. It is a political law of nature that those who are subjected to any power of very long standing never begin by complaining of the power itself, but only of the oppressive use of it. There’s never any shortage of women who complain of ill-usage by their husbands. There would be infinitely more if complaints weren’t apt to provoke the husbands to repeat and increase the ill-usage. That is what frustrates all attempts to •maintain the power but •protect the woman against its abuses. In no other case (except that of a child) is a person who has been proved judicially to have suffered an injury put back into the physical power of the culprit who inflicted it! That is why wives, even in the most extreme and long-drawn-out cases of bodily ill-usage, hardly ever dare make use of the laws that have been made for their protection; and if a woman is induced to do so—in a moment of irrepressible indignation, or through the interference of neighbours—all she does from there on is to reveal as little as possible and to beg off her tyrant from the punishment he deserves.

Affection

....Women are in a different position from all other subject classes in this: their masters require more from them than actual service. Men want not only the obedience of women but also their sentiments [see note on page 2]. All but the most brutish of men want to have, in the woman most nearly connected with them, not a •forced slave but a •willing one, not a slave merely but a favourite. So they have done everything they could to enslave women’s minds. The masters of all other slaves get obedience through fear, either of themselves or of some religious punishment. The masters of women wanted more than simple obedience, and they turned the whole force of education to get what they wanted. All women are brought up from their earliest years to believe that their ideal of character is the very opposite to that of men: not self-will and government by self-control, but submission and accepting control by someone else. All the moralities tell them that it is their duty, and all the current ideas about feelings tell them that it is their nature, to live for others—to set aside their own wishes and interests and have no life but in their affections. And by ‘their affections’ are meant the only ones they are allowed to have—those to the men with whom they are connected, or to the children who constitute an additional and unbreakable tie between them and a man. When we put together these three things—

(1) the natural attraction between opposite sexes;

(2) the wife’s entire dependence on the husband, with every privilege or pleasure that she has being either his gift or depending entirely on his will;

(3) the fact that it is only through the man that the woman can seek or obtain the principal object of human pursuit, namely consideration, or any objects of social ambition;

—it would be a miracle if the objective of being attractive to men had not become the polar star of feminine education and formation of character. And once men had acquired this great means of influence over the minds of women, an instinct of selfishness made them avail themselves of it to the utmost as a means of keeping women in subjection, by telling them that an essential part of sexual attractiveness

9

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

is meekness, submissiveness, and delivering all individual will into the hands of a man. [Mill goes on to say that if this kind of oppression-through-feelings had been built into other systems of servitude, they would have lasted longer, and would now be regarded as being just as ‘natural’ as the subjection of women, and would be challenged only by ‘a thinker here and there’.]

The course of history

What I have said up to here is quite enough to show that custom, however universal it may be, doesn’t create any presumption....in favour of the arrangements that put women in social and political subjection to men. But I go further, and maintain that the course of history and the tendencies of progressive human society create a strong presumption against this system of inequality of rights; and that if we can infer anything from the whole course of human improvement up to now—the whole stream of modern tendencies—it is that this relic of the past is out of tune with the future and must necessarily disappear.

What is the special character of the modern world—the difference that chiefly distinguishes modern institutions, modern social ideas, modern life itself, from those of times long past? It is that human beings are no longer born to their place in life, and chained down by an unbreakable bond to the place they are born to, but are free to use their talents and any good luck that comes their way to have the kind of life that they find most desirable. Human society was for ages constituted on a very different principle. All were born to a fixed social position, and were mostly kept in it by law or debarred from any means by which they could emerge from it. As some men are born white and others black, so some were born slaves and others freemen and citizens; some were born patricians, others plebeians; some were born feudal nobles, others commoners and serfs. A slave or serf could never make himself free; his only route to freedom was through the will of his master. [Mill continues with this theme: the centuries through which commoners couldn’t become nobles; a noble father couldn’t disinherit his eldest son; a worker couldn’t be a shoemaker or tailor or carpenter or the like unless he was born into the guild controlling that trade or was admitted into the guild by its members; every activity regarded as important had to be conducted according to officially dictated rules; manufacturers were punished for introducing new and improved methods for their business. Then:] In modern Europe, especially in the parts of it that have gone furthest in all other modern improvements, diametrically opposite doctrines now prevail. Law and government don’t prescribe who can and who can’t conduct any social or industrial operation, or what procedures for conducting them shall be lawful. These things are left to the free choice of individuals. Even the laws requiring workmen to serve an apprenticeship have been repealed in England, on the grounds that wherever an apprenticeship is necessary its necessity will force it to happen. The old theory was that as little as possible should be left to the choice of the individual, and that as far as was practicable his conduct should be laid down for him by superior wisdom. Left to himself he was sure to go wrong. The modern conviction, based on a thousand years of experience, is that things that directly involve a person’s interests never go right except when they are left to his own discretion; and that any regulation of them by authority, except to protect the rights of others, is sure to do harm. This conclusion was slowly arrived at, and not adopted until almost every possible application of the contrary theory had been made with disastrous result; but now the part of it that

10

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

concerns work prevails in all the most advanced countries and in most of the others that have any claim to any sort of advancement. The thesis is not:

All processes are equally good, and all persons are equally qualified for every task or trade;

but rather:

Freedom of individual choice is the only thing that leads to the adoption of the best processes, and puts each operation into the hands of those who are best qualified for it.

Nobody thinks it necessary to make a law that only a strong-armed man shall be a blacksmith. Freedom and competition suffice to make blacksmiths strong-armed men, because others can earn more in occupations for which they are more fit. In line with this doctrine, it is felt to be improper to adopt a general presumption that certain ·classes of· persons are not fit to do certain things. Everyone now knows and admits that if some such presumptions do exist, none of them are infallible. Even if a presumption is well grounded in a majority of cases (which it probably isn’t!), there will be a minority of exceptional cases where it doesn’t hold: and in those cases it is unjust to the individuals and harmful to society to put barriers in the way of their using their abilities for the benefit of themselves and others. And in the cases where the unfitness is real, the ordinary motives of human conduct will usually suffice to prevent the incompetent person from making or from persisting in the attempt.

If this general principle of social and economic science is not true—if individuals, perhaps with help from the opinion of those who know them, aren’t better judges of their own capacities and vocation than the government is—then the world should immediately abandon this principle and return to the old system of regulations and disabilities. But if the principle is true, we ought to act as if we believed it. We do accept that someone’s being

born black instead of white, or

born a commoner instead of a nobleman,

shouldn’t fix his position throughout life, barring him from all the more elevated social positions and from nearly all respectable occupations. Well, we should accept the same thing regarding someone’s being

born a girl instead of a boy.

Let us apply this to the legal requirement that a Member of Parliament must be a man. Even if we accept the strongest claims that are ever made about the superior fitness of men for this role, the legal requirement is still wrong. If it happens only once in a dozen years that this law excludes a woman who is fit to be an M.P., that exclusion is a real loss ·to society·, whereas the exclusion of thousands of unfit persons is no gain. If the electors are disposed to choose unfit persons as M.P.s, there are always plenty of those to choose from! For any difficult and important job, there is always a need for more people who could do it well than are actually available, even with the most unrestricted field of choice: and any limitation of the field of selection deprives society of some chances of being served by the competent, without ever saving it from the incompetent.

At present, in the more improved countries, the disabilities of women are the only case but one in which laws and institutions take persons at their birth and ordain that they shall never in all their lives be allowed to compete for certain things. The one exception is that of royalty. [Mill says that the status of royalty, as something one has to be born into, is felt by everyone to be an exception; the case for it appeals to customs and traditions, which are given different weights in different countries; and he emphasizes that in the modern

11

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

world monarchs don’t really do anything significant: what is ostensibly the work of the monarch is done by the prime minister, who isn’t qualified for his role by birth, though he would have been disqualified for it if he were female. Mill sums up:] So the disabilities to which women are subject from the mere fact of their birth are the only examples of the kind in modern legislation. In no instance except this, which takes in half the human race, are the higher social functions closed against anyone by the sheer fact of birth which no exertions, and no change of circumstances, can overcome.... [Mill uses the phrase ‘the higher social functions’ to refer to political office (e.g. being a Member of Parliament), high positions in the civil service, and so on. The word ‘function’ occurs very often in chapter 3, and will be left unaltered there.]

The social subordination of women thus stands out as an isolated fact in modern social institutions—a solitary infringement of what has become their fundamental law, a single relic of an old world of thought and practice.... This entire discrepancy between one social fact and all the others that accompany it, and the radical opposition between its nature and the progressive movement that is the boast of the modern world...., provides something to be thought about seriously by any conscientious observer of human tendencies. It raises a prima facie presumption on the unfavourable side, far outweighing any presumption that custom and usage could create on the favourable side. It should be enough, at least, make this an issue with two sides to it—like the issue between republicanism and royalty.

[Mill goes on to demand a real and fair discussion of the issue over the subjection of women. He warns against invalid appeals to experience. ‘Experience can’t possibly have decided between two courses of action when there has been experience of only one.’ But experience can tell us something relevant:] Experience does say that every step in ·social· improvement has been accompanied by a step made in raising the social position of women; and this has happened so invariably that historians and philosophers have been led to measure •the civilisation of a people or an age by •the status that it give to women.... This does not of itself prove that the assimilation must go on to complete equality; but it surely creates some presumption that such is the case.

The ‘nature’ of women

And it’s no use saying that the nature of the two sexes fits them for their present functions and positions.... Standing on the ground of common sense and the constitution of the human mind, I deny that anyone can know the nature of the two sexes, as long as they have only been seen in their present relation to one another.... What is now called ‘the nature of women’ is an artificial thing—the result of forced repression in some directions, unnatural stimulation in others.... A hot-house and stove cultivation has always been provided for some of women’s capabilities, for the benefit and pleasure of their masters. These sprout luxuriantly in this heated atmosphere and with active cultivation and watering; while other shoots from the same root, left outside in the wintry air with ice purposely heaped all around them, have a stunted growth, and some are burnt off with fire and disappear; and men—with that inability to recognise their own work that distinguishes the unanalytic mind—lazily believe that the tree grows •of itself in the way •they have made it grow, and that it would die if one half of it weren’t kept in a vapour bath and the other half in the snow.

What is now the biggest obstacle to the progress of thought and the forming of well-grounded opinions about life and social arrangements is mankind’s unspeakable

12

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

inattention to the influences that form human character....

•Because a peasant deeply in arrears to his landlord is not industrious, some people think that the Irish are naturally idle.

•Because constitutions can be overthrown when the authorities appointed to serve them turn their arms against them, some people think the French incapable of free government.

•Because the Greeks •cheated the Turks whereas the Turks only •plundered the Greeks, some people think that the Turks are naturally more sincere.

•Because women (they say) don’t care about politics excerpt for an interest in politicians, the general good is thought to be naturally less interesting to them than to men.

History, which is now so much better understood than it used to be, teaches another lesson, if only by showing how enormously open human nature is to external influences, and how variable are human characteristics that are supposed to be most universal and uniform. But in history, as in travelling, men usually see only what they already had in their own minds....

What are the natural differences between the two sexes? In the present state of society we can’t get a complete and correct answer to this; yet almost everybody dogmatises about it, hardly anyone attends seriously to the only source for even a partial answer. The source I’m referring to is an analytic study of the most important topic in psychology, namely the laws governing the influence of circumstances on character. ·Why the emphasis on laws?· Because however great and apparently ineradicable the moral and intellectual differences between men and women might be, the only evidence we can have for there being natural differences is negative: inferring that a given difference •is natural from evidence that it •can’t possibly be artificial. Natural differences will be what is left behind after setting aside every characteristic of either sex that can be explained through external circumstances. To be entitled to affirm that there is any difference between the two sexes considered as moral and rational beings—let alone to say what the difference is—one must have the profoundest knowledge of the laws of the formation of character; and since no-one yet has that knowledge no-one is yet entitled to any positive opinion about this topic. Regarding the lack of that knowledge: there is hardly any subject which, in proportion to its importance, has been so little studied!....

Indeed we have only rough and incomplete knowledge of what the differences between the sexes now are, never mind how they came to be that way. Medical practitioners and physiologists have discovered some of the differences in bodily constitution....but they have no special qualifications for learning about the mental characteristics of women. That is a subject on which nothing final can be known, so long as the only people who can really know it—women themselves—have little to say about it and the little that they do say is mostly suborned, ·by which I mean that women are usually under pressure not to tell the truth about their own mental abilities·. It is easy to know stupid women: stupidity is much the same all the world over; a stupid person’s notions and feelings will be simply the ones that are prevalent in the social circles he or she moves in. It’s a different story with people whose opinions and feelings come from their own individual nature and faculties. It’s a rare man who has any significant knowledge of the character even of the women of his own family. I don’t mean knowledge of •their capabilities (nobody knows what those are, not even women themselves, because most of their abilities have never been called upon); I’m talking about •their actual

13

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

thoughts and feelings. Many a man thinks he perfectly understands women because he has had romantic relations with several of them, perhaps with many of them. If he is a good observer and his experience has been of the right kind, he may have learned something about one narrow part of women’s nature—an important part, no doubt, but then there is all the rest.... In general a man’s best chance of studying the character of a woman is by attending to his own wife....and this is in fact the source from which any knowledge worth having on the subject has generally come. But most men have had the opportunity of studying only one woman in this way, so that usually one can infer what a man’s wife is like from his opinions about women in general! To make even this one case yield any result, it has to be the case that

•the woman is worth knowing,

•the man is a competent judge, and

•the man can....read her mind by sympathetic intuition or has nothing in his character that makes her shy of disclosing it.

This, I believe, is an extremely rare conjunction. It often happens that a husband and wife have complete unity of feeling and community of interests with respect to all external things, yet neither has any more admission into the internal life of the other than if they were mere acquaintances. Even when there is true affection, authority on the one side and subordination on the other prevent perfect confidence. Though nothing may be intentionally withheld, much is not shown. [Mill likens this to relations between a father and a son: even when there is real affection on both sides, there’s a lot about a son’s character that his father doesn’t know. Mill takes this to illustrate the general thesis that] for two people to know one another thoroughly, they need to be not only intimates but equals. How much more true this must be when one of the two is not only under the other’s authority but has had it drummed into her that it’s her duty to subordinate everything to his comfort and pleasure, and to speak and act only in ways that are agreeable to him! These are obstacles to a man’s getting thorough knowledge of the only woman he has sufficient opportunity of studying. Add to this the fact that to understand one woman is not necessarily to understand any other woman; that even if a man studies many women of one social level or of one country, that won’t enable him to understand women at other levels or in other countries; and even if he did that, those are still only the women of a single period of history. It is safe to say that the knowledge men can acquire of women, even as they have been and are—never mind what they could be—is wretchedly incomplete and superficial, and that it always will be so until women themselves have told all that they have to tell.

And this time has not come, and if it does come it will do so gradually. Only very recently have women been qualified by literary accomplishments and permitted by society to tell the general public anything. And very few of those have dared to tell anything that men, on whom their literary success depends, are unwilling to hear. If you remember how even a male author’s expression of uncustomary opinions or what were regarded as eccentric feelings used to be (and sometimes still is) received, you’ll get some faint conception of how hard it is for a woman, having been brought up to think custom and opinion her sovereign rule, to express in books anything drawn from the depths of her own nature. The greatest woman who has left writings behind her sufficient to give her an eminent rank in the literature of her country thought it necessary to prefix this motto to her boldest work Un homme peut braver l’opinion; une femme doit s’y soumettre—·A man can openly defy public opinion; a woman

14

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

has to submit to it·.^1 Most of what women write about women is mere sycophancy to men. In the case of unmarried women, much of it seems only intended to increase their chance of getting a husband.... Literary women are becoming more free-spoken, and more willing to express their real sentiments. Unfortunately, in this country especially, they are themselves such artificial products that their sentiments are made up of a small dose of individual observation and consciousness and a very large one of acquired associations. This will be less and less the case, but it will remain true to a great extent as long as social institutions don’t allow to women the same free development of originality that is possible for men. When that time comes, and not before, we shall see, and not merely hear, as much as it is necessary to know of the nature of women, and the adaptation of other things to it. [That last sentence is exactly as Mill wrote it. You might care to think about what he was getting at when he wrote ‘...see, and not merely hear...’.]

I have dwelt so much on the present obstacles to men’s knowing the true nature of women because in this as in so many other things opinio copiae inter maximas causas inopiae est, ·i.e. one of the great causes of ignorance is believing that one knows a lot·; and there’s not much chance of reasonable thinking on this topic while people flatter themselves that they perfectly understand a subject of which most men know absolutely nothing. Among other things, it is at present impossible for any man, or all men taken together, to have knowledge that would qualify them to dictate to women what is their vocation and what isn’t. Fortunately, no such knowledge is required for any practical purpose connected with women’s relation to society and to life, because....that question rests with women themselves—to be decided by their experience and the use of their faculties....

One thing we can be certain of—that if something is contrary to women’s nature you won’t get them to do it by giving their nature free play! There is no reason whatsoever for mankind to interfere on nature’s behalf for fear that nature won’t succeed in carrying out its purpose.... If there’s something they can do but not as well as the men who are their competitors, competition will exclude them from it; because what is being asked for is not protective duties and tariffs in favour of women, but only that the present tariffs and protective duties in favour of men should be recalled. If women have a greater natural inclination for x than for y, there’s no need for laws or social indoctrination to make most of them do x in preference to y. Whatever women’s services are most wanted for, the free play of competition will hold out the strongest inducements to them to undertake....

The ‘need’ for compulsion

The general opinion of men is supposed to be that a woman’s natural vocation is that of a wife and mother. I say ‘is supposed to be’ because judging from the present constitution of society one might think that their opinion was the exact opposite. Perhaps this is what they think:

The natural vocation of women is of all things the most in conflict with their nature: if....any other job or pastime is open to them that has any chance of appearing desirable to them, there won’t be enough of them who will be willing ·to be wives and mothers·, i.e. to accept the condition that is said to be natural to them.

If this really is what men in general believe, they should say so out loud. I would like to hear somebody openly expressing

^1 From the title-page of Delphine, a novel by Madame de Staël, ·a French romantic writer who died in 1817·.

15

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 1: The question can be raised

the doctrine (it is already implied in much that is written on the subject):

‘Society needs women to marry and produce children. They won’t do so unless they are compelled. Therefore it is necessary to compel them.’

The merits of the case would then be clearly defined. It would be exactly the same as the case of the slave-holders of South Carolina and Louisiana:

‘It is necessary that cotton and sugar should be grown. White men cannot produce them. Negroes will not, for any wages that we choose to give. Therefore, they must be compelled.’

An example closer to home is that of impressment:

‘Sailors absolutely must be had to defend the country. It often happens that they won’t voluntarily enlist. Therefore there must be the power of forcing them.’

[That is how the British navy used to acquire sailors: official ‘press gangs’ would kidnap men and force them into the service of the navy. The laws permitting this were still on the books in Mill’s time, though the practice had died out.] How often has this logic been used! and it would have been successful up to this day if it didn’t have one flaw, namely being open to the response:

‘First pay the sailors the honest value of their labour. When you have made it as well worth their while to serve you as to work for other employers, you’ll have no more difficulty than anyone else in obtaining their services.’

The only logical answer to this is ‘I will not’; and impressment is no longer defended, because people now don’t want to rob the labourer of his wages—don’t want to, and are ashamed to. Those who try to force women into marriage by closing all other doors against them are open to a similar response. If they mean what they say, they must believe that men don’t make the married condition attractive enough to women to induce them to accept it for its own sake.... And here, I believe, is the clue to the feelings of men who really dislike the idea of equal freedom for women: the outcome they are afraid of isn’t women •being unwilling to marry (I don’t think anyone really has that fear), but women •insisting that marriage be on equal conditions. They are afraid that all women of spirit and capacity might prefer •doing almost anything else that they don’t regard as degrading to •marrying, when by marrying they’ll be providing themselves with a master—of themselves and of all their earthly possessions. And indeed if marriage had to be like that, their fears would be very well founded. I agree with them that few women who are capable of anything else would, voluntarily and knowing what they were doing, choose such a fate as that kind of marriage if they had any other way of filling a conventionally honourable place in life. If men are determined to have a despotic law of marriage, they are quite right—as a matter of mere policy—to leave women no choice about it. But in that case, everything that has been done in the modern world to loosen the chain on the minds of women has been a mistake. They never should have been allowed to become literate: women who read, and even more women who write, are as things now stand a contradiction and a disturbing element: and it was wrong to bring women up with any skills except those of a sex-slave or of a domestic servant.

16

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

CHAPTER 2

The laws governing marriage

Let us consider....the conditions that the laws of this and all other countries annex to the marriage contract. Given that marriage is •the destination assigned to women by society, •the prospect they are brought up to, and •the objective they are intended to pursue (except for those who aren’t attractive enough to be chosen by any man as his companion), one might have expected that everything possible would have been done to make this condition one that they would like enough to have no cause for regret that they were denied the option of any other. Society has moved to a fairer approach in some of the relevant matters—·e.g. slavery and service in the navy·—but in this one matter of marriage laws society has persisted right up to today in getting what it wants by foul means rather than fair. ·The means used today are not as bad as they used to be·. Originally women were taken by force, or regularly sold by their father to the husband. Until fairly recently the father could dispose of his daughter in marriage at his own will and pleasure, without any regard to hers. The Church was faithful to a better morality in that it required a formal ‘yes’ from the woman at the marriage ceremony; but there was nothing to show that the consent was freely given, and it was practically impossible for the girl to refuse if the father persisted, except perhaps when she could get the protection of religion by becoming a nun. [Before Christianity, Mill says, a husband had the power of life and death over his wife; and for many years in England things weren’t much better. For example. a woman who killed her husband was guilty of ‘treason’ and was burned to death. Then:] Because these atrocities have fallen into disuse (for most of them were formally abolished, if at all, only after they had long ceased to be practised), men suppose that all is now as it should be in regard to the marriage contract; and we are continually told that civilisation and Christianity have restored to the woman her just rights. And yet the wife is the actual bond servant of her husband: so far as the law is concerned, she is as subordinate to him as slaves, commonly so called, are to their masters. She promises life-long obedience to him at the altar, and is legally held to that all through her life.... She can do no act whatever without his at least tacit permission. She can acquire no property for herself: the instant something becomes hers, even if by inheritance, it automatically becomes his. In this respect the wife’s position under the common law of England is worse than that of slaves in the laws of many countries. [Mill gives examples. He goes on to report the legal devices whereby fathers in ‘the higher classes in this country’ try to protect their daughters’ property from their husbands, and comments on how little protection can be achieved even by ‘the most powerful nobleman’. Then:] The two are called ‘one person in law,’ for the purpose of inferring that whatever is hers is his, but the parallel inference is never drawn that whatever is his is hers; the maxim is not applied against the man, except to make him responsible to third parties for her acts, as a master is for the acts of his slaves or of his cattle. I’m not claiming that wives are in general no better treated than slaves; but no slave is a slave to the same extent and in a full a sense of the word as a wife is. Hardly any slave....is a slave at all hours and all minutes; in general he has his fixed task, and when it is done he disposes up to a point of his own time and has

17

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

a family life into which the master rarely intrudes. ‘Uncle Tom’ under his first master had his own life in his ‘cabin’, almost as much as any man whose work takes him away from home is able to have in his own family. But it can’t be so with the wife. Above all, in Christian countries a female slave has an admitted right—and is thought to have a moral obligation—to refuse to her master the last familiarity [Mill’s phrase, referring to sexual intercourse]. Not so the wife: however brutal a tyrant her husbandslave is—even if she knows that he hates her, and/or it is his daily pleasure to torture her, and/or she finds it impossible not to loathe him—he can claim from her and ·legally· enforce the lowest degradation of a human being, that of being made the instrument of an animal function contrary to her inclinations.... What is her position in regard to the children in whom she and her master have a joint interest? They are by law his children. He alone has any legal rights over them. She can’t do anything for them or in relation to them except what he has instructed or allowed her to do. Even after he is dead she isn’t their legal guardian, unless his will has made her so.... This is her legal condition, and she has no means of getting out of it. If she leaves her husband, she can’t take anything with her—not her children or anything that is rightfully her own. The husband can if he chooses compel her to return, by law or by physical force; or he may settle for merely seizing for his own use anything that she may earn or be given by her relatives. It is only legal separation ordered by a court of justice that •entitles her to live apart, without being forced back into the custody of an angry jailer, and •enables her to spend her earnings in her own way, without fear that a man whom perhaps she hasn’t seen for twenty years will pounce on her some day and carry all off. [Such legal separation, Mill says, was until recently too expensive for most people; and it is still granted only in cases of desertion or of extreme cruelty.] And yet people complain that legal separation is granted too easily! Surely, if a woman is denied any prospect for her life except that of being the personal body-servant of a despot, and must stake everything on the chance of finding one who will make a •favourite of her instead of merely a •drudge, to allow her to try this chance only once is a very cruel worsening of her fate. The natural upshot of the state of affairs I have described things would be that since everything in the woman’s life depends on her obtaining a good master, she should be allowed to change again and again until she finds one. I’m not saying that she ought to be allowed this privilege. That is a totally different consideration: my present purposes don’t require me to get into the question of ‘divorce’ in the sense in which this involves liberty of remarriage. All I’m saying here is that to those to whom nothing but servitude is allowed, the only lightening of the burden (and a most insufficient one at that) is to allow a free choice of servitude. Refusing this completes the assimilation of the wife to the slave—and not even the slave under the mildest form of slavery, for in some slave codes the slave could, under certain circumstances of ill usage, legally compel the master to sell him. But no amount of ill usage, without adultery thrown into the mix, will in England free a wife from her tormentor.

Judging by the best instances

I don’t want to exaggerate—and I don’t need to! I have been describing the wife’s legal position, not her actual treatment. The laws of most countries are far worse than the people who carry them out, and many of them couldn’t remain laws if they were often enforced. If married life were just what might be expected from looking at the laws governing it, society would be a hell on earth. Fortunately, there

18

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

are feelings and interests that in many men •exclude (and in most of the others at least •mitigate) the impulses and propensities that lead to tyranny. In a normal state of things, the tie that connects a man with his wife provides by far the strongest example of such feelings. The only thing that comes anywhere near it is the tie between a man and his children, and this nearly always tends to strengthen the other tie. Because this is true—because men in general don’t inflict (and women don’t suffer) all the misery that could be inflicted (and suffered) if men used the full power of tyranny that the laws allow them—the defenders of the existing form of the institution ·of marriage· think that all its wickedness is justified, and that those who complain are merely quarrelling with the evil that is the price paid for every great good. But the loosenings in •practice—which are compatible with maintaining in full •legal force the marriage tyranny—don’t serve as any kind of excuse for this despotism (and all of this goes for any kind of tyranny). The loosenings only serve to show human nature’s power to react against the vilest institutions, and to show how energetically the seeds of good as well as those of evil in human character spread and propagate themselves. Not a word can be said for despotism in the family that can’t be said for political despotism. Not every absolute king sits at his window to enjoy the groans of his tortured subjects, or strips them of their last rag and turns them out to shiver in the road. The despotism of Louis XVI was not as bad as those of some others [Mill cites three, including Caligula], but it was bad enough to justify the French Revolution and to palliate [= ‘somewhat excuse’] even its horrors. What about the intense attachments that ·sometimes· exist between wives and their husbands? They have also existed ·sometimes· in domestic slavery. It wasn’t unusual in Greece and Rome for slaves to submit to death by torture rather than betray their masters.... In fact these intense individual feelings rise to their greatest height under the most atrocious institutions. It’s part of the irony of life that human beings have their strongest feelings of devoted gratitude towards those who voluntarily refrain from using their power entirely to crush their earthly existence! How big a place does this sentiment have in the minds of most men, even in their religious devotion? That is a cruel question, ·and I shan’t answer it here; but· we daily see how much people’s gratitude to God appears to be stimulated by the thought of fellow-creatures to whom he has been less merciful.

When we are thinking about slavery, or political absolutism, or the absolutism of the head of a family, we are always expected to judge it by its best instances; and we are shown pictures of loving exercise of authority on one side, loving submission to it on the other—superior wisdom ordering all things for the greatest good of the dependents, and surrounded by their smiles and benedictions. All this is simply irrelevant.... Who doubts that there may be great goodness, happiness, and affection under the absolute government of a good man? But laws and institutions should be adapted not to good men but to bad. Marriage is not an institution designed for a select few. Men are not required, as a preliminary to the marriage ceremony, to prove by testimonials that they are fit to be trusted with the exercise of absolute power. The tie of affection and obligation to a wife and children is very strong in men whose general social feelings are strong, and in many who don’t have much sense of any other social ties. But a man’s social feelings can come anywhere on a long scale of degrees of intensity, right down to the level of men who aren’t bound by any ties and on whom society has no grip except through the threat of legal punishment. At every level on this descending scale there are men who are given all the legal powers of a husband.

19

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

The vilest malefactor has tied to him some wretched woman against whom he can commit any atrocity except killing her—and with a little care he can do even that without much danger of the legal penalty. Among the lowest classes in every country, there are thousands of men who fit this description:

He is not in a legal sense a malefactor in any other way, because everywhere except in his marriage his aggressions meet with resistance. So the physical violence that is habitual in him is exercised on his unhappy wife, who is the only adult person who can’t block his brutality or escape from it. Her dependence on him doesn’t fill him with a generous forbearance, making it a point of honour to behave well to one whose life situation is entrusted entirely to his kindness; rather, it gives him the notion that the law has handed her over to him as his, to be used at his pleasure, and that he isn’t expected to practise the consideration towards her that is required from him towards everybody else.

Until recently the law left even these atrocious extremes of domestic oppression practically unpunished; within the past few years it has made some feeble attempts to repress them. But these attempts haven’t achieved much, and can’t be expected to do so, because it is contrary to reason and experience to suppose that there can be any real barrier to brutality when the victim is left still in the power of the executioner. Until a conviction for personal violence (or at least for a second offence) automatically entitles the woman to a divorce or at least to a judicial separation, the use of legal penalties to repress these ‘aggravated assaults’ will fail for lack of a prosecutor or for lack of a witness.

When we consider how many men are little higher than brutes, and that this never prevents them from being able through the marriage law to obtain a victim, the breadth and depth of human misery caused in this way swells to something appalling. Yet these are only the extreme cases, the lowest abysses; on the way down the scale to them, there is a sad succession of depth after depth ·with misery increasing all the way·. When we are considering domestic or political tyranny, the main point of attending to absolute monsters is to bring out the fact that there is scarcely any horror that can’t occur under this tyranny if the despot pleases, which sets in a strong light what must be the terrible frequency of things that are only a little less atrocious. Absolute fiends are as rare as angels, perhaps rarer; but •ferocious savages with occasional touches of humanity are common; and in the wide interval that separates •these from any worthy representatives of the human species, there is room for many forms and degrees of animality and selfishness. People whose nature lies in that interval often exist under an outward varnish of civilisation and even of culture, living at peace with the law and maintaining a creditable appearance to all who are not under their power, and yet make the lives of all who are under their power a torment and a burden. [Mill reminds us of the commonplace cliché about men in general being unfit for power, and remarks that it is seldom thought of in connection with the power that is given to every man, however base and ferocious. He repeats the point that a man’s conduct outside his home is not a basis for predicting how he treats his wife:] Even the commonest men reserve the violent, the sulky, the undisguisedly selfish side of their character for those who have no power to withstand it. And their ability to do this doesn’t just provide an outlet for violence, selfishness etc.; it is also the hothouse in which these vices grow and flourish. A man who is morose or violent to his equals is sure to be one who has lived among inferiors—·meaning people who have less power·—whom he could frighten or worry into submission.... We know that the bad tendencies in human nature are kept within bounds

20

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

only when they are allowed no scope for their indulgence. We know that almost everyone to whom others yield goes on encroaching on them until a point is reached at which they are compelled to resist; when this encroachment doesn’t come from deliberate purpose, it comes from impulse and habit. Because this is the common tendency of human nature, the almost unlimited power that present social institutions give to a man over his wife....seeks out and encourages the latent seeds of selfishness in the remotest corners of his nature,....giving him freedom to indulge the parts of his basic character that in all other relations he would have found it necessary to repress and conceal, and the repression of which would in time have become a second nature. I know that there’s another side to the question: if the wife can’t effectively •resist, she can at least •retaliate; she can make the man’s life extremely uncomfortable, and that power of hers enables her to prevail in many matters where she ought to prevail, and many where she ought not. But this instrument of self-protection—which may be called the power of the scold....—has a fatal defect: it is most effective against the least tyrannical superiors and in favour of the least deserving dependents. It is the weapon of irritable and self-willed women, ones who would make the worst use of power if they themselves had it, and who generally turn this power—·the power of the scold·—to a bad use.... And on the other hand, the husbands against whom it is used most effectively are the gentler and more inoffensive, the ones who even when provoked can’t bring themselves to resort to any very harsh exercise of authority. The wife’s power to be disagreeable usually serves only to establish a counter-tyranny, its victims being chiefly the husbands who are least inclined to be tyrants.

Well, then, what is it that in fact tones down the corrupting effects of the ·husband’s· power so as to allow for the amount of good that we actually see ·in many marriages·? Mere feminine blandishments [= (roughly) ‘flirtatious flattery’], though very effective in •individual instances, don’t do much to modify the •general tendencies of the situation; because their power lasts only for as long as the woman is young and attractive, often only while her charm is new and not dimmed by familiarity; and on many men they haven’t much influence at any time. The real mitigating causes are ·four in number·: (1) the husband’s affection for his wife that grows up in the course of time, to the extent that he is capable of it and her character is sufficiently like his to arouse it; (2) their common interests as regards the children....; (3) the wife’s real importance to the husband’s daily comforts and enjoyments, and the value he consequently attaches to her on his account, which (if he is capable of feeling for others) prepares the way for him to care about her on her account; (4) the influence that most human beings naturally acquire over others who are personally near to them and whom they don’t outright dislike. Such influence can be exercised through direct entreaties, and through the imperceptible contagion [see note on page 51] of the woman’s feelings and dispositions. These factors and devices, unless counteracted by some equally strong personal influence ·going in the other direction·, can enable a woman to get an altogether excessive and unreasonable degree of command over the conduct of her husband, her superior.

Through these various means the wife frequently exercises power (sometimes even too much power) over the husband; she can affect his conduct in matters where she may not be qualified to influence it for good....and where he would act better if left to his own devices. (But in families, as in states, •power is not a compensation for •the loss of freedom. Her power often gives her what she has no right to, but doesn’t enable her to assert her own rights. A Sultan’s

21

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

favourite slave has slaves under her,....but the desirable thing would be that she should neither have slaves nor be a slave.) By •entirely sinking her own existence in her husband, by •having no will (or persuading him that she has no will) but his in anything concerning their relationship, and by •making it the business of her life to work on his sentiments [see note on page 2], a wife can influence and probably pervert her husband’s conduct in matters outside the family that she has never qualified herself to judge of, or in which she is influenced by some personal or other bias or prejudice. Accordingly, as things now are, the husbands who act most kindly to their wives are as likely to be made worse as to be made better by the wife’s influence in all matters extending beyond the family. She is taught that she has no business with such matters, and accordingly she seldom has any honest and conscientious opinion on them; so she hardly ever gets involved in them for any legitimate purpose, but generally for a ·self-·interested one. She doesn’t know or care which is the right side in politics, but she knows what will bring in money or invitations, give her husband a title, her son a government job, or her daughter a good marriage.

The need for decisions

You might want to say this:

‘How can any society exist without government? In a family as in a state some one person must be the ultimate ruler. When married people differ in opinion, who is to decide? They can’t both have their way, but a decision one way or the other must be reached.’

[This is one of the few places in this work where Mill uses ‘society’ in such a way that a married couple constitute a society.] It is not true that in any voluntary association between two people one of them must be absolute master; still less that the law must determine which of them it shall be. The commonest kind of voluntary association other than marriage is partnership in business; and no need has been found for a law dictating that in every partnership one partner shall have entire control over the concern and the others will have to obey his orders. No-one would enter into partnership on terms that would subject him to the responsibilities of an executive while giving him only the powers and privileges of a clerk or salesman.... The law never does anything like this in regard to business partnerships; but if it did, this wouldn’t pose as much danger to the rights and interests of the inferior as is posed by law governing marriage. A junior business partner would still be free to cancel the power—·i.e. the absolute power that the senior partner has over him·—by withdrawing from the partnership. A wife has no such power; and even if she had, it would almost always be desirable that she should avail herself of it only as a last resort.

It’s quite true that things that have to be decided right away, and can’t adjust themselves gradually or wait for a compromise, ought to be decided by just one person. But it doesn’t follow that this should always be the same person. The natural arrangement is a division of powers between the two, with each being absolute in the executive branch of their own department, and any change of system and principle requiring the consent of both. [That sentence is as Mill wrote it.] The division ·of powers· can’t and shouldn’t be pre-established by the law, because it must depend on individual capacities and suitabilities. If the two persons chose, they might pre-appoint ·the division of powers· in the marriage contract, as financial arrangements are now often pre-appointed. There would seldom be any difficulty in deciding such things by mutual consent, unless the marriage was one of those unhappy ones where everything, including this, becomes a subject of bickering and dispute. The

22

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

division of rights would naturally follow the division of duties and functions....

[When in this next paragraph Mill speaks of what ‘will’ be the case, he evidently means what will be the case after the law governing marriage is amended in the way he is arguing for.] Whoever gets the legal authority, the actual making of decisions will largely depend—as it does now—on comparative qualifications. The husband is usually the older, and that fact alone will in most cases give him more of the decision-making power, at least until the couple have reached a time of life when the difference in their ages doesn’t matter. A more powerful voice will naturally also be given to the spouse, whether husband or wife, who brings in the income that the family live on. Inequality from this source doesn’t depend on the law of marriage, but on the general conditions of human society as now constituted. The influence of mental superiority, either general or special, is bound to carry much weight, as will superior decisiveness of character; just as they always do at present. And this fact shows how little reason there is to fear that the powers and responsibilities of partners in life (as of partners in business) can’t be satisfactorily divided up by agreement between themselves. They always are divided up like that, except in cases in which the marriage institution is a failure. Decision-making never comes down to •all the power on one side and •sheer obedience on the other, except where the marriage has been a total mistake and it would be a blessing to both parties to be relieved from it. You may think this: ‘What makes a peaceful settlement of differences possible is the power of legal compulsion that both sides know to be in reserve; just as people submit to arbitration because in the background there’s a court of law that they know they can be forced to obey.’ [What makes this work in matters other than marriage, Mill goes on to say, is its not being known in advance which side would win if the dispute were put in the hands of the law; but that isn’t the case in marriages, where the law always favours the husband. The power the law gives him may incline the wife to settle for a compromise, but it won’t incline the husband to do so! He continues:] There is always among decent people a practical compromise, though one of them is under no physical or moral necessity of making it; and this fact shows that (except in unfavourable cases) marriage partners are led by natural motives to voluntarily adjust their behaviour in ways that are acceptable to both. This situation is certainly not improved by having laws which ordain that this superstructure of free government is to be built on a legal foundation of despotism on one side and subjection on the other, so that the despot can—on a whim, and without warning—rescind any concession he has made. No freedom is worth much when held on such a precarious tenure; and anyway it is not likely to work in a fair way when the law throws so much weight into one scale....

Would liberated women be fair?

A stubborn opponent with his back to the wall may say this:

Husbands indeed are willing to be reasonable, and to make fair concessions to their partners without being forced to; but wives are not. If wives are allowed any rights of their own, they won’t acknowledge rights for anyone else, and they’ll never give way on anything unless they are compelled by the man’s mere authority to give way on everything.

Many people would have said this some generations ago, when satires on women were fashionable and men thought it clever to insult women for being what men made them. But it won’t be said now by anyone who is worth replying to. The currently fashionable doctrine is not that women are less

23

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

apt than men are to have good feelings and consideration for their spouses. On the contrary, we are perpetually told that women are better than men, this being said by people who are totally opposed to treating them as if they were as good; so that the saying ·about women’s natural goodness· has become a piece of tiresome cant, intended to put a complimentary face on an injury.... If women really are better than men in anything, it surely is in self-sacrifice on behalf of their family. But I don’t want to stress this at a time when they are universally taught that they are born and created for self-sacrifice. I believe that equality of rights would lessen the exaggerated self-denial that is the present artificial ideal of feminine character, and that a good woman would not be more self-sacrificing than the best man: whereas men would be much more unselfish and self-sacrificing than they are at present because they would no longer be taught to worship their own will as such a grand thing that it is actually the law for another human being. There is nothing that men so easily learn as this self-worship: all privileged persons, and all privileged classes, have had it. The more we descend in the ·social· scale, the more intense it is; and its greatest intensity is in those who aren’t, and can’t expect ever to be, raised above anyone except an unfortunate wife and children. There are fewer honourable exceptions to this than to almost any other human infirmity. Philosophy and religion, instead of keeping it in check, are generally suborned [= ’bribed or bullied’] into defending it; and nothing controls it but the practical feeling of the equality of human beings, which is Christianity’s theory but will never be its practice until it stops supporting institutions based on an arbitrary preference for one human being over another.

No doubt there are women, as there are men, who won’t be satisfied with mere equality of consideration—ones with whom there is no peace until their own will or wish is the only one that counts. Such people are a proper subject for the law of divorce. They are only fit to live alone, and no human beings ought to be compelled to live with them. But the legal subordination tends to increase the frequency of such characters among women. If the man exercises his whole power, the woman is of course crushed: but if he treats her more permissively and allows her to exercise some power, there is no rule to set limits to how far she takes this. Because the law doesn’t determine her rights and •theoretically allows her none at all, •practically declares that she has a right to anything she can contrive to get.

The moral education of mankind

One way to make the marriage relationship even-handedly fair and conducive to the happiness of both spouses is the equality of married persons before the law. It isn’t the only way to bring this about, but it’s the only way to make the daily life of mankind a school of moral cultivation. [Mill is going to discuss a very general moral view of his, about the importance of regarding and treating all human beings as equals. One part of this is

the equality of all persons before the law;

and that implies or includes

the equality of married persons before the law,

which is what links the special topic of this work to the more general topic that Mill is now going to discuss.]
Though the truth may not be felt or generally accepted for generations to come, the only school of genuine moral sentiment is society between equals. Until now mankind’s moral education has mainly come from the law of force, and has adapted almost solely to the relations that force creates. In the less advanced states of society, people barely have the notion of an equal: to be an equal is ·for them· to be an enemy. Society as a whole is one long ladder,

24

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

where every individual is either above or below his nearest neighbour, and wherever he doesn’t command he must obey. So existing moralities are mainly fitted to a relation of command and obedience. But command and obedience are merely unfortunate necessities of human life; society in equality is its normal state. Already in modern life, and increasingly so as it progressively improves, •command and obedience become special cases whereas •equal association is the general rule. The morality of the first ages [Mill’s phrase] rested on (1) the obligation to submit to power; and the morality of the ages next following rested on (2) the right of the weak to the forbearance and protection of the strong. How much longer is one form of society and life to content itself with the morality made for another? We have had (1) the morality of submission, and (2) the morality of chivalry and generosity; the time has now come for (3) the morality of justice. Whenever in earlier times any approach was made to society in equality, justice was claimed to be the foundation of virtue. That is how it was in the free republics of antiquity; but even in the best of these, the equals were limited to the free male citizens; slaves, women, and residents without a vote were under the law of force. The joint influence of Roman civilisation and of Christianity obliterated these distinctions, and in theory (if only partially in practice) declared the claims of the human being as such to outrank the claims of sex, class, or social position. The barriers that had begun to be levelled were raised again by the northern conquests [Mill’s phrase]; and the whole of modern history consists of the slow process of grinding them down again. We are now entering into an order of things in which justice will again be the primary virtue, based as before on association of equals but now also on association of sympathy [here = ‘fellow feeling’]. Justice is no longer rooted in •the instinct of equals for self protection, but in •a cultivated sympathy between equals; and because no-one is now left out, an equal measure ·of fellow-feeling· is extended to all. It’s well known that human beings don’t clearly foresee their own changes, and that their sentiments are adapted to past ages rather than to future ones. To see the future of the species has always been the privilege of the intellectual élite, or of those who have learned from them; to have the feelings that mankind will have in the future has been the distinction—and usually the martyrdom—of a still rarer élite. Institutions, books, education, society, all go on training human beings for the old ·way of looking at things· even while the new one is coming, and long after it has actually come. But the true virtue of human beings is fitness to live together as equals; claiming nothing for themselves except what they freely concede to everyone else; regarding command of any kind as an exceptional and temporary necessity; and preferring the society of those who are willing to take turns leading and following. Life as at present constituted does not help to develop these virtues by allowing them to be practised. The family is a school of despotism, in which the virtues of despotism, but also its vices, are nourished. Citizenship in free countries is partly a school of society in equality; but citizenship fills only a small place in modern life and comes nowhere near to people’s daily habits or inmost sentiments. If the family were justly constituted, it would be the real school of the virtues of freedom. It is sure to be a good enough school for everything else: it will always be a school of obedience for the children and of command for the parents. What is needed is for the family to be a school of sympathy in equality, of living together in love, without power on one side or obedience on the other. That’s what it ought to be between the parents. It would then be an exercise of those virtues that each spouse requires to fit him or her for all other relationships; and it would be a model to the children

25

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

of the feelings and conduct that could become habitual and therefore natural to them—that being the intended end-point of their temporary training by means of obedience. [Mill goes on to say that ’the moral training of mankind’ will never be satisfactory until it has as a basis a morally satisfactory family structure.]

Even under the present law, many married people (in the higher classes of England probably a great majority of them) live in the spirit of a just law of equality. I readily admit this; indeed it is the very foundation of my hopes. Laws never would be improved if there weren’t many people whose moral sentiments are better than the existing laws. Such people ought to support the position I am advocating here, because its only objective is to make all other married couples similar to what they are now. But even persons of considerable moral worth, unless they are also thinkers, are very ready to believe that laws or practices from which they haven’t personally suffered any harm •don’t do harm to anyone, •probably do good (if they seem to be generally approved of), and •ought not to be objected to. The legal conditions of the marriage tie may not occur to the thoughts of such people once in a year, and they live and feel in every way as though they were legally equals; but they would be making a great mistake if they supposed that the same is the case with all other married couples (or anyway with all in which the husband is not a notorious ruffian).... In fact, the less fit a man is for the possession of power—the less likely to be allowed to exercise it over anyone with that person’s voluntary consent—the more he •soothes himself with the awareness of the power the law gives him, •exercises that power to the utmost point that custom (the custom of men like himself!) will tolerate, and •enjoys using the power as a way of enlivening his agreeable sense of possessing it. Furthermore: in the naturally most brutal and morally uneducated part of the lower classes, the legal slavery of the wife and something in her merely physical subjection to the husband’s will (her role as his instrument) causes him to feel a disrespect and contempt towards her that he doesn’t feel towards any other woman—or any other human being—with whom he comes in contact; and this makes her seem to him an appropriate subject for any kind of indignity....

Perhaps we’ll be told that religion imposes the duty of obedience ·on women·—as every established fact that is too bad to be defended in any other way is said to be required by religion. Indeed the church does enjoin obedience in her marriage rituals, but it would be hard to derive any such command from Christianity. We are told that St. Paul said, ‘Wives, obey your husbands’, but he also said, ‘Slaves, obey your masters.’ His business was the propagation of Christianity, and it wouldn’t help him in that to incite anyone to rebel against existing laws. His acceptance of all social institutions as he found them doesn’t express a disapproval of attempts to improve them at the proper time, any more than his declaration ‘The powers that be are ordained by God’ implies support for military despotism as the only Christian form of political government.... To claim that Christianity was intended to freeze existing forms of government and society, protecting them against change, is to reduce it to the level of Islamism or of Brahminism. It is precisely because Christianity has not done this that it has been the religion of the •progressive portion of mankind, and Islamism and the rest have been the religions of the •stationary portions, or rather of the •declining portions (because there’s no such thing as a really stationary society). Throughout the history of Christianity there have been plenty of people trying to make it something of the same kind, converting us into a sort of Christian Moslems with the Bible for a Koran, prohibiting all improvement. These people have been powerful, and

26

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

resistance to them has cost many other people their lives. But they have been resisted; the resistance has made us what we are; and will yet make us what we are to be. [That last clause is as Mill wrote it. You might care to think about what he might mean by ‘what we are to be’.]

Property rights

After what I have said about the ·general· obligation of obedience, it is almost superfluous to say anything about the more specific topic of a woman’s right to her own property.... The rule is simple: whatever would be the wife’s if she were not married should be under her exclusive control during marriage, and similarly for the husband. This still leaves them free to tie up property by settlement, in order to preserve it for children. Some people are shocked by the idea of a wife and a husband having separate interests in money matters; this, they sentimentally think, is inconsistent with the ideal fusion of two lives into one. ·They are (a) right about the ideal, (b) wrong about the practice·. Speaking for myself: I strongly support (a) community of goods when this results from a complete unity of feeling among the owners, but I have no taste for a (b) community of goods that relies on the doctrine that what is mine is yours but what is yours is not mine; and I would choose not to entire into such a contract with anyone, even if I were the person to profit by it.

This particular injustice and oppression to women is to the casual observer more obvious than all the rest; and it could be remedied without interfering with any other mischiefs, and there can’t be much doubt that it will be one of the first to be remedied. Many states in the USA have gone so far as to put into their written Constitutions provisions that guarantee women equality of rights in this respect. At least for a woman who has property, this materially improves her situation in the marriage relation by leaving her one instrument of power that she hasn’t signed away; and it also prevents the scandalous abuse of the marriage institution in which a man traps a girl into marrying him without a settlement, purely so as to get her money. When the support of the family depends on earnings, the common arrangement in which •the man earns the income and •the wife superintends the domestic expenditure seems to me in general the most suitable division of labour between them. Given that the wife has

•the physical suffering of bearing children,

•the whole responsibility of their care and education in early years, and

•the careful use of the husband’s earnings for the general comfort of the family,

she does not only her fair share but usually the larger share of the bodily and mental exertion required by their joint existence. If she takes on any further share ·by having paid employment outside the family·, it seldom relieves her from this [meaning: ‘from care of the children and management of the household’] but only prevents her from doing it properly. ·And that is very serious, because· the care that she now can’t take of the children and the household isn’t taken by anyone else; the survivors among the children have to grow up as they best can, and the management of the household is likely to be so bad as to cancel much of the monetary value of the wife’s earnings. In a just state of things, I don’t think it is desirable that the wife should usually contribute by her labour to the income of the family. In an unjust state of things ·such as we now have·, her doing so may be useful to her by increasing her value in the eyes of the man who is legally her master; but against that it also enables him to abuse his power still further by forcing her to work and provide the family’s entire financial support, while he spends

27

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 2: The laws governing marriage

most of his time in drinking and idleness. If a woman doesn’t have independent property, the power to earn is essential to her dignity. But if

•marriage were an equal contract, not implying the obligation of obedience; if

•the marriage tie were no longer enforced on those who are oppressed by it, so that a separation on fair terms (I’m not talking here about divorce) could be obtained by any woman who was morally entitled to it; and if

•she then found all honourable employments as freely open to her as to men,

she wouldn’t need for her own protection to make this particular use of her abilities during marriage. Like a man when he chooses a profession, so a woman who marries can in general be understood to be •choosing the management of a household and the bringing up of a family as the first call upon her exertions, for as many years as may be needed for this purpose; and to be •renouncing all other objects and occupations that are not consistent with this. On that basis, regular occupations outside the home would be practically ruled out for most married women. But it should be thoroughly possible to adapt the general rules to fit individual cases: if a woman has abilities that are exceptionally adapted to some other occupation, she should be allowed to pursue that despite being married; as long as arrangements are made to fill any gap that this might make in her performance of the ordinary functions of mistress of a family. These things might with perfect safety be left to be regulated by opinion, without any interference of law, once public opinion has been rightly directed on the subject.

28

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

CHAPTER 3

Occupations for women outside marriage

If you agree with me about •the equality of women in the family, I don’t expect to have much trouble convincing you about the other aspect of the just equality of women, namely their admissibility to all the functions and occupations that have until now been the monopoly of the stronger sex [Mill’s phrase]. Why have women’s disabilities outside the home been clung to? ·I mean, of course: why have men clung to their belief in the disabilities of women outside the home·? I think it has been in order to maintain their subordination in domestic life, because the general run of the male sex still can’t tolerate the idea of living with an equal. If it weren’t for that, I think that almost everyone—given the actual state of opinion in politics and economics—would admit the injustice of excluding half the human race from most money-earning occupations, and from almost all high social functions [see note on page 12], decreeing from their birth that either

•they aren’t, and can’t possibly become, fit for employments that are legally open to the stupidest and lowest of the other sex, or else

•however fit they may be, those employments will be barred to them and reserved for the exclusive benefit of males.

In the last two centuries, when it was thought necessary (it usually wasn’t!) to justify the exclusion of women from those functions and occupations, this wasn’t often done in terms of their inferior mental capacity. (Actually, no-one back then really believed in that, because in those times the struggles of public life sometimes provided a real test of personal abilities, a test in which women sometimes took part.) The reason given for the exclusion of women in those days was not •women’s unfitness but rather •the interests of society, meaning the interests of men; just as the most wicked crimes were thought to be explained and excused by the raison d’état, meaning the convenience of the government and the support of existing authority. These days power speaks with a smoother tongue: when it oppresses people it always claims to do so for their own good. Thus, when any activity is forbidden to women, it is thought necessary to say (and desirable to believe) that they are incapable of doing it, and that in aiming for it they are leaving their real path of success and happiness. But to make this reason plausible (I don’t say valid!), those who offer it must be prepared to push it much further than anyone ventures to do in the face of present experience. It’s not enough for them to maintain that

(1) Women on average are less gifted than men on average, in certain of the higher mental faculties that are needed for higher social functions.

What they have to maintain is that

(2) No women at all are fit for those functions; the most eminent women are the intellectual inferiors of the most mediocre of the men who currently fulfill those functions.

·You may at first think that (2) is wildly extravagant; but· think about (1)’s short-fall from what is needed to defend the status quo. All you can get from (1) is

(3) fewer women than men are fit for occupations and functions of the highest intellectual character.

If that is as far as we can go, then if the performance of a given important function is decided by competition or in any other way that respects the interests of the public, there’s

29

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

no need to fear its falling into the hands of women inferior to average men, or to the average of their male competitors. The only result will be that there will be fewer women than men in such employments; and that is bound to happen in any case, if only because most women are likely to prefer the one vocation in which there’s nobody to compete with them. Now, ·no-one will now support (2), not even the most determined depreciator of women·. Down through the years, women—many women—have shown themselves to be capable of everything that men do, and of doing it successfully and creditably. The most that can be said is that there are many things that no woman has succeeded in doing as well as they have been done by some men—many in which women have not reached the very highest rank. But there are extremely few activities depending only on mental skills in which women haven’t attained the second-to-highest rank. Isn’t this more than enough to make the refusal to let them compete with men for these roles a tyranny to them and a detriment to society? Isn’t it a mere truism to say that such functions are often filled by men who •are far less fit for them than plenty of women and •would be beaten by women in any fair competition? ‘Perhaps there are some, fully employed in other ways, who are even better qualified for the functions in question than these women.’ What of it? Isn’t this the case in all competitions? Is there such a surplus of men fit for high duties that society can afford to reject the service of any competent person? Finding a man who is just right for some duty or function of social importance that falls vacant—are we always so sure we can do this that we lose nothing by ruling out half of mankind, refusing in advance to make any use of their abilities, however distinguished they may be? And even if we could do without them, would it be just to refuse to them their fair share of honour and distinction....? And the injustice isn’t confined to them: it is shared by all who might benefit by their services. To ordain that no-one of a certain kind may be a physician, or a lawyer, or a Member of Parliament, is to injure not only persons of that kind but also anyone who employs physicians or lawyers, or elects Members of Parliament....

Women as governors

Perhaps it will be enough if in the details of my argument I confine myself to functions of a public nature: if I succeed regarding those, it will probably be readily granted that women should be admissible to any occupation where it matters whether they are admitted or not. Let me begin by selecting one function....their right to which is entirely independent of any thesis about their abilities. I mean the vote, both parliamentary and municipal. The •right to share in the choice of those who are to exercise a public trust is utterly distinct from the •right to compete for the trust itself. If to vote for a Member of Parliament one had to be fit to be a candidate, the government would be a narrow oligarchy indeed! To have a voice in choosing those by whom one is to be governed is a means of self-protection that everyone should have, even ones who are for ever excluded from the function of governing; and that includes women. They must be thought fit to have such a choice, because the law already gives to a woman the most important choice of all—the choice of the man who is to govern her throughout her life, which is always supposed to be voluntarily made by herself.... There’s not a shadow of justification for not allowing women the vote under whatever conditions, and within whatever limits, men are allowed it. The majority of women of any class are unlikely to differ in political opinion from the majority of the men of the same class, unless the issue somehow involves the interests of women as such; and

30

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

in that case women require the votes as their guarantee of just and equal consideration. This ought to be obvious even to those who reject every other doctrine I have been arguing for: even if every woman were a wife, and every wife ought to be a slave, these slaves would stand in need of legal protection, and we know what legal protection slaves have when the laws are made by their masters.

With regard to women’s fitness not only to participate in elections but themselves to hold offices or practise professions involving important public responsibilities: I have already remarked that this consideration isn’t essential to the practical question under discussion, because any woman who succeeds in an open profession thereby proves that she is qualified for it. As for public offices: if the country’s political system excludes unfit men, it will equally exclude unfit women; and if it doesn’t, there is no additional evil in the fact that the unfit persons whom the system admits may be either women or men. Thus, as long as it is admitted that even •a few women may be fit for these duties, the laws that shut the door on those exceptions can’t be justified by any opinion that can be held regarding the abilities of •women in general. But though this last consideration is not essential, it is far from being irrelevant. An unprejudiced view of women’s competence strengthens the arguments against their subjection, reinforcing them by high considerations of practical benefit.

Let us start by entirely setting aside all psychological considerations tending to show that any of the mental differences supposed to exist between women and men are only effects of differences in their •education and circumstances, and don’t indicate any radical difference—let alone any radical inferiority—of •nature. Let us consider women only as they actually are or are known to have been, and the abilities that they have already shown in practice. Anything that they have done at least proves that they can do that! When we consider how carefully they are all trained away from (rather than towards) any of the occupations or objects reserved for men, it becomes evident that I am taking a very humble ground for them [Mill’s phrase] when I base their case on what they have actually achieved, because in this matter negative evidence is worth little, whereas any positive evidence is conclusive. No woman has yet actually produced works comparable to those of Homer, Aristotle, Michelangelo, or Beethoven, but it doesn’t follow from this that that no woman can attain any such height as they did. The negative fact merely leaves the question uncertain, and open to psychological discussion. On the other hand, it is quite certain that a woman can be a Queen Elizabeth or a Deborah or a Joan of Arc, because this is not inference but fact. [Deborah was a judge and had command of an army in ancient Israel. See Judges 4–5.] It’s an odd thing that the only things the existing law excludes women from doing are the very ones that they have proved they can do! There is no law to prevent a woman from having written all the plays of Shakespeare, or composed all the operas of Mozart. But if Queen Elizabeth and Queen Victoria had not inherited the throne they couldn’t have been entrusted with the smallest political duties—the sort of duties in which Queen Elizabeth showed herself to be supreme.

If anything conclusive could be inferred from empirical data without psychological analysis, it would be that the things women aren’t allowed to do are the very ones for which they are specially qualified. Their aptitude for government has become conspicuous through the very few opportunities they have been given; whereas in lines of distinction that apparently were freely open to them they have by no means so eminently distinguished themselves.

31

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

History presents us with far fewer reigning queens than kings, but a talent for ruling has been shown by a higher proportion of the queens than of the kings—despite the fact that many of the queens have occupied the throne in difficult periods.

It is remarkable too that they have often been distinguished by merits flatly opposite to the imaginary and conventional character of women: they have been noted for their rule’s firmness and vigour as much as for its intelligence. When to queens and empresses we add regents and viceroys of provinces, the list of eminent women rulers swells to a great length.^2 This is so clearly the case that someone once tried to run the argument in reverse, turning the admitted truth into an additional insult by saying that queens are better than kings because under kings women govern, but under queens men do.

It may seem a waste of reasoning to argue against a bad joke; but such things do affect people’s minds, and I have heard men quote this saying in a manner suggesting that they thought there is something in it. Anyway, it will serve well enough as a starting-point for my discussion. So: it is not true that under kings women govern. Such cases are entirely exceptional, and weak kings have governed badly through the influence of male favourites as often as of female. When a king is governed by a woman merely because of his love relationships, good government is not probable, though even then there are exceptions. But French history counts two kings who chose to have affairs directed for many years by a woman—one to his sister, the other to his mother. One of them, Charles VIII, was a mere boy, but in giving power to his sister he was following the intentions of his father Louis XI, the ablest monarch of his age. The one whose mother was powerful in his reign was ·Louis IX, since canonized and now known as· Saint Louis. He was the best and one of the most vigorous rulers since the time of Charlemagne. Both of these princesses—·Charles’s sister and Louis’s mother·—ruled in a manner hardly equalled by any prince among their contemporaries. The Emperor Charles V, the most politic prince of his time, •had as many able men in his service as a ruler ever had, and •was utterly unlikely to sacrifice his interests to personal feelings; yet he made two princesses of his family successive governors of the Netherlands.... Both ruled very successfully, and one of them, Margaret of Austria, was one of the ablest politicians of the age. So much for one side of the joke. As for the other: When it is said that under queens men govern, is this meant to be taken in the same way as the statement that kings are governed by women? Is it meant that queens choose the associates of their personal pleasures as their instruments of government? The case is rare even with queens who are as unscrupulous in their love affairs as Catherine II [Catherine the Great, of Russia]: and we won’t find in these ·rare· cases the good government that is supposed to arise from male influence on queens. So if it is true that the administration ·of a country· is in the

^2 Especially if we bring in Asia as well as Europe. If a Hindu principality is strongly, vigilantly, and economically governed; if order is preserved without oppression; if the people are prosperous and culture is growing among them, three times out of four that principality is under a woman’s rule. [The bit about ‘culture’ replaces Mill’s ‘cultivation is extended’, which could mean something more like ‘agriculture is thriving’.] I have gathered this surprising fact from a long knowledge of Hindu governments. There are many examples of this; for although Hindu institutions won’t let a woman reign, she is the legal regent of a kingdom while the heir to the throne is a minor; and minorities are frequent ·in India· because male rulers there often die young through the effect of inactivity and sensual excesses. Bear in mind that these princesses •have never been seen in public, •have never conversed with any man not of their own family except from behind a curtain, •don’t read, and if even they did there’s no book in their languages that could give them the slightest instruction on political affairs—they provide a very striking example of women’s natural capacity for government.

32

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

hands of better men under a queen than under an average king, it must be that queens are better able to choose good men; and women must be better qualified than men both to be sovereign and to be Prime Minister, because the Prime Minister’s principal business is not to govern in person but to find the fittest people to run every department of public affairs..., But actually most great queens have been great by their own talents for government ·more than by their talent for picking good ministers·.... They kept the supreme direction of affairs in their own hands; and if they listened to good advisers, that was itself the strongest proof that their judgment fitted them for dealing with the great questions of government.

Is it reasonable to think that those who are fit for the greater functions of politics can’t qualify themselves for the less? We know this:

(1) The wives and sisters of monarchs, when they are called on, are found to be as competent as the monarchs themselves in the business ·of royalty·.

There is no reason in the nature of things why this shouldn’t also be true:

(2) The wives and sisters of statesmen, administrators, company directors, and managers of public institutions are capable of doing what is done by their brothers and husbands.

·If in fact (2) is not true, the reason for that doesn’t lie in the nature of things·. The real reason ·why wives etc. of kings have done better than we would expect the wives etc. of business men to do· is plain enough. It has to do with how princesses have related to the common run of men; their rank has put them above men to a greater extent than their sex has put them below them. So they haven’t been taught that it was improper for them to concern themselves with politics; but have been allowed to feel the wide-ranging interest that is natural to any cultivated human being in the great events occurring around them, events in which they might be called on to take a part. The only women who are allowed the same range of interests and freedom of development as men are the ladies of reigning families, and it is precisely in their case that no inferiority is found. Women’s capacities for government have been found adequate in every place where they have been tried, and to the extent that they have been tried.

Practice versus theory

This fact fits with the best general conclusions that our imperfect experience seems to suggest concerning the special tendencies and aptitudes that are typical of women, as women have hitherto been. I don’t say ‘...as they will continue to be’ because (I repeat) it would be presumptuous to make claims about what women are or are not, can or cannot be, by their natural constitution. They have always been kept in such an unnatural state (as regards spontaneous development) that their nature must have been greatly distorted and disguised; and no-one can safely assert that any significant difference would show up between men’s and women’s characters and capacities if women’s nature were left to choose its direction as freely as men’s.... I’ll show later on that even the most undeniable differences that now exist ·between the sexes· may have been produced merely by circumstances, without any difference of natural capacity. Still, looking at women as they are known in experience, we can say (with more truth than most generalisations about women possess) that the general bent of their talents is towards the practical. This statement is consistent with all the public history of women, past and present. It is also confirmed by common and daily experience. The mental

33

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

capacities that are most characteristic of a woman of talent are all of a kind that fits them for practice, and makes them tend towards it. What is meant by a woman’s being good at intuitive perception? It means rapid and correct insight into present fact. It has nothing to do with general principles: nobody ever perceived a scientific law of nature by intuition, or reached a general rule of duty or prudence by it. These ·laws and rules· are results of slow and careful collection and comparison of empirical data, and ‘intuitive’ people—men or women—don’t usually shine in this department, unless they can acquire the needed experience by themselves. ·That ‘unless...’ condition is crucial·, because their so-called ‘intuitive’ insight makes them especially good at arriving at such general truths as can be collected from their individual observations. So when they happen to be as well provided as men are with the results of other people’s experience, by reading and education, women are better equipped than men generally are with what is needed for practical success. (I say happen to be, because ·it won’t be a result of anyone’s designs·; in respect of the knowledge that tends to fit them for the greater concerns of life, the only educated women are self-educated.) Highly educated men are apt to be deficient in the sense of present fact; in the facts they have to deal with they don’t see •what is really there but •what they have been taught to expect. This is seldom the case with women of any ability: their capacity for ‘intuition’ preserves them from it. When a man and a woman are equal in what experience they have had and in general intellectual level, she will usually see much more of what is immediately before them than he will; and this awareness of the present is the main quality that is needed for practical (as distinct from theoretical) ability.... Of course there can be no good practice without principles; and I admit ·another drawback in this aspect of a woman’s abilities, namely· that her quickness of observation has such a dominant place in her abilities that she is especially apt to form rash generalisations on the basis of her own observation; though she is equally ready to correct those generalisations when her range of data widens. But the corrective to this defect is •access to the experience of the human race, i.e. •general knowledge, which is exactly the thing that education can best provide. A woman’s mistakes are like those a clever self-educated man, who often •sees things that are overlooked by men who have been through training-drills, but •falls into errors through ignorance of things that have long been known....

Women’s minds, then, are drawn to the present, to the real, to actual fact; this can be a source of errors because of what it leaves out, but it is also a useful antidote to the contrary error. Where theorising minds primarily and typically go wrong is through having too little of this lively perception and ever-present sense of objective fact. [Mill says this about ‘speculative minds’. In this version, his uses of ‘speculation’ and its cognates will be replaced by ‘theorising’ and its cognates.] For lack of this they often overlook conflicts between outward facts and their theories, and also

lose sight of the legitimate purpose of theorising in the first place, and let their theory-building skills stray into regions that are populated

not by real beings, animate or inanimate or even idealised, but by personified shadows created by the illusions of metaphysics or by the mere entanglement of words,

and think these shadows are the proper objects of the highest philosophy.

For a theorist who is engaged not in •collecting empirical data but in •working data up by processes of thought into comprehensive truths of science and laws of conduct, hardly anything can be of more value than to do this work with a

34

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

really superior woman as a companion and critic. There’s nothing comparable to this for keeping his thoughts within the limits of real things and the actual facts of nature.... A woman’s mind is always directed towards dealing with things as individuals rather than in groups, and—closely connected with that—to having a more lively interest ·than a man does· in the present feelings of persons; and this aspect of her mind determines how she approaches anything that claims to have practical applications. For her the first question is always ‘How will individual people be affected by this?’ So she is extremely unlikely to put faith in any theory that loses sight of individuals and (a) deals with things as if they existed for the benefit of some imaginary entity, some mere creation of the mind that doesn’t (b) boil down to the feelings of living beings. [Mill has in mind here (perhaps among other things) the difference between two views of morality: (a) in one kind, questions like ‘Was that action wrong?’ and ‘Would that be a good outcome?’ are somehow basic; (b) in the other, such questions are mere conceptual vehicles for really basic questions such as ‘Did that hurt anyone?’ and ‘Is that something we would try to bring about?’ In the last chapter of Utilitarianism Mill tries to explain the (a) notion of justice in terms of (b) facts about how people think and feel and act.] Women’s thoughts are thus as useful in giving reality to thinking men’s thoughts as men’s thoughts are in giving breadth and scope to women’s. In depth, as distinguished from breadth, I strongly suspect that women, even now, do as well as men.

If it’s true that women’s existing mental characteristics are valuable aids even in •theorising, they are still more important in •applying theories to the world. I have explained why women are less likely than men to fall into the error of sticking to a rule in a case whose special features make the rule inapplicable or require it to be specially modified. Another of the admitted superiorities of clever women is greater quickness on the uptake; isn’t this pre-eminently a quality that fits a person for practice? In •action, everything constantly depends on prompt decisions; in •theorising nothing does. [In reading on, remember that in Mill’s day ‘philosophy’ was still used to cover science. A magazine of that day includes an advertisement for ‘a more philosophical way of making coffee’.] A mere thinker can wait, take time to consider, collect more evidence; he isn’t under pressure to complete his philosophy at once so as not to miss his opportunity. [Mill says that the theorising ‘philosopher’ may be helped by an ability to draw plausible conclusions from inadequate data; but that is a side-help to his work, not at the centre of it; and anyway the theorist doesn’t have to do it in a hurry; he can slog away slowly ‘until a conjecture has become a theorem’. Mill continues the contrast thus:] For those whose business is with the fleeting and perishable—with individual facts, not kinds of facts—speed of thought is second only to power of thought in importance. If someone dealing with the contingencies of action doesn’t have his faculties under immediate command, he might as well not have them! He may be fit to criticise, but he isn’t fit to act. Now, this is what women are agreed to excel at—women and men who are most like women. The other sort of man, however able he may be, arrives slowly at complete command of his faculties: rapidity of judgment and promptness of judicious action, even in the affairs he knows best, are the gradual and late result of strenuous effort grown into habit.

‘Nervous temperament’

It may be said that women’s greater nervous susceptibility disqualifies them for any practical activities except domestic ones, by making them

35

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

•mobile,

•changeable,

•too intensely under the influence of the moment,

•incapable of dogged perseverance,

•uneven and uncertain in their command of their faculties.

Those phrases, I think, sum up most of the objections commonly made to women’s fitness for the higher class of serious business. ·In so far as the phrases apply·, much of this is the mere overflow of nervous energy run to waste, and would cease when the energy was given a definite purpose. Much is also the result of conscious or unconscious cultivation [i.e. results from social leads and pressures]; as we see from the almost total disappearance of ‘hysterics’ and fainting-fits since they have gone out of fashion. Moreover, when people are brought up as....a kind of hot-house plants, shielded from the wholesome ups and downs of air and temperature, and not trained in any of the occupations that make the blood flow and strengthen the muscles, while the emotional part of their nervous system is kept in unnaturally active play, it’s no wonder if those of them who don’t die of consumption [= ‘tuberculosis’] grow up with constitutions that are liable to be upset by slight causes, both internal and external, without the stamina to keep up any physical or mental task requiring continuity of effort. But women brought up to work for their livelihood show none of these morbid characteristics, unless indeed they are chained to sedentary work in small unhealthy rooms. Women who in their early years have shared in the healthy physical upbringing and bodily freedom of their brothers, and who have enough pure air and exercise in adult life, rarely have excessively fragile nervous systems that would disqualify them for active pursuits. There are indeed some people—men and women—who have an unusual degree of nervous sensibility as a feature of their constitution, a feature which they have so strongly that it has more influence than anything else does over every aspect of their health. Like other aspects of one’s physical constitution, this so-called ‘nervous temperament’ is hereditary, and is transmitted to sons as well as daughters; but it could be—and apparently is—inherited by more women than men. Assuming that this is so, let us ask: Are men with the nervous temperament found to be unfit for the duties and pursuits usually followed by men? If not, why should women of the same temperament be unfit for them? Peculiarities of temperament are, within certain limits, obstacles to success in some employments though aids to success in some others. Men of high nervous sensibility have succeeded brilliantly in occupations that are suitable to that temperament—and sometimes even in one’s that aren’t. The main way in which the temperament contributes to a man’s practical success is this:

Because he is susceptible of a higher degree of excitement than people with a different physical constitution, the difference between •his powers when they and he are aroused and •his powers at other times is greater than the corresponding difference in other people. In his excited state he is raised above himself, as it were, and easily does things that he couldn’t possibly do at other times.

This lofty excitement is usually not a mere flash that •leaves no permanent traces and •is incompatible with persistent and steady pursuit of an objective. It is typical of the nervous temperament to be capable of sustained excitement that holds out through long-continued efforts. It is what is meant by ‘spirit’. It is what makes the high-bred racehorse maintain his speed till he drops down dead. It is what has enabled so many delicate women to maintain the most sublime constancy....through lengthy mental and bodily

36

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

tortures. People with this temperament are particularly well suited for the executive department of the leadership of mankind. They are the material of great orators, great preachers, impressive spreaders of moral influences. You might think that their constitution makes them less suitable for the role of a statesman in the cabinet, or of a judge; and so it would, if it were the case that people who are excitable must always be in a state of excitement. But this is wholly a question of training. Strong self-control can •grow out of and •contain strong feeling, but strong feeling has to be trained to go that way. When it is, it creates not only the heroes of impulse but also the heroes of self-conquest. History and experience prove that the most passionate characters are the most fanatically rigid in their feelings of duty, when their passion has been trained to act in that direction. The judge who gives a just decision in a case where his feelings draw him strongly to the other side gets from that same strength of feeling the fixed sense of the obligation of justice that enables him to win this victory over himself. [And the fine things that such a person achieves in states of high excitement, Mill says, come to affect his character in general, providing standards that he sets for himself at other times. Then:] The thesis that people with excitable temperaments are on average less fit than others for theory or for practice is shown empirically to be false not only of individuals but also of races. The French, and the Italians, are undoubtedly by nature more nervously excitable than the Teutonic races; their habitual daily emotional life is a richer affair than that of the English, at least. But have they been less great ·than the English· in science, in public business, in legal and judicial eminence, or in war? There is abundant evidence that the Greeks of ancient times, like their descendants today, were one of the most excitable of the races of mankind, and they excelled in every kind of human achievement. As an equally southern people, the ancient Romans probably had the same native temperament: but the stern character of their national discipline, like that of the Spartans, made them an example of the opposite type of national character. The main way in which the strength of their natural feelings showed up was in the intensity with which they worked on replacing their natural temperament with an artificial one. If these cases show what a naturally excitable people can be turned into, the Irish Celts provide a fine example of what such people are when left to themselves (if they can be said to be ‘left to themselves’, given centuries of indirect influence from bad government and the direct influence of Catholic teaching and of a sincere belief in the Catholic religion). The Irish character must be considered as an unfavourable case, ·i.e. a naturally excitable people who have not as a race achieved anything great·. But whenever the circumstances of individual Irish Celts have been at all favourable, what people have shown greater capacity for the most varied individual excellence? Like

the French compared with the English,

the Irish compared with the Swiss,

the Greeks or Italians compared with the Germans,

so also

women compared with men

may be found on average to do the same things, though with some variety in the details. I don’t see the smallest reason to doubt that they would do them every bit as well if their education and development were adapted to correcting instead of worsening the infirmities that their temperament brings.

Suppose ·for purposes of argument· that all this is true:

Women’s minds are naturally more mobile than men’s, less able to persist for long in one continuous effort, more fitted for dividing their abilities among many

37

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

things than for travelling a single path to the highest point that can be reached by it;....which is why they have climbed as high as the best men in precisely the endeavours that seem to need most of this absorption of the whole mind in one set of ideas and occupations.

[Mill speaks of ‘supposing’ that to be true, but he crams two qualifications into his ‘supposition’: it only concerns ‘women as they now are’, and there are ‘great and numerous exceptions’ to it. With those two qualifications, it seems, the indented passage expresses something that he thinks probably is true.] Still, this difference ·between women and men· can only affect what sort of excellence and achievement each has, not how excellent it is or how practically valuable it is. ·And the underlying hint in all this that the man’s kind of mind is somehow primary, central, optimal, should be challenged·. This exclusive working of a part of the mind, this absorption of the whole thinking faculty in a single subject and concentration of it on a single work—is this the normal and healthful condition of the human faculties? It hasn’t been shown to be so, even in theorising activities. What this concentration gains in specialised projects is lost, I believe, in the capacity of the mind for the other purposes of life; and even in abstract ·theorising·, I am firmly convinced, the mind achieves more by frequently returning to a difficult problem than by sticking to it without interruption. Anyway, in practical projects, great and small, the ability to pass promptly from one thing to another without letting the active spring of the intellect lose energy between the two is a much more valuable power ·than the ability to stick at a problem without any breaks·; and this more valuable power is one that women pre-eminently possess because of that very ‘mobility’ of which they are accused.... People have often noticed women’s ability to do their thinking in circumstances and at times that almost any man would make an excuse to himself for not even trying; and a woman’s mind, though it may be occupied only with small things, can seldom permit itself to be vacant, as a man’s mind so often is when he isn’t engaged in what he chooses to consider the business of his life....

The size and quality of brains

This is sometimes said: ‘There is anatomical evidence that men’s mental capacity is superior to women’s: they have a larger brain.’ In fact, it is by no means established that a woman’s brain is smaller than a man’s.... The size of the brain in human beings, anatomists say, varies much less than the size of the body or even of the head, and the one can’t be at all inferred from the other. Some women certainly have as large a brain as any man. I know of a man who weighed many human brains and said that the heaviest he knew of....was that of a woman. Furthermore, the precise relation between the brain and the intellectual powers is a controversial matter that isn’t yet well understood. We can’t doubt that there is a very close relation. The brain is certainly the material organ of thought and feeling (never mind the ongoing controversy about which mental abilities correspond to which parts of the brain); and it would be anomalous—an exception to everything we know of the general laws of life and organisation—if brain-size didn’t contribute something to mental power. But it would be an equally anomalous exception if the brain influenced thought only through its size. In all nature’s more delicate operations—of which the physiology of living things are the most delicate, and the workings of the nervous system by far the most delicate of these—differences in the effect depend on differences of •quality in the physical agents as much as on their •quantity; and if we judge by outputs, the level of fineness of quality in the brains and nervous systems of women is higher on

38

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

average than that of men. Never mind abstract difference of quality, which is hard to verify. We know that an organ’s efficiency depends not only on its •size but on its •activity: and we can get a rough measure of this in how energetically the blood circulates through the organ, because the organ’s activities and its ability to repair itself depend mainly on blood-circulation. The differences that we see between the mental operations of the two sexes suggest that men on the average have the advantage in the size of the brain, and women in the activity of blood in the brain. That conjecture about difference of brain-organisation, based on analogy, suggests differences in output of kinds that we do most commonly see. ]Mill goes into this a little, along lines already developed. Women are quicker in having thoughts and feelings, but less apt to stay with a given line of thought or activity after it has become tiring. In the first place, men’s mental operations might be expected to be slower than women’s; men wouldn’t be as prompt as women in thinking, or as quick to feel. Mill suggests (though he doesn’t explicitly state it) a comparison with wheels: small ones are easier to start going but also easier to stop. Then:] This speculation is entirely hypothetical; all it does is to suggest a line of inquiry. I repeat that we don’t yet know for sure that there is any natural difference in the average strength or direction of the mental capacities of the two sexes. And this can’t be known when •the psychological laws of the formation of character have been so little studied....and when •the most obvious external causes of difference of character are habitually disregarded—left unnoticed by the observer, and looked down on with haughty contempt by the prevalent schools of natural history and of mental philosophy. Those schools disagree about what the source is of what mainly distinguishes human beings from one another—disagree about whether it is material or spiritual—but they agree in belittling those who explain these differences in terms of the different ways in which human beings relate to society and to life.

Different nations, different views

People’s views about the nature of women are mere empirical generalisations, formed on the basis of the first instances that present themselves, with no help from philosophy or analysis. This is so true that the popular idea of women’s nature differs in different countries, according to how women have been shaped by the opinions and social circumstances of the country in question. An oriental thinks that women are by nature peculiarly voluptuous.... An Englishman usually thinks that they are by nature cold. The sayings about women’s fickleness are mostly French.... The English commonly remark on how much more constant women are than men. The attitude that inconstancy is discreditable to a woman has been prevalent in England for much longer than in France; besides which Englishwomen are in their inmost nature much more subdued to opinion ·than Frenchwomen are·. Incidentally; Englishmen are especially poorly placed to judge what is or isn’t natural—to women, or to men, or to human beings altogether—if they have only English experience to go on; because there is no place where human nature shows so little of its basic structure as it does in England. For better and for worse, the English are further from a state of nature than any other modern people; more than any other people, they are a product of civilisation and discipline. England is the country in which social discipline has most succeeded not so much in •conquering as in •suppressing whatever is liable to conflict with it. The English, more than any other people, not only act according to rule but feel according to rule. In other countries, the

39

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

taught opinion or the social requirement may be the stronger power, but the promptings of the individual nature are always visible under it, and often resisting it: rule may be stronger than nature, but nature is still there. In England, rule has largely replaced nature. [Mill develops this line of thought: an Englishman will get human nature wrong because he doesn’t see it; a Frenchman sees it, but only in a form distorted by civilisation, so that he gets it wrong too.]

I have said that we can’t now know ·for sure· how much of the existing mental difference between men and women is natural and how much artificial, or whether there are any natural differences at all, or what they are if there are any.... But where certainty can’t be had, there may be ways of arriving at some degree of probability. The first question to tackle, and one we have the best chance of answering, is: What is the origin of the differences between women and men that we actually observe? I’ll explore for the answer to this along the only path by which it can be reached, namely by tracing the mental consequences of external influences. We can’t isolate a human being from his ·social· circumstances, so as to learn experimentally what he would have been by nature; but we can consider •what his circumstances have been, and •what he is, and whether one could have produced the other.

So let us consider the only conspicuous example we can see of apparent inferiority of women to men, apart from the merely physical one of bodily strength. No top-ranking production in philosophy, science, or art has been the work of a woman. Can we explain this without supposing that women are naturally incapable of producing them?

Women in the arts and sciences

The first point is that we don’t have enough empirical evidence to support an induction. With a very few exceptions, women didn’t begin to try their abilities in philosophy, science, or art until the past three generations. Only in England and France have many made the attempt even today. Calculating the probabilities, was it to be expected that a mind having the requisites of first rate eminence in •theorising or creative work would have shown up during that ·rather short· period of time among the women whose tastes and social situation allowed them to devote themselves to •these pursuits? In every kind of activity that there has been time for, women have done quite as much (at all but the very highest ranks in the scale of excellence), and have obtained as many high prizes as could be expected, given the length of time and the number of competitors. This is especially true in the art in which they have been active for the longest, namely literature—both prose and poetry. If we go back to the time when very few women even tried, some of those few were highly successful. The Greeks always counted Sappho among their great poets; and we may well suppose that Myrtis, who is said to have been •Pindar’s teacher, and Corinna, who five times defeated him in the competition for the poetry prize, must at least have been good enough poets to be compared with •that great name. Aspasia did not leave any philosophical writings; but it’s an acknowledged fact that Socrates went to her for instruction and reports that he obtained it.

If we consider women’s works in modem times, and contrast them with men’s, either in literary or in the ·fine· arts, the inferiority that we can see boils down to one thing—a very significant thing—namely a lack of originality. Not a total lack; for any production that has any substantive value

40

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

has an originality of its own—is a conception of the mind that produced it, not a copy of something else. The writings of women abound in thoughts that are ‘original’ in the sense of being not borrowed but derived from the thinker’s own observations or intellectual processes. But women haven’t yet produced any of •the great and luminous new ideas that form an era in thought, or any of the •fundamentally new conceptions in art that open a vista of possible effects not before thought of, and found a new school. Their compositions are mostly based on the existing fund of thought, and their creations don’t deviate far from existing types. This is the sort—·the only sort·—of inferiority that their works do manifest. There is no inferiority in execution, the detailed application of thought, the perfection of style. In respect of composition and the management of detail, our best novelists have mostly been women; and modern literature doesn’t contain a more eloquent vehicle of thought than the style of Madame de Staël, or a finer specimen of purely artistic excellence than the prose of Madame Sand, whose style acts on the nervous system like a symphony of Haydn or Mozart. What is mainly lacking, I repeat, is high originality of conception. Let me consider how we might explain this deficiency.

Let us remember....that

during all the period in the world’s existence and development of civilisation in which great and fruitful new truths could be arrived at by sheer force of intellect, with little previous study and accumulation of knowledge

women didn’t concern themselves with theorising at all. From the days of Hypatia [a famous mathematician, astronomer and philosopher, 4th century] to those of the Reformation, the illustrious Heloisa is almost the only woman for whom such an achievement might have been possible; and we don’t know how great a capacity for theory-building may have been lost to mankind by the misfortunes of her life. [Héloise, as she is usually named these days, was a notable scholar of the 12th century; the ‘misfortunes of her life’ refer to troubles arising from her being the lover of Abelard]. And in the times when a significant number of women have began to cultivate serious thought, originality has never been easy to achieve. Nearly all the thoughts that can be reached by mere strength of basic intellect were reached long ago; and originality in any high sense of that word is now scarcely ever attained except by minds that have undergone elaborate discipline, and are deeply versed in the results of previous thinking. Someone remarked regarding the present age that its most original thinkers are those who have known most thoroughly what their predecessors had thought: and this will always be the case. Every fresh stone in the structure has to be placed on the top of so many others that anyone who wants to take a share in the present stage of the work has to go through a long climb, carrying up materials. How many women have gone through any such process? Mrs. Somerville may be the only woman who knows as much mathematics as is needed for making any considerable mathematical discovery; she happens not to be one of the two or three persons who in her lifetime have been associated with some striking advance in mathematics; is this a proof that women are inferior? Since economics became a science, two women have known enough of it to write usefully on the subject; countless men have written on economics during the same time—of how many of those can we claim more ·than that they have written usefully·? If no woman, so far, has been a great historian, what woman has been learned enough for that? If no woman is a great philologist, what woman has studied Sanscrit and Slavonic, the Gothic of Ulphila and the Persic of the Zendavesta? Even in practical matters we all know

41

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

how little value the originality of untaught geniuses has. It means re-inventing in a rudimentary form something already invented and improved on by many successive inventors. When women have had the preparation that all men now need to be importantly original, then we’ll be in a position to begin judging by experience their capacity for originality.

No doubt it often happens that someone who •hasn’t widely and carefully studied the thoughts of others on a subject has through natural intelligence a bright idea which he can suggest but can’t prove, but which when matured may be an important addition to knowledge. But justice can’t be done to it until someone who •does have the required knowledge takes it in hand, tests it, gives it a scientific or practical form, and fits it into its place among the existing truths of philosophy or science. Does anyone think that women don’t have such ideas? They occur by the hundreds to every woman of intellect. But they are mostly lost for lack of a husband or friend who has the knowledge that enables him to value them properly and bring them before the world; and even when that happens, they usually appear as his ideas, not their real author’s. Who can tell how many of the most original thoughts put out by male writers belong to a woman by •suggestion, to the man only by •verifying it and working it out? If I may judge by my own case, a very large proportion indeed! [See the last four lines of the editorial introduction to this text.]

If we turn from pure theory-building to •literature in the narrow sense of the term and •the fine arts, there is a very obvious reason why women’s literature is broadly....an imitation of men’s. Why is Roman literature, as critics proclaim until we are sick of it, not original but an imitation of Greek literature? Simply because the Greeks came first. If women lived in a different country from men, and had never read any of their writings, they would have had a literature of their own. As it is, they haven’t created one, because they found a highly advanced literature already created. If the knowledge of antiquity hadn’t been in abeyance for several centuries, or if the Renaissance had occurred before the Gothic cathedrals were built, they never would have been built ·because the builders would have had models in mind—ancient Greek temples or Renaissance buildings—which would have deprived them of the freedom to be original·. We see that in France and Italy imitation of ancient literature stopped original development even after it had started. All women who write are pupils of the great male writers. A painter’s early pictures, even if he is a Raphael, are indistinguishable in style from his master’s. Even a Mozart doesn’t display his powerful originality in his earliest pieces. What years are to a gifted individual, generations are to a mass. If women’s literature is ever to have a different collective character from men’s because of differences in their natural tendencies, it will need much more time than it has had so far before it can free itself from the influence of accepted models and guide itself by its own impulses. I don’t think that there will turn out to be any natural tendencies common to women that distinguish their highest intellectual capacities from those of men; but even if that is right, every individual woman writer has her own individual tendencies, which at present are still subdued by the influence of precedent and example; and it will require generations more before their individuality is well enough developed to make headway against that influence.

It is in the fine arts, properly so-called, that the prima facie evidence of inferior original powers in women is the strongest, because (it may be said) opinion doesn’t exclude them from these but rather encourages them, and in the affluent classes the education of women is mainly composed of training in the fine arts. [In that sentence as Mill wrote it,

42

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

there is a charming triple dose of caution: ‘...the (i) prima facie evidence (etc.) (ii) at first sight (iii) appears to be the strongest’.] Yet the gap between the best that women have done and the highest eminence attained by men has been greater in this line of activity than in many others. What explains this, however, is the familiar fact—more universally true in the fine arts than anywhere else—that professionals are vastly superior to amateurs. Nearly all women in the educated classes are taught a certain amount of some branch of the fine arts, but not so that they can earn their living or their social consequence by it. Women artists are all amateurs. The only exceptions to this confirm the general truth: women. are taught music, but only as performers, not as composers; and accordingly men are superior to women in music only as composers, not as performers. The only one of the fine arts that women do seriously follow as a profession and an occupation for life is the theatrical; and it is commonly agreed that in that they are as good as men if not better. To be fair about this, we should compare the productions of women in any branch of art with those of men who don’t follow it as a profession. Women have surely produced musical compositions, for example, that are every bit as good any produced by male amateurs. There are now a few women, a very few, who practise painting as a profession, and these are already beginning to show quite as much talent as could be expected. Even male painters (pace Mr. Ruskin) haven’t done anything very remarkable in the last few centuries, and it will be long before they do so. The reason why the old painters were so greatly superior to the modern is that a greatly superior class of men took up painting. In the 14th and 15th centuries the Italian painters were the most accomplished men of their age. The greatest of them had encyclopaedic skills and powers, like the great men of ·ancient· Greece. But in their times fine art was felt and thought to be among the grandest things in which a human being could excel; and through it men became the companions of sovereigns and the equals of the highest nobility—which they can’t become these days by anything but political or military distinction. In the present age, men of anything like that calibre seek to become famous and useful to the world by something more important than painting: and it is only now and then that a Reynolds or a Turner (of whose relative rank among eminent men I don’t offer an opinion) applies himself to that art. Music belongs to a different order of things; it doesn’t require the same general powers of mind, and seems to depend more on a natural gift; and it may be thought surprising that no great musical composer has been a woman. But even this natural gift can’t be made available for great creations without study and professional devotion to the pursuit. [The only first-rate composers, Mill says, have been German or Italian; and those are countries where the development of women’s intellects is grossly neglected, far worse than France and England. And he adds another point about Germany and Italy: there have probably been thousands of men who have learned ‘the principles of musical composition’ and barely scores of women who have done so. From this guess, Mill does the math:] On the doctrine of averages, we can’t reasonably expect to see more than one eminent woman to fifty eminent men; and the last three centuries have not produced fifty eminent male composers either in Germany or in Italy.

There are other reasons, too, that help to explain why women remain behind men even in the pursuits that are open to both. For one thing, very few women have time for them. This may seem a paradox, but it is an undoubted social fact. (1) The superintending of the family and the domestic expenditure which occupies at least one woman in every family, usually the one of mature years and long

43

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

experience; unless the family can afford to hire domestic help, opening the door to waste and dishonesty. Even when the superintending of a household isn’t laborious in other ways, it’s a very heavy burden on the thoughts; it •requires incessant vigilance, an eye that catches every detail, and it •constantly presents inescapable problems to be solved. If a woman has the rank and wealth to be somewhat relieved from these cares, she still has on her shoulders the management of the family’s relations with other families—its relations with ‘society’, as it is called—and the less she has to do on the domestic side, the greater becomes the ‘social’ task: dinner parties, concerts, evening parties, morning visits, letter-writing, and all that goes with them. In addition to all this, society imposes on women, and only on them, the engrossing duty of making themselves charming. A clever woman of the higher ranks finds her talents being exercised almost to the full by her development of graces of manner and the arts of conversation. Let us look just at the outward side of the subject. Any woman who attaches any value to dressing well (I don’t mean expensively, but with taste and awareness of what is naturally and socially appropriate) must give to her own clothes and perhaps those of her daughters an amount of time and thought that would go a great way towards achieving respectable results in art, or science, or literature^3.... And there is another burden. Independently of the regular domestic and social duties that are laid on a woman, she is expected to have her time and abilities always at the disposal of everybody. Even if a man doesn’t have a profession to exempt him from such demands, no-one is offended if he devotes his time to some pursuit that he has chosen; ‘I am busy’ is accepted as a valid excuse for not responding to every casual demand that may be made on him. Are a woman’s occupations, especially the ones she chooses, ever regarded as excusing her from any of the demands of society? Even her most necessary and recognised duties are barely allowed as exempting her. To be entitled to give precedence to her own •business over other people’s •amusement [those are Mill’s nouns], she needs an illness in the family or something else out of the common way.... Is it surprising, then, if she doesn’t reach the highest eminence in activities that require unbroken attention and have to be focussed on as the chief interest of life? Such is philosophy, and such above all is art, in which besides the devotion of •the thoughts and feelings •the hand must also be kept constantly at work to attain high skill.

[Mill now has a paragraph about what is required for ‘the great productions that immortalise a name’—far more than what’s needed to earn a living as a professional artist. That higher level requires a passionate desire for fame, which carries the person through years of drudgery; and Mill continues:] Women seldom have this eagerness for fame.... The influence they seek is over those who immediately surround them. They want to be liked, loved, or admired by those whom they see, and they usually settle for the level of proficiency in knowledge, arts etc. that suffices for that. [This fact about women, Mills says, is a product of the circumstances in which society has placed them; it isn’t part of their nature; but it is real, and shouldn’t be forgotten.

^3 ‘The sound turn of mind that enables a man to acquire a just idea of what is right in •ornaments seems to be the same as what gives him good judgment in •the more stable principles of art. Ornamentation has the same centre of perfection as the more serious arts; it’s just that it is the centre of a smaller circle.—To illustrate this by fashion in dress, in which there is agreed to be a good or bad taste.... He who invents with the most success, or dresses in the best taste, if he had employed his skills and insight to greater purposes, would probably have revealed himself to have just as much skill—i.e. to have formed the same correct taste—in the highest labours of art.’—Sir Joshua Reynolds’s Discourses, Disc. vii.

44

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

Also, men are encouraged to seek fame, whereas for women] the desire of fame is considered daring and unfeminine.... If you have any ability to estimate •the influence on the mind of the entire domestic and social position and the whole habit of a life, you’ll see that •that influence completely explains nearly all the apparent differences between women and men, including all that imply inferiority ·on the part of women·.

Moral differences

As for moral—as distinct from intellectual—differences, it is commonly said that women are ‘better than men’. This empty compliment will provoke a bitter smile from every woman of spirit, because it implies that the situation of women is unique: there’s no other context in which it is regarded as natural and suitable that the better should obey the worse! If this piece of idle talk is good for anything it is only as men’s admission that power corrupts; because that is the only truth that is proved or illustrated by the fact, if it is a fact, that women are better. And ·it may indeed be a fact, because· it is true that servitude, except when it actually brutalises, is less corrupting to the slaves than to the slave-masters. Of these two situations:

•being restrained, perhaps by arbitrary power,

•being allowed to exercise arbitrary power without restraint,

it is the former that is more wholesome for one’s moral nature. Far fewer women than men commit crimes, it is said, and no doubt far fewer slaves than free men do so. Those who are under the control of others cannot often commit crimes, unless commanded by their masters and serving their purposes. The world, including the herd of studious men, blindly ignore and pass over all the influences of social circumstances; and I don’t know of any more blatant example of this than men’s silly....hymns of praise to the moral, nature of women.

The complimentary dictum about women’s moral superiority might be paired off with the disparaging one about their greater liability to moral bias. Women, we are told, can’t resist their personal partialities: their judgment in serious affairs is warped by their sympathies and antipathies. Even if this is so, it is still to be proved that women are oftener misled by their personal •feelings than men are by their personal •interests. The chief difference there seems be that men are led from the course of duty and public interest by their concern for •themselves, whereas women (not being allowed to have private interests of their own) are led astray by their regard for somebody else. Bear in mind also that all the education that women get from society •instills in them the feeling that the only duty of care that they owe is to individuals who are ·personally· connected with them, and •doesn’t introduce them to the ideas—even the elementary ideas—that are involved in any intelligent concern for larger interests or higher moral objects. The complaint against them resolves itself merely into this, that they fulfill only too faithfully the only duty they are taught, which is also almost the only one that they are allowed to practise.

When the privileged make any concession to the unprivileged, it is nearly always because the unprivileged have had the power to extort those changes. This is so much so that no arguments against the subjection of women are likely to be attended to by people in general as long as they can tell themselves that ‘women don’t complain of it’. [See also the section starting on page 8.] That fact certainly enables men to retain their unjust privilege some time longer, but it doesn’t make it less unjust.... Actually, women do complain of the general lot of women; plaintive elegies on that are very common in the writings of women, and were still more

45

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 3: Occupations for women outside marriage

so back when the lamentations couldn’t be suspected of having any practical objective. ·But· their complaints are like men’s complaints about the general unsatisfactoriness of human life; they aren’t meant to imply blame or to plead for change. But though women don’t complain about the power of husbands, each complains about her own husband, or the husbands of her friends. It is the same in all other cases of servitude, at least at the start of the movement towards liberation. The serfs at first complained not about the power of their lords but only about their tyranny. The commoners began by claiming a few municipal privileges; then they asked to be freed from being taxed without their own consent; but they would have thought it very presumptuous [= ’thoroughly] out of line’ to claim any share in the king’s sovereign authority. The only rebellion against established rules that is viewed in that way today is that of women against their subjection. A woman who joins in any movement that her husband disapproves, makes herself a martyr, without even being able to be an apostle, for the husband can legally put a stop to her apostleship. Women can’t be expected to devote themselves to the emancipation of women until considerable numbers of men are prepared to join with them in the undertaking.

46

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

CHAPTER 4

What good would reform do?

There remains a question that is as important as those I have discussed—a question that will be asked with the most persistent vigour by opponents whose conviction is somewhat shaken on the main point—namely:

What good are we to expect from the changes you propose in our customs and institutions? Would mankind be better off if women were free? If not, why disturb their minds and try to make a social revolution in the name of an abstract right?

This question isn’t likely to be asked regarding the proposed change in the condition of women in marriage. The countless instances of suffering, immorality, evils of all sorts that come from the subjection of individual women to individual men are far too terrible to be overlooked. Thoughtless or dishonest people who attend only to cases that are extreme or that receive publicity may say that these evils are ‘exceptional’; but no-one can be blind to their existence or (often) to their intensity. And it is perfectly obvious that •the abuse of the power can’t be lessened very much while •the power remains. This power is given or offered not to good men or to decently respectable men, but to all men, including the most brutal and the most criminal. The only constraint is that of opinion, and such men are usually unaffected by any opinion except that of men like themselves.... The law of servitude in marriage is a monstrous contradiction to all the principles of the modern world, and to all the experience through which those principles have been slowly and painfully worked out. Now that negro slavery has been abolished, marriage is the only institution in which a human whose faculties are all in excellent order is delivered up to the tender mercies of another human being, in the hope—yes, really—that this other will use the power solely for the good of the person subjected to it. Marriage is the only actual bondage known to our law. There are no longer any legal slaves except the mistress of every house.

So the question Cui bono? [Latin = ‘Who will benefit from this?] is not likely to be asked regarding the reform of the marriage law. We may be told that the evil ·of such reform· would outweigh the good, but there can be no denying that there would be good results. In regard to the larger question, however—

•removing women’s disabilities,

•recognising them as the equals of men in every aspect of citizenship,

•opening up to them all honourable employments, and

•allowing them to have the training and education that would qualify them for those employments

—for many people it isn’t enough that this inequality has no just or legitimate defence; they demand to know what definite positive •advantage would come from abolishing it.

The moral education of males

My first answer is: the •advantage of having the most universal and pervading of all human relations regulated by justice instead of injustice. That bare statement will tell anyone who attaches a moral meaning to words what a vast gain this would be for the human condition; it’s hardly possible to make it any stronger by any explanation or illustration. All of mankind’s selfish propensities, the self-worship, the

47

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

unjust self-preference, are rooted in and nourished by the present constitution of the relation between men and women. Think what it does to a boy to grow up to manhood in the belief that—without any merit or any exertion of his own, though he may be the most frivolous and empty or the most ignorant and stolid of mankind—by the mere fact of being born a male he is by right the superior of every one of half the human race. That ‘inferior’ half probably includes some whose real superiority to himself he has daily or hourly occasion to feel! But even if his whole conduct is guided by a woman ·governess or teacher·, if he is a fool he thinks that of course she isn’t and can’t be his equal in ability and judgment; and if he isn’t a fool he does worse—he sees that she is superior to him, and believes that still he is entitled to command and she is bound to obey. What effect on his character will this lesson have? And men of the cultivated classes are often not aware how deeply the lesson sinks into most male minds. That is because among right-feeling and well-bred people the inequality is kept out of sight as much as possible—especially out of sight of the children. Boys are required to be as obedient to their mother as to their father; they aren’t allowed to domineer over their sisters, and aren’t accustomed to seeing their sisters made subordinate to them; on the contrary, feelings of chivalry towards females are highlighted, while the servitude that requires those feelings is kept in the background. Well brought up youths in the higher classes thus often escape the bad influences of the subordination of women in their early years, and experience them only when they arrive at manhood and fall under the dominion of facts as they really exist. Such people are little aware, regarding a boy who is differently brought up, of

•how early the notion of his inherent superiority to a girl arises in his mind;

•how it grows with his growth and strengthens with his strength;

•how schoolboys inject it into one another;

•how early the youth thinks himself superior to his mother, owing her patience but no real respect; and

•how lofty and sultan-like a sense of superiority he feels over the woman whom he honours by admitting her to a partnership of his life.

Isn’t it obvious that all this perverts the whole manner of existence of the man, both as an individual and as a social being? It matches a hereditary king’s feeling that he is excellent above others because he was born a king, or a noble because he was born a noble. The relation between husband and wife is like that between lord and vassal, except that the wife is held to more unlimited obedience than the vassal was. The vassal’s character may have been affected for better and for worse by his subordination, but it is obvious that the lord’s character was affected greatly for the worse. If he came to believe that his vassals were really superior to himself, or to feel that he was given command over people as good as himself, through no merits or labours of his own but merely for having....taken the trouble to be born, ·still the situation will have harmed his character·. The self-worship of the monarch or of the feudal lord is matched by the self-worship of the male. Anyone who grows up from childhood with unearned distinctions is bound to become conceited and self-congratulatory about them, this being the worst sort of pride.... And when the feeling of being raised above the whole of the other sex is combined with personal authority over one woman, the situation ·may be ‘educational’ in either of two ways·. (1) To men whose strongest points of character are conscience and affection, the marriage may be •a school of conscientious and affectionate gentleness and patience, but (2) to men of a different sort it will be •a regularly constituted College for training them in arrogance

48

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

and overbearingness....

Basing domestic existence on a relation that conflicts with the first principles of social justice—think about the example this sets and the education that it gives to the sentiments! The very nature of man ensures that it will have such an enormous perverting influence that we can hardly even imagine the enormous improvement that would come about if the unjust basis for marriage were removed. Everything that education and civilisation are doing to erase the influences on character of the law of force, and replace them by influences of the law of justice, remains merely on the surface as long as the enemy’s stronghold is not attacked. The principle of the modern movement in morals and politics is that what entitles someone to respect is his conduct and nothing else; that men’s claim to deference comes not from what they are but from what they do; that (above all) the only rightful claim to power and authority comes from merit, not birth. If no human being were given permanent authority over any other, society wouldn’t be employed in building up with one hand character-traits that it has to curb with the other. For the first time in man’s existence on earth, the child would really be trained in the way he should go, and when he grew up there would be a chance of his staying on that path. But so long as •the right of the strong to have power over the weak rules in the very heart of society, the attempt to get people’s conduct to be guided by •the principle of equal rights for the weak will always be an uphill struggle....

Doubling the brain pool

The second benefit to be expected from giving to women the free use of their abilities by leaving them free to choose their employments and opening up to them the same range of occupation and the same rewards and encouragements as other human beings have, would be doubling the supply of abilities available for the higher service of humanity. Where there is now one person qualified to benefit mankind....as a public teacher or an administrator of some branch of public or social affairs, there would then be a chance of two. As things now stand, there is a terrific shortage of people who are competent to do excellently anything that needs any significant amount of ability to do; so that the world suffers a serious loss by refusing to make use of half the talent it possesses. It’s true that this amount of mental power isn’t totally lost: much of it is employed, and would in any case be employed, in domestic management and in the few other occupations open to women; and the personal influence of individual women over individual men brings some indirect benefit to other activities. But these benefits are partial; their range is extremely narrow; and if you insist on •deducting them from the total amount of fresh social power that would be gained by liberating women, then you must •add to that total the benefit of the stimulus that men’s intellects would get from the competition ·posed by liberated women·....

This great gain for the intellectual power of our species....would come partly through better and more complete intellectual education of women, which would then improve in step with the improvement of men’s. Women in general would be brought up with the same ability to understand business, public affairs, and the higher matters of theorising as men in the same class of society; and the select few of either sex who were qualified not only to understand the work and thought of others but to think or do something considerable themselves would get the same help in improving and training their capacities. In this way, the widening of women’s sphere of action would operate for good, by raising their education to the level of men’s and making it share in all improvements made men’s education. But

49

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

independently of all this, merely breaking down the barrier would have an educational virtue of the highest worth. The mere getting rid of the idea that

all the wider subjects of thought and action, all the things that are of general and not solely of private interest, are men’s business from which women are to be warned off—positively debarred from most of it and coldly tolerated in the little that is allowed them—

the mere consciousness a woman would then have of being a human being like any other, entitled to choose her pursuits, urged or invited....to interest herself in whatever is interesting to human beings, entitled to have her opinion (like any other) taken account of in human concerns, whether or not she tried to participate in them—this alone would enormously expand women’s faculties while also broadening the range of their moral sentiments.

The moral influence of women: chivalry

So the liberation of women would double the amount of individual talent available for the conduct of human affairs, which certainly aren’t at present so rich in able guidance that they can afford to do without half of what nature offers! The result of that would be that women’s opinions would have a more beneficial influence than they now do on the general mass of human belief and sentiment. A ‘more beneficial’ rather than a ‘greater’ influence? Yes, because women’s influence over the general tone of opinion has always—or at least from the earliest known period—been very considerable. •Mothers’ influence on the early character of their sons, and the •desire of young men to be liked by young women, have throughout history been important factors in the formation of character, and have determined some of the chief steps in the progress of civilisation. Even in the Homeric age, the great Hector acknowledged being powerfully motivated by his concern for how he would appear to the Trojan women. [Mill says this by quoting a line from Homer’s Greek.] The moral influence of women has worked in two ways. (i) It has been a softening influence. Those who were most liable to be the victims of violence have naturally tended as much as they could towards limiting its scope and cutting back its excesses. Those who were not taught to fight have naturally tended to favour any way of settling differences other than fighting. In general, those who have suffered most from others’ giving free rein to their selfish passions have ·naturally· been the most earnest supporters of any moral law that offered a way of controlling passion. Women were powerfully instrumental in inducing the northern conquerors to adopt the creed of Christianity, a creed so much more favourable to women than any that preceded it. The conversion of the Anglo-Saxons and of the Franks may be said to have been begun by the wives of Ethelbert and Clovis. (2) Women’s opinions have conspicuously given a powerful stimulus to the qualities in men that women needed their protectors to have because they weren’t themselves trained in them. Courage and the other military virtues have always been greatly indebted to men’s wish to be admired by women; and this mechanism works for far more than just this one class of eminent qualities, because....being thought highly of by men has always been the best passport to the admiration and favour of women.

The combination of (1–2) those two kinds of moral influence by women gave birth to the spirit of chivalry, the special feature of which is that it aims at combining the highest standard of (2) the warlike qualities with (1) the development of gentleness, generosity, and self-denial towards the non-military and defenseless classes generally, with a special submission and worship directed towards

50

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

women. What distinguished women from the other defenceless classes was their power to give high rewards to those who tried to earn their favour rather than forcing them into obedience. The practice of chivalry fell sadly short of its theoretical standard—even more than practice generally falls below theory!—and yet it remains one of the most precious monuments of humanity’s moral history. It was a remarkable example of an organised joint effort by a most disorganised and distracted society to raise up and act on a moral ideal greatly in advance of its social condition and institutions. It was indeed so far in advance that it was completely frustrated in the main objective; and yet it was never entirely ineffective, and has left its mark—a very detectable and (for the most part) highly valuable mark—on the ideas and feelings of all subsequent times.

The chivalrous ideal is the high point of women’s influence on the moral development of mankind; and if women are to remain in subjection it is lamentable that the chivalrous standard has passed away, because it’s the only standard that has any power to alleviate the demoralising influences of the subjection of women. But changes in the general state of mankind made it inevitable that the chivalrous ideal of morality would be replaced by a totally different one. Chivalry tried to infuse moral elements into a state of society in which everything depended for good or evil on •individual strength and skill, under the softening influences of •individual delicacy and generosity. In modern societies everything....is settled not by individual effort but by the combined operations of many people, and society’s main occupation has changed from fighting to business, from military to industrial life. The demands of this new life don’t rule out the virtues of generosity, any more than the demands of the old life did, but the new life doesn’t entirely depend on them ·as the old life did·. The main foundations of the moral life of modern times must be

•justice: each person’s respect for the rights of every other person, and

•prudence: each person’s ability to take care of himself.

Chivalry didn’t erect legal barriers to any of the forms of wrong that reigned unpunished throughout society; the most it achieved in that line was to steer the instruments of praise and admiration in such a way as to encourage a few men to do right in preference to wrong. But what morality must really depend on are its penal sanctions—its power to deter people from acting badly. The security of society cannot rest merely on honouring right behaviour: that is a relatively weak motive in most people, and in some it has no force at all. Modern society can repress all kinds of wrong conduct by an appropriate use of the superior strength that civilisation has given it, and thus make life tolerable for the weaker members of society (who are no longer defenseless but protected by law), doing this without having to rely on the chivalrous feelings of those who are in a position to tyrannise. The beauties and graces of the chivalrous character are still what they always were, but the rights of the weak and the general comfort of human life now rest on a far surer and steadier support. Or, rather, they do so in every relation of life except the marriage relation.

The moral influence of women: charity

The moral influence of women these days is just as real as it used to be, but it is no longer so marked and definite: it has moved nearer to being merged in the general influence of public opinion. [Regarding the phrase ‘the contagion of sympathy’: The root meaning of ‘sympathy’ is ’feeling with’; in early modern times the word covered kinds of going-along-with that didn’t involve feelings at all—e.g. a violin’s G-string starts vibrating because another nearby

51

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

G-string has been plucked. Mill is thinking about feelings, of course, but not only feeling for people’s misfortunes: in his day someone’s sharing a friend’s pleasure could be called ‘sympathy’. You can see why he used ‘contagion’; he wasn’t implying that there is anything wrong with sympathy.] Both through the contagion of sympathy, and through men’s wish to shine in the eyes of women, the feelings of women have great effect in keeping alive what remains of the chivalrous ideal—in encouraging the feelings and continuing the traditions and spirit of generosity. In these aspects of character, women’s standard is higher than men’s; in the quality of justice, it is somewhat lower. As regards the relations of private life, the influence of women is—broadly speaking, but with some individual exceptions—encouraging to the softer virtues, discouraging to the sterner ones. Virtue’s biggest trials in the concerns of life involve •the conflict between interest and principle; and women’s influence •in these is of a very mixed character. When the principle involved happens to be one of the very few that women’s religious or moral education has strongly impressed on them, they are powerful aids to virtue; and their husbands and sons are often prompted by them to acts of self-denial that they couldn’t have performed without that stimulus. But the moral principles that have been impressed on women, given their present education and position, cover only a small proportion of the field of virtue, and they are principally negative—forbidding particular acts but having little to do with the ·positive· direction of thoughts and purposes. I’m afraid it must be said that women’s influence does little to encourage or support the devotion of the energies to purposes that don’t promise private advantages to the family. It is small blame to them that they discourage projects of which they haven’t learnt to see the advantage, and which take their men away from them and from the interests of the family. But the consequence is that women’s influence is often anything but favourable to public virtue.

But they do today have some influence in setting the tone for public moralities; that has been the case since their sphere of action has been a little widened and a good many of them have worked to promote objectives that stretch beyond their own family and household. The influence of women counts for a great deal in two of the most marked features of modern European life—its aversion to war, and its addiction to philanthropy. Excellent characteristics both; but unfortunately the influence of women, while it is valuable in encouraging these feelings in general, does at least as much harm as good in the directions in which it steers them. On the philanthropic side more particularly, the two areas chiefly cultivated by women are •religious missionary-work and •charity. Religious missions at home are merely ways of making religious animosities even more bitter; and foreign missions usually involve blindly running at an object without either knowing or caring about the fatal harms—fatal to the religious purpose itself as well as to any other desirable purpose—which may be produced by the means the missionaries employ. As for charity: that is an affair in which •the immediate effect on the persons directly concerned are apt to be completely at war with •the ultimate consequence to the general good; and women can’t see and are unwilling to admit the ultimately harmful tendency of any form of charity or philanthropy that commends itself to their sympathetic feelings. This is result of •their education—which educates their feelings rather than their understanding—and of •the habit that their whole life has instilled in them of looking to immediate effects on individuals and not to more distant effects on classes of people. The large and growing mass of unenlightened and shortsighted benevolence, which,

by taking the care of people’s lives out of their own hands and relieving them from the disagreeable conse-

52

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

quences of their own acts, undermines the very foundations of the self-respect, self-help, and self-control that are essential both for individual prosperity and for social virtue

—this waste of resources and of benevolent feelings in doing harm instead of good, is immensely increased by women’s contributions and stimulated by their influence. This mistake isn’t likely to be made by women who have the practical management of projects for helping people. It sometimes happens that women who administer public charities recognise clearly the demoralising influence of the help that is given, and could give lessons on this to many a male political economist. (They are brought to this recognition by an ability that women usually have more than men do, namely insight into present fact, and especially into the minds and feelings of those with whom they are in immediate contact.) But women who only give their money, and aren’t brought face to face with the effects it produces—how can they be expected to foresee the effects? If a woman is born to the present lot of women, and is content with it, how is she to appreciate the value of self-dependence? She is not self-dependent; she is not taught self-dependence; her destiny is to receive everything from others, and why should what is good enough for her be bad for the poor? The notions of good that she is familiar with are of blessings descending from a superior. She forgets that •she isn’t free and that the poor are; that •if what they need is given to them unearned, they can’t be compelled to earn it; that •everybody can’t be taken care of by everybody, but people need some motive to take care of themselves; and that •the only charity that turns out in the long run to be charity is: helping people to help themselves if they are physically able to do so.

If women were socially and politically emancipated, they would be better educated and would have more practical experience of the things that their opinions influence; and the points I have been making show that those changes would improve the part that women take in the formation of general opinion. ·I now go on to argue that· an even more remarkable improvement would be made in the influence each woman has within her own family.

The moral influence of wives on husbands

It is often said that in the classes that are most exposed to temptation, a man’s wife and children tend to keep him honest and respectable—through his wife’s direct influence and his concern for the family’s future welfare. No doubt this is often the case, with men who are more weak than wicked; and this beneficial influence would be preserved and strengthened under laws that put the wife on a level with her husband.... But when we go higher in the ·social· scale, we encounter a totally different set of moving forces. The wife’s influence tends....to prevent the husband from •falling below the country’s common standard of approval; and it tends quite as strongly to hinder him from •rising above it. The wife is the assistant of common public opinion. A man who is married to a woman who is his inferior in intelligence finds her a perpetual dead weight—or, even worse, a drag—on every active wish he has to be better than public opinion requires him to be. It is hardly possible for someone who is in these bonds to achieve a really high level of virtue. If a man differs in his opinion from the mass—if he sees truths that haven’t yet dawned on them, or if he would like to act more conscientiously than most people do on truths that they all nominally recognise but don’t feel in their hearts as he does—to all such thoughts and desires marriage is the heaviest of drawbacks, unless the lucky man has a wife who is as much above the common level as he is.

53

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

One reason for this is that there is always some sacrifice of personal interest required, either of social status or of money, perhaps even a risk to the means of subsistence. A man may be willing to confront these sacrifices and risks for himself, but he will hesitate to impose them on his family. In this context, ‘his family’ refers to his wife and daughters; for he always hopes that his sons will feel as he does, and that anything he can do without they will also do without, willingly, in the same cause. But his daughters ·are in a different situation·: their marriage may depend on it. And if his wife

•can’t enter into or understand the objectives for which these sacrifices are made,

•if she thought them worth any sacrifice, would think so solely for his sake and taking his word for it, and

•couldn’t join in any of the enthusiasm or self-approval that he may feel, when the things that he is disposed to sacrifice are everything to her,

won’t the best and most unselfish man be the most reluctant to bring this consequence down on his wife? And if what is at stake is not the comforts of life but only social status, the burden on his conscience and feelings is still very severe. Anyone who has a wife and children has given hostages to •Mrs. Grundy [a character in an 18th century play, embodying the thoughts and feelings of conventional society, especially attitudes of prudish disapproval]. The approval of •that potentate may not matter to him but it is of great importance to his wife. The man may be above that sort of thing, or he may feel sufficiently compensated by the approval of those of his own way of thinking. But he has no compensation to offer the women connected with him. The almost invariable tendency of the wife to throw the weight of her influence on the side of social status is sometimes made a reproach to women, and represented as a streak of weakness and childishness in their character, but that is surely most unfair. Society makes the whole life of a woman in the easy classes [Mill’s phrase] a continual self-sacrifice; it exacts from her an unceasing restraint of all her natural inclinations; and the only return it makes to her for what often amounts to a martyrdom is consideration [= ‘social acceptance and respect’]. Her consideration is inseparably tied to her husband’s; and after paying the full price for it she finds that she is threatened with losing it for no reason that she can feel to be valid. Having sacrificed her whole life to it, she’s not going to let her husband sacrifice it to a whim, a caprice, an eccentricity—something not recognised or allowed for by the world, and which the world will agree with her in thinking to be at best a folly. This dilemma is hardest on the very meritorious man who doesn’t have talents that qualify him to be prominent among those whose opinion he shares, but who holds his opinion from conviction and feels bound in honour and conscience to serve it by professing his belief and giving his time, labour, and means to anything undertaken on its behalf. It is hardest of all when such a man happens to be of a rank and position that doesn’t automatically include him in what is considered the best society but does debar him from it either. His admission to the best society depends mainly on what people think of him personally—and his being identified with opinions and public conduct unacceptable to those who set the tone for society would operate as an effective barrier. Many a woman soothes herself with the thought (nine times out of ten a wrong thought) that nothing prevents her and her husband from moving in the highest society of her neighbourhood—society in which others well known to her, and in the same class of life, mix freely—except that her husband is unfortunately a dissenter [= ’a non-Anglican protestant’], or has the reputation of mingling in low radical politics.... With such an influence

54

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

in every house, either exerted actively or operating all the more powerfully for not being asserted, is it any wonder that people in general are kept down to the middling level of respectability that is becoming a marked feature of modern times?

The moral effects of difference

Let us look now not at women’s disabilities directly but at the broad line of difference those disabilities create between a woman’s education and character and a man’s. The difference has very harmful consequences; indeed, nothing can be more unfavourable to the union of thoughts and inclinations that is the ideal of married life. An intimate relation between people who are radically unlike one another?—that is an idle dream! Unlikeness may attract, but likeness is what retains; and the more alike a couple are the better fitted they are to give each other a happy life. While women are so unlike men, it’s not surprising that selfish men should feel the need to have arbitrary power in their own hands, to stop a life-long conflict of inclinations before it gets started, by deciding every issue on the side of their own preference. When people are extremely unalike, they can’t have any real identity of interest. Very often a married couple have a conscientious difference of opinion concerning the highest points of duty. Is there any reality in the marriage union where this is the case? Yet it is common enough wherever a married woman has any earnestness of character; and it is very common in Catholic countries, when the wife is supported in her dissent by the only other authority to which she is taught to bow, the priest. With the usual barefacedness of power that isn’t used to being challenged, the influence of priests over women is attacked by Protestant and Liberal writers, less for being bad in itself than because •it is a rival to the husband’s authority, and •raises up a revolt against his infallibility.... When there is no difference of ·moral or religious· opinion, mere differences of taste can detract greatly from the happiness of married life. [Differences of taste, Mill says, are created by differences in education. Girls are trained in music, dancing etc. rather than (he implies) spending that time and energy on an education more like their brothers’; and although that may ‘stimulate the amatory propensities of men’ it creates differences that aren’t conducive to married happiness. He continues:] If the married pair are well-bred and well-behaved, they tolerate each other’s tastes; but is mutual toleration what people look forward to when they enter into marriage? These differences of inclination will naturally make their wishes different, if not restrained by affection or duty, with regard to almost all domestic questions that arise. What a difference there must be in the society the spouses will wish to frequent! Each will want associates who share his or her own tastes; the persons agreeable to one will be indifferent or positively disagreeable to the other; yet all their associates must be common to both, because married people these days don’t live in different parts of the house and have totally different visiting lists.... They can’t help having different wishes about the upbringing of the children: each will want to see reproduced in the children his or her own tastes and sentiments; and either there is a compromise, giving only half satisfaction to each, or the wife has to yield—often with bitter suffering....

It would of course be foolish to suppose that these differences of feeling and inclination exist only because women are brought up differently from men. Obviously there would be some differences of taste under any imaginable circumstances. But it isn’t foolish to say that the difference in upbringing immensely increases those differences and makes them wholly inevitable. While women are brought up

55

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

as they are, a man and a woman will rarely find themselves in real agreement of tastes and wishes regarding daily life. They will generally have to give up as hopeless the attempt to have in their private daily life the idem velle, idem nolle [Latin = ‘same desires, same dislikes’] which is the recognised bond of any society that really is a society. [See note on ‘society’ on page 22.] Or the man succeeds in obtaining it by choosing a woman who is so complete a •nullity that she has no velle or nolle at all, and is as ready to go along with one thing as with another if anybody tells her to do so. Even this calculation ·of the man’s· is apt to fail; dullness and lack of spirit are not always a guarantee of the submission that is so confidently expected from them. But even if they were, is this the ideal of marriage? What in this case does the man get by marriage except an upper servant, a nurse, or a mistress? On the other hand, when each of two persons instead of being a •nothing is a something; when they are attached to one another and are not too unalike to begin with; the constant shared experience of the same things, assisted by their sympathy [see note on page 51], draws out the latent capacities of each for being interested in the things that were at first interesting only to the other. This produces a gradual assimilation of their tastes and characters to one another, partly by the gradual modification of each but more by a real enriching of the two natures, each acquiring the tastes and capacities of the other in addition to its own. This often happens between two friends of the same sex who are much in one another’s company in their daily life: and it would be common in marriage if it weren’t that the totally different bringing up of the two sexes make it nearly impossible to form a really well-suited union. If this were remedied, whatever differences there might still be in individual tastes, there would usually be complete unity and unanimity regarding the great objectives of life. When spouses both care for great objectives, and help and encourage each other in anything concerning these, the minor matters on which their tastes may differ are not all-important to them; and there’s a basis for solid friendship of an enduring character, more likely than anything else to make it a lifelong greater pleasure for each to give pleasure to the other than to receive it.

The moral effects of inferiority

So much for the effects of mere unlikeness between the wife and the husband on the pleasures and benefits of marriage; but the power for bad is vastly increased when the •unlikeness is •inferiority. When unlikeness is merely difference of good qualities, it may be more a benefit in the way of mutual improvement than a drawback from comfort. When each spouse wants and tries to acquire the other’s special qualities, the difference ·between them· doesn’t drive their interests apart but rather pulls them together, making each spouse still more valuable to the other. But when one of them has much less mental ability and cultivation than the other, and isn’t actively trying with the other’s aid to rise to the other’s level, this marriage will have a wholly bad influence on the mental development of abler of the two; and even more in a reasonably happy marriage than in an unhappy one. Someone who shuts himself up with an inferior, choosing that inferior as his one completely intimate associate, is doing himself harm. Any society that isn’t improving is deteriorating: and the closer and more familiar it is, the more it deteriorates. Even a really superior man, in nearly all cases, begins to deteriorate when he is habitually (as the phrase is) ‘king of his company’, and someone whose habitual ‘company’ is a wife who is inferior to him is always ‘king’ of it. While his self-satisfaction is constantly ministered to on the one hand, on the other he

56

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

unconsciously acquires the ways of feeling and of looking at things that belong to a more ordinary or a more limited mind than his own. [Mill goes on to say that this ‘evil’ in marriages, unlike many others that he has discussed, is becoming worse, because men are increasingly pulling away from ‘the rough amusements and convivial excesses that formerly occupied most men in their hours of relaxation’ and spend correspondingly more time with ‘the home and its inmates’. He continues:] The improvement that has been made in women’s education has made them in some degree capable of being men’s companions in ideas and mental taste, but it still leaves most women hopelessly inferior to their spouses. What generally happens, then, is that the husband’s desire for mental communion is satisfied by a communion from which he learns nothing. An unimproving and unstimulating companionship is substituted for (what he might otherwise have been forced to seek) the society of men whose abilities equal his and who share his interest in the higher pursuits. Thus, we see that very promising young men usually stop improving as soon as they marry, and when they don’t improve they inevitably degenerate. If the wife doesn’t push the husband forward, she always holds him back. He stops caring for what she doesn’t care for; he no longer wants—and eventually he dislikes and avoids—the company of people who share his former aspirations...., and his higher faculties of mind and of heart are no longer called into activity. This change coincides with the new and selfish interests that are created by the family, so that after a few years he doesn’t differ significantly from those who never did have any higher aspirations.

When two persons of high ability, identical in opinions and purposes, have the best kind of equality—

similarity of powers and capacities, with each being superior to the other in some things, so that each can enjoy the luxury of looking up to the other, and they can take turns in the pleasure of leading and the pleasure of being led in the path of development

—I shan’t try to describe what that marriage will be like. Those who can conceive it don’t need my description; those who can’t conceive it would brush off my description as the raving of a fanatic. But I am deeply convinced that that this, and only this, is the ideal of marriage; and that all opinions, customs, and institutions that favour any other notion of marriage, or turn the ideas and aims connected with marriage into any other direction....are relics of primitive barbarism. The moral renewal of mankind won’t really start until the most basic of all social relations is placed under the rule of equal justice, and human beings learn to develop their strongest sympathy with someone who is their equal in rights and in cultivation.

Benefits to the individual woman

Up to here I have discussed the social rather than the individual benefits that would come from abolishing the subjection of women;....but it would be a grievous understatement of the case to omit the most direct benefit of all, the indescribably great gain in the private happiness of members of the liberated half of the species [Mill’s phrase]—the difference to them between a life of subjection to the will of others and a life of rational freedom. After the basic needs for food and clothing, freedom is the first and strongest want of human nature. While mankind are lawless, they want lawless freedom. When they have learned to understand the meaning of •duty and the value of •reason, they are increasingly inclined to be guided and restrained by •these in the exercise of their freedom; but that doesn’t mean that they desire freedom less; they don’t become disposed to

57

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

accept the will of other people as the representative and interpreter of those guiding principles ·of duty and reason·. On the contrary, the communities in which reason has been most cultivated and the idea of social duty has been most powerful are the very ones that have most strongly asserted the freedom of action of the individual—the liberty of each person to govern his conduct by his own feelings of duty, and by such laws and social restraints as his own conscience can subscribe to.

Anyone who wants a sound sense of the worth of personal independence as an ingredient in happiness should consider how he values it as an ingredient in his own happiness. What a man judges for himself on this subject—as much as on any subject—differs from what he judges for other people. When he hears others complaining that they aren’t allowed freedom of action—that their own will has too little influence in the regulation of their affairs—he is inclined to ask: ‘What are their grievances?’ ‘What positive damage are they suffering?’ ‘How do they think their affairs are mismanaged?’; and if they can’t answer these questions in a way that seems to him to be adequate, he turns a deaf ear, and regards their complaint as the fanciful querulousness of people whom nothing reasonable will satisfy. But he has a quite different standard of judgment when he is deciding for himself. In that case, faultless administration of his interests by a tutor who has been set over him doesn’t satisfy his feelings: the sheer fact of his personal exclusion from the deciding authority is the greatest grievance of all, removing any need to go into the question of mismanagement. It is the same with nations. What citizen of a free country would listen to any offers of good and skilful government in return for the abdication of freedom? Even if he believed •that good and skilful administration can exist among a people ruled by a will not their own—·better and more skillful, indeed, than his country now has·—his feelings about the rough and imperfect handling of public affairs is compensated for by his sense that he and his fellow-citizens are working out their own destiny under their own moral responsibility. Well, whatever he feels about this, he can be sure that women feel it just as much. Whatever has been said or written, from the time of Herodotus [the first historian] to the present, about the enobling influence of free government—

•the nerve and spring that it gives to all the faculties,

•the larger and higher objectives that it presents to the intellect and feelings,

•the more unselfish public spirit, and calmer and broader views of duty, that it creates, and

•the higher platform on which it elevates the individual as a moral, spiritual, and social being

—is every bit as true of women as of men. Aren’t these things an important part of individual happiness? Let any man recall what he felt on emerging from boyhood—from the tutelage and control of even loved and affectionate elders—and entering on the responsibilities of manhood. Wasn’t it like the physical effect of taking off a heavy weight....? Didn’t he feel twice as alive, twice as much a human being, as before? And does he imagine that women have none of these feelings? [Mill goes on to say that personal pride is all-important to men although they don’t take it seriously in others. Women have their pride also, and when it is thwarted the energies behind it flow in other directions:] An active and energetic mind, if denied •liberty, will seek •power; refused the command of itself, it will assert its personality by trying to control others. To allow to any human beings no existence of their own except what depends on others is motivating them to bend others to their purposes. Where liberty can’t be hoped for, and power can, power becomes the grand object of human desire.... Hence women’s passion for

58

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

personal beauty, and dress and display, and all the evils that flow from that.... The love of power and the love of liberty are in eternal antagonism. Where there is least liberty, the passion for power is the most ardent and unscrupulous. The desire for power over others can’t cease to be a depraving agency among mankind until each individual human being can do without it, and that can’t happen until respect for each person’s liberty is an established principle.

But it is not only through the sense of personal dignity that the free direction and disposal of their own faculties is a source of individual happiness, and to be fettered and restricted in it is a source of unhappiness, to human beings, and not least to women. Apart from disease, extreme poverty. and guilt, nothing is as fatal to the pleasurable enjoyment of life as the lack of something worthwhile to do. While a woman has the care of a family, that provides an outlet for her active faculties, and usually that is enough. But what about the ever-increasing number of women who have had no opportunity of exercising the vocation that they are mocked by telling them is their proper one [i.e. women who have no families]? What about the women whose children •have been lost to them by death or distance, or •have grown up, married, and formed homes of their own? There are many examples of men who after a life taken up by business retire with a pension....and find that their change to a life of inactivity brings boredom, depression, and premature death; their trouble being their inability to acquire new interests and excitements to replace the old. Yet no-one thinks of the parallel case of so many worthy and devoted women, who,

•having paid what they are told is their debt to society,

•having brought up a family blamelessly to manhood and womanhood,

•having kept house as long as they had a house needing to be kept,

are deserted by the only occupation they have fitted themselves for, and are left with undiminished activeness but with no use to make of it, unless perhaps a daughter or daughter-in-law is willing to let them do the same work in her own younger household.... For women like these, and for others who have never had this task....the only resources, speaking generally, are religion and charity. But their religion, though it may be one of feeling and of ceremonies, can’t be a religion of action except in the form of charity. Many of these women are by nature admirably fitted for charitable work; but to practise charity usefully—indeed, to practise charity without doing harm—one needs the education, the skills, the knowledge and the thinking powers of a skilful administrator. Anyone who is fit to do useful charitable work could performs almost any of the administrative functions of government. In this as in other cases (notably the education of children), the duties permitted to women can’t be performed properly unless they are trained for duties that (to the great loss of society) they aren’t allowed to perform.

Let me point out here the strange way in which the question of women’s disabilities is often presented by people who, confronted by the prospect of something they don’t like, find it easier to draw a ludicrous picture of it than to answer the arguments for it. When it is suggested that women’s executive capacities and prudent advice might sometimes be valuable in affairs of State, these lovers of fun hold up to the ridicule of the world a picture of girls in their teens or young wives in their early twenties being transported bodily, exactly as they are, from the drawing-room to the House of Commons or the Cabinet room. They forget that males aren’t usually selected at this early age for a seat in Parliament or for responsible political functions. Common sense, ·if they had any·, would tell them that if such trusts were confided to women it would be to •women with no

59

The Subjection of Women John Stuart Mill 4: What good would reform do?

special vocation for married life, •or women who choose some other employment of their abilities,....or more often perhaps •widows or wives of forty or fifty who could, with the aid of appropriate studies, make available to the wider world the knowledge of life and skill in government that they have acquired in their families. In every European country the ablest men have often experienced and keenly appreciated the advice and help of clever and experienced women of the world, in achieving both private and of public objectives; and there are important aspects of public administration in which few men are as competent as such women—e.g. the detailed control of expenditure. But my present topic is not society’s need for women’s services in public business, but the dull and hopeless life it condemns them to by forbidding them to exercise the practical abilities that many of them are conscious of having, in any wider field than one that is now closed to some of them and to others was never open. If there is anything vitally important to the happiness of human beings it is that they should like what they habitually do. This requirement for an enjoyable life is very imperfectly granted, or entirely denied, to a large part of mankind; and because of the lack of it many a life that seems to have everything needed for success is actually a failure. But if such failures are often inevitable now, because of •circumstances that society isn’t yet skilful enough to overcome, society needn’t itself inflict •them! Many men spend their lives doing one thing reluctantly and badly when they could have done other things happily and well; this may come about through bad choices by parents, or a youth’s own inexperience, or the absence of opportunities for the congenial vocation and their presence for an uncongenial one. But on women this sentence is imposed by actual law, and by customs equivalent to law. What in unenlightened societies colour, race, religion, or nationality are to some men, sex is to all women—an abrupt exclusion from almost all honourable occupations except ones that others can’t perform or aren’t willing to perform. Sufferings arising from this cause usually meet with so little sympathy that few people realize how much unhappiness is produced, even now, by the feeling of a wasted life. This will happen even more frequently when increased cultivation [Mill’s word] creates a greater and greater disproportion between women’s ideas and abilities and the scope that society allows for their activity.

When we consider the positive evil caused to the disqualified half of the human race....first in the loss of •the most inspiriting and elevating kind of personal enjoyment, and then in the weariness, disappointment, and profound dissatisfaction with life that are so often the substitute for •it, one feels that among all the lessons that men [here = ‘human beings’] need to learn for carrying on the struggle against the inevitable imperfections of their lot on earth, no lesson is more needed than not to add to the evils that nature inflicts by their jealous and prejudiced restrictions on one another. Their stupid fears only substitute other and worse evils for the ones that they are lazily anxious about; while every restraint on the freedom of conduct of any of their human fellow-creatures (otherwise than by making them responsible for any evil actually caused by their conduct) does its bit towards drying up the principal fountain of human happiness, and leaves our species less rich....in all that makes life valuable to the individual human being.

60

A Review of the Principal Questions in Morals

Richard Price

Copyright ©2010–2015 All rights reserved. Jonathan Bennett
[Brackets] enclose editorial explanations. Small ·dots· enclose material that has been added, but can be read as though it were part of the original text. Occasional •bullets, and also indenting of passages that are not quotations, are meant as aids to grasping the structure of a sentence or a thought. Every four-point ellipsis .... indicates the omission of a brief passage that seems to present more difficulty than it is worth. Longer omissions are reported between brackets in normal-sized type. Price sometimes puts between sentences a dash like this—usually to indicate that the line of thought is changing direction a bit, but not enough to merit starting a new paragraph. Such dashes between sentences are all Price’s. So are all extra spaces between some pairs of paragraphs. Many of Price’s uses of the word ‘principle’ give it the meaning of ‘source’, ‘cause’, ‘drive’, ‘mechanism’ or the like. In this version, every occurrence of it in that sense of it will be written ‘principlec’, suggesting ‘principle = cause’. A ‘principle’ without the subscript is a proposition.
First launched: December 2008 Last amended: September 2009
[This single-column (but otherwise unrevised) version by Philosophy Ink derives from the original two-column PDF version at http://www.earlymoderntexts.com. Even Bennett's pagination has been retained since he sometimes makes in-text references to his own page numbers.]

Contents

Preface   1

Introduction   2

Chapter 1: The origin of our ideas of right and wrong   3

i: What is the question concerning the foundation of morals?...... 3

(ii): The origin of our ideas in general...... 6

iii: The origin of our ideas of moral right and wrong...... 20

Chapter 2: Our ideas of the beauty and ugliness of actions   29

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price

Chapter 3: The origin of our desires and affections   36

Chapter 4: Our ideas of good and ill desert   41

Chapter 5: How morality connects with God’s nature. The reliability of our faculties. The grounds of belief   44

Chapter 6: Fitness and moral obligation. Other accounts of obligation. How rightness relates to obligation. How other writers have expressed themselves when explaining morality   53

Chapter 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?   66

Chapter 8: The nature and essentials of virtue in practice as distinct from absolute virtue. From what principlec or motive does a virtuous agent act?   84

Chapter 9: What does it mean to say that some actions and characters are more virtuous than others? How do we judge this? Difficulties in the practice of virtue, the use of trial and discipline in getting reasonable beings to be virtuous, and the essentials of a good and bad character   97

Chapter 10: Using my account of morality to explain and support some of the principal doctrines of natural religion, particularly God’s moral attributes, his moral government, and a future state of rewards and punishments   110

Conclusion   124

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price Preface

Preface

I am well aware that this work comes to the public with many disadvantages, and at a time when it isn’t likely to get much attention from people. But the questions discussed in it are so important that if along with its many imperfections it has some merit, it can’t be badly timed and will probably get a candid and careful reading from some people. The Notes that I include are mainly a result of my having set this work aside for several years, during which time I intermittently revised it. –By far my greatest intellectual debt is to Dr. Butler, the late Bishop of Durham. Whenever I have been conscious of following him in something I write, I either mention him or quote his words; and I am careful to do the same with respect to other writers as well. [The present version omits many of the footnotes in which Butler and others are quoted.]

The part of this work that I most want you to attend to, and that needs attention, is chapter 1, especially its section ii. If I fail in that section, then I fail in what I primarily set out to achieve in this book. But I would be sorry if you reached that conclusion without first going through the whole thing and comparing the different parts of it—you’ll find that they have a considerable dependence on one another. [In Price’s day to ‘compare’ two things was not necessarily to liken them; it could be just to consider them together in order to see how they are related.] •The result I try to prove in chapter I section iii will seem obvious to readers who haven’t much studied the question of the foundation of morals, or who haven’t looked at it in the light that I have placed it in. So obvious, indeed, that I’m afraid that those readers will find it hard to avoid the conclusion that in taking so much trouble to establish •it I have merely been trifling [= ‘pointlessly fooling around’]. ·I sympathize with this view, because the •result in question ought to found obvious by everyone·. I’m talking about the thesis that right and wrong, or moral good and evil, signify something that is really true of actions and not merely of sensations. Recent controversies, and the doubts of some of the wisest men, have made it necessary to defend this view with many arguments. My own belief in it is so strong that I can’t help seeing it as a reproach to human reason that there is any need for these arguments.

1

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price Introduction

Introduction

The readers of a book have a right to pass judgment on its merits; and a writer who objects to this, or isn’t ready to face what comes of it, isn’t properly equipped to be a writer. But it is not satisfactory that readers generally pass judgment on a book without spending much time thinking about what it says. Very few subjects are so straightforward that a competent judgment of them can be reached without care and attention. So what are we to think of those whom we continually see making free with their opinions on matters they have never thought about, and dogmatically answering the most difficult questions without thought or study? If they are ever right about anything it can be only by chance! They speak and think entirely at random, and therefore don’t deserve to be taken seriously. As for those who do take some trouble to examine the issues, many even of them are as little entitled to be taken seriously; they are equally incompetent judges, equally careless and unthinking, and are led to their opinions by the most trifling arguments under the influence of passions that are harmful to the discovery of truth. It is a sad sight!

These considerations present a discouraging prospect to writers in general, and especially to ones who write on abstruse and controversial subjects. Most people don’t attend; they think quickly and carelessly, yet decide boldly; and they mostly like or dislike according to their pre-conceived notions and prejudices and not •according to reason or •guided by any close and impartial consideration. All this is so true that an author who allowed himself optimistic hopes of success—whatever he might think of his doctrines or his arguments—would probably be letting himself in for humiliation. I should add that we are generally as much inclined to •attach ourselves immoderately to our opinions as we are to •embrace them before thinking them out thoroughly.

Speaking for myself: I have such a sense of the truth of these remarks that there may be few people who are more pessimistic than I am about their chances of ever convincing one person that he has been guilty of error! The more we know of men, the more we find that in forming and maintaining their opinions they are governed by their temperaments, their interests, their moods and passions, and a thousand nameless causes and particular turns and casts of mind that •are bound to produce the greatest diversity of opinions among them and •make it impossible for them not to err. The fact is that none of us has the cool and calm temperament, the freedom from all wrong biases, the habit of attention and patience of thought, or the sharpness and competence in thinking, that are the proper guarantees against error. [Price quite often expresses emphatic assertions in the form of questions. Here is an example of that, and of the kind of way in which this version will often deal with such ‘questions’:]
Price’s next sentence: How much then do modesty and diffidence become us? how open ought we to be to conviction, and how candid to those of different sentiments?
How we should understand it: That is all the more reason for us to be •modest and cautious in our opinions, to be •open to having our minds changed, and to be •fair and open with those whose beliefs are different from our own.
Indeed, when you think about the various ways in which error can slide into our minds—

•the many latent prejudices by which we’re liable to be influenced,

2

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

•the countless facts about our own dispositions, and about the appearances of things, that can lead us astray without our noticing it, and

•the unavoidable darkness and infirmities of even the best and ablest men, often showing up in mistakes of the strangest kind

—such reflections are enough to lead a thinking man to distrust almost all his opinions.

But it would be unreasonable to go that far. Despite these difficulties and discouragements, •truth is still discoverable, and honest hard-working people can expect to have at least some success in their search for •it—at least on the most important points. The facts I have called attention to provide the strongest arguments for caution and care in enquiring, but none for despair or casual joking and lightly switching opinions. They shouldn’t make us sceptical, though they do demonstrate the folly of being dogmatic.

In this book most of the questions that are of any importance regarding morality and virtue will be considered—many in a different way from any previous treatment of them. I am somewhat shy about offering this work to the public because I am aware that it has many defects, and conscious of my liableness to the causes of blindness and error that I have mentioned. My principal aim has been to trace •the obligations of virtue up to •the truth and the nature of things, and these to •the Deity. The considerations I shall offer on this important matter have to a large extent satisfied my own mind, and this has led me to hope they may give some help to others enquiring into these matters.

Chapter 1

The origin of our ideas of right and wrong

In considering the actions of moral agents we have three different perceptions concerning them, and these must be carefully distinguished.

(1) Our perception of right and wrong.
(2) Our perception of beauty and ugliness. [chapter 2]
(3) What we express when we say what actions, for better or worse, deserve. [chapter 4]

I shall examine each of these perceptions separately, with special emphasis on the first, with which I shall begin....

i: What is the question concerning the foundation of morals?

[In Price’s day, to be ‘determined to’ do something was to be made or caused or led to do it.] There are some actions that we all feel ourselves irresistibly determined to approve, and others to disapprove. There are some that we can’t help thinking to be right, and others wrong. And of every action we are led to form some opinion—

•that it ought to be performed, item •that it ought not to be performed, or

3

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

•that it neither ought nor ought not to be performed—i.e. it is indifferent.

The question we are to consider is: What is the power within us that determines us to make these judgments?

A very distinguished writer, the late Dr. Hutcheson, derives our moral ideas from a ‘moral sense’, meaning by this a power within us, different from reason, which makes certain actions pleasing to us and others displeasing. Hutcheson’s view went like this [not a quotation from him]:

We are so made that certain impressions on our bodily organs arouse certain ideas in our minds, and certain outward forms when presented to us inevitably give rise to pleasure or pain. Similarly, we are so made that certain affections and actions of moral agents inevitably give rise to agreeable or disagreeable sensations in us, and get us to love or dislike them.

[•This work often uses ‘form’ to mean ‘action’, ‘item of behaviour’—a sense that the word has since lost. ‘Outward forms’ are simply bits of physical behaviour. Occasionally, e.g. on page 7, Price seems to use ‘forms’ for any kind of particular item, not necessarily a particular action. •In this work, as in other writings of the same period, ‘affection’ means something like ‘feeling that includes a desire or practical attitude’; see the paragraph starting ‘This may give...’ on page 39. An ‘affection’ (in this sense) might be full of hate.]
He has indeed well shown •that we have a faculty ·or power· that determines us immediately to approve or disapprove of actions, setting aside any thought of private advantage; and •that the highest pleasures of life depend on this faculty. If he had left it at that, meaning by ‘the moral sense’ nothing but our moral faculty in general, there would have been little to object to in his position. But then what he was saying wouldn’t have been anything new—he couldn’t have been regarded as the discoverer of it. ·Anyway, he didn’t ‘leave it at that’·. •His choice of the term ‘sense’ as a label for this faculty, •his rejection of all the arguments that have been used to show it to be an intellectual power, and •the whole of his language on this subject—all these make it clear that he regarded the moral faculty as an upshot of the way our minds are constructed, an implanted and arbitrary principlec that makes us like certain moral objects and dislike others, similar to the likes and dislikes created by our other senses. [Any principlec resulting from how our minds are constituted is ‘implanted’ in us by God, and is ‘arbitrary’ in the early modern sense of ‘chosen by someone’—in this case, chosen by God. It isn’t implied that the choice is capricious or unreasonable.] In other words, if Hutcheson is right then our ideas of morality have the same origin as our ideas of the sensible qualities of bodies, the harmony of sounds, or the beauties of painting or sculpture—namely God’s mere choice to make our mind and its organs responsive in a certain way to certain objects. [In Price’s day, ‘object’ often had an extremely broad meaning. Any item x—any item at all—could be called an ‘object’ in the context of ‘idea of x’, ‘think about x’, ‘respond to x’, ‘make a moral judgment about x’, ‘see or feel etc. x’, ‘have a belief about x’, ‘have a duty towards x’; e.g. ‘moral objects’ a few lines back, ‘objects that the understanding perceives to be contingent’ page 10.] According to those who accept this theory, virtue is a matter of taste. The moral terms ‘right’ and ‘wrong’ don’t stand for anything in the objects—·the actions or affections·—to which they are applied, any more than do ‘agreeable’ and ‘harsh’, ‘sweet’ and ‘bitter’, ‘pleasant’ and ‘painful’; all they signify are certain effects in us. Our perception of right (wrong) or moral good (bad) in actions is merely the agreeable (disagreeable) emotion or feeling that certain actions produce in us. They are particular states of our minds—impressions they are made to receive from contemplating certain actions, impressions that would have come from the contrary actions if the Author of nature had so chosen; and to suppose them to belong to those

4

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

actions themselves is as absurd as to ascribe the pleasure or unpleasure that comes from observing a particular form to the form itself. According to this account, therefore, it is improper to say of an action that ‘it is right’, in about the same way as it is improper to say of an object of taste that ‘it is sweet’ or of pain that ‘it is in fire’.

So this is the question that now confronts us: Is this a true account of virtue? Does it have a foundation in the nature of its object? Are right and wrong real features of actions or only qualities of our minds? In short, do ‘right’ and ‘wrong’ stand for •what actions are or only for •what sensations we get from actions because of the particular frame and structure of our natures?

Any attentive person who hasn’t already thought about this question will, I am sure, be surprised at its being a subject of dispute, and will think that there is no need for what I am going to undertake. I have given the naked and just state of it [that sentence is verbatim Price].... It is in fact the only question about the foundation of morals that can rationally and properly be made a subject of debate. We do have perceptions of moral ‘right’ and ‘wrong’, and those words must name either (1) the nature of the actions to which we apply them or (2) the nature of our feelings; and the power of perceiving them must be either (1) the power whose object is truth or (2) some implanted power or sense. If (1) is true, then morality is as unchangeable as all truth is; and if (2) is true, then morality is only what it appears to be to our senses, according to their various constitutions.

[We are about to meet the phrase ‘positive laws’. That means ‘laws that were laid down or ordained by someone’—it could be a human being or God.] As for theories that base morality on self-love, on positive laws and compacts, or on the Divine will: they must either

(a) mean that ‘morally good’ and ‘morally evil’ are only other words for ‘advantageous’ and ‘disadvantageous’, ‘willed’ and ‘forbidden’,

or else

(b) relate to a very different question—not to the question ‘What is the nature and true account of virtue?’ but ‘What is the subject-matter of virtue?’, i.e. what kinds of items are virtuous?’^1

To the extent that the theories I have mentioned intend (a), they afford little room for controversy. ‘Right’ and ‘wrong’, when applied to actions that are commanded or forbidden by the will of God, or that produce good or harm, don’t mean merely that such actions are commanded or forbidden, or that they are useful or hurtful. Rather, they express an opinion concerning them and our consequent approval or disapproval of the performance of them. If that were not so, it would be obviously absurd to ask whether it is right to obey a command or wrong to disobey it, ·or whether it is right to produce happiness·. The propositions Obeying a command is right or Producing happiness is right would be utterly trivial, because all they would mean is that obeying a command is obeying a command, or that producing happiness is producing happiness! Furthermore, on the supposition that ‘right’ and ‘wrong’ denote only the relations of actions to will and law, or to happiness and misery, there could be no dispute about the faculty that perceives right and wrong—it would have to be agreed by everything that these relations are objects of the investigations of reason.

Happiness requires something in its own nature or in ours to give it influence, and to make us want it and approve

^1 Bear in mind that the phrase ‘foundation of virtue’ is ambiguous. It may refer to (i) a consideration or principle implying virtue and proving it in particular cases, or (ii) a motive for the practice of virtue. I am using it in sense (i) only.

5

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

of pursuing it. Similarly, all laws, will, and compacts are effective only because of independent facts about what is right; so instead of being the constituents of right they owe their whole force and obligation to it.

After these preliminary remarks, I return to our question: What is the power ·or faculty· within us that perceives the distinctions of right and wrong?

My answer is. The understanding. [Price always treats ‘understanding’ and ‘reason’ as equivalent terms. See for example footnote 2. He also equates them with ‘intellect’ and with ‘intelligence’.]

To show that this is right, I must ·first· explore in detail the origin of our ideas in general, and the distinct domains of the understanding and of the senses.

(ii): The origin of our ideas in general

Sensation and reflection have commonly been regarded as the sources of all our ideas, and Locke went to a lot of trouble to prove this. Greatly as I admire his excellent Essay, I don’t think he was sufficiently clear or explicit on this subject. It is hard to work out exactly what he meant by ‘sensation’ and ‘reflection’. At the start of his Essay he said that sensation is the effects arising from the impressions made on our minds by external objects, and that reflection is the notice the mind takes of its own operations. If those are right, it will be impossible to derive some of the most important of our ideas from sensation or reflection. But what Locke mainly meant, probably, was that all our ideas are either •derived immediately from those two sources or •ultimately based on ideas that are derived from them; which is to say that they provide us with all the subjects, materials, and occasions of knowledge, comparison, and internal perception. This is far from saying that sensation and reflection are ‘the sources’ of all our ideas in any proper sense of ‘source’, ·but Locke seems to have thought otherwise·. Despite all that he had to say about the mind’s operations on its ideas, he doesn’t seem to have thought that we have any faculty other than sensation and reflection that •could give rise to any simple ideas, or •could do more than compounding, dividing, abstracting, or enlarging ideas that are already in the mind. Well, be this as it may, I believe that the ·rival· view that I am going to present will be found to be true.

I contend that we have a source of new ideas in •the power that understands, i.e. •the faculty within us that discerns truth, and that compares all the objects of thought and makes judgments concerning them.^2

Because the question before us is ‘Are our moral ideas derived from the understanding or from a sense?’, we need

^2 Please bear in mind that by ‘ideas’ I nearly always mean simple ideas, basic uncompounded perceptions of the mind. [An example of a ‘compounded perception of the mind’ is the idea of squareness, which is ‘compounded’ out of planeness, four-sidedness, rectangularity and equal-sidedness. An example of an uncompounded idea is the idea of redness, which is simple or uncompounded because there is no way of completing a definition of the form ‘for something to be red is for it to be—and...’.] I shall later be arguing that our ideas of right and wrong are of this sort. I should point out too that I am always using ‘the understanding’ in the most confined and proper sense of that phrase. Some writers have ·used it much more broadly·, dividing all the powers of the soul into •understanding and •will, so that ‘the understanding’ covers all the powers of external and internal sensation, as well as those of judging and reasoning....
The understanding performs actions of two kinds—intuition and deduction, I have in view intuition; but it’s obvious that the writers who argue against referring our moral ideas to reason usually have in mind only deduction. [‘Intuition’ as used here refers to seeing at a glance that necessarily P or that Q follows necessarily from P; while ‘deduction’ was seeing through a several-step argument that necessarily P or that Q follows necessarily from P.]

6

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

first to do something that hasn’t been given the attention it deserves, namely to say clearly how the nature and the domain of the senses differs from the nature and domain of reason. My first point about this is the following. The power that

•judges regarding the perceptions of the senses and contradicts their decisions, and that

•discovers the nature of the sensible qualities of objects, enquires into their causes, and distinguishes what is from what is not real in them,

must be a power within us that is superior to the senses.

It’s obvious that one sense cannot judge regarding the objects of another sense—the eye can’t judge harmony, or the ear judge colours. So the faculty that views and compares the objects of all the senses cannot itself be a sense. For example, when we consider sound and colour together, we observe in them •essence, •number, •identity, •diversity etc., and determine that their reality consists not in their being properties of external substances but in their being states of our souls. The power that takes note of all this and gives rise to these notions must be a power that can inspect anything and can acquaint itself with necessary truth and existence.

Sense consists in the way certain impressions force themselves upon us, independently of our wills; but it can’t perceive what they are or where they come from. Sense lies prostrate under its object [Price’s phrase]. Sense is only the soul’s capacity for having its own state altered by the influence of particular causes. So it remain a stranger to the objects and causes affecting it.

If sense and knowledge weren’t entirely different, we would settle for having sensible impressions—light, colours, sounds etc.–without enquiring any further into them, at least when the impressions were strong and vigorous. Whereas in fact we necessarily want some further acquaintance with them, and can’t ever be satisfied until we have subjected them to the survey of reason. ·Here are four large differences between these two faculties·. (1) Sense presents particular forms to the mind [see note on page 4], but it can’t rise to any general ideas. It’s the intellect that examines and compares the presented forms, rising above individuals to ·the level of· universal and abstract ideas. This enables it to look down on objects, getting an infinity of particulars into one view, and enables it to discover general truths. (2) Sense sees only the outside of things, whereas reason acquaints itself with their natures. (3) Sensation is only a kind of feeling in the mind, whereas knowledge implies an active and vital energy of the mind. Feeling pain, for example, is the effect of sense; but the understanding is employed when pain itself is made an object of the mind’s reflection, i.e. is held up before the mind in order to discover its nature and causes. Mere sense can’t perceive anything in the most exquisite work of art except what is painted in the eye [Price’s phrase]; it can’t, for example, see that this is a picture of a plant or an animal. It is the intellect that must perceive in the art-work order and proportion, variety and regularity, design, connection, skill, and power; aptitudes, dependences, correspondences, and the inter-relating of parts so as to serve a purpose, composing one perfect whole^3—things that can never be represented on a sense-organ, and the ideas of which can’t be passively communicated or stamped on the mind by the

^3 Cudworth in his Treatise of Eternal and Immutable Morality remarks that the mind is prompted by outer objects to perceive much more than is represented to it by sense, just as a learned man perceives in the best written book more than is perceived by an illiterate person or a non-human animal. [Price then quotes a long passage in which Cudworth likens a learned man’s ability to •read wonderful things in a book to a thinking person’s ability to •‘read’ God’s wisdom and goodness in the universe.

7

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

operation of external objects. (4) Sense cannot perceive any of the modes of thinking beings; these can be discovered only by the mind’s survey of itself. [Modes are properties or qualities of things. Not essential properties: a mind’s thinking isn’t a mode of it. But also not particular episodes: a particular stab of pain suffered by a mind wouldn’t be called a mode of it. Modes are universals; they are ways things can be.]

In short, we see that sense and understanding are totally different faculties of the soul—

•one dealing only with particulars, the other only with universals;

•one not discerning but suffering, the other not suffering but discerning.

[That involves a now rare sense of ‘suffer’ in which it means ‘passively undergo’. Price is contrasting the understanding which actively does things with the senses that only passively undergo or are on the receiving end of things.] Understanding is the soul’s power of surveying and examining all things, in order to make judgments about them....

To get a better idea of •how small the scope of sense is (and this applies also to imagination, a faculty closely related to sense) and •how greatly we depend on our higher thinking powers for many of our basic ideas, I shall discuss six such ideas.

(1) The idea of solidity has usually been counted among the ideas we owe to sense; but it might be hard to show that we ever have actual experience of impenetrability, which is an ingredient in our idea of solidity and is regarded as essential to all bodies. To show this we would have to be sure that we have at some time •made two bodies really touch and •found that they wouldn’t penetrate one another; but ·we aren’t entitled to be sure of that, because· all the facts we know by observation could be explained without supposing that it ever happens that two bodies are in absolute contact. And even if we could conduct that experiment, a single experiment couldn’t be a sufficient foundation for our absolute confidence that no two bodies can penetrate one another—nor indeed could a million experiments! Not to mention the fact that in any such experiment all we would perceive by our senses would be the •conjunction of two events, not their •necessary connection. [One event would be the coming into contact of the two bodies; the other, presumably, would be the bodies’ either staying in that position or bouncing back.] Are we then to that there isn’t any idea of impenetrability? That two atoms of matter could occupy the same place ·at the same time· while still keeping their distinct identities, neither of them annihilating the other? That all the atoms of matter in the universe could be crowded into the space now occupied by one? That the space occupied by these could become smaller and smaller, to infinity, without reducing at all the quantity of matter in the universe? We might have to say Yes to all of that, if it were certain that all our ideas about this are derived from sensation, and that reason had nothing to work on here except what is revealed by the senses. It often happens that two material substances appear to us to penetrate one another; and it is our reason which, on the basis of its own perceptions, concludes that those are misleading appearances and assures us of the universal and strict necessity of the contrary. The same power that perceives two particles to be •different also perceives them to be •impenetrable, because they can’t be different without being impenetrable; it is self-evident that they can’t occupy the same place ·at the same time· without losing all difference ·from one another·.

(2) Now let us consider inertia, i.e. the inactivity of matter. This too is a perception of reason rather than an idea conveyed to the mind by the senses. This property of matter is the basis for all our reasoning about it. To those who reject

8

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

it, or who insist that all our knowledge of matter and motion must come from experience, i.e. the information conveyed to the mind through the senses, I put a question concerning the three axioms (or laws of motion) on which Sir Isaac Newton bases his philosophy: are they unsupported by evidence and devoid of meaning?—What is it that tells us that every body will continue for ever in the state of rest or motion it is in unless something produces an alteration of that state? that every alteration of a body’s motion must be proportional to the force exerted on it and in the same line of direction as that force? and that a body’s action on another body is always equal and contrary to the other body’s action on it? In other words, what gives us our ideas of resistance and inactivity? Not experience! [Price now says that untutored sense-experience would seem to suggest that Newton’s three laws are false. He continues:] Ideas so •contradictory to sense cannot be •derived from it. So they must be ascribed to a higher origin, ·namely, the understanding·.

And another point: suppose that Newton’s laws were constantly illustrated by experience as well as by the perceptions of reason, the backed-by-experience version of them would have to be very different from the backed-by-reason version which is what they actually are. Even if experience and observation taught us always that the alteration of motion in a body is proportional to the force acting on it and is in the line of direction in which this force acts, the senses could only teach us this very imperfectly—they couldn’t inform us of it with precision and exactness. They could only show us that what this law states is nearly the case, which is the same, strictly speaking, as its not being the case! The eye of sense is blunt. The conceptions of the imagination are rough and ready, falling infinitely short of the certainty, accuracy, universality, and clarity that belong to intellectual discernment.

(3) The idea of substance, similarly, is one to which our minds are necessarily carried, beyond what is suggested by mere sensation, which can show us nothing but accidents, sensible qualities, and the outsides of things. It is the understanding that discovers the general distinction between substance and accident [= ‘between things and their properties’], ·and there is no doubt that it gets this right·. There couldn’t be a more unavoidable perception than that motion implies something that moves, extension implies something extended, and in general modes imply something modified.

[Although Price does not say so, the next paragraph was written with one eye on what Locke wrote in Essay II.xiv.3: ‘There is a sequence of ideas constantly following one another in our mind.... Reflection on these appearances of various ideas one after another is what provides us with the idea of succession; and the distance between two any parts of that sequence, i.e. between the appearance of any two ideas in our minds, is what we call duration.’ This makes succession basic and duration derivative from it; Price reverses that.]

(4) The idea of duration accompanies all our ideas; it is included in every notion we can form of reality and existence. What is suggested by the observation of the sequence of thoughts following one another in our minds, or the constant flux of external objects, is succession. This, like every other idea, presupposes the idea of duration; but it is as different from it as are the ideas of motion and shape. Rather than saying ·as Locke did· that the idea of duration is derived from that of succession, I think it would have been better to say that reflecting on the succession of ideas in our minds is the basis for our estimate of how much duration has intervened between two events.

(5) Similar remarks can be made regarding ·the idea of· space. Like duration, this is included in every reflection we can make about our own existence or that of other

9

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

things; because it’s self-evident that saying that something is nowhere is the same as saying that it doesn’t exist. Like everything else that exists at all, we exist in •time and •place; so that as self-conscious and thinking beings we must have ideas of •them.

Another point worth making about space and duration is that we perceive intuitively [see note on page 6] their necessary existence. The notion of annihilation is the notion of removing a thing from space and duration; to suppose that space and duration might be annihilated is to suppose that they might be separated from themselves! In the same intuitive manner we perceive they can have no limits, and from this we get the idea of infinity.
what Price wrote next: The very notion of bounds implies them, and therefore cannot be applicable to them, unless they could be bounded by themselves.
what he meant: The notion of x’s being limited in space (time) involves the notion of there being space (time) outside the limit—the space (time) that x is limited by. So the notion of space (time) itself being limited involves the ·absurd· notion of space (time) being limited by space (time) outside the limit. These perceptions are plainly the result of the understanding’s attention to necessary truth; and the account of how we come by our ideas of infinity and necessity in time and space.... also applies to how we come by our ideas of any other self-evident reality—e.g. of the equality between the opposite angles of two lines crossing one another, or of the identity of any particular object while it continues to exist.

There are other objects [see note on page 4] that the understanding perceives just as evidently to be contingent, or whose existence it sees to be not necessary but only possible.

Thus, the understanding, by attending to different objects and observing what is or is not true of them, acquires the ideas of necessity, infinity, contingency, possibility, and impossibility.

(6) The next ideas I shall discuss are those of power and causation. Some of the ideas mentioned above imply them; but we should attend to them separately and with care. At first sight it may seem utterly obvious that one way in which they get into our mind is by our observing the various changes that happen in our environment, and our constant experience of the events that occur when external objects are made to interact in this or that specific manner. [Thus Locke, Essay II.xxi.1.] And yet I am quite convinced that these ideas can’t possibly be given to us by this experience alone.

What we observe by our external senses is, strictly speaking, merely that one thing follows another,^4 or the constant conjunction of certain events.... That one thing is the cause of another, or produces it, we never see. And in countless instances where men commonly think they observe causation at work it isn’t at work! Suppose that nothing ever did contribute through its own force to the production of any new event; suppose (that is) that the apparent causes of things were never their causes but always only their occasions or concomitants;.... we would still have the same ideas of cause, and effect, and power ·as we do have now·. Our certainty that every new event requires some cause doesn’t depend on our experience any more than does any other intuitively known truth. The idea of every change includes within it the idea of its being an effect.

The necessity that everything that happens should have a cause is an essential principle, a primary perception of the

^4 Malebranche says various things to that effect; he is well know to have maintained that nothing in nature is ever the proper cause of anything else, only the occasion; according to him, God is the sole agent ·or cause· of all effects and events. Hume has even more strongly emphasized that all we perceive is events following (·not causing·) one another, though with a different purpose.

10

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

understanding. Nothing is more obviously absurd than the notion of

•a change that has been derived from nothing,

•a change for which there is no reason,

•an existence that began but was never produced,

•a body that has ceased moving but hasn’t been stopped.

•a body that has begun to move but hasn’t been moved.

If someone says he denies this, nothing can be done to convince him except referring him to common sense. If he can’t find there the perception I have mentioned, there can be no further argument with him, because the subject doesn’t admit of argument. ·Why doesn’t it?· Because there isn’t anything more clearly true than the proposition in question, so there’s nothing we can bring forward to support it. Someone might say: ‘We do indeed have such a perception, but it comes from some power other than the understanding, ·so that our having it isn’t a reason to think it true·’, but then I would demand to know why he doesn’t say the same thing about all self-evident truth!

I have not said that we have no idea of power except from the understanding.
what Price wrote next: Activity and self-determination are as essential to spirit as the contrary are to matter;
what he meant: We are active; we get ourselves to move; and this is as essential to minds as it is essential to matter that it is passive and doesn’t move unless something else moves it;
so our inward consciousness gives us the idea of the •particular sort of power implied in activity and selfdetermination. But the •universal source of the idea of

•power, as we conceive it to be necessary to the production of everything that happens,

and of

•our notions of influence, connection, aptitude, and dependence in general,

must be the understanding. Some active or passive powers, some capacities for making changes or for being changed, are an essential part of our ideas of all objects. (These powers differ according to the different natures of the objects and the different relations amongst them.) An item that •can’t do anything, that •isn’t fit to serve any purpose, and •has no kind of dependence or aptitude or power belonging to it, can’t be anything real or substantial. If all things were wholly unconnected and loose, if no one event or object ever, in any circumstances, implied anything beyond itself, all the foundations of knowledge would be destroyed. Everyone agrees that things don’t appear to us as loose and unconnected, and that in countless instances we can’t help regarding them as connected and inferring one from another. Why shouldn’t this be accounted for by a real connection between the things themselves? Can there be anyone who thinks that there’s no real connection, perceivable by reason, between •having an honest mind and •acting justly, or between •certain collisions and •changes in how bodies move?

Indeed, the whole meaning of ‘accounting for’ [= ‘explaining’] a fact implies that in the nature of objects and events there is something that involves a connection between them, or a fitness to influence one another in certain ways. Until we can discover this ‘something’ we are always aware that there’s more to be known. For as long as we only see one thing constantly accompanying or following another, without perceiving the real dependence and connection (as with gravitation, and the sensations that accompany certain impressions on our bodily organs), we can’t help being dissatisfied. Our state of mind about that is very different from the complete acceptance that we experience when we think about Newton’s laws of motion or any other facts in

11

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

which we see the necessary connection and truth.

We always find that when we have adequate ideas of the natures and properties of any beings or objects, we at the same time perceive their powers and can predict, independently of experience, what they will produce in given circumstances and what will follow their interacting with one another in given ways. If we were thoroughly acquainted with the heart of a man, the nature of his temperament, and the structure of his mind, we wouldn’t need experience to tell us what he will do or how far he is to be trusted. Similarly, if we knew the inward fabric and constitution [or, as we might say, the molecular stucture] of the bodies surrounding us on which all their properties and powers depend, we would know in advance what the result would be of any experiments we could make with them. Just as from having a complete idea of the real essence of a circle we can deduce its various properties that depend on that essence.... And if we had perfect insight into the constitution of nature—the laws that govern it and the motions, texture, and relations of all the bodies that compose it—the whole chain of future events in it would be laid open to us. Experience and observation are useful only when we are ignorant of the nature of the object, and can’t in a more perfect, short, and certain way determine what the outcome will be of particular experiments, and what are the uses of particular objects.^5 Instinct is an even lower and more imperfect means of making up for the same lack of knowledge.

With regard to all the ideas I have been discussing, and particularly (6) causation, it is worth pointing out that even if it were as difficult to discover their true origin as it is to derive them from the sources commonly assigned to them by writers on these subjects, it would surely still be very unreasonable to conclude that we have no such ideas. And yet that’s the very conclusion some have drawn! If then we do indeed have such ideas; and if they have a foundation in truth and are ideas of something that really exists, what difficulty can there be in allowing that they may be known to ·the understanding·, the faculty whose object is truth? If we don’t have any such ideas, or if they denote nothing real except the qualities of our own minds, I needn’t say what an abyss of scepticism that will plunge us into.

Let me add, finally, that our abstract ideas seem most properly to belong to the understanding. They’re undoubtedly essential to all its operations, because every act of

^5 The conviction produced by experience is based on the same principle that assures us that there must be a cause of every event and some explanation of whatever happens. The frequent repetition of a particular event, e.g. the falling of a heavy body to the earth, makes us expect that it will happen again in future trials: Because we see intuitively that because there is some reason or cause for this constancy of outcome it must be derived from a cause that operates regularly and constantly in given circumstances. On the same principle, if we observed a die being thrown very often and always falling with ‘6’ uppermost, we would conclude that the same thing would happen with any future throws of this die. And the more frequently and uninterruptedly we knew this had happened, the stronger would be our expectation of its happening again, because the more evident it would be that either •the die was marked ‘6’ on every side or •the thrower had some special skill or •there was something in the die’s constitution that made it turn with ‘6’ uppermost.—I have a suggestion—a surprising one, but I think it is true—about why some people have doubts and difficulties with this and some other points of the clearest nature. It is that when they say:

‘It is not reason that informs us that there must be some explanation of everything that happens and some established causes of constant and uniform events, and that order and regularity must come from design’

what they mean is that these propositions can’t be established by deduction. They are right about that, but only because the propositions are self-evident, ·known by intuition·, so plain that there is nothing plainer from which they can be inferred!

12

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

judgment implies some abstract or universal idea. For them to be formed by the mind in the way they are generally said to be, it seems that the mind would have to have them already at the very time when it is supposed to be busy forming them. We are told, for example, that from any particular idea of a triangle we can form the ·abstract· general one; but doesn’t the thought process required by this.... imply that the general idea is already in the mind? If it isn’t, how can the mind know how to go to work, or what to think about?—Some have held that a universal idea isn’t a special kind of idea, but rather an ordinary idea associated with a name that signifies a number of particular ideas resembling that one; but this can’t be right, because unless we have a ·genuinely· universal idea we can’t know which other ideas to allow into the group signified by the name, i.e. which particular objects had the resemblance necessary to bring them within the meaning of the name. Someone who reads a geometrical demonstration is aware that it relates to •something more than just the precise figure presented in the diagram. But if he doesn’t know •what more, what use is the demonstration to him? How is his knowledge enlarged by it? How will he know afterwards what to apply it to?—It is true •that everything pictured in the imagination, and everything we observe by our senses, is particular; and •that while any general notions are present in the mind, the imagination is usually busy representing to itself some of the particulars that fall under them. But it would be strange to infer from this that the only ideas we have are particular ideas! That wouldn’t be much better than inferring from the fact that

•things are so tightly associated in our minds with their names that we can’t separate them from their names

that

•our only notion of any thing is an idea of is name.

Or inferring from the fact that

•whenever we think about the sun, we are apt to have an image of a white bright circle

that

•our only notion of the sun is the idea of a white bright circle.

[At this point Price has a long footnote, which is here raised into the main text:]
START OF REID’S FOOTNOTE

According to Cudworth, abstract ideas are implied in the cognitive power of the mind, which (he says) contains potentially within itself general notions of all things, notions that unfold and reveal themselves as proper circumstances occur—in much the way a future tree is potentially contained in a seed. I don’t agree with those who condemn this as whimsical and extravagant, but I wouldn’t like to have to defend it!....

Cudworth rejects as very absurd the opinion that universal ideas are formed out of particular ones by separating things’ common properties from the ones that individuate them from one another; he says that it comes from a misunderstanding of Aristotle. As for the other opinion that

•universal ideas are only singular ideas tied to a common term, i.e. they are names without any meaning

—a view that used to be accepted by the appropriately named Nominalists [from Latin nomen = ‘name’], and has recently been revived—he says that this is so ridiculously false that it doesn’t deserve to be argued against. [Price now quotes a longish passage in which Cudworth starts from the premise that God can ‘signify his will to men’, who can ‘signify their wants to God’. It would be an incredible coincidence if the ideas involved in such communications had one source for God and a different source for man. If we credit God with deriving his ideas from something other than himself, ‘we

13

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

quietly fall into a kind of atheism’. So we have to think that God’s mind generates its own ideas, which makes it reasonable to think that our ideas are made in our minds and don’t owe anything to the world of matter. [Price now ends the footnote with another quotation from Cudworth:]
‘The philosophers whose ideas of being and knowledge are derived from body and sensation have a short method to explain the nature of truth. It is an invented thing made by every man for himself, which comes and goes, i.e. is remembered and forgotten. In the ·metaphysical· order of things truth comes at the bottom, not only below objects that we see and feel but even below our sensations of them.... Other reasoners.... represent truth not as the lowest but as the highest of beings; they call it immutable, eternal, omnipresent—attributes which all indicate something more than human.... For my part, when I read the detail about sensation and reflection, and learn the main outlines of how my ideas are all generated, I seem to view the human soul as resembling a crucible in which truths are produced by a kind of logical chemistry.’
END OF THE FOOTNOTE
It is a fatal error that people run into when they confuse the understanding with the imagination, and deny reality and possibility to anything that the imagination can’t represent, however clear and certain it is to the understanding. The powers of the imagination are very narrow; if the understanding were confined to the same limits, nothing could be known and the understanding itself would be annihilated.—It is utterly obvious that one of these ·faculties· often perceives where the other is blind, is surrounded with light where the other finds only darkness, and in countless cases knows things to exist of which the other can’t form any idea. Of course the imagination can’t represent to itself matter without colour; but that is how it is perceived by the understanding, which announces without doubt or hesitation that colour is not a property of matter. Points, lines and surfaces, as mathematicians consider them, are entirely intellectual objects—never picked up by the senses and inconceivable to the imagination. Does this imply that there are no such things? Are we to believe that there cannot be any particles of matter smaller than we can imagine to ourselves, or that there is no degree of equality except what can be judged by the eye? This has been maintained! And on the same principles we must go on to say that

the mind itself and its operations are just what they appear to everyone’s reflection; it isn’t possible for us to go wrong in our thinking about what we have formerly done or thought, or what we will do or think in the future.

What an unattractive philosophy it is that thus explodes all independent truth and reality, reduces knowledge to particular states of sense and imagination, making these the measures of all things!

Here is an example of the stock of knowledge and new ideas that the understanding can derive from one object of contemplation.

Let us suppose someone who is sensorily confronted by one cubic inch of matter. If he has no intellect, he will stick for ever with that individual sense-perceptible object, never getting to anything more than what it immediately presents to him. Now add intellect, and let us observe what follows.

First, there will appear the ideas of •thing, •possibility, and •actual existence. Because every perception is the perception of something, it implies some kind of reality distinct from and independent of itself. ‘Might not the perception be a perception of itself?’ Nothing could be more grossly absurd than that! If it were right, any examination might be identical with the thing being examined—the eye identical with visible

14

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

objects; memory with the fact remembered, desire with the object desired. And yet this absurdity seems to be the basis for a system of scepticism that has been lately taught to the world.

I needn’t labour this. Every idea implies the possibility of the actual existence of its object; nothing being clearer than that there can’t be any idea of an impossibility, a conception of what cannot exist. These are obviously true intuitions of the intellectual faculty, which is unavoidably led to then by every object it thinks about.

[In the third edition—20 years after the first—Price appended an end-note relating to what he has just said.]
·START OF END-NOTE·
Dr. Reid, in his very valuable work on the intellectual powers of man, disputes this assertion (4th Essay, chapter 3). His principal reasons seem to be (a) that we can understand a proposition that expresses what is impossible, and (b) that in mathematical demonstrations we are often directed to suppose what is impossible. (b) But supposing is not the same as conceiving. I can be directed to •suppose any absurdity, but it doesn’t follow from this that I can •conceive any absurdity. A believer in transubstantiation may •suppose that Christ held his own body in his hand and gave it to his disciples; but if he claimed to have a clear and distinct •conception of this he would be making himself as ridiculous as if he were to say that he saw it happen.

(a) And a man can •understand what is meant by a proposition that expresses an impossibility—e.g. ‘The whole of something is smaller than a part of it’. But he certainly doesn’t have any real •conception of this. He may think he has a clear •idea of an object when in fact he doesn’t, just as he may think that he has a clear •perception of an object when in fact he doesn’t perceive it. But just as in the latter case

•he must believe in the existence of what he thinks he perceives,

so in the former case

•he must believe in the possibility of what he thinks he conceives.

I must emphasize that my topic here is the conception of objects and not the understanding of propositions. Because impossibilities are not realities, conceptions of them would be conceptions of nothing.
·END OF END-NOTE·

·Continuing with the account of what the understanding can extract from a cubic inch of matter·: We may next observe that the possibility of the existence of matter implies the actual existence of space. Without space, matter could not be possible, nor could there be any idea of it. And our grasp of space’s status as necessary and inseparable from the idea of matter is our grasp of the necessary existence of space. And once we have the idea of space, we perceive its infinity.—From the idea of matter we are in the same way informed of the necessary existence of duration. By further examining our supposed portion of matter we shall find that we can conceive, without contradiction, of one part of it as being in one place and another part in another place, and that consequently it is divisible. For the same reason it will appear that this division can be continued, and that an intelligent mind can penetrate so far beyond all the boundaries of imagination that it perceives that there certainly can be no end to this division—which is to say that matter is infinitely divisible.

[In the third edition Price appended an end-note confessing (not a change of view, but) a loss of confidence.]

15

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

·START OF END-NOTE·
This property of matter—·infinite divisibility·—convinces me that I don’t know what it is, and that the common ideas of it are extremely inadequate. The Scholastic maxim Every entity is one seems to me indisputable. What could something be that was neither •one thing nor any •number of things?

Isn’t it absurd to say that one thing was moved by another, which was moved by another, and so on backwards to infinity, without any first mover? And isn’t it equally absurd to say that a particle of matter can be divided into other particles, which can be divided into others, and so on downwards to infinity, without ever coming to a particle that is properly one—·meaning a particle that is indivisible·?

You might want to try this: ‘There are atoms that have no pores, and therefore can’t be divided except by the power of the Creator.’ But such an atom would have parts, and it would be possible that one part should exist in one place and another part in another place; so that this ‘atom’ would really be a multitude of atoms, just as if its parts were actually separated. Whatever is really one can’t be divided without being annihilated. This is true of the being that each person calls himself. No-one can conceive of half of himself.

Those are the difficulties that press my mind with respect to the nature of matter. But they have no effect on my belief in the existence of a material world. In this case, as in countless others, I feel my own ignorance, without being led to reject convictions that I am forced to accept without being able to explain them. ·Here is one of the other cases·: I know that my will moves my limbs. There is nothing more familiar to me—and nothing that I understand less!
·END OF END-NOTE·
From the same source—·our supposed piece of matter·—the understanding can further gain the ideas of •cause and effect, and •connection. Let it conceive of two of the separated parts as moving in a direct line towards one another, and consider what would follow. Because it can’t conceive them to pass through one another, the understanding will unavoidably conclude that there will be contact and impulse [= ‘a collision’], and also (as necessarily connected with these) some change in the motions of the colliding bodies.—To avoid these conclusions one would have to suppose that two bodies can

•penetrate one another, or

•move towards one another without meeting and pushing, or

•push one another without altering how they move or having any other effect.

Someone who has no difficulty conceiving any of those—well, what criterion can he be using to judge concerning what is true or false? and why will he refuse his assent to any absurdity that can be put to him?

But not only would the mind [here = ‘the understanding’] thus perceive causation and necessary connection, but ·it could also make predictions on that basis·. Given the direction and momentum of the moving bodies before the collision, it could foretell the precise change of direction and momentum that the collision would produce; and could go on from that to working out—a priori and with no possibility of error—all the laws and effects of •the collision of bodies, •the division and composition of motions, and •the resistance of fluids and centripetal forces, as they have been investigated by natural scientists.

And it is obvious that with this as a foundation the mind would gain the ideas of number and proportion, and lines and figures; and could proceed to arithmetic, geometry, and all the different branches of mathematics.—In short, from this single subject of enquiry—·the cubic inch of matter that we started out with·—the mind can learn not only the elements and principles but the main part of the whole body

16

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

of science.—Such is the fruitfulness of reason, and so great the injury it suffers by being kept within the limits of sense, imagination, or experience.^6

When I consider these things I am amazed that people who are enquiring into the origin of our ideas overlook the understanding; although it isn’t the temporally first of our idea-sources it is the most important source of them. It has indeed always been regarded as the source of •knowledge; but there has been too much neglect of the fact that it couldn’t be a source of knowledge without also being a source of new ideas. The various kinds of •agreement and •disagreement between our ideas, which Locke says it is the understanding’s job to discover and trace, are so many new simple ideas obtained by the understanding’s discernment [Price’s word]. Thus, when the understanding considers the two angles made by a straight line meeting another straight line, and perceives that they agree with two right angles, isn’t this agreement simply (i) equality? And isn’t the idea of (ii) this equality a new simple idea that the understanding has acquired, completely different from the ideas of the two angles, and denoting (iii) self-evident truth? [In that sentence, Price seems to move from (i) the idea of equality to (ii) the idea of the equality of those two angles and from that to (iii) the proposition that the two angles are equal.]—In much the same way in other cases,...
how Price finished this sentence:... knowledge and intuition suppose somewhat perceived in their objects, denoting simple ideas to which themselves gave rise.
what he meant:... we know by intuition—·i.e. by seeing it as self-evident·—some truth about something, a truth involving an idea that the understanding comes to have through having this very intuition.
—This is true of our ideas of proportion, of our ideas of identity and diversity, existence, connection, cause and effect, power, possibility and impossibility; and—jumping ahead to something I shall discuss fully later on—our ideas of moral right and wrong. Proportion concerns quantity; right and wrong concern actions; and all the others concern everything. They are involved in the most considerable part of what we can want to know about things, and are the topics of most reasonings and treatises. [Reid has a long footnote here, which is raised into the main text.]
·START OF REID’S FOOTNOTE·
[The footnote quotes Socrates (in Greek) as accepting the general line Price has been taking here, including this:] ‘For the perception of these things, a different organ or faculty is not appointed, but the soul itself in virtue of its own power observes these general states of all things.’.... James Harris writes in his book Hermes: ‘Notice the order of things according to our later metaphysicians. •First comes that huge body, the sensible world. •Then this world and its

^6 And so false is the scholastic maxim There is nothing in the intellect that wasn’t first in the senses.—Something that is relevant to this, though not directly relevant to my purposes in this chapter, is worth notice. It is the case, mentioned by Locke, of the man had been born blind, gained his sight, and was then required to distinguish between a globe and cube just by looking at them. I agree that this man wouldn’t be able •readily or immediately to say which was the globe and which the cube, but it seems certain that •with the help of a little reflection he could tell which was which. First, let us vary the example and suppose that the born-blind man is confronted with—instead of the •globe and cube—a •square and a rectangular parallelogram of unequal sides. To both senses, touch and sight, the sides of one would appear equal and of the other unequal. So why should it be hard for him to determine that what he saw with equal sides was the square, and with unequal the oblong? Could he possibly suspect that sight is so fallacious a sense that it represents the most unequal things as equal, or represents a great multitude of things as one and vice versa? In the same way he could distinguish between a square and a circle, and therefore between a globe and a cube; and in this and many other cases he could determine how something he •saw would •feel, doing this before having any experience of feeling the item in question....

17

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

attributes beget sensible ideas. •Then a kind of lopping and pruning of sensible ideas creates intelligible ideas, both specific and general. Thus, if they admitted that the mind came into existence at the same time as the body, until the body gave the mind ideas and awakened its dormant powers, it could at best have been merely a sort of dead capacity; for it couldn’t possibly have any innate ideas—·i.e. ideas that it had when it first came into existence·.—At another time we hear of bodies so exceedingly fine that their very fineness makes them capable of having sensation and knowledge, as if they had shrunk into intellect by their exquisite subtlety, which made them too delicate to be bodies any longer. But the intellectual scheme that never forgets •God regards every corporeal thing as coming from the primary mental •Cause. That is where it looks for the origin of intelligible ideas, even the ones that human beings have. Sensible objects may be God’s chosen medium to awaken the dormant energies of man’s understanding, but those energies themselves aren’t contained in sense, any more than the explosion of a cannon is contained in the spark that set it off.’
·END OF REID’S FOOTNOTE·

In short. Just as bodily sight reveals visible objects to us, the understanding (the eye of the mind, and infinitely more penetrating ·than the bodily eye·) reveals intelligible objects to us. And just as bodily vision is the inlet through which ideas enter the mind, so the understanding becomes the inlet of new ideas that the senses cannot provide....

For several reasons, the classification of our ideas that I like best is the following.

(1) First, ideas that imply nothing real outside the mind, i.e. nothing real apart from the mind’s own feelings and sensations.

(2) Secondly, ideas that denote something distinct from sensation, and imply real and mind-independent existence and truth.

Each of these classes can be further subdivided: The first class into (1a) ideas that denote the immediate effects of impressions on the bodily senses without presupposing any previous ideas, e.g. all tastes, smells, colours, and so on, and (1b) ideas that arise only when prompted by other ideas, e.g. the effects in us of experiencing or thinking about order, happiness, and the beauties of poetry, sculpture, painting, and so on.

The second class can be subdivided into (2a) ideas that denote real properties of external objects, and the actions and passions of the mind, and (2b) those that I have described as derived immediately from intelligence. (2a) From the information that reaches •it through the organs of the body, and from •its observation of the necessary accompaniments of certain sensations and impressions, •the mind perceives the shape, extension, motion, and other primary qualities of material substances. By contemplating itself, it perceives the properties of spiritual substances, volition, consciousness, memory, and so on. It is essential to each of these ideas that it has an invariable archetype that actually exists and that it is supposed to fit.^7utcheson is right when he says that extension, shape, motion and so on are more properly •ideas accompanying the sensations of sight and touch than •sensations of sight and touch. I think it would be best never to give the name ‘ideas’ to sensations themselves, any more than we call volitions or desires ‘ideas’; but to confine the word to the mind’s conception of or notice of any object. According to that usage, then, an idea would always imply something distinct from itself, ·namely its object· [see the note

^7 H

18

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

on page 4], and the proper classification of our ideas would sort them according to their different objects—•those whose objects are matter and spirit and their qualities, •·those whose objects are· •the general contingent qualities of all things, and •·those whose objects are· necessary truths....

In short. There are three senses in which the word ‘idea’ has been used: (1) It has been used to signify sensation itself, so that tastes, sounds and colours are often called ‘ideas’. There is no justification for using the word in this way. (2) It is also used to signify the mind’s conception or apprehension of any object. I regard this as the soundest and most proper sense. (3) It is also used to signify the immediate object of the mind in thinking. This third sense of ‘idea’ comes from the notion that when we think of any object there is something immediately present to the mind that it perceives and contemplates. But what is this? Shall we call it a representation or image of the object? This, I think, is improper language. Must we then deny the existence of an immediate object of the mind in thinking? When an abstract truth is contemplated, isn’t the very object itself present to the mind? When millions of intellects contemplate the equality of every angle in a semicircle to a right angle, don’t they all have the same object in view? Is this object nothing?

[Strictly, an ‘archetype’ is something from which copies are made, but Price here means only that each idea is of something other than itself, something that it fits, something that it is accurately of; he probably doesn’t think that either ‘x is y’s archetype’ or ‘y fits x’ means that y resembles x in some way. Why is the archetype ‘invariable’? Because Price is thinking not of (say) the idea of this ball that I hold in my hand but rather of the idea of sphericalness, an unchanging universal property.] (2b) After the mind has been provided with •ideas of objects—from whatever causes—•those ideas themselves become objects for our intellectual faculty, and from this there arises a new set of ideas that are the perceptions of this faculty. Until that happens we may be provided with many ideas but we don’t understand anything. Whatever subjects of knowledge there may be in the mind, nothing is known.

[In the third edition Price appended an end-note relating to what he has just said.]
·START OF END-NOTE·
Notice that I have all along tried to avoid speaking of an idea as the mind’s image of the object we are thinking of. It is difficult not to fall sometimes into language of this kind; but it can be misunderstood. The deeply reflective Reid has accused it of laying the foundation of all modern scepticism.

I am always upset when I find that my opinions differ from Reid’s. According to Hume, •the immediate object of the mind in perception is •the perception itself—which annihilates all external existence. Reid, if I understand him, asserts.... that there is no such object, and thus seems to me to annihilate all perception! When we investigate the properties of triangles or circles, aren’t there present to our minds at that time objects that don’t depend on our minds? ·Of course there are, and· we call these objects ‘ideas’. Because this word usually signifies the apprehension or conception of an object, it oughtn’t to be used to signify the object itself; but the poverty of language obliges us to do this, so it must be excused and care must be taken not to be misled by it, as I think Hume and some other writers have been.

In such cases, I have said, we call the objects present to our minds ‘ideas’. If ideas have no existence, and nothing is present to our minds when we contemplate these objects, doesn’t it follow that we then don’t contemplate anything? The same question arises about our perception of external objects. Since these objects are not themselves present ·to

19

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

our minds· when we perceive them, they must be perceived through ideas of them. And it doesn’t follow from this that we can’t be sure of the existence of external objects. All ideas imply the possibility of the existence of objects corresponding to them, and our belief in the actual existence of the objects of sense can be understood (as it is by Reid) as:

•impressions on our senses forcing belief ·on us· at the moment of the impression, in a manner that we can’t explain.

And this goes through better •with the supposition of ideas than •without it. Why? Because scepticism seems to be less favoured by supposing that in sense-perception something distinct from the mind and independent of it really is perceived than by supposing that in sense-perception nothing is perceived. [Price concludes this end-note by saying that the unavoidable question ‘In sense-perception, what is it that is present to our minds?’ has to be answered in a way that brings God into the story, implying that God is present with us and that we depend on him] more closely and constantly and necessarily than we are apt to suspect or can easily believe.
·END OF END-NOTE·
Of all the kinds of ideas I have mentioned, the ones derived from the external senses are what non-human animals seem mainly to have, and perhaps they have no others. They think, and will, and remember; but aren’t capable of attending reflexively to these ·operations· so as to obtain ideas of them. They can hear all the sounds in music, and see all the lines and colours in a picture; but they don’t perceive harmony or beauty. So it seems that all the ideas based on •inward reflection, on •a previous assemblage and comparison of ideas, and on •intelligence, are to a large extent restricted to us humans.

Before we leave this topic it is important that I make this clear: The source of ideas that I have been emphasising—·which I have variously referred to as ‘understanding’, ‘reason’, ‘intellect’ and ‘the mind’·—is different from the power of reasoning, and mustn’t be confused with it. Reasoning is investigating certain relations between objects, ideas of which must already be in the mind; so it can’t give rise to new ideas. No mind can be engaged in

•investigating it knows not what, or

•trying to learn something about an object of which it has no conception.

What happens with regard to ideas such as those of proportion, identity, connection and so on is that •first we get these ideas from the view of objects to which they belong self-evidently, and •then we employ deduction or reasoning to track down proportions, identities etc. in other contexts where they can’t be perceived immediately.

iii: The origin of our ideas of moral right and wrong

[Re the use of ‘simple’ in this paragraph, see the note in footnote 2.]
Let us now return to our original question and apply the things I have been saying to our ideas of right and wrong in particular. It has to be grasped from the outset that our ideas of right and wrong are simple ideas; ·so they can’t be acquired by attending to definitions of them, and· must be ascribed to some power of immediate perception in the human mind. If you doubt this, try to construct definitions of them that amount to more than merely producing synonymous expressions ·as in ‘right = correct’, for example·. The issue about the foundation of morals has involved a great deal of confusion, most of which has come from inattention to this matter. There can be no doubt that some actions are

20

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

ultimately approved, with no reason for the approval being givable; just as some ends are ultimately desired, with no reason for choosing them being givable. If this were not so, there would be an infinite sequence of reasons and ends, and therefore nothing could be approved or desired.

Taking it as granted that we have some power of immediately perceiving right and wrong, what I shall try to prove is that this power ·or faculty· is the understanding, which is what I said at the end of section i. The main obstacle to the acceptance of this has—I think and hope—been removed by what I said in section ii to show that the understanding is a power of immediate perception that gives rise to new original ideas. If that had been properly considered, I don’t think there could have been many disputes about the source of our ideas of right and wrong.

But in order to present the case more explicitly and clearly (in the only way the nature of the question seems capable of) let me

(1) point out that it implies no absurdity, and obviously could be true. It is undeniable that many of our ideas are derived from our intuition of truth, i.e. our understanding’s discernment of the natures of things. So this could be the source of our moral ideas. It is at least possible that right and wrong denote what we understand and know concerning certain objects, just like proportion and disproportion, following-from and inconsistency, contingency and necessity, and the other ideas I have mentioned. [Price speaks of what ideas ‘denote’ = ‘name’ or ‘stand for’, as well as (more correctly) of what words denote. The present version doesn’t try to sort all that out.]—And no-one has said anything in support of the view that this is not how things stand. What about Hutcheson’s objections and reasonings in his Enquiry into the Original of our Ideas of Beauty and Virtue? All that they show is something that I have already asserted, which doesn’t in the least affect the present debate. That is, they show that the words ‘right’ and ‘wrong’, ‘fit’ and ‘unfit’, express simple and undeniable ideas. But Hutcheson hasn’t said anything in support of his thesis that the power perceiving right and wrong etc. is really a •sense and not •reason, and that these ideas don’t denote anything that is true of actions, anything about the nature of actions. He seems to have taken for granted that if virtue and vice are immediately perceived, they must be perceptions of an implanted sense. An amazingly hasty conclusion! For will anyone have the rashness to say that all powers of immediate perception must be arbitrary [see note on page 4] and implanted; or that simple ideas can’t denote anything except the qualities and passions of the mind?—In short, whatever some writers have said to the contrary, it certainly has not yet been established that virtue is something ·that God has· made for a purpose, and is to be felt rather than understood. [We have just seen Price using ‘vice’, and starting on page 41 he will quite often use ‘vicious’. For him and his contemporaries, these words cover every kind of moral wrongness. In our day, the noun is narrower than this in one way, and the adjective in another; try to keep these narrowings out of your mind.]

Just as •some propositions, when they are attended to, necessarily make all minds believe them; and just as •some ends, when their natures are perceived, immediately and necessarily make all beings desire them (I’ll defend this later), so also it is very credible that •some actions, when their natures are observed, immediately and necessarily make all rational beings approve them.

I’m not interested in what follows from Hume’s assertion that all our ideas are either impressions or copies of impressions, or from Locke’s assertion that ideas are all derivable from sensation and reflection.—Hume’s thesis

•is destitute of all proof,

•when applied in this and many other cases assumes

21

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

the point in question, and

•when pursued to its consequences ends in the destruction of all truth and the subversion of our intellectual faculties.

—As for Locke’s thesis: it needs much more explanation if it is to be consistent with any tolerable account of the origin of our moral ideas. To be convinced that all our ideas are not derivable from sensation and reflection (unless this is taken in a very broad and loose sense), all you need do is to look at how Locke derives our moral ideas ‘from sensation and reflection’. He places the moral ideas among our ideas of relations, and represents rightness as signifying the conformity of actions to some rules or laws, which (he says) may be

•the will of God,

•the decrees of the magistrate, or

•the fashion of the country.

[For Price and his contemporaries, ‘the magistrate’ stood for whoever makes the laws of the land (and sometimes also whoever enforces them).] It follows from this that it is an absurdity •to apply ‘right’ to rules and laws themselves, •to suppose that the divine will is directed by ·considerations of· rightness, or •to consider rightness as being a rule and law. There can be no doubt that this great man would have detested these consequences; and indeed it is clear enough that he was enormously tangled in his notions on this as well as some other subjects. But

(2) I know of no better way of settling this point—·i.e. of satisfying everyone that rightness etc. are objective properties of actions· than by challenging those who doubt it to bring common sense to bear on the issue, and to consider the nature of their own perceptions.—Does it make sense to suppose that a person might perceive an external object and not know whether he was seeing it or feeling it?.... There’s no possibility of doubting in a case like that; it doesn’t seem any harder to work out the answer in the present case.

Suppose that this question were raised:

What is the perception that we have of number, diversity, causation or proportion? Do our ideas of them signify truth and reality perceived by the understanding, or impressions made on our minds by the objects to which we ascribe them?

To answer this question, wouldn’t it be sufficient to appeal to every man’s consciousness?—·Obviously· the answer would be that of course judgments we make involving any of these concepts are judgments about what is objectively the case out there in the world, not mere reports on the impressions that things have made on our minds. Yet these perceptions seem to me to have no better claim to be called ‘perceptions of the understanding’ than do ·perceptions of· right and wrong.

It’s true that our perceptions of virtue and vice are usually accompanied by impressions of pleasure or pain, satisfaction or disgust. But these are only effects and accompaniments, not the perceptions themselves. Confusing •perceptions of right and wrong with •these accompaniments would be as bad as confusing •a theorem in geometry with •the pleasure the geometer had when he discovered it! It may be that some emotion or other accompanies all our perceptions, but this is most notably true of our perceptions of right and wrong. And this has led to the mistake of thinking that they signify nothing but impressions; an error that some have extended to all objects of knowledge, thus being led into an extravagant and monstrous scepticism. I shall say more about this in the next chapter.

Returning now to my topic: compare •the ideas arising from your powers of sensation with •the ideas arising from your intuition of the natures of things, and ask yourself: Which of these is more like your ideas of right and wrong? We can safely let the answer to that question settle the debate.

22

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

It is scarcely conceivable that anyone who impartially attends to the nature of his own perceptions will decide that when he thinks Gratitude is right or Beneficence is right he isn’t perceiving any truth about gratitude or beneficence, isn’t understanding anything, but is merely receiving an impression from a sense! If someone were able to question whether his idea of equality was gained from sense or intelligence, he could soon be convinced by asking himself this: ‘Aren’t I sure that •certain lines or figures are really equal, and that •their equality must be perceived by all minds as soon as the objects themselves are perceived?’—In this same way we can satisfy ourselves concerning the origin of the idea of right: For don’t we have a similar awareness that we discern rightness, as well as equality, in certain objects? What possible grounds could we have for assigning rightness to sense and equality to reason? Wouldn’t a being who had intelligence but no senses, and who had happiness within his reach, approve of getting it for himself? Wouldn’t he think this right—and wouldn’t it be right?....

It seems utterly certain that every being must desire happiness for himself. Given that a being’s nature is such that he desires happiness and is averse to misery, can he have absolutely no approval of actions that produce one or prevent the other? Is there nothing that any understanding can perceive to be wrong in a creature’s bringing calamities and ruin upon himself or others? Is there nothing truly wrong in the absolute and eternal misery of an innocent being?—‘It appears wrong to us.’—And what reason can you have for doubting that it is as it appears?—Suppose that a being, having been soothed with hopes of bliss and his expectations raised by encouragements and promises, found himself for no reason plunged into irretrievable torments—wouldn’t he justly complain? Wouldn’t the idea of wrong arise in his mind without his having any ·moral· sense to provide it?—Can goodness, gratitude, and veracity appear to any mind under the same characters, with cruelty, ingratitude, and treachery? [That sentence is verbatim Price.]—Darkness may as soon appear to be light!

One might argue further from the fact that everyone naturally takes it that our ideas of right and wrong belong to the understanding, and denote qualities that actions actually have; but this line of argument wouldn’t be useful because it will be easy to reply that •everyone has a similar opinion about the sensible qualities of bodies, and that men very commonly mistake their own sensations for the properties of the objects producing them, or apply to the object itself something that they find always accompanying it whenever it is observed. [Price writes here as though it were an uncontroversially soundly established fact that material things don’t have colours etc., and that statements purporting to attribute such qualities to them ought to be replaced by statements about observers’ sensory states.] Let it therefore be observed,

(3) that if right and wrong denote effects of sensation, it is utterly absurd to suppose them to be applicable to actions. That is,

the ideas of •right and wrong must be incompatible with the idea of •action,

just as

the idea of •pleasure is incompatible with the idea of •such-and-such a shape, and
the idea of •pain is incompatible with the idea of being-hit-by-a-rock.

—-All sensations are states of consciousness, or feelings of a sentient being, which must be of a totally different nature from the particular causes that produce them. A ‘coloured body’ if we speak accurately is absurd in the same way as a ‘square sound’. We don’t need experiments to prove that heat, cold, colours, tastes and so on are not real qualities

23

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

of bodies; because the idea of matter is incompatible with the ideas of any of these qualities.^8—But is there any such incompatibility between action and right? Or any such absurdity in affirming of an action that it is right?—Are those two ideas as different from one another as the idea of a sensation is from the idea of its cause?

On the contrary! The more we enquire, the more indisputable I think it will appear to be that when we say of some actions that they are right and of others that they are wrong, ·so far from being guilty of absurdity or self-contradiction· we are expressing a necessary truth. Some of the most careful enquirers think in this way, and find themselves compelled to believe that right/wrong is a real distinction that applies to the natures of actions. Can it be so difficult to distinguish the ideas of sensibility from ·those of· reason? to distinguish the passions of the mind from the intuitions of truth? Can we become fond of a theory of morals according to which our perceptions of moral good and evil in actions and conduct are all vision and fancy? Can’t everyone see that ‘right’ and ‘wrong’ are absolutely unintelligible and devoid of sense and meaning when they are supposed to signify nothing true of actions, no essential inherent difference between one action and another?....

(4) Finally, think about this: All actions undoubtedly have a nature- i.e. some character certainly belongs to them and there’s something to be truly affirmed of them. This might be that some of them are right, others wrong. But if this is not allowed—if no actions are in themselves either right or wrong, or anything of a moral and obligatory nature that could be an object to the understanding—what follows is this:

Actions in themselves are all indifferent [= ‘neither morally required nor morally forbidden’]. That’s what is essentially true of them, and it is what they must be perceived to be by all understandings that are working properly.

But aren’t we conscious that we perceive the contrary of this? And haven’t we as much reason to believe the contrary as to put any trust at all in our own discernment [= ‘our ability to make distinctions and see logical truths’]?

Here is another way of putting it. Everything has a nature or essence from which such-and-such truths about it necessarily follow, which it is the understanding’s role to perceive. Nothing whatever can be exempted from the understanding’s inspection and judgment; it is the natural and ultimate judge of every thought, sentiment, and subject—so that its domain includes •actions, •purposes and •outcomes.—What is its judgment about •these?—One would think it impossible for anyone to reply confidently and cheerfully that his judgment—·i.e. the judgment of his understanding·—is that •they are all essentially indifferent, and that no one thing is fitter to be done than any other. This is very obviously not a judgment that we make; so if it is correct, our strong inclination to think otherwise is a flaw in our characters as rational creatures. Shouldn’t we then work to suppress this inclination in ourselves, and to sweep

^8 [In a footnote Price remarks that most of the facts that have been adduced as evidence that colours, smells etc. are not really in bodies are useless for that purpose, because if they were valid they would equally prove that shapes and sizes etc. are not really in bodies either. He then adds a point that has nothing to do with his present topic but (he says) he can’t help bringing it in. It is a side-swipe at materialist theories of mind. When everyone agrees that sensible qualities aren’t inherent in matter; it’s strange (Price says) that some philosophers refuse to take the same line about thought and consciousness. He continues:] Is the notion of conscious, thinking, reasonable matter less absurd than that of white matter or red matter ?.... Is it less plain that shape, solidity, magnitude, motion, and juxtaposition of parts are not and cannot be desire, volition, and judgment than it is that they cannot be cold or sour or that any one thing is not and cannot be another?

24

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

out from our natures all the delusive ideas of morality, worth, and virtue? If the ruin of the world should follow—what of it? There would be nothing really wrong in this conduct.

A rational agent who •makes no moral judgments, who •can’t perceive differences amongst actions in respect of their fitness and unfitness to be performed, and who •acts from blind drives without any beliefs concerning what he does, is unimaginable! And we’ll find that however hard we try we can’t •genuinely persuade ourselves that reason can have no role in judging and directing our conduct, or •exclude from our minds all notions of right and wrong in actions.

What deserves special notice here is this. If all actions and all dispositions of beings are in themselves indifferent, this must be known by God’s all-perfect understanding; so he can’t approve or disapprove of any of his own actions, or of any actions by his creatures. He must regard as completely morally neutral the end he pursues and his way of treating his creatures. What foundation, then, is left for his moral perfections? How can we think of God as pursuing universal happiness if we think that there’s nothing in the nature of universal happiness for the choice of any being to focus on? Aren’t we lessening his perfect character if we suppose him to be guided by mere unthinking inclination, with no direction from reason and no moral approval?....

From the arguments that I have been presenting we can draw the important conclusion that Morality is eternal and immutable. ‘Right’ and ‘wrong’, we find, denote what actions are. Now, whatever a thing is, it is by nature and necessity, not by will or decree or power. Whatever a triangle or circle is, that’s what it is unchangeably and eternally. It doesn’t depend on anyone’s will or power whether •the three angles of a triangle shall be equal to two right angles, whether •the circumference of a circle shall be incommensurable with its diameter, or whether •matter shall be divisible, movable, passive, and inert. Every object of the understanding has an indivisible and invariable essence, which is the source of its properties and countless truths about it. Omnipotence doesn’t consist in a power to alter things’ natures and to destroy necessary truth (for this is contradictory, and would imply the destruction of all wisdom and knowledge). Rather, omnipotence consists in an absolute command over all particular external existences—a power to create or destroy them or produce any possible changes among them.—Because the natures of things are immutable [= ‘unchangeable’ or, sometimes, ‘unchanging’], whatever we suppose the natures of actions to be they must be immutably. If they are indifferent, this indifference is itself immutable, and there isn’t and can’t be any one thing that we really ought to do rather than doing something else. This also holds for right and wrong, and for moral good and evil, as far as they express real characters of actions. They must immutably and necessarily belong to the actions of which they are truly affirmed.

Thus, no will can make good and obligatory anything that wasn’t so already and hadn’t been so from eternity; nor can any will make right any action that isn’t right in itself. What I mean by an ‘action’ is not

•the mere external effect produced, ·i.e. the mere physical movement·, but rather

•the ultimate principlec of conduct, i.e. the decision of a thinking being considered as arising from the perception of some motives and reasons and intended for some end.

According to this sense of the word ‘action’, whenever the principlec from which we act is different the action is different, even if the external effects that are produced are the same. If we attend to this, the meaning and truth of what I have just said will be easily seen.—Take the case of any action the performance of which is indifferent—i.e.

25

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

something that the agent’s circumstances don’t make better or fitter to be done than to be omitted. Isn’t it clear that if nothing in the situation changes it’s impossible for any will or power to make acting obligatory, just as its impossible for any will or power to make two equal things unequal without producing any change in either of them? It’s true that the doing of some •indifferent thing may become •obligatory because of a command from a being who has rightful authority over us; but it’s obvious that in this case the command produces a change in the agent’s circumstances, so that the action that it makes obligatory is not the action that previously was indifferent. The external effect—·i.e. the physical movement·—is indeed the same; but it’s perfectly clear that actions that are the same in this sense, involving the very same ·physical· movements, may from the moral point of view be totally different because of differences in the ends aimed at by them and the principles of morality that apply to them.

When an action that would otherwise have been indifferent becomes obligatory through someone’s promising to perform it, don’t think that the promiser’s will—or his breath!—alters the nature of things by taking something indifferent and making it not indifferent. In fact, the action that was indifferent before the promise is still indifferent; to suppose that after the promise that same action becomes obligatory involves a contradiction. All that the promise does is to alter the connection of a particular effect, or to cause that to be an instance of right conduct that was not so before. [That sentence is verbatim Price.] Any effect that we might produce can in this way fall under different principles of morality, coming to be connected sometimes with happiness and sometimes with misery, and thus coming to stand in different relations to the eternal rules of duty. [Notice that Price speaks here of ‘effects that we might produce’: he is saying that a given physical performance might change its moral status, but only through a change in what action it expresses or involves or is ‘produced’ by. There is no question of changing the moral status of a single action.]

The position I have been taking is sometimes objected to on the grounds that something’s moral status could be altered by positive laws [see note on page 5] or by promises; but now we can see that this objection has no weight. It turns out that when an obligation to a particular indifferent action arises from God’s command or from positive laws, this doesn’t show that obligation is the creature of will, i.e. that something that was indifferent has had its nature changed. The item that is obligatory after the divine command is obedience to God’s will and just authority; and that was obligatory before the command—indeed, obligatory from eternity. [Price goes on to say that a command or a law couldn’t make any moral difference unless there were already an obligation to obey it. He concludes:] It is always truth and reason that oblige, and not mere will. It is so far from being possible that any will or laws should create right, that they can’t have any effect except in virtue of natural and antecedent right....

One last point before I bring this chapter to a close: The opinion that our ideas of morality are derived from the senses is far from being entirely modern. Some ancient philosophers (notably Protagoras and his followers) had a similar view; but they extended it much further, denying that there is absolute and immutable truth in any of the sciences, and asserting everything to be relative to perception. It does indeed seem to be a fairly natural transition, from •denying absolute moral truth to •denying all truth; from •making right and wrong, just and unjust, dependent on perception to •asserting the same of everything that we ordinarily count as objects of the understanding. If someone rejects the reality of rightness in beneficence, and of wrongness in producing needless misery,

26

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

why shouldn’t the same steps lead him to deny the certainty of other self-evident principles?.... If he distrusts his reason in one case, why shouldn’t he also distrust it in the other? If he relates moral perceptions to a sense, why shouldn’t he join Protagoras in basing all knowledge on sense?—The consequences of

(1) making all the principles of knowledge arbitrary and contrived ·by God·, supposing that all we perceive of the natures and relations of things really denote sensory states of our minds,

can’t be much worse than the consequences of

(2) making morality arbitrary and contrived ·by God·, supposing that the objects of our moral discernment are really states of our minds.

Where (1) overthrows all truth, (2) overthrows the most important and interesting part of truth. Where (1) destroys the necessary wisdom and intelligence of God (because the very idea of a mind and of knowledge is impossible if there is nothing permanent in the nature of things, nothing necessarily true, and therefore nothing to be known), (2) just as thoroughly destroys his moral perfections.^9

One argument that Protagoras apparently made great use of in maintaining his opinions was that •colours, tastes, sounds and the other sensible qualities of bodies exist only when they are perceived, and therefore •colours etc. are not qualities inherent in bodies but merely constantly changing sensations produced by the action of the perceived object on the sense-organ; from which he inferred that •a single object often appears to different people to have different qualities, and that •no two people have exactly the same ideas of any one sensible quality of any object. This thesis is not very consistent [Price’s phrase] with another of Protagoras’s views, namely that consciousness and understanding really come down to mere matter and motion; ·but he did nevertheless hold both theses, and from them· he concluded that all things are in a perpetual flux, and that nothing is true or false.... in itself, but only relative to the perceiving mind. Several passages in Plato’s Theætetus indicate that Protagoras applied this ·line of thought· particularly to moral good and evil.... If you want a fuller discussion of this matter, see that Dialogue of Plato’s, or Cudworth’s Treatise of Immutable and Eternal Morality.

Such is the agreement, in this instance, between the opinions of modern times and those of Socrates’ time! That is what tends to come from accepting the account of •morality that I have opposed; it is astonishing how far some who have accepted it have extended it to our •other perceptions, and have revived or even exceeded the wildest doctrines of

^9 Suppose someone conducts an enquiry like my present one, into what necessity is being referred to when we say ‘It is necessary there should be a cause of whatever begins to exist’. He asks:

•‘When we say this, are we only expressing a feeling of sense or some state of our own thoughts, and not a judgment of the understanding?’
and
•‘Is it indeed true that there is no such necessity in the natures of things?’

—-If these questions are answered in the affirmative, there is an end of all knowledge, and we are plunged into the abyss of atheism.—Modern scepticism has not stuck at this; and it has the considerable excuse that in taking this line it has merely extended further what some writers (decent people!) have defended with respect to moral rectitude.—But for as long as men retain common sense, such opinions can’t possibly gain ground. •The faculty by which we distinguish self-evident truths from obvious contradiction may be called into question by the refinements and subtleties of very clever men, but •it can’t ever lose its authority—no real and lasting conviction could be produced against it.

27

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 1: Origin of ideas of right and wrong

ancient scepticism. They have

•represented as mere qualities of our minds the primary as well as the secondary qualities of matter, cause, effect, connection, extension, duration, identity, and almost everything about which there can be knowledge;

•confused ideas with the objects of ideas;

•maintained that existing and being perceived are universally the same; and

•asserted the impossibility of everything except impressions.

According to them there is neither matter, nor morality, nor God, nor any kind of external existence left. All our discoveries and boasted knowledge vanish, and the whole universe is reduced to a figment of the imagination. Every sentiment of every being is as right as every other. Because nothing is present to our minds besides •our own ideas, we can’t have any conception of anything distinct from •them; no beings but ourselves;^10

no distinction between past and future time; no possibility of remembering wrongly or foreseeing wrongly. For these sceptical philosophers the wisest man is the one who has the most fertile imagination, the one whose mind is stored with the greatest number of notions. Do his notions conform to the truth of things? That question (they say) cannot even be raised.... It is high time to leave these sceptics to themselves.

[In the third edition Price appended an end-note relating to what he has just said.]
·START OF END-NOTE·
The point that I try to prove in chapter 1 section iii seems to me, when I look back over it, to be so obvious that I’m afraid I shall be thought to have trifled in this section, wasting my time and attention. It is indeed a reproach to human reason that there should be any occasion for showing that when we say of certain actions that they are right (wrong) we express truth and not merely an impression of pleasure (pain),

After the publication of the first two editions of the present work, Adam Smith (the author of the valuable work on the wealth of nations, and a writer above any praise from me) published his Theory of Moral Sentiments, the chief purpose of which is to prove that our perceptions of moral distinctions have the same sources in our natures as sympathy does, i.e. that moral approval and disapproval are a species of fellow-feeling with moral agents, by which we are made to enter into their views and emotions and to share in their pleasures and pains. As for the ·general· thesis that our basic notions of moral good and evil are derived from sensation and not from reason, i.e. that they are feelings of some sort and not perceptions of the intellectual faculty,

^10 And not ourselves either! Why? Because (according to these philosophers) existing is the same as being perceived; so perceptions themselves can’t exist unless there can be perceptions of perceptions ad infinitum. And there is another reason also. According to this system, the only idea of what we call ‘ourselves’ is the contradictory and deformed idea of a series of successive and separable perceptions, none of which last through time—i.e. none of which exist—and all this without any substance that perceives.—And there is another point: Although this scheme takes away the distinction between past and future, and doesn’t allow for anything really existing independently of perception, it also depends on—is based on—the contrary of both of those! It supposes that there have been past impressions of which all ideas are copies; and that certain objects have been observed as conjoined in past instances, which has given the imagination the habit of moving from one of them to the other—which is what these philosophers say that reasoning consists in. I wouldn’t have troubled you with a mention of these extravagances if it weren’t for the fact that some of them have been started •by Berkeley, who has followed his principles through to a system of scepticism that clearly includes them all; and •by another highly talented writer, Hume.

28

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

Smith says that he thinks this has been so abundantly proved by Hutcheson as to make it amazing that there is still any controversy about it.

This opinion, delivered in this way by such an able writer, would influence me more than it does if it weren’t for the contrary opinion of another equally able writer, Thomas Reid. I get particular satisfaction from the fact that my views agree with Reid’s on all the most important points. At the end of his Essays on the Intellectual Powers of Man, he declares an intention to make the active and moral powers of man the subject of a future publication; and all enquirers after truth must hope that nothing will prevent him from doing that. ·END OF END-NOTE·

Chapter 2

Our ideas of the beauty and ugliness of actions

Having considered our ideas of •right and wrong; I come now to consider our ideas •of beauty and its contrary. [Price calls its contrary ‘deformity’, which in this version is replaced by ‘ugliness’, a word that Price doesn’t use.] Of the three kinds of sentiment or perception regarding actions that I listed at the start of chapter 1, this is the second. I needn’t say much to show that it is different from the first of the three. We are plainly conscious of more than the bare discernment of right and wrong, i.e. the cool judgment of reason concerning the natures of actions. We often say of an action not only that it is right but that it is ‘amiable’; and of another action not only that it is wrong but that it is ‘odious’ and ‘shocking’. [Current English has no one word expressing what Price means by ‘amiable’. To get the general idea, think of ‘That was amiable’ as short-hand for something like ‘What a lovely thing to do!’] Everyone must see that these words express the delight—or in the other case the horror and detestation—that we feel, and consequently signify not •any real qualities or characteristics of actions but rather •the particular pleasure or pain caused in us when we consider the actions.

What is the true account of these perceptions? Mustn’t they arise entirely from an arbitrary [see note on page 4] structure of our minds such that when we observe certain objects we experience certain sensations and feelings? And if that’s so, don’t we now have to bring in the notion of a ·moral· sense? Can perceptions be connected with particular episodes of pleasure and pain in the perceiving mind in any way except through implanted principlesc?

I answer that there can be such a connection, and that in many cases there is one, especially in this present case ·of perceptions of moral beauty and ugliness·.

It isn’t possible for us to discover why or how the impressions made by external objects on our bodily organs produce the sensations that always come with them. The same is true of the sensations and feelings produced by the objects of many of our internal senses. In such instances we can’t conceive of any connection between the effects in us and

29

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

their apparent causes; and the only explanation we can give is: ‘That is how we are built; God saw fit to relate particular objects to our faculties in those ways rather than in some others.’ But in many cases we don’t have this need to bring in God’s choices. Some objects have a natural aptitude to please or displease our minds. The situation is the same with regard to the mental world as it is with the world of bodies. With regard to the latter, although

•there are events that we can’t explain, and countless instances where we know that x caused y though we don’t know anything about how because we don’t know enough about the inward structure and constitution of x and y,

•there are also causes that operate in a manner that we do understand, and events between which we discern a necessary connection.

So one possible explanation of the sentiments we are now examining is: ‘Certain actions have natures such that when they are perceived they must result certain emotions and feelings.’

It seems to me beyond question that some objects have a natural aptitude to please or offend; there is a necessary congruity or incongruity between these objects and the contemplating mind.—What are we to say of supreme and complete excellence? Here are three accounts:

(1) When we call something ‘supremely and completely excellent’ all we mean is that it causes in us a particular kind of sensation.

(2) Supreme and complete excellence is real and objective, and instances of it can it be contemplated without emotion. For the ·supremely and completely excellent· character of God to appear amiable to us, we have to have a special sense, because pure and abstract reason is indifferent to it.

(3) All that is needed for us to love and admire God’s character is knowing it. The more it is known, and the better it is understood, the more it delights.

·It seems clear that (3) is by far the most plausible of these·. Consider the example of a being who •has reason, •knows what order and happiness are, and •surveys a universe where perfect order prevails: to get pleasure from this prospect, I don’t think he’ll need any arbitrary mental structures or special moral senses! Similarly with his being offended by the prospect of universal confusion and misery.

Here’s another example: your own happiness and misery are undeniably objects that you can’t contemplate with indifference! More about this in chapter 3.

What is true in these and other instances is especially clearly true in our present case. Of all the cases of correspondences and connections among things, all the cases where one event has a tendency to produce another, none is plainer than the fact that virtue is naturally adapted to please every observing mind, and vice the contrary.—I can’t perceive an action to be right without approving it; and I can’t approve it without being conscious of some degree of satisfaction. I can’t perceive an action to be wrong without disapproving it; and I can’t disapprove it without being displeased by it. So right actions as such must be welcome to us and wrong ones unwelcome to us. [In that sentence and a few others later on, ‘welcome’ replaces Price’s ‘grateful’, used in a now obsolete sense.] Right actions must appear amiable, and wrong ones must appear unamiable and base.—Goodness, faithfulness, justice, and gratitude cannot appear to any mind in the same way that cruelty, treachery, injustice and ingratitude do. To all who perceive and compare these ·two kinds of actions· they must have opposite effects: the first group must be liked, the second disliked; the first must be loved, the second hated. And it isn’t possible that these sentiments should be reversed.

30

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

To behold virtue is to admire it. To behold it in its intrinsic and complete importance, dignity, and excellence is to have supreme affection for it. On the other side: to perceive vice is the very same as to blame and condemn ·it·. To perceive it in its naked form and malignity is to dread and detest it above all things.

Self-approval and self-reproach are the chief sources of private happiness and misery. They are connected with—and entirely dependent on—awareness of practising or not practising virtue. Self-approval can’t be separated from the memory of having done well, and self-condemnation is inseparable from the memory of having done wrong. For a being who is obliged to be perpetually reflecting on himself, nothing can matter more than to be at peace with himself and to be able to bear the survey of his ·past· actions. So virtue and vice are, from the natures of things, the immediate and principal and most constant and intimate causes of private happiness and misery.

It should be remembered here that the effects produced by considering virtue and vice must be different in different beings, and ·different even· in the same being in different circumstances. The pleasure received from virtuous actions, (that is the sense of beauty in them) must be varied by countless causes, both in the circumstances of the actions and in the understandings and conditions of the perceiver. •Pain or sickness, •the influence of implanted biases and propensities, •many different conditions of the temperament, and •associated ideas can lessen or prevent effects that would otherwise follow the perception of moral good and evil. But the essential tendencies don’t alter; morally good actions must always be acceptable to every healthy rational mind, and can’t ever of themselves offend; and morally evil actions must always be disagreeable, and can’t ever of themselves please.—Of course a single object of moral discernment (·e.g. an action or a person’s character·), however it is naturally disposed to affect a percipient, will affect different reasonable people differently because of differences in their frames of mind or the clarity of their perceptions. ·This is just a special case the very general fact that· the effects produced by any cause depend on the particular circumstances in which it operates, and must differ as these differ.

These observations seem to lead to an idea of God’s happiness that may deserve to be just mentioned. If the foundations of happiness were something that someone has constructed for a purpose, it would be impossible to conceive how the Being who is himself the cause of all things ·and thus the maker of all constructions·, and who can’t draw anything from any source outside himself, could be happy. But I have shown that some objects of contemplation naturally produce delight, and some perfections or qualities imply blessedness. A •being who has reason is capable of greater happiness than a being who only has senses, because •he has in himself the sources of greater enjoyment; and the more wisdom and reason a being has, the higher is the bliss he is capable of. So there is in the natures of things a stable and permanent foundation for happiness. And God’s happiness may result necessarily and wholly from what he is—from his having in himself all truth, all good, all perfection, all that blesses.—But in discussing this topic we are in over our heads; I suspect that we are falling into some gross misconceptions when we think of God as a happy being.

I return now to my main topic. The points I have made here won’t account for all our feelings relating to virtue and vice. The lowest levels of reason are sufficient to reveal moral distinctions in general, because these distinctions are •self-evident, and are •included in the ideas of certain actions and characters, so that they must appear to anyone who is

31

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

capable of thinking about actions in any way at all. But how completely they appear to someone, and how accurately and strongly he discerns them, and thus how much influence they have on him, must be in proportion to •the strength and improvement of his rational faculties and •his acquaintance with truth and the natures of things. And our intellectual faculties are in their infancy!

That is why men need to have instinctive determinations as aids to the rational principlec, i.e. as aids to the intellectual discernment of right and wrong.—The dictates of mere reason are slow and deliberate, so that on their own they would be much too weak. The condition in which we are placed makes it necessary for us to have many urgent passions, and these inevitably interfere with our sentiments of rightness, thereby exposing us to ·moral· danger. We can’t be defended against this by unaided reason, because our reason is so imperfect. Our maker has, therefore, wisely provided remedies for reason’s imperfections by giving us a constitution in which balance can be preserved, by tying our •intellectual perceptions sensations to •instincts that give them greater weight and force. [In Price’s day, perhaps more than now, ‘imperfect’ could mean ‘incomplete’ or ‘not yet fully developed’; and so it does here. When Price says that human reason is •imperfect, •in its infancy,and •slow, he isn’t alleging any positive defect.]

So here is the situation in a nutshell: When we contemplate the actions of moral agents, we have both a perception of the understanding and a feeling of the heart. And the feeling depends on two causes: partly on •how we are constituted, but principally on •the essential congruity or incongruity between moral ideas and our intellectual faculties. [The ‘principally...’ phrase in that is verbatim Price.]

It may be hard to determine exactly where the line falls between these two sources of our mental feelings, or to say how far the effects of one are blended with those of the other. There’s no doubt that we would have felt and acted differently from how we now do if the decisions of ·our· reason had been left entirely without support; and it isn’t easy to imagine how pernicious to us this would have turned out to be. On my theory it can’t be doubted that both the causes I have mentioned are at work in us; and the great question in morality is not ‘Do we owe a lot to implanted senses and determinations?’ but ‘Do we owe everything to them?’

When Hutcheson in his Enquiry into the Origin of our Ideas of Beauty and Virtue tried to derive all our ideas of virtue from an implanted sense, this was probably because he didn’t pay proper attention to the distinction I have been insisting on

between honestum and pulchrum [Latin],
between ‘right’ and ‘morally beautiful’,
between the moral discernment of the mind and the sensations that come with it.

He always describes moral good and evil in terms of the effects accompanying the perception of them. The rightness of an action is, for him, the same as its welcomeness to the observer; and wrongness the same as its unwelcomeness. But it is utterly evident that •right is as different from pleasure, and •wrong as different from pain, as

•a cause is different from its effect,

•what is understood is different from what is felt, and

•a proposition’s absolute truth is different from its agreeableness to the mind.

—-It can’t be denied that (a) some degree of pleasure is inseparable from the observation of virtuous actions. But to infer from this that (b) the discernment of virtue is nothing but the reception of this pleasure is just as unreasonable to infer—as some have done—from the premise that (a) whenever solidity, extension, and shape are perceived they are accompanied by some sensations of sight or touch, without which those

32

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

qualities can’t be conceived by the imagination, the conclusion that (b) those qualities are nothing but particular kinds of sensation.

An able writer on these subjects [John Balguy] tells us that after some doubts he finally became convinced that all beauty, whether natural or moral, is a species of absolute truth because it results from or consists in the necessary relations and matchings of ideas. It is not easy to say what this means. I’ll come to natural beauty shortly. As for moral beauty, one would think that the meaning of the phrase ‘moral beauty’ must involve its standing for a real quality of certain actions. But the word ‘beauty’ seems always to refer to the getting of pleasure; so the beauty of an action or character must signify its.... being apt to please us when we perceive it; and it is wrong to think that an object’s beauty consists in anything more in the action that just this aptness, as distinct from the objective goodness or rectitude on which the beauty depends....

It may be worthwhile to point out that in everyday speech the adjectives ‘beautiful’ and ‘amiable’ are applied only to actions and characters that please us highly because of the especially high degree of moral worth and virtue that we find in them. All virtuous actions must be pleasing to an intelligent observer; but they don’t all give enough pleasure to be entitled to those descriptions.—Later on I’ll discuss in detail the nature and origin of our ideas of the different degrees of virtue and vice in actions.

These remarks, slightly modified, also apply to natural beauty. The general source of natural beauty, according to Hutcheson, is •uniformity amidst variety. Why is •this pleasing? I think it’s because •it is adapted by its nature to please.—There seems to be no more call for an implanted sense for natural beauty than there is for moral beauty.—I have shown that some things are necessarily satisfactory to our thoughts and carry in themselves a power to give pleasure when observed or thought about. In many particular cases this pleasure is lost. Sometimes, indeed, the influence of counteracting causes can make regular and harmonious forms downright offensive; but they can’t offend as such, i.e. can’t offend-because-they-are-regular-and-harmonious. The pain never comes from them, but only from some malady in the mind or some disagreeable idea associated with them.

The following notable facts probably contribute greatly to the satisfaction that our minds get from things that are regular, and to our preference for such things. (1) Regular things are more easily viewed and comprehended by our minds. Everyone knows how much harder it is to retain in the memory a multitude of things that are unconnected and lie in confusion than it is to remember a multitude of things laid out according to a rule and plan. It is order that unites the parts of a complicated object so that we can take it in all at once, clearly and with satisfaction; whereas if it lacked order it would be not one object but a crowd of them, and our conceptions of it would be broken and confused between many different parts that had no correspondence to one another and would require a separate idea for each. Regularity enables us to measure and fix variety; it enables our mind to (so to speak) conquer infinity itself. To see the soundness of these points, think about abstract truths and the general laws of nature; or contrast a thousand equal lines •arranged as a regular polygon with the same lines •all jumbled together.

(2) Order and symmetry give objects their stability and strength, fitting them to be useful for good purposes. What strength would an army have without order? What does the health of animal bodies depend on but the due order and adjustments of their various parts? What happiness could there be in the world if it were a chaos?

33

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

(3) Regularity and order are evidence of skill and design. Regular and orderly objects bear the stamp of intelligence, and this may be one of the principal causes of their agreeableness to us.

Confusion is nothing but the negation of regularity and order, and it isn’t positively displeasing except •where we expected order or •where the confusion seems to come from weakness and lack of skill.

You don’t need me to tell you that brutes [= ‘non-human animals’] are incapable of the pleasures of beauty because those beauties come from comparing objects and noticing analogy, design, and proportion among them, which the faculties of brutes aren’t capable of.

It has been said that what pleases us in beautiful objects it is just variety, and that the uniformity is only needed to make the variety clearly perceivable by the mind. One might as well say that what pleases us is just uniformity, and that variety is only needed for the uniformity to be exhibited and displayed in a higher degree!

I have called attention to the opinion [of John Balguy] that natural beauty is a real quality of objects.—It seems impossible conceive the objects themselves to have anything more than

•a particular order of parts—·a particular structure·—and •the powers arising from that structure, powers that include certain relationships to our perceptive faculties.

If we call this ‘beauty’ then beauty is indeed a non-relational inherent quality of certain objects—one that exists whether or not any mind discerns it. But surely order and regularity aren’t beauty—they are causes of beauty.

It may be worth your while to think about how far my account of the pleasures received from contemplating moral good and natural beauty can be applied also to the pleasures received from many other sources—the approval of our fellow-creatures, the greatness of objects, the discovery of truth and increase of knowledge.

I will only add that in such enquiries as these we are forced to consider the nature and origin of our notions of perfection and excellence.

There are people who think that actions and characters don’t really, objectively, differ from one another in excellence and worth. How will they account for our preferences for some actions and characters over others?^11

Probably by bringing in the notion of a sense ·and of sense-deception. Their account will go like this·:

We do have ideas of different degrees of perfection in different objects, but those are all an illusion. To the eye of right reason, the entire range of existence is in this respect entirely on a level. The very notion of intrinsic excellence and.... of different degrees of objective perfection and imperfection implies an impossibility—it is self-contradictory.

—How could anyone accept such an opinion? When we conceive of a thinking being as having a more noble and perfect nature than a clod of earth, are we wrong? Is it because of an implanted power ·or sense· that we distinguish thinking beings as higher than clods of earth? And is that

^11 We have the ideas of greater decency and dignity in some pleasures than in others—e.g. in the pleasures of the imagination or the understanding as against those of the bodily senses. Hutcheson, after remarking on this, seems unsure how to explain it. Perhaps it should be attributed to a general view that the former pleasures are innocent, in which case (he says) our preference for the mental pleasures over the bodily ones is a deliverance of the moral sense. But he allows that these distinctions ·between higher and lower pleasures· come from perceptions of a different sort—perceptions that should be regarded as forming their own special class of sensations.

34

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 2: Ideas of beauty and ugliness

why we esteem God’s nature as infinitely surpassing all other natures in excellence and dignity? The truth is this: The ideas of excellence and dignity, like the others discussed in chapter 1, are ideas of the understanding. They are derived from the understanding’s knowledge of the comparative essences of things; and they arise necessarily in our minds when we consider certain objects and qualities, because they denote not what we feel, but what such objects and qualities are.

Nature contains an infinite variety of existences and objects, and we can’t think about them as being different from one another without conceiving of them as having various degrees of perfection. It isn’t possible to contemplate and compare

living things with dead matter,
reason with brute-animal,
happiness with misery,
virtue with vice,
knowledge with ignorance,
power with weakness, or
God with inferior beings

without acquiring the ideas of better and worse, perfect and imperfect, noble and ignoble, excellent and base.—One step up from •nothing is •unformed matter; the next step takes us to •vegetative life, and a step up from there takes us to •sentient animal life, and from there we move up to •happy and active intelligence, of which there are countless different degrees and different orders and classes of beings, rising without end, above one another. Every step our thoughts take up this scale conveys the notion of a higher excellence and worth, until at last we arrive at uncreated and complete excellence. If this is not intellectual perception, but sensation merely, then it could be that our ideas of nature have it backwards, so that the dust under our feet has the supreme excellence that we now attribute to God!....

35

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 3: Origin of desires and affections

Chapter 3

The origin of our desires and affections

Of the three topics listed at the start of chapter 1, there remains only the third to be discussed, our perception of good and ill desert. But before I come to that, I want to present to you something else that is closely connected with the topic I have just finished with; my plan for this book requires me to deal with it somewhere. It is the question of the origin of our affections in general, and especially of self-love and benevolence. [‘benevolence’ from Latin bene = ‘well’ and volo = ‘want’; contrasted with ‘beneficence’, which comes from bene and facio = ‘do’.]

Each of our affections has its particular end [= ‘purpose’ or ‘aim’]. •Self-love leads us to desire and pursue ·our own· private happiness; •benevolence leads us to desire and pursue public happiness; •ambition is the love of fame and distinction; and •curiosity is the love of what is new and uncommon. The objects of these and all our other affections are desired for their own sakes, and ·those desires· constitute so many distinct principlesc of action. Something that is wanted not for itself but only as a means to something else can’t properly be called the object of an affection. If it were true—as some say it is—that we want things only as means to our own good, then would really desire nothing but our own good, and would have only one affection—self-love.

Just as some writers have (i) ascribed all moral approval and disapproval, and our ideas of beauty and ugliness, to an internal sense, meaning by this not an inward power of perception but an implanted power that is different from reason, so also some writers have (ii) ascribed all our desires and affections to instinct, taking an instinct to be not merely an immediate desire for something but an implanted drive that causes such a desire.—I have already extensively examined (i). Now I turn to (ii).

Is all desire to be considered as wholly instinctive? If we are at all concerned for our own good or for the good of others, is this purely the result of an in-born bias given our natures—a bias that they could have lacked or even have had in the reverse direction?

Insofar as this relates to ·our own· private good, we can unhesitatingly answer No. The desire for our own of happiness certainly does not arise from instinct. What does explain it, fully and adequately, is the nature of happiness. It is impossible that creatures capable of both pleasant and painful sensations should fail to love and choose one and dislike and avoid the other. The supposition that a being who knows what happiness and misery are has no preference between them is plainly self-contradictory. Pain is not a possible object of desire; happiness is not a possible object of aversion. No power whatsoever can cause a creature in the agonies of torture and misery to be pleased with his state, to like it for itself, to want to remain in it. Nor can any power cause a creature rejoicing in bliss to dislike his state or be afraid that it will continue. For such things to be the case, pain would have to be agreeable and pleasure disagreeable—i.e. pain would have to be pleasure, and pleasure to be pain.

From this I infer that it is by no means a generally absurd method of explaining our affections to derive them from the natures of things and of ·sentient· beings. There’s no doubt that that’s the way to account for one of the most important and active of all our affections: for any being to prefer and desire ·his own· private happiness, all that is needed is for

36

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 3: Origin of desires and affections

him to know what it is.—And mightn’t this be true also of public happiness? Given that self-love is essential to sentient beings, mightn’t benevolence be essential to thinking beings?

But to go into this in a little more detail: Let us return to the case of the being [page 30] who has reason and nothing else. It is evident that although he is stipulated as having no implanted biases he wouldn’t lack all principlesc of action and all inclinations. I have shown that he would perceive virtue, and would have affection for it in proportion to the degree of his knowledge. The nature of happiness also would draw him to choose and desire it for himself. And is it credible that, at the same time, he would be necessarily indifferent about it for others? Can it be supposed that something in happiness would make him seek it for himself, while nothing in happiness would draw him to approve of it for others? Wouldn’t this imply that the nature of things—·and especially the nature of happiness·—was inconsistent? Wouldn’t he be able to see that •the happiness of others is as important to them as his happiness is to him, and •that it is in itself equally valuable and desirable, whoever has it?

Let us ask again: wouldn’t this being assent to the proposition that Happiness is better than misery?—Someone has demanded a definition of the word ‘better’ as used here. It would be equally reasonable to ask for a definition of the word ‘greater’ as used in the proposition that The whole is greater than a part. Both denote simple ideas, and both ·are being used to express· truth. One expresses what happiness is, compared with misery; the other expresses what the whole is, compared with a part. And a mind that thought happiness not to be better than misery would making as gross a mistake as a mind that believed the whole not to be greater than a part. So it can’t reasonably doubted that such a being, on comparing happiness with misery, couldn’t help •preferring one to the other ·for himself· and •choosing one rather than the other for his fellow-beings, any more than he could help •perceiving the difference between them.

If the idea that the word ‘better’ stands for in the proposition ‘Happiness is better than misery’ really does mean something about ·the deliverances of· a sense rather than being about something true—if in the judgment of right reason there’s nothing objectively good about happiness or bad about misery—then this must be something that God perfectly understands. In that case, he can’t have a preference for one over the other; there’s nothing in happiness to engage or justify his choice of it. In that case, what account [here = ‘explanation’] can we give of God’s goodness?—Some will say ‘The same account that is to be given of his existence, namely none at all’. But there is an account to be given of God’s existence; it is the account that is to be given of all necessary truth. And this account is fully applicable to God’s benevolence as well, given what I have said about its origin. [Price emphasizes his point that if for us moral concepts come from ‘an implanted and factitious principlec’—i.e. if they result from something that was designed and constructed (by God) and then implanted in us—then such concepts can’t have any role in God’s own thinking; and that makes it seem odd to think of God as good. How can we conceive God as good is we can’t think of him as agreeing with us about this?]....

The philosophers I am opposing here accept that in our inward sentiments we are caused [Price: ‘determined’] to distinguish public happiness from public misery, and to see one of them as preferable to the other. But they say that this is because of our constitution; it arises from (i) senses and instincts that we have been given, and not from (ii) the nature of happiness and misery.—What reason have they for saying this? The preference in question could come from (ii)—the instance of self-love demonstrates this [i.e. is a rigorously logically

37

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 3: Origin of desires and affections

knock-down proof of it].—I challenge my opponents to produce anything that is as helpful to their thesis that the explanation lies in (i)!

We can account for some of our other affections in the same way as I have explained self-love and benevolence. But these others are of less importance ·than those two·, and my present project doesn’t require me to tackle them. So I shall touch on only ·two of the others·, the love of fame and the love of knowledge.

[This next paragraph was drastically compressed by Price. Here is its content: Consider the following happenings:

(1) We see that certain actions and dispositions of ours or of others are right.

(2) We approve of those actions and dispositions.

(3) We approve of the state of being known and thought about in certain ways.

(4) We want and try to get ourselves into that state.

Now, unaided intellect is enough for (1)—that has been the principal thesis of this book up to here, defended at length in chapter 1. In the present chapter I have been arguing that (1) is enough for (2), and from that it follows that (1) is enough for (3), which is only a special case of (2). Putting all that together: unaided intellect is sufficient for the approval of fame and honour; and it follows almost as obviously that it is sufficient also for (4)—that’s merely the move from finding fame and honour desirable to desiring fame and honour. Thus, the love of fame and honour doesn’t have to be explained in terms of an implanted instinct.]

Can a reasonable being be indifferent about his own approval? ·Clearly not!· And if he cares about being approved of by himself, why should we think him necessarily indifferent about having the approval of others? Is there nothing in the •good opinion and esteem of his fellow-beings that can incline him to choose •them rather than their contempt and aversion?

The desire for knowledge also, and the preference for truth, must arise in every intelligent mind. Truth is the proper object of mind, as light is of the eye, or harmony of the ear. The mind is by its nature fitted to truth, and its existence depends on this, because there’s no possible idea of mind or understanding without something to be understood. Truth and knowledge are of infinite extent, and it’s inconceivable that the understanding should •be indifferent to them, should •lack an inclination to search into them, should •get no satisfaction from its progress in the discovery of them, or should •be capable of being contented with error, darkness, and ignorance when it sees before it the prospect of limitless scope for improvement and endless acquisition of knowledge.

Why do reasonable beings love truth, knowledge, and honour? The answer to that is the same as the answer to the question: Why do reasonable beings love and desire happiness?

I could continue in this way to give detailed explanations of the causes and grounds of the various sentiments of veneration, awe, love, wonder, esteem and so on that are produced in us by the contemplation of certain objects [see note on ‘object’ high on page 4]. Just as some objects are adapted to please, and as others necessarily excite desire, so almost every different object has a different effect on our minds according to its particular nature and qualities. And these emotions or impressions are almost as various as their objects. Why should we hesitate to say that there’s a necessary correspondence between them and their respective objects?—The thesis we are up against here is this:

If it weren’t for features of our minds that God chose to give them, our feelings would be neutral, indifferent, with respect to all objects and qualities—we wouldn’t

38

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 3: Origin of desires and affections

like (dislike) or be drawn to (away from) any objects at all.

This can’t be true! Anyone who asserts it is denying all real connection between causes and effects.

But it mustn’t be forgotten that the sentiments and tendencies of our intelligent nature are to a large extent mingled with the effects of our arbitrary constitution. I said this before, and need to remind you of it now. Rational and dispassionate benevolence would, in us, be a principlec much too weak and utterly insufficient to meet our needs in the present world; what produces sufficient benevolence in us is the addition to •the rational principlec of •certain feelings that come from the arbitrary [= contingent] part of our nature. And the same is true of our other rational principlesc and desires.

This may give us a good basis for distinguishing affections from passions. We attribute ‘affections’ to all reasonable beings. In the best meaning to give the word, ‘affections’ signify the desires that are founded in and essential to the reasonable nature itself—e.g. self-love, benevolence, and the love of truth.—When an affection is strengthened by an instinctive determination, the result is a passion properly so-called.—The tendencies within us that are merely instinctive, such as hunger, thirst and so on are usually called ‘appetites’ or ‘passions’—interchangeably—but seldom or never ‘affections’. [See note on page 4.]

I can’t help pausing here to say a little about an opinion that I have already referred to, namely the view that there is no ultimate object of desire except private good. This opinion has arisen from inattention to how •desire differs from •the pleasure implied in the gratification of desire. The pleasure comes after the desire, and is founded in it. The situation is not that

we desire an object—fame, knowledge, the welfare of a friend, or whatever—because we foresee that when obtained it will give us pleasure.

Rather, it is the reverse of that:

obtaining the object gives us pleasure because we previously desired it or had an affection carrying us to it and resting in it.

If there were no such affections, the very foundations of happiness would be destroyed. It is inconceivable that we should get pleasure from obtaining something that we don’t desire, i.e. that something we are perfectly indifferent to—something that isn’t aimed at by any affection that we have—should give us any kind of gratification when we have it.

[Price adds that if there were nothing to desiring x except believing that having x would give us pleasure, it would be hard for us to know what to desire, because we wouldn’t know in advance what would give us pleasure.]

To be further convinced, consider this: If you desire something, while also thinking that you would enjoy the same pleasure if you didn’t get it, would that make you indifferent to it, ·wiping out your desire·?.... Would you lose all curiosity, and be indifferent whether you stirred a step to gratify it, if you were sure that you would get equal sensations of pleasure by staying where you are? If you believed that the prosperity of your nearest kindred, your friends or your country wouldn’t bring you any more happiness than would their misery, would you lose all love for them and all desire for their good?—Wouldn’t you choose to enjoy the same quantity of pleasure •with virtue rather than •without it?—An unbiased mind must scornfully reject such questions. If you put such questions to yourself you will easily find that all your affections and appetites (except

39

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 3: Origin of desires and affections

for self-love itself) are in their nature disinterested [= ‘not self-interested’], and that although •they are in yourself and •carrying them out will bring gratification to yourself, their direct tendency is always to •something other than private pleasure, i.e. pleasure for yourself, and they don’t lead you to look any further than •that. ‘In following the impulses of •our affections and appetites, we aim at nothing but our own interest’—that is so far from being true that we continually feel •them drawing us aside from what we know to be our interests, and can observe men every day carried by •them to actions and pursuits that they admit are ruinous to them.

But to return from this digression: Some of our passions and appetites are subordinate to self-love, and have been given to us for the preservation and welfare of individuals. Others are subordinate to benevolence, and were given in order to secure and promote the happiness of our species. There is a need for the benevolent ones only because of our deficiencies and weaknesses. If we possessed reason in a higher degree, it alone would achieve everything that the benevolent passions do.—For example, there would be no need for parental affection if all parents were •well enough acquainted with the reasons for undertaking the guidance and support of those whom nature has placed under their care, and were •virtuous enough to be always determined by those reasons. The same holds for all the other implanted principlesc: it’s clear that each of them would be made superfluous by a certain degree of knowledge and goodness.

Those of us who see this, and can regard the fit between •appetite and nature’s design only as something needed to make up for the imperfections of •reason, ought to work to improve our reason, to extend its influence as much as possible, to learn increasingly to substitute it for appetite, and to diminish continually the occasion for instinctive principlesc in ourselves.—All the lower animals, and men themselves during their first years, have no guide except instinct. The longer men live and the wiser and better they grow, the more disengaged they are from instinct; and there may be countless orders of superior beings who are absolutely above it and are influenced and guided solely by reason.

Considering the present weak and imperfect state of human reason, we cannot sufficiently admire God’s wisdom and goodness in providing us with particular instinctive determinations as a security against the dangers that could come from our reason’s imperfection. When men don’t have the wisdom that would lead them to eat regularly the food needed for their support, given the mere knowledge that this should be done at certain intervals, it is kind ·of God· to remind them of this and urge them to do it through the solicitations of hunger! Given that men would probably not be sufficiently drawn to the relief of the miserable without the sympathies and impulses of compassion, it is proper that these should be given to them! And given that if left to mere reason men wouldn’t attend to the care of their offspring, it is wise ·of God· to bind them to their children by parental fondness, not letting them neglect their children without doing violence to themselves!....

So the wisdom and benevolence of our maker appear clearly in the way we are built.—It is true that these very principlesc that are needed for the preservation and happiness of our species often turn out to be the causes of many grievous evils. But they are plainly intended for good: those evils are the •accidental and not the •proper consequences of them. They come from the unnatural misuse and corruption of the principlesc in question, and happen entirely through our own fault; they are contrary to what appears to be the constitution of our nature and the will of our Maker. It is impossible to produce a single case in which the basic

40

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 4: Ideas of good and ill desert

direction of nature is towards evil or towards anything that isn’t best on the whole.

I’m not interested in determining precisely, in all cases, which elements of our natures are instinctive and which are not. It is enough to show that the most important of our desires and affections have a higher and less precarious basis than instinctive appetites.

Chapter 4

Our ideas of good and ill desert

[Just to get the terminology clear: We have three words:

‘desert’—pronounced desert—a wild and empty place.
‘desert’—pronounced desert—deservingness (noun), ‘abandon’ (verb).
‘dessert’—pronounced desert—the sweet course to end a meal.

Price’s topic is the middle one (noun): questions about someone’s deserving praise or reward etc.–or deserving blame or punishment etc.–for something he did. You’ll see right away that he means the words ‘worthy’ and ‘unworthy’ (actually, he says ‘worthy... and the contrary’) to convey the ideas of good or ill desert.]

There is no need for me to argue that the ideas of good and ill desert necessarily arise in us when we consider certain actions and characters, or that we conceive virtue as always worthy and vice as unworthy. These ideas are plainly special cases of the ideas of right and wrong. But there’s a difference between them that may be worth mentioning. When used strictly the adjectives ‘right’ and ‘wrong’ are applicable only to •actions, whereas good and ill desert belong rather to the •agent. It is only the agent who is capable of happiness or misery, so it is only he who can properly be said to ‘deserve’ these.

I don’t expect much difficulty in explaining these ideas. They take cases where virtue has been practised or neglected, and they concern the treatment due to beings in consequence of this. They signify the propriety that there is in making virtuous agents happy, and in upsetting the vicious [re ‘vicious’ see note on page 21]. When we say of a man that he ‘deserves well’, we mean that •his character is such that we approve of showing him favour, or that •it is right he should be happier than he would have been if he’d had a contrary character. We can’t help loving a virtuous agent and wanting him to be happy—more than we want this for other people. Reason tells us at once that his virtue ought to make things better for him.—And on the other side we can’t help hating and condemning a vicious being. Our concern for his happiness is diminished, and we find it utterly self-evidently that it is improper that he should prosper in his wickedness, or that he should be as happy as are people with worthy characters or as he himself would have been if he had been virtuous.

Different characters require different treatments: virtue provides a reason for making the agent happy, and vice a reason for withdrawing favour from the agent and for

41

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 4: Ideas of good and ill desert

punishing him.—This seems to be very intelligible, but let us not misunderstand the reason for it. It is not the case that the sentiments I am discussing are based wholly on the fact that virtue tends to produce happiness in the world while vice tends to produce misery.—·On the contrary·, our approval for making the virtuous happy and discouraging the vicious is immediate, and doesn’t have to involve any thought about consequences. [(i) The consequences of virtue and vice? or (ii) the consequences of rewarding virtue and punishing vice? Price has introduced his present topic explicitly in terms of (i), but from here on he wavers between (i) and (ii).] If a virtuous person and a vicious one were somehow cut off from being noticed by anyone else, or if they were the only beings in the universe, we would still approve of different treatments of them. It would appear to us wrong that the good being should be less happy, or a greater sufferer, than his evil fellow being.

Suppose you had a particular benefit that you could bring to either one of two people who differed only in that one was virtuous and the other vicious, what reason could you have to hesitate? Wouldn’t you immediately decide in favour of the virtuous character? ‘It wouldn’t matter which of the competitors was preferred if there were no other beings in the world, or if all memory of the giving of the benefit were to be immediately obliterated’—could anyone say that? Everyone would think that the virtuous person is worthy of the benefit, and the other unworthy—i.e. their respective characters are such that it is right for the benefit to go to one rather than to the other. What makes it right? Not the effects of the two characters (which in many such cases we don’t take time to consider); rather, is it immediately and ultimately right, for the same reason that beneficence is right, and quite generally the reason that objects and relations are what they are.

So the moral worth or merit of an agent is

his virtue considered as •implying that good should come to him in preference to others, and as •inclining all observers to esteem and love him and try to bring him happiness.

—Virtue naturally and of itself recommends a person for favour and happiness, and makes the virtuous person a proper object of encouragement and reward....

I don’t deny that one important reason for the rightness of favouring virtue and disfavouring vice is the obvious tendency that this has to prevent misery and to preserve order and happiness in the world. All I’m saying is that that’s not the only thing that makes such a ·reward/punishment· procedure right, and that even apart from any consideration of public interest it would still be right to distinguish how the virtuous are treated from how the vicious are treated.... Imagine this:

A race of reasonable beings are made to pass through a particular stage of existence and are then annihilated. While they existed, differences in their ·moral· characters didn’t bring any difference in how they were treated. Virtue was not favoured, or vice punished; happiness and misery were distributed randomly, the guilty often prospered and flourished, the good were often afflicted and distressed.... The most wicked were generally the least sufferers, and the most upright the least happy; though over-all there was more happiness than unhappiness. And there was no connection between these beings and the rest of the universe.

Will anyone say that there was nothing wrong in this total state of affairs?—It will be said ·by those who insist that the reward/punishment procedure is justified only by its consequences·—indeed it’s the only thing they can say—that

42

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 4: Ideas of good and ill desert

the described state of affairs can’t be approved because there would have been more happiness among those beings if their different life-outcomes had been ordered in accordance with the rules of distributive justice. ·Perhaps there would·, but is this so blazingly obvious that everyone’s disapproval must be always immediately determined by it? ‘It could have produced more happiness than it did’—is that the only thing that can be wrong with a social arrangement? ·I say that it is not·. To an unbiased mind one state of affairs x will give more satisfaction than another state of affairs y if they involve the same total amount of happiness but in x the happiness is distributed with a regard for the moral characters of the individual people while in y it isn’t.

Take the case of a single, solitary evil being: it may be that the only thing that could justify putting him into a state of absolute misery would be that this would tend to reform him. But why do we approve of doing things to bring about his reformation? Don’t say ‘It is because his reformation would make him happier’, or anyway don’t say that that’s the whole reason. If it were, there would no moral difference between

•the case where he is made happy as a result of being punished and thus reformed

and

•the case where he is made happy by being given such an extraordinary supply of advantages that it outweighed any sufferings that inevitably followed from his vices.

Can we equally approve these opposite methods of treating such a being? Supposing the same quantity of happiness is enjoyed, does it make no moral difference whether a being enjoys it in a course of wickedness, or of virtue?—Someone who disagrees with the line I am taking here might reject that last example by claiming that there’s no possible way for a being to escape the hurtful effects of his vices or lose the beneficial effects of his virtue. That is extravagant, and we see enough in the present world to convince us that it is false!

[Price now has a paragraph referring to all the •questions that arise about guilt and innocence, and propriety of punishment or reward, in particular cases. He says that he has no general answers to •these, and that he doesn’t need to because •they don’t touch his central thesis about the moral basis for rewards and punishments.]

This perception of good and ill desert is the source of •the passion of resentment, •the hopes that unavoidably spring up in every virtuous mind, and the •terrors and anticipations of punishment that accompany a consciousness of guilt.

Let me add that there’s no perception of our minds that is more fitting for us to attend to than this one ·about reward/punishment·.... To have this perception is to see that, according to just order and equity, sin is the forfeiture of our expectations of good, and virtue is the ground of the highest hope.—Considered merely as a principlec in the natures that God has given us, i.e. a determination that is built into our constitution, it carries with it a declaration by the Author of our minds, telling us how he will deal with us and what the exercise of his goodness to us depends on. [The next sentence contains ‘evidentness’, which will recur on page 49 and several places after that. It replaces Price’s ‘evidence’, which he and his contemporaries used in two ways: (i) in talk about the evidence for P or evidence that P; (ii) in talk about the ‘evidence’ of P, the ‘evidence’ that P itself—or an argument for P—has. We still have sense (i), but (ii) has almost disappeared. (It lingers on only in the phrase ‘self-evidence’: to speak of P’s self-evidence is to speak of its being evident taken on its own, not to speak of its constituting evidence for its own truth.) Throughout this version, ‘evidence’ in sense (ii) will be replaced by ‘evidentness’.]—But considered as a necessary

43

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

perception of reason, it proves—with the evidentness of a demonstration—what supreme reason will do, what laws and rules it observes in carrying on the happiness of the universe, and that what it aims at is not simply happiness but happiness enjoyed with virtue. [A footnote here quotes from Butler’s Analogy of Religion a passage agreeing with what Price is saying.]

Before moving to the next chapter, I can’t help asking you once more to reflect on the reverse of nature that could have occurred if the opinion about the foundation of morals that I have opposed were true. Try to conceive of the world, and of all our ideas of good, of morality, of perfection, and of God, as turned upside down—with the principal things we think about being not •what they now seem to be but •as perceived in terms of entirely contrary notions by all intelligent beings:

•what is now approved and esteemed instead being disapproved and hated,

•what is now seen as fit, worthy, lovable and excellent instead seeming evil and base,

•cruelty, impiety, ingratitude and treachery seen as virtue and beneficence,

•piety, gratitude and faithfulness seen as wickedness,

•the aversion we feel for cruelty etc. being produced by piety etc.,

•respect and love aroused by harmful behaviour,

•contempt and resentment aroused by acts of kindness,

•misery prevailing throughout the world as happiness now does, and chosen and pursued with the same universal approval and ardor,

•virtue conceived as having demerit, and vice as deserving of reward.

—-Can these things be? Does nothing in any of them conflict with the natures of things?

Chapter 5

How morality connects with God’s nature.

The reliability of our faculties. The grounds of belief

1. I have contended that morality is necessary and immutable. There’s an objection to this that some writers have thought to have considerable weight, and it should be examined. It could be expressed thus:

‘Your thesis about the nature of morality sets up something distinct from God, something that is independent of him, and equally eternal and necessary.’

It’s easy to see that this difficulty doesn’t bear on morality any more than it bears on all truth. If this point forces us to •give up the unalterable natures of right and wrong and •make them dependent on the Divine will, then it also forces us to •give up all necessary truth and •assert that contradictions may be true. [The occurrences of ‘truth’ and ‘necessary truth’ in this version exactly follow Price’s.]

44

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

What I have tried to show is that morality is a branch of necessary truth, and that it has the same foundation as it, ·i.e. as every other necessary truth·. If this is accepted, the main point I contend for is granted, and I shall be content to let truth and morality stand or fall together. Still, an adequate treatment of the source of morality requires that this latest difficulty be thought about; it’s one that naturally occurs to people in all enquiries of this sort.

Notice first that there is certainly something that we must allow to be independent of the will of God. ·In fact there are several things·: this will itself, God’s own existence, his eternity and immensity, the difference between power and impotence, wisdom and folly, truth and falsehood, existence and non-existence.

No-one would assert anything as extravagant as that these depend on God’s will, because that would imply that he is a changeable and unstable being, making it impossible for us to form any consistent ideas of his existence and attributes. But if all truth were a creature of ·God’s· will, then these would have to be so too, ·and that is a proof that all truth is not a creature of God’s will·.—There is another view of this notion, which shows that it overthrows the Divine attributes and existence, because...

... Mind presupposes truth, and intelligence presupposes something intelligible. Wisdom presupposes things one can be wise about, and knowledge presupposes things that can be known.—An eternal and necessary mind presupposes eternal and necessary truth, and infinite knowledge presupposes an infinity of things that are knowable. So if there were no infinity of knowable things, and no truths that are eternal, necessary, and independent, there could be no infinite, necessary, independent mind or intelligence, because there would be nothing to be certainly and eternally known. Just as, if there were nothing possible, there could be no power; and if there were no necessary infinity of possibles, there could be no necessary and infinite power; because power presupposes objects, and eternal, necessary, infinite power presupposes an infinity of eternal and necessary possibles.

In the same way it can be said that if there were no moral distinctions, God couldn’t have any moral attributes. If there were nothing eternally and unalterably right or wrong, nothing could be meant by talk of God’s eternal, unalterable rectitude or holiness.—It is obvious, then, that annihilating (i) truth, possibility, or moral differences is annihilating (ii) all mind, all power, all goodness; and that so far as we make (i) unstable, dependent, or limited, to that extent we make (ii) unstable etc. also.

Hence we see clearly that to conceive of •truth as depending on God’s will is to conceive of •his intelligence and knowledge as depending on his will. Can anyone think that this is as reasonable as the rival view that God’s will is dependent on and regulated by his understanding?—What can be more preposterous than to make the Deity consist of nothing but •will, and to raise •this up in honour over the ruins of all his attributes?

You may want object as follows:

‘Those remarks don’t remove the difficulty; they strengthen it. They still leave us having to conceive of certain objects, distinct from Deity, that are necessary and independent and the basis for his existence and attributes....’

I answer that we ought to distinguish God’s will from his nature. Things that are independent of his will aren’t on that account independent of his nature. To conceive truth etc. as independent of God’s nature would indeed involve us inconsistency; any thoughts we have involving necessity and infinity involve acknowledging the eternal nature of God.

45

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

I think we’ll be more willing to accept this when we have attentively considered what abstract truth and possibility are. Our thoughts are here lost in a bottomless abyss where we find room to push deeper and deeper and the very notion of reaching a point beyond which there is nothing further implies a contradiction. There is a genuine infinity of ideal objects and truths that could be known; and of....worlds that could exist although they are wholly inconceivable by finite minds. We can’t think away this infinity of truth and possibility; try as we may, it always returns on us. Every thought and every idea of every mind, every kind of agency and power, and every degree of intellectual improvement and pre-eminence amongst all reasonable beings, imply its necessary and unchangeable existence.—This has to be the uncreated, infinite •reason and power of God, from which all other reason and power are derived, offering •themselves to our minds and forcing us to see and acknowledge •them....—There is nothing so intimate with us, so united with our natures, as God. We find that he is included in all our conceptions, and necessary to all the operations of our minds. He couldn’t be necessarily existent if this weren’t true of him, because the idea of •necessary existence implies that •it is fundamental to all other existence and presupposed in every notion we can form of anything....

It is worth observing that this gives us a kind of intuition of the •unity of God. Infinite, abstract truth is essentially •one. It is just as clear that there is only one infinite truth as that there is only one space and one time. When we have fixed our thoughts on infinite truth, and try to imagine a another infinity of it, we find ourselves trying absurdly to imagine another infinity of the same truth. So it is self-evident that there can only be one infinite mind. Infinite truth implies the existence of
Price’s phrase: one infinite essence as its subtratum,
probably meaning: one total-state-of-affairs that it is the truth about,
and only one. If there were more, they wouldn’t be necessary.—Particular truths that are contemplated at the same time by many different minds aren’t different, any more than the present moment of time is different in one place from what it is in another, or than the sun is different because it is viewed at the same time by many eyes.

Bear in mind that necessary truth includes •the comparative natures of happiness and misery, •the rightness of producing the one and the wrongness of producing the other, and quite generally •moral truth, moral fitness and excellence, and all that is best to be done in all cases, and with respect to all the variety of actual or possible beings and worlds.—This is the necessary goodness of God’s nature.—It demonstrates that absolute rectitude is included in the God’s intellect, and that eternal, infinite power and reason are essentially combined with—and imply—complete moral excellence, and especially perfect and boundless benevolence. It shows us that whenever we go against truth and right, we immediately insult God who is truth and right, and that whenever we conduct ourselves in ways that conform to truth and right, we pay immediate homage to him.

All this makes it clear that no-one has reason to be offended when morality is represented as eternal and immutable, because it turns out that this is only saying that God himself is eternal and immutable, and making his nature the high and sacred original [Price’s word] of virtue, and the sole fountain of all that is true and good and perfect.

[After mentioning two writers who have argued in the same way as himself, Price adds:] There is perhaps no subject where more must be trusted to each person’s own reflection, where the deficiencies of language make themselves

46

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

more felt, or on which it is more difficult to write so as to be entirely understood....

2. This is the place to discuss another difficulty that has been raised—one that concerns morality. It ·can be expressed in three questions·:

•Doesn’t the truth of all our knowledge presuppose that our faculties are properly constituted?

•Isn’t it possible that they have been so constituted that they inevitably deceive us in everything we get from them?

•How can we know that this isn’t actually the case?^12

You may imagine that these questions present difficulties that can’t be overcome, and that they tie us down to universal and incurable scepticism. We can’t test the truth of our faculties (you may say) except by these very suspected faculties themselves, and testing them in that way would be pointless, achieving nothing but to lead us back to our starting-point.—·You could take this further·: it is not only •us but •all thinking creatures who are thus reduced to a state of everlasting scepticism. And even further: it must be impossible for God to make any creature who could satisfy himself about anything—who could even be sure of his own existence! What satisfaction can any creature obtain except through the intervention of his faculties? and how can he know that they aren’t deceivers?—These are very strange consequences, but let us consider the following two points.

(1) If we do have this difficulty, we are informed of it by our faculties; so if we don’t know that they should be trusted we don’t know that this difficulty is real!—A little later on I shall show that it is a contradiction to suppose that our faculties can teach us to suspect all their deliverances.

(2) Our natures are such that we can’t believe something if we see (or think we see) evidence against it. So if we are confronted by anything that appears to be evidence against the proposition that our faculties are so built that they always deceive us, we are obliged to reject this proposition. Evidence must produce •conviction proportioned to how strong the evidence is thought to be, and •conviction is inconsistent with suspicion. ‘In our present case no evidence should be given any weight, because all our evidence comes through our suspected faculties’—that claim is just empty, because we can never suspect or doubt without reason, let alone against reason. Doubting presupposes evidence, so there can’t be any such thing as doubting whether evidence itself is to be given weight. A man who doubts the veracity [= ‘truthfulness’] of his faculties must do this on their own authority—i.e. at the very time and in the very act of suspecting them he must trust them! It is obviously self-destructive to •try to prove by reason that reason shouldn’t be trusted, or to •assert that we have reason for thinking that there is no such thing as reason; and it is certainly no less self-destructive to claim that we have reason to doubt whether •reason is to be trusted or (the same thing) whether •our faculties are to be trusted. When it is acknowledged there is no reason for doubt, it will be ridiculous to claim to doubt.

These remarks might be enough, because they show us that the point in debate is something that we are obliged to take for granted and that can’t be questioned. Still, it will be of some use to go into more detail about the meaning of the question ‘Do our faculties always deceive us?’, and to show what the evidence really is that they don’t.

It’s impossible to perceive something that isn’t true.—Now, it is certain that there is a great variety of truths that we think we perceive, so the whole question is whether we

^12 I probably wouldn’t have discussed this objection if it hadn’t been raised by Cudworth at the end of his work on eternal and immutable reality, and answered in a way that I think is not quite clear and satisfactory.

47

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

really perceive them. The existence of absolute truth is presupposed in the ·sceptical· objection. Suspicion of our faculties and fear of being deceived obviously imply that there is truth; to deny that it exists would be to contradict oneself, because it would be to assert that it is true that nothing is true! This holds also for doubting whether there is anything true, because doubting involves •a hesitation or suspense of the mind about the truth of what is doubted, and therefore •a tacit acknowledgment that there is something true. Take away this, and there is no idea of it left [that sentence is verbatim Price].

So universal scepticism is impossible; truth remains even after we have taken it away! There is perceivable truth, then, and we are unavoidably led to believe that we may—and that we often do—perceive it. But the point I wanted to make here was that •to doubt the reliability of our faculties is •to suspect that our reason may be so formed that it misrepresents every object of science to us—to question whether we ever know or only imagine we know, e.g. whether we actually perceive or only imagine that we perceive a circle to be different from a triangle, or a whole to be bigger than a part.

To the extent that we •can’t doubt concerning these things, or •find ourselves forced to think we perceive them, to that extent we can’t doubt our faculties, and are forced to think them right.—So it turns out that we have all the reason for believing our faculties that we have for •assenting to any self-evident propositions or for •believing that we have any real perceptions.—Whatever we perceive, we perceive as it is, and to perceive nothing as it is is to perceive nothing at all. A mind can’t be without ideas, and what ideas it has must be true ideas, because a wrong idea of an object is the same as no idea of it or as the idea of some other object.

Observations of this kind may show us the truth of the following conclusions.

(1) No being can be made who will perceive falsehood. What is false is nothing. Error is always an effect not of perception but of lack of perception. As far as our perceptions go, they must correspond to the truth of things.

(2) No being can be made who will have different ideas yet not see them as different. This would involve having the ideas and at the same time not having them.^13

So there can’t be any rational beings who don’t assent to all the truths that are involved in the apprehended difference between ideas.—For example, to have the ideas of a whole and a part is the same as seeing one to be greater than the other. To have •the ideas of two figures and •an exact coincidence between them when laid on one another is the same as seeing them to be equal. The point holds also for many of the truths that we establish by demonstration [= ‘logically rigorous proof’], because demonstration is only the self-evident application of self-evident principles.

In short, either there are truths that we are forced to think we know, or there are not. Probably no-one will assert that there are not—i.e. declare seriously there’s nothing that he can’t help believing. (If there were such a person, he couldn’t be reasoned with; his declaration gives itself the lie, but there would be no point in telling him this!)—So if there are truths that we think we perceive, it is the greatest folly to claim at the same time that we aren’t sure of the reliability of our understandings with respect to them, i.e. to be unsure

^13 ·There are two ways in which we can go wrong about our ideas·: We can mis-name an idea, and we can wrongly think that an idea present in our minds at one time is the same as one that was present at another time. But it’s inconceivable that a being contemplating two ideas at the same time should then think them to be not two ideas but one. You can’t have two ideas before your mind without being conscious of it; and you can’t be conscious of it without •knowing them to be different and •having a complete view and discernment of them as far as they are your ideas.

48

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

whether we perceive them or not.—•Thinking we are right, •believing, and •thinking our faculties to be right are one and the same. Someone who says that he isn’t sure that his eyes are not so made as always to deceive him can’t consistently go on to say that he believes he sees some external object. If there is anything that we have a necessary determination to believe [i.e. that we are compelled by our nature to believe], we have a necessary determination to believe our faculties; and to the extent that we believe them, we can’t distrust them. When people say things of the form

•‘On the supposition that my faculties are properly made, I am sure of such-and-such things’,

they have it backwards. What they ought to say is:

•‘I am sure of such and such truths, and therefore I am to that extent sure that my faculties inform me rightly.’

You may want to object: ‘I have found myself mistaken in many cases; how can I know that I am not mistaken in all cases?’—I answer: look into yourself and examine your own conceptions. You can tell from how clear and distinct your apprehension is ·regarding any particular proposition· whether you are right about it or whether instead you may be wrong. Don’t you really know that you are not deceived when you think that if equals are taken from equals, the remainders will be equal? Can you have the least doubt about whether the body of the sun is bigger than it appears to the naked eye? or do you think you get a reason to question this from the fact that you once thought otherwise? Granted that you have judged wrongly in some cases—through ignorance, haste, prejudice, or the like—is it reasonable for you to suspect that you judge wrong in all cases, however clear they may be? Granted that through bodily indisposition or other causes •our senses sometimes misrepresent outward objects to us, does that discredit •them for ever? Because we sometimes dream, must it be doubtful whether we are ever awake? Because one man deceived us once, are we to conclude that no trust should be put in any human testimony? Because our memories have deceived us with respect to some events, must we question whether we remember rightly what happened a moment ago?^14

But let’s suppose that for this or some other reason it is possible that all our recollections are wrong, all our opinions false, and all our ‘knowledge’ delusion, that is still only a bare possibility to set against all reason and evidentness,

^14 Inferences of this sort—strange as they may seem—have been actually conducted. It has been argued that because in adding a long series of numbers we are liable to err, we can’t be sure that we are right when we add the smallest numbers, and therefore may be wrong in calculating that twice two equals four.
Another sceptical argument that has been insisted on is this: In every judgment that we can form, besides (i) the uncertainty involved in our original consideration of the subject itself, there is (ii) another uncertainty involved in our consideration of the fallibility of our faculties and the past instances in which we have been mistaken. And then we must add (iii) a third uncertainty derived from the possibility of error in the estimate that we make at level (ii), to which must be added (iv) a fourth of the same kind, and so on ad infinitum; the final result being that the evidentness [see note on page 43] of the original proposition is whittled away to nothing. See Hume’s Treatise of Human Nature I.iv.1. The part of this strange reasoning that isn’t above my comprehension proves just the reverse of what was intended by it. Granted: the consideration of the fallibility of our understandings, and of the cases where they have deceived us, necessarily lessens our confidence that we are right in our opinion that P (let P be anything you like); but when we go on to think about the uncertainty involved in this judgment about our faculties, this strengthens our confidence in P rather than lessening it! Why? Because if proposition Q is unfavourable to proposition P, anything that counts against confidence in Q counts somewhat in favour of confidence in P.

49

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

and the whole weight and bent of our minds [Price’s phrase] obliging us to think the contrary. It’s not in our power to give any weight to a simple may be in opposition to any apparent evidentness [see note on page 43],^15 much less in opposition to the strongest.—Let’s go even further, and suppose that there could be a set of rational beings in a state of necessary and total deception, ones to whom nothing of truth and reality ever appears. This is in fact absolutely impossible; I have already pointed out that this amounts to supposing these beings to have no intellectual perception; it is inconsistent with the very idea of their existing as thinking beings. However, let’s grant it as a possibility; we still can’t help thinking that we are not such beings, and that such beings couldn’t possibly think and perceive as we do.

In short, whatever things seem to us to be, we must take them to be; and whatever our faculties inform us of, we must accept.—Therefore much of the scepticism that some ·philosophers· have professed and defended has to be mere affectation and self-deception.

3. I shall conclude this chapter with a few remarks about the general grounds of belief and assent. These grounds fall into three classes.

(1) The first is immediate consciousness, i.e. feeling. It is absurd to ask why we believe what we feel, i.e. what we are inwardly conscious of. A thinking being must have a capacity for discovering some things in this way. It is especially from this source that we get the knowledge of our own existence, and of the various operations, passions, and sensations of our minds. In this category I also include the information we get from our powers of recollection or memory.

(2) The second ground of belief is intuition, by which I mean the mind’s survey of its own ideas and the relations between them, and the notice it takes of what is true or false, consistent or inconsistent, possible or impossible in the natures of things. As I explained at length in chapter 1, this is the source of all our •beliefs in self-evident truths, our •ideas of the general abstract states and relations of things, our •moral ideas, and •everything else that we discover without using any process of reasoning.—It is essential to all rational minds to have some degree of this power of intuition, and the whole possibility of all reasoning is based on it. It is always the final court of appeal....—There have to be some truths that can appear only by their own light and can’t be proved; otherwise nothing could be proved or known, just as there could be no words if there were no letters, and no complex ideas if there were no simple and undefinable ideas.—Many truths can only be known intuitively, though learned men have enormously confused and obscured them by supposing that they could be known by reasoning and deduction. The subject of this book is one of the most important examples of this; another example is our notion of the necessity that whatever begins to exist has a cause, and our general ideas of power and connection. Sometimes, reason has been ridiculously employed to prove even our own existence!

(3) The third ground of belief is argumentation or deduction. We resort to this when intuition fails us; and, as I have just been hinting, it is highly necessary that we carefully distinguish intuition from deduction, mark their differences and limits, and take note of what we learn from one of them and what we learn from the other.—Our ideas are such that

^15 How trifling then is it to allege, against something that seems to have the balance of evidence in its favour, that if we knew more perhaps we might see equal evidence against it! It is always a full answer to this, to say ‘Perhaps not’.—Something that we are wholly unacquainted with may, for all we can tell, count as much for any of our opinions as against them.

50

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

by comparing them with one another [see note in Preface] we can discover countless truths concerning them, and therefore truths concerning actually existent objects so far as they correspond to our ideas—truths that would otherwise be undiscoverable. Thus, a particular relation between two ideas that can’t be seen by any immediate comparison may very satisfactorily appear with the help of a mediating idea whose relation to each is either self-evident or established by previous reasoning....

There is no need for me to give examples of knowledge derived from argumentation. We can ascribe to it everything that we ·know and· haven’t received from either immediate consciousness or intuition.

[Price now spends a paragraph saying that each of the three bases for belief produces beliefs that vary in how evident they are. Even intuition is ‘sometimes faint and obscure’. In the next paragraph he says that we do or could discover some things in two or even all three of the ways he has described; and he adds an emphatic lecture on the advantages to us of getting clear about what the basis is for each of our beliefs.]

An example of something discovered in all three of the ways I have described is the existence of matter. (1) Immediate feeling reveals to us our own organs and the states they are in; the soul perceives these by being present with them. We have the ideas of matter and of a material world, so we (2) see intuitively that the existence of material things is possible. (Something that is impossible is nothing, and therefore not an object of reflection, i.e. not something of which there can be an idea. So any idea of any object implies that it’s possible for that object to exist.) ·And then (3) argumentation, reasoning, plays its part, as follows·. We are conscious of certain impressions made on us....from outside ourselves, and know they are produced by some external cause. We touch a solid substance and feel resistance. We see certain images drawn on our organs of sight and know that something is acting on them. The resistance may be due to a resisting body, and the scenes painted before us may be derived from a corresponding external scene revealing itself to us by means of intermediate matter. If there is an external world, in what better manner could we be informed about it? The sceptical challenge says this:

All the information conveyed to us by our senses, and all the impressions made upon them—corresponding in detail to the supposition of an external world and confirming one another in countless ways—are entirely visionary and delusive.

What is more incredible than that? Admittedly, it is still possible that matter doesn’t exist. Just as it is possible •that the planets are not inhabited, though every particle of matter on the earth abounds with ·living· inhabitants; •that the power that keeps them in their orbits is something other than gravity, though it’s certainly gravity that keeps our moon in its orbit; and •that we are the only beings in the world and the only productions of divine power, though we have the greatest reason to think otherwise—namely the bare fact that we exist, and the consequent possibility and likelihood that countless other beings exist also.... In short, it is self-evident that a material world matching •our ideas and •what we feel and see is possible. We have no reason to think that it doesn’t exist. Everything appears as if a material world did exist, and against the reality of its existence there is nothing but a bare possibility, to be weighed against actual feeling and all the evidence that our circumstances and condition as embodied spirits seem capable of.

It is well known what controversies have recently been raised on this subject. Some writers have denied the existence of a material world; others, finding that they couldn’t

51

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 5: Morality and God’s nature etc.

seriously doubt that there is such a world, treat their conviction as something we can’t help having though we can’t account for it. It would take me too far afield to add to what I have already said about the nature and grounds of this conviction of ours. So I shall just make one point: the principles on which the existence of •matter is opposed lead us equally to deny the existence of •spiritual beings. Anyone who rejects matter but believes in minds should tell us what reasons he has to believe there exist any beings whatsoever beside himself!

This dispute, after all, turns chiefly on the question ‘Is matter, considered as something actually existing outside the mind and independent of its perceptions, possible?’ There are probably not many people who will deny the existence of matter for any reason except their belief that it is impossible.—One would think that there’s no need to spend time in refuting this. Whatever is conceivable can’t be impossible—if that isn’t indisputable, nothing is!....

But it is time to get to topics that are more closely related to my plans for this book.

[In the third edition Price appended an end-note commenting on what he has just said.]
·START OF END-NOTE·
I have to admit that my observations about the grounds of our belief in the existence of material objects don’t entirely satisfy me; but I have chosen to leave them as they were in the earlier editions, thinking that they might give some help to future enquirers. If you would like to be entertained as well as instructed by a detailed discussion of this subject, and by a full account of all the different theories and opinions concerning it, you should read the two first of Reid’s Essays on the Intellectual Powers of Man. Reid’s own opinion seems to be that the perception of external objects by our senses is •a conception of them and •a belief in their present existence—a belief that our constitution causes to accompany the impressions on our sense-organs, a belief of which no further explanation can be given. It seems to me that a perception by our senses involves more than is here expressed. A •conception of objects is often produced by impressions on the senses, and accompanied by a •belief in their present existence, without anything like an actual •perception of them. But whatever problems there may be here, the evidence of sense (like the evidence of memory) will always maintain its authority; and it may be best for us to •content ourselves with feeling this, and to •accept our natures as they are, rather than risking creating confusion and darkness by refining too much and trying to explain something that is so clear that it can’t be explained.
·END OF END-NOTE·

52

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

Chapter 6

Fitness and moral obligation. Other accounts of obligation.

How rightness relates to obligation.

How other writers have expressed themselves when explaining morality

1. After the account I have given of the nature and origin of our ideas of morality, it will be easy to perceive the meaning of many terms and phrases that are commonly used in speaking about this subject.

‘Fitness’ (and ‘unfitness’) often mean (i) something about how a certain means relates to a certain end—that it is apt or appropriate (inapt or inappropriate) for reaching that end. But when they are applied to actions, these words generally mean (ii) the same as ‘right’ and ‘wrong’; and it is usually easy to tell which of these senses these words are being given. It is worth noting that ‘fitness’ in sense (i) is just as indefinable as ‘fitness’ in sense (ii): it is as impossible to say what we mean when we say of certain objects, that (i) they have a fitness to one another, i.e. are fit to serve certain purposes, as it is to say what we mean when we say that (ii) reverencing God is fit, or that beneficence is fit to be practised. [Price includes a clause in that sentence, allowing that in either case we might ‘say what we mean’ by presenting a synonym for the word in question—e.g. equating (i) ‘fit’ with ‘apt’. Though he doesn’t say so, explanations through synonyms are regarded as useless because in each case it is a single word that is presented, rather than a several-word phrase that could help to spell out the meaning of the word that is being defined.] It must be obvious to everyone that it would be absurd to maintain that the source of the idea of (i) fitness is an arbitrary sense of the word ‘fitness’, and to conclude that •it signifies nothing real in objects and that •no one thing can be properly the means of another. In both sense (i) and sense (ii), the term ‘fit’ signifies a simple perception of the understanding. [For this use of ‘arbitrary’, see the note on page 4. By ‘can be properly the means of...’ Price evidently means ‘can be, as a matter of cold objective fact, the means to...’.]

‘Morally good’ and ‘evil’, ‘reasonable’ and ‘unreasonable’ are terms that are also commonly applied to actions, obviously meaning the same as ‘right’ and ‘wrong’, ‘fit’ and ‘unfit’.

‘Approving’ an action is the same as seeing it to be right, just as ‘assenting’ to a proposition is the same as seeing it to be true.

But the term that most needs consideration here is ‘obligation’, and more than two-thirds of this chapter will be devoted to it. [The chapter’s other topic starts on page 62, number 4.]

Obligation to action obviously coincides with—is identical to—rightness of action, to such an extent that we can’t form a notion of either of them without taking in the other. To see this for yourself, consider: can you point out any difference between •what is right, meet or fit to be done and •what ought to be done? Think about how clear it is that

•shape implies something that has the shape,

•solidity implies resistance, and

•an effect implies a cause;

—well, it is as clear as that that rightness implies oughtness (if I may be allowed this word) or obligatoriness. Just as we can’t conceive of shape without extension, or motion without a change of place, we can’t conceive of an action’s being fit

53

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

for us to do without its being something that we should do, that it is our duty to do, or that we are under an obligation to do.—Thus, ‘right’, ‘fit’, ‘ought’, ‘should’, ‘duty’ and ‘obligation’ express ideas that necessarily include one another. From this I draw five conclusions.

(1) •Virtue as such has a real obligatory power independently of •all positive laws and of •all will, because (as we have just seen) obligation is involved in the very nature of •it. To affirm something of this form:

It would be wrong not to do A, but doing A is not obligatory unless it is conducive to private good (or: unless it is commanded by a superior power)

is an obvious contradiction. It amounts to saying that it’s not true that •a thing is what it is, or that •we are obliged to do what we ought to do, unless it is commanded or is in some way privately useful!—If any actions are fit to be done by an agent—other than those that tend to his own happiness—those actions are obligatory independently of their influence on his happiness. [Price says that this is so ‘by the terms’, apparently meaning that it is so because of the meaning(s) of ‘fit’ and ‘obligatory’.]—If it is wrong for us to do something then it is our duty not to do it, whether or not we are commanded by any positive law.^16—-I can’t conceive of anything much more evident than this.—So it turns out that those who maintain that all obligation is derived from positive laws or God’s will or self-love, if they mean anything that conflicts with what I have been saying, are asserting that the words ‘right’ and ‘just’ don’t stand for any real and distinct properties of actions, but merely signify what is willed and commanded or conducive to private advantage, whatever that may be; so that •anything can be right and wrong at once, morally good and evil at once, depending on what has been commanded or forbidden by different laws and wills; and •even the most pernicious effects will become ‘just’ and ‘fit to be produced’ by anyone to whom they offer even the smallest degree of clear advantage or pleasure.

Those who say that nothing can create an obligation but the will of God generally hold that God’s power to create obligations consists in his power to assign rewards and punishments for various actions. Thus they in fact subvert entirely the independent natures of moral good and evil, and are forced to maintain that nothing can give us an obligation except the prospect of pleasure to be had ·from divine rewards· or pain ·from divine punishents·. This implies that •vice is really mere imprudence, that •nothing is right or wrong, just or unjust, except insofar as it affects selfinterest, and that •an independently and completely happy being can’t have any moral perceptions. The soundness of these inferences is guaranteed by the coincidence between obligation and virtue that I have been insisting on

Let’s pursue this point further. If a person believed either that •there is no God or that •God doesn’t concern himself with human affairs, would he escape being in any way accountable for his actions because he felt no moral obligations? If someone happened not to be convinced that virtue tends to his happiness in this life or the next, would he be released from every bond of duty and morality? And what about someone who didn’t believe in any future state and did believe that acting virtuously in certain cases would be against his present interests—would he in those cases be truly obliged to be wicked?....

Those who contend that self-interest is the only ground of moral obligation sometimes say that when virtue clashes with present enjoyment all motives to virtue cease (supposing

^16 Obviously, this is very different from saying (absurdly) that if a given action would be wrong to perform in certain circumstances then it will continue to be wrong when the circumstances are greatly altered.

54

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

that there is no future state). This is strange, because on their principles the truth is not that in those circumstances all motives to practise virtue would cease, but rather that virtue itself would cease; indeed, that it would be changed into vice, so that something that would otherwise have been fit and just would become unlawful and wrong....

Something else worth mentioning here is that rewards and punishments presuppose, in the very idea of them, moral obligation; they are based on it. Rather than •creating obligations, they •enforce them.... A •reward presupposes something done to deserve •it, something conforming to an obligation that existed previously to it; and punishment is always inflicted on account of some breach of obligation. If we had no obligations before the proposal of rewards and punishments, it would be a contradiction to suppose that we could be rewarded or punished.—Someone who was led only by the light of nature, and who was ignorant of a future state of rewards and punishments and of the will of the Deity, might discover these—·i.e. discover that there is a future state of rewards and punishments, and that there is a God who has a will·—by reasoning from his natural notions of morality and duty. But if those ·moral· notions depend on the other (·theological·) ones, this discovery couldn’t be made, and we would be left with nothing from which to learn God’s will and the conditions of his favour to us.

(2) Rectitude [= ‘rightness’] is a law as well as a rule to us, i.e. it doesn’t only •direct us but •binds us as far as we perceive it.—It certainly is a rule: taking it that ‘rule of action’ signifies some measure or standard to which our actions should conform, or some information we have regarding what we ought to do, rectitude is in this sense the only rule of action; anything else that is properly called a ‘rule’ is merely a help to the discovery of the rectitude rule. To perceive or to be informed about how it is right to act is the very notion of a direction to act. And it must be added that it is a direction that implies authority, and that we cannot disregard or neglect it without remorse and pain. Reason is the natural and authoritative guide of a rational being. The only rational beings who are (morally speaking) free are those who have no discernment of right and wrong. Someone who has this discernment—through which moral good appears to him and he can’t help judging of some action that it is fit to be done and evil to omit it—is strictly and absolutely tied in bonds that no power in nature can dissolve, and from which he can’t ever break loose without •doing unnatural violence to himself, •conducting an assault on his own soul, and immediately •pronouncing his own sentence. [The phrase ‘tied in bonds’ echoes the origin of ‘oblige’ and ‘obligation’ in the Latin obligare = ‘to tie down’.]

Something is strictly speaking a law to us if we always and unavoidably feel and admit ourselves to be obliged to obey it, and if our obedience (or disobedience) to it brings the immediate sanctions of •inward triumph and self-applause (or inward shame and self-reproach), together with •secret thoughts of the favour (or displeasure) of a superior righteous power, and •expectations of future rewards (or punishments).—Something has proper authority over us if our refusal to submit to it involves •transgressing our duty, •incurring guilt, and •exposing ourselves to just vengeance. All this is certainly true of our moral judgment, and contained in the idea of it.

So rectitude—i.e. virtue—is a law. It is the first and supreme law; all other laws owe their force to it, depend on it, and create obligations because of their relation to it. It is a universal law. The whole creation is ruled by it: men and all rational beings exist under it. It is the source and guide of all the actions of God himself, and his throne and government are founded on it. It is an unalterable and indispensable

55

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

law. There’s a contradiction in supposing that it might ever be suspended, or even relaxed a little, in any part of the universe. Any other law

•has had a date—a time when it was enacted and came into force,

•is confined to a particular region of the universe,

•rests on insecure foundations, and

•can lose its vigour, grow obsolete with time, and become useless and neglected.

Nothing like this can be true of the law of rectitude. It has no date: it never was made or enacted; it has always been in force. It is prior to all things. It is self-valid and self-originated, and must forever retain its usefulness and vigour, without any possibility of being lessened ·in scope· or relaxed ·in severity·. It is

•as unalterable as any necessary and everlasting truth is,

•as independent as the existence of God is, and

•as sacred and awe-inspiring as God’s nature and perfections are.

—Its authority is essential to it, underived and absolute. It is superior to all other authority, and is indeed the basis and parent of all other authority. Strictly speaking, in fact, there is no other authority, nothing else that can claim our obedience or that ought to guide and rule heaven and earth.—Summing up: it is the one authority in nature, the same at all times and in all places; in a word, it is the divine authority.

(3) It is absurd to ask ‘What obliges us to practise virtue?’, as though obligation were not part of the idea of virtue but something extraneous and foreign to it, i.e. as though what is due might not have been our duty, or what is wrong might not have been unlawful....—The question ‘Why are we obliged to practise virtue, to abstain from what is wicked, and do what is just?’ is exactly the same as asking ‘Why are we obliged to do what we are obliged to do?’—I can’t help wondering at those •who have so unaccountably tangled themselves in difficulties over a subject that one would think had no difficulty, and •who, because they can’t find anything in virtue and duty themselves that could induce us to respect them in our behaviour, fall back on self-love, maintaining that it is the sole source of all inducements and obligations.

(4) Now we can see in what sense God can be said to ‘have obligations’. Saying this about him is merely •saying that he has a perception of what is right, or •saying that in the government of the world there are certain ends and certain means that he approves, and that are better to be pursued than others.—But we must be very careful about what language we use in discussing this topic. ‘Obligation’ is a word to which many people have attached various ideas that certainly shouldn’t be retained when we speak of God. Whenever we are talking or thinking about God, our language and our conceptions are extremely defective and inadequate, and often very erroneous.—Many •people think it absurd and shocking to attribute anything like an obligation or law to a being who is necessarily ·self·-sufficient and independent, and to whom nothing can be prior or superior—·earlier or higher·. I have already indicated, to some extent, how we should form our thoughts on this subject. The •people I have mentioned should be satisfied with this: the obligations that God is said to have arise entirely from—and exist entirely in—his own nature; and the eternal, unchangeable law by which I have said he is directed in all his actions is nothing but himself—his own infinite, eternal, all-perfect understanding.

(5) It is clear now what the basis is for the obligations of religion and God’s will. Those obligations are clearly branches of universal rectitude. To say that we have an

56

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

obligation to obey God’s will is merely to say that....it is right and fit to obey it. How absurd it is to make obligation •subsequent to God’s will, and •created by it! If that were right, wouldn’t all will oblige equally? If there’s anything that makes one will preferable to another, it is, by the terms [see note on page 54], moral rectitude. What would the laws or the will of any being signify, what influence could they have on the decisions of a moral agent, if there were •no good reason to obey them, •no obligation to respect them, •no pre-existing right of command?—‘We are obliged, but not in virtue of reason and right’—that is just to say that we ·are obliged but· are not obliged at all!—Furthermore, nothing could be ever commanded by God if there was no prior reason for commanding it....

Notice how the ideas of right and wrong force themselves on us, staying with us in some form or other even when we think we have annihilated them. For example, after we have supposed that all actions and ends are in themselves indifferent [= ‘neither morally required nor morally ruled out’], one naturally thinks that it is right to give ourselves up to the guidance of unrestrained inclination, and wrong to be careful in our actions or to give ourselves any trouble in pursuing any ends. Or if we join Hobbes and the orator in Plato’s Gorgias in supposing that

the strongest may •oppress the weakest and •take for themselves whatever they can seize,

or that

unlimited power confers an unlimited right,

this obviously still leaves us with the idea of right, and merely establishes another species of it.—Similarly, when we suppose that all the obligations of morality are derived from •laws and contracts, we at the same time find that we have to suppose something before •them—something not absolutely indifferent in respect of choice, something good or evil, right or wrong—that gave rise to •them and led to their being respected after they were made.

Returning now to my main topic: God’s sovereign authority comes not merely from •his almighty power but also from

•his necessary perfections,

•the infinite excellences of his nature as the fountain of reason and wisdom,

•the entire dependence of all beings on him, and

•their getting from his bounty their existence and all its blessings and hopes.

These are the reasons that make him the proper object of our supreme homage, create his right to govern,....and make it the first duty of the whole thinking world to obey, to please, and to honour him in everything they think and do.—Those who hold that God’s power to make us happy or miserable is all the reason we have to obey him and all the meaning there is in our ‘obligation’ to obey him—those people are maintaining something that it’s amazing to see seriously accepted by a human mind! They’re maintaining that •if we could suppose that we had nothing to hope or fear from God we wouldn’t have the least desire for his approval, or the least concern about what he expects from us, or any reason for paying any attention to him; that •setting aside the consideration of our own ·self·-interest, it simply doesn’t matter what our dispositions and behaviour are with regard to God; that •his nature, attributes and benefits—however glorious they may be—are in themselves incapable of having any effect on any rational nature; and that •if we suppose God to have his actual power but to have the rest of his character changed or reversed, we would still be equally obliged to love, revere, and obey him, to resign our wills to his, and to try to win his approval.

57

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

2. What I have said will tell us what to think about various accounts and definitions of obligation that have been given. These are clear cases of the puzzles that arise from trying to define words that express simple perceptions of the mind. ·I shall discuss six of them·.

(i) An ingenious and able writer, John Balguy, defines ‘obligation’ as ‘a state of the mind into which it is brought by perceiving a reason for action’. If you substitute this definition for every occurrence of the words ‘duty’, ‘should’ or ‘obliged’, you’ll soon see how defective it is. What it is saying is that ‘obligation’ denotes the attraction or excitement that the mind feels when it perceives right and wrong. But that isn’t •obligation—it’s merely •the effect of perceiving an obligation. Also, apply that definition to the correct statement ‘The duty or obligation to act is a reason for acting’ and you get ‘Obligation is a state of the mind into which it is brought by perceiving an obligation to act’! [Price reports and criticises another part of Balguy’s account of obligation, and diagnoses its trouble:] What produces confusion in these cases is the failure to distinguish •perception from •the effect of perception, between •obligation and •motive. Not all motives are obligations, though all obligations create motives....

(ii) Several writers have said that obligation is the necessity of doing a thing in order to be happy.^17

I have already said enough about the opinion from which this definition is derived, and therefore shall here only ask: If this is the only meaning of ‘obligation’, what is the meaning of the statement ‘A man is obliged to take account of his own happiness’? Isn’t it obvious that this statement means only that it is right to take account of our own happiness, and wrong to neglect it? If we interpret the statement in terms of the definition at the start of this paragraph, taking ‘obliged’ to mean ‘required for happiness’, the statement is ridiculous because then it means only that if you are to be happy you need to take account of your happiness.

(iii) The very learned William Warburton maintains that ‘moral obligation’ always denotes some object of will and law, i.e. implies some obliger. If that were right, it would be jargon to talk about our being ‘obliged to obey the Divine

^17 Bishop Cumberland in his treatise On the Laws of Nature etc. writes: ‘The whole force of obligation is this: the legislator has annexed natural good to the observance of his laws and natural evil to the transgression of them, and the prospect of such ·rewards or punishments· moves men to perform actions agreeing with the laws rather than disagreeing with them.’—And again: ‘I think that moral obligation can be universally and properly defined thus: Obligation is the act of a legislator by which he declares that actions conformable to his law are necessary for those for whom the law is made. An action is then understood to be necessary for a rational agent when it is certainly one of the causes required for the happiness that he naturally—and therefore necessarily—desires.’....—The remarks made on these passages by Maxwell, the translator of Cumberland’s treatise from the Latin in which he wrote it, are so good that I cannot help copying some of them here. Speaking of the necessity of observing the law as a means to our happiness, Maxwell writes: ‘If this is the whole of the law’s obligation, then breaking the law is not •unrighteous, sinful and criminal, but merely •imprudent and unfortunate.... But the obligation or bond of the law is the legal restraint expressed by non licet, “you may not do it”; but a bare non licet or prohibition isn’t sufficient to enforce the law; so the legal restraint links the sin with punishment—links the precept with a sanction—and the full expression of it is non licet impune, “you may not do it with impunity”. But though sin and punishment are closely connected, the obligation of non licet (it may not be done) is distinct from the obligation of non impune (not with impunity), because sin and punishment are distinct things to think about. But if a man can’t do a thing •without sin, or can’t do a thing •without punishment, he is bound [= ‘obliged’] either way; and both these obligations are in every •law, and they jointly create the obligation to keep •it.’ [Maxwell goes on to say that the obligation of non licet comes before the obligation of non impune, which is to say that the law has moral force independently of there being punishments for breaking it. He develops this line of thought at some length.]

58

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

will’, whereas in fact that is a perfectly proper thing to say. Actually, he seems to mean that the word ‘obligation’ signifies only the special case of the fitness of obeying the Divine will, and can’t properly be applied to any other fitness; and this narrows the sense of the word in a way that doesn’t fit the common use of it.

(iv) The sense that Hutcheson gives to ‘obligation’ agrees to some extent with my account of it. He says that a person is obliged to perform an action if every spectator—and the person himself, on reflection—must approve of his performing it and disapproving of his not performing it. But this isn’t perfectly accurate, and here is why. Although

•obligation to act, in one sense,^18

and although

•obligation to act (in that sense) implies and is implied by •reflex approval and disapproval,

they seem to differ as an act of the mind differs from an object of the mind, or as perception differs from the truth that is perceived. Saying that it is our duty to do A isn’t just the same as saying that we approve of doing A; one is the quality of the action, the other the mind’s discernment of that quality. The two are so strongly connected that there is often no great need to distinguish them, and in ordinary speech the term ‘obligation’ often stands for the sense and judgment of the mind regarding what is fit or unfit to be done. [In the phrase ‘sense and judgment’, the word ‘sense’ isn’t doing much work. (The same is true of its occurrence in ‘sense and conscience’ quoted from Clarke on the next page, where Clarke implicitly equates that phrase with ‘judgment and conscience’.) Price is not slipping into the view that we have an implanted and arbitrary moral sense.] Still, I think it would prevent some confusion, and keep our ideas more distinct and clear, if we bore in mind that a man’s •judgment that he has an obligation to do something is not strictly speaking •the obligation itself, and that ‘obligation’ in its primary and basic meaning coincides with ‘rectitude’ ·or ‘rightness’·, however variously and loosely the word may

^18 Why only ‘in one sense’? Because a man may, through involuntary error approve of doing something that he ought not to do, or think to be his duty something that is really contrary to it; and yet in such a case it is really his duty to act in conformity with his judgment. So there are two views of obligation, which will be apt to produce confusion if we don’t attend to them. In one sense, a man’s being (i) obliged to act in a particular manner depends on his knowing that he is; in another sense, his being (ii) obliged doesn’t depend on this. Without (i) we could incur guilt when acting with the fullest approval of our consciences. Without (ii) it would make no sense to speak of showing someone what his obligations are.... This perfectly fits the division of virtue into •absolute and •relative, which I shall explain in chapter 8. [In this footnote, every occurrence of ‘sense’ is Price’s; so is the word ‘views’—it seems that the ‘two views of obligation’ somehow correspond to the two senses of ‘obligation’.] does always accompany •reflex approval and disapproval,
^19 I notice that William Adams in his excellent sermon on The Nature and Obligation of Virtue agrees with me in his account of obligation. What does the obligation to virtue and right action consist in? He answers:

‘The idea of right includes the idea of duty. To perceive an action to be right is to see a reason for doing it—seeing this in the action itself, abstracted from all other considerations. This perception, this acknowledged rightness of the action, is the very essence of obligation; it is what commands the approval and choice, and binds the conscience, of every rational being.’

And again:

‘Nothing can bring us under an obligation to do what appears to our moral judgment to be wrong. We can make sense of “Consider a case where it is in someone’s interests to do something he thinks to be wrong”, but we can’t make any sense of “Consider a case where it is someone’s duty to do something he thinks to be wrong”.’

59

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

be used in common speech.^19

(v) I leave it to you to judge how far these remarks are applicable to what Samuel Clarke says on this topic in his Evidences of Natural and revealed Religion. His account of obligation is very like the one I have just been discussing, and it may be worthwhile to quote some of his remarks. ‘The truest and most formal obligation to act in a certain way comes from

the judgment and conscience of a man’s own mind concerning the reasonableness and fitness of acting in accordance with a given rule or law.

This is more properly and strictly obliging than

any opinion regarding the authority of the giver of a law,

and than

any concern he may have regarding its sanctions by rewards and punishments.

What gives primacy to the first of these is the fact that anyone who acts contrary to this sense and conscience of his own mind is necessarily self-condemned, and the greatest and strongest of all obligations is the one that a man can’t break through without condemning himself.—The obligation that is the source of all other obligations is the eternal reason of things, the reason that God himself—despite having no superior to direct him, and being happy in a way that can’t be increased or lessened—constantly obliges himself to govern the world by.’....

(vi) Joseph Butler in his Sermons on Human Nature and the explanatory remarks on them in the Preface, insists strongly on •the obligation implied in reflex approval—i.e. a man’s approval of his own conduct when he reflects on it—on •the supremacy of the principlec of reflection within us; and on •the authority and right-to-direct that are constituent parts of the idea of self-approval. Let me borrow one more observation from this incomparable writer (I am not quoting him verbatim):

Every being who is endowed with reason and conscious of right and wrong is necessarily a law to himself. So the greatest possible degree of ignorance or scepticism concerning •the likely effects of virtue, •the authority of the Deity, •a future state, and •the rewards and punishments to be expected in it, still leaves us fully accountable, guilty, and punishable, if we break this law. Our ignorance or scepticism won’t do anything to exempt us from justice, won’t help in the slightest to excuse or save us, if it should turn out that such authority and future state do really exist. What makes an agent ill-deserving is not •any opinion he may have about a superior power or positive [see note on page 5] sanctions, but •his doing wrong by acting contrary to the conviction of his mind.....

3. A certain objection to this deserves to be considered. [In a footnote Price refers to Henry Home’s Essays on the Principles of Morality and Natural Religion.] It may be asked:

‘Aren’t there many actions—e.g. returning good for evil, acting generously and kindly—of which it can’t

[He talks a little about other pressures to do what one thinks to be wrong. Then:]

‘Power may compel, interest may bribe, pleasure may persuade, but only reason can oblige. This is the only authority that rational beings can accept and the only one to which they owe obedience.’

I have been very agreeably surprised by the agreement—here and elsewhere—between my opinions about virtue and those of this most judicious writer. It has given me more confidence in some of the opinions I have maintained than I would otherwise have had.

60

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

be said that we are bound ·or •obliged· to perform them, but which it is •right for us to perform? And doesn’t the actual performance of these actions appear to us even more morally attractive than if they had been strictly our duty?’

I answer that the most that can follow from this is not that rightness doesn’t imply obligation, but that it doesn’t imply it so absolutely and universally that there can be no sense in which actions can be called ‘right’ without implying that they are obligatory. The nature of rightness may vary according to the objects or actions to which it is ascribed. It is not the case that all right actions are ‘right’ in precisely the same sense of the word, and it wouldn’t do much harm to the position I have been defending if we granted that some things are ‘right’ in a sense that doesn’t imply that they are our indispensable duty. But then let it be remembered that this proposition:

Whatever is ‘right’ in a sense such that the omission of it would be wrong is always and indispensably obligatory,

holds universally and incontestably. And let it be understood also that although the idea of •rightness may be more general than that of fitness, duty, or obligation,....this can’t be said of •wrongness. The ideas of wrongness and obligation certainly have the same range: I mean that although there may be cases where something that we approve of as right isn’t something that ought to be done, everything that we disapprove of as wrong is something that ought not to be done.

I have dealt with ·Home’s· point by restricting my initial position regarding how rightness relates to obligation; but a more careful enquiry will reveal that no such restriction is needed. The following remarks support this.

(a) Beneficence in general is undoubtedly a duty, and it is only with respect to the particular acts and instances of it that we are at liberty. Someone performs an act of kindness to someone else: we say ‘He might not have done it’ or ‘He wasn’t obliged to do it’—i.e. he wasn’t obliged to perform this particular kind act. But everyone is obliged to be kind sometimes, to do all the good he can to his fellow-creatures; and we necessarily regard a person as blameworthy and guilty if he •doesn’t have that aim and •contents himself with merely abstaining from injury and mischief. We owe to those about us a certain part of our fortunes and labour, but the particular objects and methods of beneficence are not absolutely fixed. Here we are left to our own choice, and....there may be nothing in any particular objects or methods of beneficence that make it fit and right they should be chosen rather than others. (·Though sometimes there is·.... Other things being equal, it is right that friends, relations, and benefactors should be preferred to strangers, and anyone who does otherwise is acting contrary to his duty.)

(b) The precise limits of some general duties can’t be determined by us. No-one can tell exactly how beneficent he ought to be, how far he is obliged to exert himself for the benefit of other men.... To form a judgment about this in particular cases, we must attend to so many details in our own circumstances and abilities, and in the state of mankind and the world, that we can’t help being in some uncertainty.... The same is true of the general duty of worshipping God. Exactly how and how often God ought to be worshipped has not been clearly marked out to us.... ·But· whenever any degree of beneficence, or any particular method and frequency of divine worship, appears to be—all things considered—best, then it becomes obligatory....

‘But what shall we say regarding the greater amiableness [= ‘moral attractiveness’; see note on page 29] of the actions in

61

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

question? How can there be greater virtue, or any virtue at all, in performing particular actions that we could have omitted without any blame?’—The answer is easy. What makes an agent qualify as ‘virtuous’ and entitles him to praise is his acting from a regard for goodness and right. Now, someone may be acting from a regard for goodness and right when he does something that he was morally required to do or something that he wasn’t; relieving a miserable person is virtue, even if there is no reason that obliges the agent to select this miserable person in particular out of many others. Worshipping God may arise from a general sense of duty, even in someone who knows that the particular times and manner of his worship have nothing morally better in them.—And as to the greater merit we see in many actions of this kind,....here is the explanation of that.—Everything an agent does is virtuous to the extent that he was determined to it by a concern for virtue, so the more of this concern the action reveals, the more we must admire it. Someone who fixes on more rather than less ·beneficence, worship, or whatever· reveals a correspondingly stronger virtuous principlec. If he chooses to devote more of his fortune, time, and labour to promoting the happiness of his fellow-creatures, or to serving his neighbours or his country, when for all he knows to the contrary he might have done much less and still deserved commendation, it is more obvious that he is acting from good motives. And even when someone goes too far in this direction, being led to visible extremes and an inappropriate neglect of his private concerns, we always approve—except when we suspect the influence of indirect motives....

(c) It has been said that the performance of mere duty produces no love or friendship towards the agent. This is far from being true; on the contrary, someone who—however tempted and opposed he may be—does his whole duty, trying faithfully and uniformly to be and do in every way just what he ought to be and do, is the object of our highest love and friendship. ·The false thesis about ‘mere duty’ in relation to love and friendship seems to be based on the idea that we will have affectionate feelings about someone who does more than his ‘mere duty’. But that is false too·. To aim at acting beyond obligation is the same as aiming at acting contrary to obligation; doing more than is fit to be done is the same as doing wrong.

4. Having presented what appears to me to be the true account of the nature and foundation of moral good and evil and of moral obligation, I will now add, as a supplement to this chapter, an examination of some of the forms of expression that various eminent writers have used on this subject.

To grasp the meaning and design of these expressions, bear this in mind: necessarily all actions are •right, •indifferent, or •wrong; and which category a given action belongs to is the truth of the case—i.e. the facts about the agent and the objects and the relations between them. There are certain ways of behaving that we unavoidably approve of as soon as we know what the relations are—·i.e. how the agent or the action relates to other people or other facts or things·. Change the relations and a different way of behaving becomes right. Nothing is clearer than that what is due or not due, proper or improper to be done, must vary according to the different natures and circumstances of the things and people involved. If a particular treatment of one nature is right, it can’t possibly be the case that the same treatment of a different nature, or of all natures, is right.

That is the source of the expressions

‘acting suitably to the natures of things’,
‘treating things as they are’,
‘conformity to truth’,

62

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

‘agreement’ and ‘disagreement’ between actions and relations.

These expressions are useless, almost senseless, if considered as intended to define virtue, because they evidently presuppose virtue. Treating an object ‘as being what it is’ is treating it in the way that is right for such an object. ‘Conforming ourselves to truth’ means the same as conforming ourselves to the true state and relations we are in, which is the same as doing what is right in such a state and such relations. In given circumstances, there is some particular definite action that is the best to be done; and when these circumstances cease, that action stops being the best, and other obligations arise. This naturally leads us to speak of ‘acting suitably’ to circumstances, natures, and characters, and of the ‘agreement’ and ‘disagreement’ between them. When these ways of speaking are understood in this way, they are wholly proper and intelligible. But it is very obvious that they are only different phrases for ‘right’ and ‘wrong’! I wish that the writers who have used them had attended more to this, and avoided the ambiguity and confusion arising from •seeming to deny that there is any immediate perception of morality without any deductions of reasoning, and from •trying to give definitions of words that can’t be defined. If someone defined ‘pleasure’ as ‘the agreement between a faculty and its object’, what would we learn from that? Wouldn’t we be entitled to ask: ‘What is this “agreement”? Do you mean by it anything other than the pleasure itself that the object is fitted to produce by its influence on the faculty?’

It is well known that William Wollaston, in a work that has rightly obtained a great reputation, places •the whole notion of moral good and evil in •signifying and denying truth. If he means that all virtue and vice comes down to these particular instances of them, it’s very obvious that this leaves the nature and origin of our ideas of virtue and vice as undetermined as they were before. It doesn’t tell us where our ideas of the rightness of telling the truth and wrongness of lying come from; it supposes them to be perceptions of self-evident truths, as indeed they are, but no more so than our ideas of the other principles of morality.—The evil of ingratitude and cruelty is not the same as the evil of affirming a lie. [Price’s next bit is stated awkwardly, in terms of a technical term of Wollaston’s. Its gist is that lying or producing false beliefs doesn’t define what it is for an action to be subjectively wrong, wrong from the point of view of the agent] because there may be no intention to deny anything true, or to get anyone to accept anything false. If someone were the only rational creature in the world, he couldn’t aim to declare a falsehood to anyone; but ingratitude and cruelty would still be wrong, because they are quite distinct species of evil.—Someone who neglects the worship due to God may have no thought of denying God’s existence or of conveying that denial to anyone else. It’s true that he acts •as if God didn’t exist, i.e. •in a manner that can’t be justified unless God doesn’t exist, and so figuratively speaking he may be said to contradict truth and to declare himself to be self-caused and self-sufficient.^20

This eminent writer probably meant to say little more than this, and I don’t absolutely condemn the ·figurative· language that he has introduced. All I want is to guard

^20 It is so obvious that the basis for talking in this way in this case is our perceiving that if God exists then this way of behaving is wrong—this being a perception that we have independently of any ‘figurative’ talk about ‘contradicting truth’! Similarly with any other examples Wollaston might produce. In short: We can never know when to say that an action affirms or denies truth unless we already have a perception of its being right or of its being wrong. So how can such language explain and define right and wrong?

63

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

against applying it wrongly.

With that same aim in mind, I must add that when it is said that

P: virtue consists in conformity to the relations of persons and things,

this mustn’t be considered as a definition of ‘virtue’ or as intended to give a reason justifying the practice of virtue. Nothing can be gained by P when it is used with ·either of· those intentions. If we ask ‘Why is it right to conform ourselves to the relations in which persons and objects stand to us?’, we’ll find ourselves obliged to end up with a simple perception ·through which· something is ultimately approved, ·i.e. approved· without any justifying reason being givable for it.—Explaining virtue by saying that

Q: virtue consists in the conformity of our actions to reason

is even less proper, because this ‘conformity to reason’ can only mean that our actions are such as our reason discerns to be right, so that Q says only that virtue is doing right. [Price has a footnote here, quoting William Adams—already invoked in the footnote on page 59—saying things that agree with what Price has just been saying.]

Note also that P and Q don’t direct us to proper criteria by which to judge in all cases what is morally good or evil. If after weighing the state and circumstances of a case, we don’t perceive how it is proper to act, it would be word-spinning to tell us ‘Well, find out which action is in conformity with the state and circumstances’! If in a given case we can’t discover what is •right then we must be also equally unable to determine what is •suitable to those circumstances. It is indeed very proper to direct us, in order to judge an action, to try to discover the whole truth about its probable or possible consequences, the circumstances and features of the object, and the relations the agent has ·to that object·, because this (I repeat) is what determines the moral nature of the action; and that is all that can ·properly· be intended by presenting truth and relations as criteria of virtue.

‘If the language we are considering—·i.e. the likes of P and Q above·—doesn’t express either definitions or proper criteria of virtue, what use is it? What is it for? I answer that it is clearly intended to show that morality is based on truth and reason, i.e. that it is as necessary and immutable as the natural proportions and essential differences of things, and is perceived by the same power as they are.

‘But is it anything more than a bare assertion? What proof of this does it convey?’ In reply to this, one might point out that the same questions can be put to those who have maintained the contrary view, namely that our ideas of morality are derived from an arbitrary •sense [see note on page 4], and not from ideas of the •understanding. They regard this as something that has been decided; but before reaching that conclusion, I think, they should have examined the matter more thoroughly.

The (1) agreement of proportion between certain quantities—·as expressed for example in the truths of arithmetic·—is •real and necessary, and is •perceived by the understanding. Why should we doubt that the (2) agreement of ·moral· fitness between certain actions and certain relations is also •real and necessary, and •perceived by that same faculty? The different natures, properties, and positions of objects necessarily result in

(1) different relative ·non-moral· fitnesses and unfitnesses,

different productive powers, different aptitudes to different ends, and agreements or disagreements among themselves. Where’s the absurdity in saying that the various relations of beings and objects result in

(2) different moral fitnesses and unfitnesses of action,

64

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 6: Other writers on morals

different obligations of conduct, which are just as real and unalterable as the former, and equally independent of our ideas and opinions? For (1) any particular natural objects to exist at all is the same as their existing with such-and-such mutual proportions. Similarly, for (2) reasonable beings of particular natures and capacities to exist at all in such-andsuch circumstances and relations is the same as its being the case that such-and-such conduct is fit or proper. And just as the Author of nature in creating the objects in (1) willed the existence of the proportions and truths implied in them, so also in creating the beings in (2) and placing them in their respective relations to one another and to himself, he willed that such-and-such actions should be performed and such-and-such duties observed.—When we (2) compare [see note in Preface] innocence and eternal misery, the idea of unsuitableness between them arises in our minds. And from (1) comparing together many natural objects and beings we get an idea of a totally different kind of unsuitableness, perceiving some kind of clash between them—e.g. that one can’t be made to fit into the other, or that their different properties cannot co-exist in a single thing, or that they can’t produce such-and-such particular effects on one another. Why should the mis-match in (2) be regarded as less real than the mis-matches in (1)?—No-one can avoid admitting that he has the idea of unsuitableness (i.e. a sentiment of wrong) in the application of eternal misery to innocence. I challenge him to find a reason for denying that this is a sentiment of his understanding and a perception of truth.

The advocates of ‘fitness’ as the foundation of morality have been arguing to this purpose; the drift of their assertions and reasonings seems to me to have been in the direction of views like mine. But it must be admitted that they have used ·certain· words too loosely, providing an opening for the objections of those who have embraced and defended the contrary opinion. It wouldn’t be difficult to show how a similar dispute might break out concerning the origin of our ideas of power and connection—the same objections offered, and the same tangles produced!

[The chapter finishes with a paragraph comparing knowledge of good and evil with knowledge of equality and inequality. It consists mainly in a criticism of certain misuses of language that might infect either of these topics; the misuses are not intrinsically interesting, and Price does not name any of the culprits.]

65

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

Chapter 7:

What are the main kinds of virtue?

There are still three more questions to be considered regarding virtue:

(1) What are the main kinds of virtue? What specific sorts of behaviour do we label as ‘virtuous’?

(2) What is the principlec or motive from which a virtuous agent acts?

(3) What does it mean when we say that some actions and characters are more virtuous than others? And how do we judge this?

I shall address the questions in that order—·(1) in this chapter, (2) in chapter 8, and (3) in chapter 9·.

There would be less need to raise question (1) if it weren’t for the fact that several writers have maintained that the whole of virtue consists in benevolence. I can’t improve on what Bishop Butler said about this:

‘Benevolence and the lack of it, considered on their own, are nothing like the whole of virtue and vice. If they were the whole of virtue and vice,....we would approve of benevolence to some persons rather than to others only on the grounds that this was thought likely to produce more happiness ·than any other distribution of benevolence·, and we would disapprove of injustice and falsehood only because of the misery they are likely to produce. But that isn’t how we think about these matters. Take the case of two men who are competitors for some good that would be equally advantageous for both of them. It would be grossly impertinent for a stranger to busy himself with getting one of them preferred over the other; but if such efforts were exerted on behalf of a friend or a benefactor they would count as virtuous, quite apart from any thoughts about distant consequences (e.g. that examples of gratitude and care for friendship would in a general way be good for the world). [Butler then gives a second example: increasing the amount of happiness in the world by stealing something from one person and giving it to another who would enjoy it more.] (This is from the fifth observation in the Dissertation on the Nature of Virtue, appended to Butler’s Analogy of Religion.)

The cases Butler presents are clear and decisive, and it’s hard to think of anything that can be said in reply to them. And many other cases could be cited.—Promises, for example: it can’t be true that •promises are never binding on anyone except when he thinks that keeping them will produce good for the whole to society, or that •we are free from any obligation to keep a promise as soon as we believe that breaking it won’t hurt the person to whom it was made; or that •if breaking a promise would harm to the person to whom it was made, that will be balanced by the benefit it will bring to ourselves....[Price continues with colourful presentations of treacherous actions that would obviously be morally vile, whatever difference their consequences made to the balance of good and evil. Followed by similar exclamations about the wrongness of lying, even in a case where lying would result in more over-all happiness than telling the truth. He sums up:]—Can we, when we consider these things, avoid declaring that there is intrinsic rightness in keeping promises and in sincerity, and an intrinsic evil in their contraries?....We are faced here with the idea that the goodness of the end always

66

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

consecrates the means, i.e. that other things being equal it is as innocent and laudable to achieve our purposes by lies, prevarication and perjury as it is to achieve them by faithful and open dealing and honest labour! Could this be seriously defended? Could it even be tolerated by an honest mind?....

This is about as bad as a mistake can be, because, as Butler observes, ‘it is certain that some of the most shocking instances of injustice, adultery, murder, perjury, and even persecution could sometimes not seem likely to produce an overbalance of misery in the present state [see note on page 119], and sometimes may even appear to produce an overbalance the other way’....

No-one denies that the human mind disapproves of ingratitude, injustice, and deceit; what we are arguing about is the ground for this disapproval. Does it arise solely from thoughts about inconvenience to others and the confusion that such behaviour causes; or is the behaviour immediately perceived to be wrong, independently of its effects? The examples and considerations that I have offered seem to settle this well enough; it appears that when the behaviour in question produces no harm, even when it is in some degree beneficial, we still disapprove of it.

It may be replied that in cases of this kind the source of our disapproval is ·connected with the thought of beneficial consequences, in one or other of these two ways·:

•Custom has established in our minds the idea of a plan or system of common benefit, and we see these vices as inconsistent with that.

•We are in the habit of considering these vices as having generally bad consequences, and we’re unconsciously influenced by that when we think about particular cases.

—But why must we have recourse to the influence of habits and associations ·or general plans· in this case? This has been the refuge of everyone who wants to reduce all our moral perceptions to thoughts about private advantage, and it can be used to evade almost any evidence provided by our experience of the workings of our minds and the motives of our actions. ·To see that it doesn’t work, consider this·: From the cases I have mentioned we can remove entirely the idea of a public, and suppose that no-one exists whose state can be in any way affected by the actions in question; or we can suppose that all memory of the action will be lost for ever as soon as it is done, and that the agent foresees this; and either way the same ideas of the ingratitude, injustice, or violation of truth will remain.—If the whole reason for respecting truth-telling arose from its influence on society, a primitive Christian wouldn’t have been blameworthy for renouncing his religion, blaspheming Christ, and worshipping the pagan gods (all of which are merely denials of the truth) whenever he could purchase his life by these means and at the same time avoid discovery, and thus prevent any harm to Christians and pagans that might arise from his conduct!....

Also, it doesn’t seem that mankind in general does pay much attention to remote consequences. Children, especially, can’t be supposed to think about consequences, or to have any fixed ideas of a public or a community, yet we see in them the same aversion to falsehood and liking for truth as in the rest of mankind.... Those who derive all our desires and actions from self-love are often met with the objection that they are crediting men with views and reasonings which never entered the minds of most of them, and which probably haven’t been thought of by anyone in ordinary everyday life.—The same objection holds against those who derive all our sentiments of moral good and evil from our approval of benevolence and disapproval of the lack of it; and both ·of these schools of thought· have, in my opinion, undertaken tasks that are almost equally

67

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

impracticable. Look impartially into your own mind: in your dislike of various vices don’t you feel something different from a thought about how they will lessen happiness or produce misery? Isn’t it easy for you to see that it isn’t merely under those notions that you always censure and condemn them? It is true that when you do have this thought ·about bad consequences· it heightens your disapproval. Falsehood, ingratitude, and injustice undermine the foundations of all social relations and happiness, and if they became universal the consequences would be terrible.—For this reason, if morality were based on an arbitrary structure of our minds, there would have to be distinct senses—·one each for lying, ingratitude, and injustice·—that immediately condemned and forbade them. The alternative would be leaving them to the influence of a general disapproval of all actions showing a neglect of public good, with no particular attitude against them except to the extent that people thought them likely to produce more misery than happiness; and the effects of that arrangement would be dreadful. It probably wouldn’t even come close to giving human society a reasonable degree of order. Many people are incapable of thinking broadly; their thoughts are confined within the narrowest limits. And all people are naturally •disinclined to pay any attention to remote events, and •liable to take up the wrongest opinions about the probable consequences of their actions....

[In unhelpfully elaborate prose, Price now refers to the conflict between ‘All virtue is benevolent’ and ‘Each of us cares only about his own interests’; and between ‘All morality is a matter of asserting or denying the truth’ and ‘The moral status of truth-telling comes entirely from its relation to beneficence’. He responds to this pair of debates with a protest:] Why must there be in the human mind approval only of one sort of actions? Why must all moral good be reduced to one particular species of it....? Why mightn’t we have an immediate liking for truth, for candour, sincerity, piety, gratitude, and many other kinds and principlesc of conduct?—If all our ideas of morality are to be derived from implanted attitudes, the attitudes towards candour, sincerity etc. are just as possible as the attitude towards benevolence; and, as I indicated earlier, securing the general welfare requires all of them as well as the benevolence one, so that one would expect that a good Being would give them to us.

Men have such a love of uniformity and simplicity that they look for them where it is difficult to find them! This is unreasonable, and in other intellectual areas it has often led men astray. In natural philosophy [here = ‘science’] great mistakes and extravagances have been produced by the desire to discover •one principlec to account for •all effects. I don’t deny that in the human mind, as well as in the material world, examples of wonderful simplicity are to be found; but we should learn to wait until careful observation and enquiry shows us what that simplicity consists in, and not •permit ourselves to rush to any conclusion about it, or to •accept any ·claims about· general causes and principlesc that can’t be proved by experience.

If the account of morality that I have given is sound, it’s inconceivable that the whole of our duty should consist in promoting the happiness of others, or that we could determine what is right or wrong without taking account of anything except the public good....

With these remarks as an introduction, I shall now proceed to list six of the most important branches of virtue, or types of rectitude and duty.

(1) What requires the first place is our duty to God—i.e. the whole of that regard, subjection and homage that we owe him. [Price will reach (2) on page 71.] These seem unquestionably to be objects of moral approval independently of any question of utility. They are regarded as indispensably obligatory, but

68

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

when we perform those duties the source of our conduct can’t be an intention to be in any way useful or profitable to the object of them [i.e. to God]! It would take an uncommonly weak and ignorant man to intend by his religious services to increase the happiness of the Deity, or to think that God expects his gratitude and prayers because of what they will do for Him. I know that some very worrhy writers have written as though they thought that the secret spring of all obedience to God....is a desire to contribute to his satisfaction and delight. It would be wasting the time of most of my readers to spend much time showing the prodigious absurdity of such an opinion!

[Price writes this next paragraph as an indirect-speech report on a possible conversation; this version instead presents it directly as a conversation. The content has not been altered.] Let us suppose we are questioning a pious man who has good sense and no superstitions:

‘Why do you approve of piety to God? Is it to make God happy? Do you submit to his will and worship and pray to him because you think that these activities will—in the literal sense of the words—please or gratify him?’

‘Certainly not! (pause) I obey and worship God because it is right for me to do so—because I see it as my duty.’

‘Why do you think that obedience and devotion to God is your duty?’

‘Because God is the creator, governor, and benefactor of the whole world; and especially because he is my creator, governor, and benefactor.’

‘Why do you think it is your duty to honour and worship your maker, benefactor and governor?’

Our pious man would wonder at this question, as well he might! It would seem to him to be like asking ‘Why is twenty greater than two?’—Why shouldn’t we admit here the natural and unperverted sentiments [Price’s word] of men, and acknowledge that submission, reverence, and devotion to such a being as God are—as much as any behaviour towards our fellow-men—instances of immediate duty intuitively perceived, the perception of which is a spring and motive of action, just as friendly feelings are. There’s no difficulty about this, and it seems obviously right.

[Price says now that no-one who thinks about it will believe that we could have an effect on God’s ‘state and happiness’; but even if we could do this (he continues), that wouldn’t ‘have any effect in releasing’ us from our religious duties. Then:] It is true that pious and virtuous people are actuated by their love for God, which implies joy in his happiness; but this love would never produce any acts of acknowledgement and obedience towards him, or any care for the good of others in accordance with his intentions, if the people in question •didn’t think they could affect his happiness, and at the same time •had no perception of fitness in such behaviour independently of such effects.

These remarks apply in some degree to superiors and benefactors among created beings; the grounds of duty towards them are of the same general kind as the grounds of our duty to God. A fellow-man may be so much above us in station and character, and so little within the reach of any effects of our conduct, that the reason for our respectful and submissive behaviour towards him can’t be any prospect of bringing him benefit; the main spur to action—perhaps the only one—is our sense of what is in itself right, decent, or appropriate.—To any being we owe suitable feelings, attitudes and ways of behaving—made suitable by his nature, character, abilities, and relation to us. And as long as his character and relation to us don’t change, the behaviour we owe to him doesn’t change either; the two are tied together as invariably as the proportion between any two numbers or geometrical figures.—The •higher the rank of any being is,

69

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

the more perfect his nature, the more excellent his character, the closer his connections with us, and the more he has done for us, •the more strict and indispensable our duty to him is, and the greater is the degree of regard, affection, and submission that we owe him.

This last remark shows us what ideas we ought to have of the importance of the duty we owe to God, and of its place among our other duties. [Price fills a vast paragraph with details about this, a rhapsodic account of the worship we owe to God because of the infinite greatness (also ecstatically described) of his power, goodness, superiority to us, and so on. For example, ‘The whole universe, compared with God, is nothing in itself, nothing to us. He ought then to be all to us....’. The paragraph touches on moral philosophy here:] It is here, undoubtedly, that virtue ought to begin. It should arise out of this. A regard for God as our first and sovereign principlec of conduct should always possess us, accompany us in the performance of all our private and social duties, and govern our whole lives. [Price will expand on that soon. A couple of fragments from the remainder of this paragraph:] Every degree of real worth that we observe among inferior beings should be properly acknowledged and esteemed, but only as being mere rays from God’s glory and faint resemblances of his perfectionsld God ought to have supremacy in our minds; every action and design should be sacred to him....

I should remark on the extremely defective characters of people who, whatever they are like in other respects, live in neglect of God. It is a melancholy thing to see so many people able to maintain a good opinion of themselves although they know that they don’t think about piety or attend to the Author of all good. Misbehaviour of this kind is as truly inconsistent with goodness of character and sound virtue....as any other misbehaviour—can anyone seriously question that? If neglect and ingratitude towards the Author of the world doesn’t show great evil of character, what could do so? Why should impiety be less wicked than dishonesty?

Every man is to be loved and valued to the extent that he performs his private and social duties, and there’s nothing we can say that should discourage him. However much ·or little· real virtue a person possesses, he is sure to be better off—somehow or other—for any good that he does. Even if it isn’t what is needed to save him from just condemnation ·on the day of judgment·, it will at least make him that much less guilty and unhappy.—But as long as men continue to live without religion and piety, there is great reason to think that they don’t have the genuine principlec of virtue ·within them·, and don’t have much true moral worth. Their good behaviour of other kinds will probably come more from •instinct and natural temperament, or from •the love of distinction, authority, and private advantages, than from •a sincere concern for what is reasonable and fit as suchld—Someone who forgets God and his government, presence, and laws, lacks the main support and the living root of genuine virtue, as well as the most fruitful source of tranquillity and joy; and he won’t be capable of performing his duties to himself and others in an appropriately exact, careful, and reliable way. In fact, someone who doesn’t have the proper feelings towards the Author of his being....should be ashamed to present himself as having any integrity and goodness of character....

But I must add that the persons who fall into the contrary extreme are in every way the most inexcusable and wicked. I’m talking about those who purport to be religious though they have neither benevolence nor honesty, who are zealously devout but at the same time envious, peevish, perverse, spiteful, and can cheat and trick, lie and slander. Nothing can be conceived that would be more inconsistent or shameful than this.... Religion gives us the strongest motives for social

70

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

duties, and lays us under additional obligations to perform them. It is in the nature of religion to increase our zeal for everything just and good, to increase our love of all men, and to make us more gentle, mild, fair, honest, and upright, in proportion to the degree in which it truly possesses our hearts. So anyone who does something wrong while he is under some influence from religion and has the idea of God in his mind is that much more blameworthy and shows that much greater degeneracy and viciousness of character.

Before we leave this subject, let me pause a little in order to consider •what is meant by the will of God, and •how important and awe-inspiring a motive to action it implies. [What Price says on the strength-of-motive theme is pretty much what we would expect. One sample:] If someone who is tempted to do something unlawful would hold back until he had duly attended to the sense and felt the weight of the truth that ‘God disapproves of and forbids my doing this’, he would tremble at the thought of what he had been planning to do, and would lose all inclination to do it....

We aren’t in general at a loss to know what God wills. Whatever afflictions or disappointments happen to us....it is as certain that •he wills us to bear them and accept them as it is that •we suffer by them. ·Is it really as certain as that? Yes!· because it is demonstrable that in God’s world and under his eye nothing can happen to us that isn’t consented to him and directed by him. [Then some more about the strengthening effect of the conviction that what one is doing has God’s support, enabling one to think:] ‘I am doing the will of him to whom the world owes its birth, and whom the whole creation obeys; I am imitating the perfections and securing the friendship of the Being who •is everlasting truth and righteousness, who therefore •can’t be conceived to be indifferent to those who are truthful and righteous, and •who has infinite power and can cause all of nature to bless me with its provisions.’....

I don’t think that even the most casual reader will think that what I have been saying puts a greater stress on ·God’s will· than is consistent with the foundation of morals that I have been defending.

I have not said that God’s will can, of itself, have any effect on morality, or be an end and rule of action. Whether we take ‘God’s will’ to stand for •the general power of producing effects or •the actual exercise of this power, it is perfectly obvious that God’s will implies nothing in the nature of a rule, direction, or motive. It is entirely at the service of these, and presupposes them. •Understanding comes before •will, because when any thinking agent exercises his will he must be planning to produce some effect that he thinks to be possible; and •knowledge comes before •power, because when any thinking agent exercises his power he must know what he is doing. Any being that is capable of design and action has will in the general sense; so the mere fact that someone or something wills that we do A can never put pressure on us to do A.

What makes obedience to the will of God such a high and indispensable duty is precisely its being the will of God, the will of the universal and almighty parent, benefactor, and ruler, a will that

•is necessarily united with perfect rectitude,

•always acts on the dictates of perfect rectitude, and

•directs to what is absolutely best.

When we obey this will, then, what we are obeying is unerring rectitude, the voice of eternal wisdom, so that that is when we act most wisely.

(2) The second kind of virtue to be discussed [the first began on page 68] is the kind that has ourselves for its object. There is undoubtedly a certain way of behaving towards ourselves that is properly a matter of duty to us. ‘An action’s relation

71

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

to our own happiness or misery, when no other beings are affected, can’t have any influence in settling whether the action ought to be performed....’—that is too absurd to be maintained by anyone!—It is contradictory to suppose that the necessity that makes us choose and want a certain end is not accompanied by approval of using the means for attaining that end. •How we employ our faculties in doing things relating to our own interest is no more morally indifferent than is •how we behave to our fellow-creatures. If it is my duty to promote the good of someone else and to avoid hurting him, it most certainly must be my duty to promote my own good and to avoid hurting myself. It would be contrary to all reason to deny this, i.e. to assert that I ought to be careful about the good of others but not of my own....—The truth of the matter is far from that. Other things being equal, it is right and appropriate for me to prefer myself to someone else—e.g. keeping for myself a means of enjoyment that I own rather than giving it to a stranger to whom it won’t be more beneficial than it is to me. It would be strange if anyone could avoid admitting this.

Clearly this provides another instance of right behaviour that doesn’t come from •friendly feelings, and can’t be explained in terms of any thoughts about •public utility or •sympathy with others. We have here •an indisputable proof that actions showing friendly feelings are not the only ones we approve of, namely •the fact that in many cases we approve of letting self-love prevail against friendly feelings for others, and are aware that in these cases it should thus prevail. Self-interest provides us with the fullest scope for virtue; the practice of this branch of duty is just as hard, and demands just as much resolution and zeal, as the practice of any other branch of duty. Our lower principlesc and appetites are by no means always friendly to true self-love. They interfere with it almost as often as they interfere with benevolence. We continually see men, through the influence of their lower principlesc and appetites, acting in opposition to their own acknowledged interests as well as to the interests of others, and sacrificing to them their fortunes, healths, and lives.—Now, when a person is tempted by a clamorous appetite to forgo his own happiness, it really is as praiseworthy to •overcome the temptation and preserve a steady regard for his own interests as it is to •perform any acts of justice or to overcome temptations to be dishonest or cruel.

•Restraining unruly passions,

•strict temperance, sobriety and chastity,

•rejecting present good for greater good in the future,

•governing all our lower powers so that they don’t disturb the order of our minds,

•acting in a way appropriate to the dignity and hopes of thinking immortal beings, and

•uniformly and steadfastly pursuing our own true perfection in opposition to any difficulties that come in our way

—this is high and true virtue! We can’t help approving and admiring such conduct. [There now follows half a page of colourful stuff about how a person’s life will fall apart if he doesn’t take intelligent care of his own interests; and then a short paragraph saying that in general the virtue of someone’s intentions shows up more clearly in what he does for others than in what he does for himself.]

(3) Another part of rectitude is beneficence, i.e. care for the good of others. Public happiness is something that necessarily determines all minds to prefer and desire it. It is of essential and unchangeable value and importance, and there’s nothing that appears to our thoughts in a brighter or more evident manner, or of which we more undeniably have an intuitive perception, than that it is right to promote

72

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

and pursue public happiness.—This is such an important a part of virtue, and is so universally acknowledged, that a considerable debate has broken out over whether it is the whole of virtue.

In discussing (2) I remarked that it would be strange if an action’s tending to the good of someone else could make it fit for me to perform and yet its tending to my own good couldn’t have that moral effect. And now the converse point can be made: it can’t be consistently supposed that an action of mine could be justified by its favouring my own good but couldn’t be justified by its favouring the good of others.

All thinking beings ought to have a share in our friendly wishes and feelings. But we are surrounded with fellow-men, beings with the same nature as ours, in the same circumstances and having the same wants; so we are linked and related to them in a very special way, and their happiness and misery depends greatly on our behaviour towards them. These considerations should draw us into working to be useful to mankind, cultivating to the utmost the principlec of benevolence towards them. [Price goes on about the ‘amiable’ nature of the man who has ‘this divine principlec’ reigning within him.]

(4) The next kind of virtue to be mentioned is gratitude. When we have received benefits, that fact gives us special obligations to our benefactors, and makes it wicked for us to behave towards them in certain ways that would be innocent if towards others. Is this merely an effect of the utility of gratitude? That it is not so is shown clearly enough, I think, in the passage quoted from Butler at the start of this chapter.

Gratitude is only one of many areas of morality in which particular facts and circumstances make a difference to what conduct is right towards this or that person—facts and circumstances that don’t include anything about the conduct’s consequences. There are countless cases where such moral differences come from differences in people’s •moral qualifications, •degrees of nearness (of various kinds) to the agent, and •many details of their situations and characters, which make it right to prefer some of them to others. Some of these details matter so little in themselves that their moral effect can be cancelled by almost any appearance or possibility of greater good, though when there is no such appearance they have a full effect in settling what is right. I shall mention an example of this when I come to (6) justice [page 75].

I accept that in all our enquiries into rightness the most general and central consideration is the question of what will be most beneficial, i.e. productive of the greatest public good. This is so important in cases where the public interest depending on it is very considerable that it can dislodge every obligation that would otherwise arise from •the common rules of justice, or from •promises, •private ·self·-interest, •friendship, •gratitude, and all particular attachments and connections.

(5) Veracity [= ‘truthfulness’] is a most important part of virtue. I have already said a good deal about it, ·but I shan’t rush through or past it now·. The morality of veracity depends to a certain extent on different beliefs and feelings regarding truth and falsehood, and it would be as well for me to go into some details about the foundation of these.

The difference between •truth and •falsehood is the same as the difference between •something and •nothing. It’s a much bigger difference than that between •realities and •illusions or fictions, because illusions have a real existence in the mind, and that gives them a possible existence in the outer world....—Now, it’s inconceivable that •what is real should be regarded by the mind in the same way as •what is not real. Truth must be pleasing and desirable to any thinking nature, and it is bound to be disagreeable to such

73

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

a nature to find itself in a state of deception and mocked with error.—The more error there is in any mind, the more darkness it contains, the closer it is (if I may put it this way) to not existing! And the more truth it possesses, the more perception and knowledge it has. To dislike truth or to love error is to want not to see anything as it is. It’s true that we are often pleased with finding that we have been mistaken, but what pleases us in those cases is not having been mistaken but rather some advantage that came to us through the mistake. In the same way we may be pleased by an act of villainy—meaning that we are pleased by some of its consequences or circumstances, not by the villainy itself. We frequently delight in our errors, but not as errors. As soon as we discover that we have been in error about something we are no longer in error about it, and this discovery is always welcome to us for the same reason that truth is welcome to us.—All this tells us something about the view that

•our liking for truth and •the difference between our attitude to truth and our attitude to falsehood are arbitrary, ·i.e. result from the workings of some God-given feature of our make-up that could have been otherwise·.

We find that this view implies something that is impossible.

So truth necessarily recommends itself to our preference. And lying, the essence of which consists in using established signs in order to deceive, must be disapproved by all thinking beings for the same reasons that they desire truth and knowledge and prefer right judgment to mistake and ignorance. Anyone who had no preference for truth over falsehood, and who didn’t care which of them he embraced, couldn’t possibly take offence at being lied to or at anyone else’s being lied to.
what Price writes next: And he who will not say, that, consequences apart, (which is all along supposed) to know is not better than to err, or that there is nothing to determine any being as rational, to chuse wisdom rather than folly, just apprehensions rather than wrong, to be awake and actually to see rather than to be in a continual delirium: He, I say, who will not maintain this, will scarcely be unwilling to acknowledge an immediate rectitude in veracity
what that boils down to: And anyone who does prefer truth to falsehood will accept that there’s something intrinsically right about veracity.
I include under ‘veracity’

•impartiality and honesty of mind in our enquiries after truth,

•a sacred regard for truth in all we say,

•fair and honest dealing,

•openness and simplicity of temperament that excludes guile and prevarication and all the contemptible arts of craft, equivocation and hypocrisy,

•fidelity to our promises,

•sincerity and uprightness in our transactions with ourselves as well as with others, and

•careful avoidance of all secret attempts to deceive ourselves and to evade or disguise the truth in examining our own characters.

Some of those, though they belong to the division of rectitude I am now discussing, which is defined by its being aimed at truth, are not properly included in the meaning of ‘veracity’.—But it should be understood that promise-keeping is a kind of veracity.—We must look into this with care, because the nature of promises and the obligation to keep them have been said to be very difficult topics.^21

^21 See Hume’s Treatise of Human Nature III.ii.5.

74

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

By a promise a declaration is made or assurance given to someone else, giving us an obligation to behave in some way that we wouldn’t have been bound to without the promise. Merely •declaring what you intend to do doesn’t create such an obligation, so •promising must mean more than this; the whole difference is that one relates to the present and the other to the future.—When I say ‘I intend to do A’ I affirm only a present fact.—But ‘I promise to do A’ declares that A will be done.... After declaring an intention to do A, a man is under no obligation actually to do A, because he didn’t say he would; his word and veracity are not at stake,and his not doing A doesn’t imply that he is guilty of violating truth. On the other hand, when a person declares that he will do A he becomes obliged to do it, and can’t afterwards not do A without being open to the charge of declaring a falsehood—just as really as •if he had said something he knew to be false about the past or the present, and in much the same way as he would have done •if he had claimed to know and had accordingly asserted that a certain event would happen at a certain time and it didn’t happen then. But there’s a considerable difference between this last case and the falsehood implied in breaking promises: the object of a promise that someone makes is something the existence of which depends on him; and he has it in his power to make it happen; and therefore the falsehood in this case must be known to him and deliberate, and entirely chargeable to his own neglect and guilt. But in the case of predicting events that are not under our control, if there is any blame it must be for claiming to have knowledge that we really don’t have, asserting absolutely something we’re not sure of.

So that’s what it is to promise to do something: it is to assert something whose truth depends on the promiser, with an intention to produce faith in it and reliance on it as something that is certainly going to happen; so the obligation to keep a promise is the same as the obligation to be truthful. Some writers have said that the intention in making a promise is to create a new obligation; but this can’t be right, taken in the sense in which they meant it, unless it can be claimed that the obligation to be truthful is created by the mere breath of men every time they assert anything! Of course, if by ‘creating a new obligation’ we mean merely ‘doing something as a result of which one has an obligation that one didn’t have before’, then it can be agreed that promising is creating a new obligation; but there is nothing in the least mysterious about this, ·and nothing worth making a philosophical fuss about·. All we have is that after promising to do A one is obliged to do A; just as after doing something wrong one is obliged to repent, after doing harm one is obliged to make reparation, and so on....

This account of promising hardly needs any further confirmation, but here is a confirming point: What kinds of circumstances make a false declaration less bad than it might have been? and what kinds make it worse? The answers have to do with how solemnly the declaration was made and how important its subject-matter is; and those are exactly the things that make a broken promise less bad or worse!

(6) The last part of virtue that I shall discuss is justice—meaning by ‘justice’ the part of virtue that has to do with property and commerce. [Price may have been using ‘commerce’ in the sense—dominant in his day but receessive now—of ‘social interactions’.]

The origin of the idea of property is the same as that of right and wrong in general. It stands for a relation that a particular person has to a particular object, implying that it is •fitting that he rather than anyone else should have this object at his disposal, •and wrong to deprive him of it. This is what everyone means by calling a thing ‘his right’, or saying

75

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

that it is ‘his own’.

Two questions arise: (a) How does an object come to relate to a person in this way? (b) How are we to analyse and understand the right and wrong that we perceive in these instances?

(a) Writers on ethics are very well agreed in their answers to the first of these questions. It is obvious that an object will acquire the ‘is owned by’ relation to a person as a result of •first possession, •its being the fruit of his labour, •donation, •succession, and many other ways that I needn’t list here. [In this context Price, like some other early modern writers, uses ‘possession’ to mean something like ‘having in one’s physical control’. I may take possession of a book by picking it up and walking away with it; possession doesn’t necessarily involve ownership or having the thing as one’s property.]

(b) There is much less agreement about how this ought to be explained, though I can’t find any special difficulties about this. Countless facts and circumstances vary and modify the general law of right, and alter the relations of particular effects to it [the last nine words are Price’s]. Consider this as a way of behaving, considering just this and abstracting from all the details of the situation:

Taking possession of an object and disposing of it as I please.

That is innocent. But suppose that the further details include this:

The object was previously possessed by someone else who made it and doesn’t consent to be deprived of it.

In that case my conduct is wrong, not merely because of its consequences, but immediately wrong.—Taking to ourselves some means of enjoyment that is quite loose from our fellow-creatures, i.e. not related to them in any of the ways that create ownership, can’t be the same as doing this when the contrary is true; it’s not possible to give the same moral judgment on such an action in those different circumstances. ·There really is no mystery about this·.

That •first possession, •prescription, •donation, •succession etc. should be facts that alter the nature of a case, determine right and wrong, and create obligations ·relating to property· where otherwise there wouldn’t have been any

is no harder to conceive than

that •benefits received, •private or public interest, •the will of certain beings, or any of the other considerations I have discussed, should have this effect.

There is no way to account for this other than ‘Such is the truth, such is the nature of things’. Whenever this account distinctly appears [Price’s phrase] it is ultimate and satisfactory and leaves nothing further for the mind to desire.

Peoples’ limbs, faculties, and lives are theirs, i.e. to be counted among their properties—·the things they own·—in much the same sense and for the same reasons as their external goods and acquisitions ·such as teaspoons and houses·. The former don’t differ from the latter any more than the latter differ among themselves; ·my right leg is very unlike my watch, but my watch is at least as unlike, for example, my house·. The right to them is obtained in different ways, but is equally real and certain. Some say that before society and conventions were entered into for common convenience there was no property of the latter kind—·no such thing as owning a watch or a house·—so that if we took and held something for our own use there was no moral significance in any fact about how the thing had related to someone else. If that was ever true, presumably it would also be true of the other kind of property—·limbs, lives etc.·—so that there was no-one had a right to anything. It would be hard to show that this didn’t follow.

Then there is the view that when we speak of someone

76

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

x as having a ‘right’ to some object y, all we mean is that it best for society as a whole that x should have the exclusive enjoyment of y. This implies that when general utility is not involved, •a man has no more right to his liberty or his life than he has to objects that have nothing to do with him, and •because he has no property a man can’t suffer injurious or unjust treatment. [Price applies this to a supposed case of two men who live together with no connection to the rest of the world, contending that according to the view he is discussing there would be nothing wrong with any treatment that either of them gave to the other. He sums up:] We wouldn’t have much reason, on these principles, for rejecting the opinion that a state of nature is a state of war!

These remarks can be more clearly applied to independent societies of men, which are to be looked on as in a state of nature with respect to one another. If the notions of property and justice are not natural, being derived wholly from the consideration of public good, it’s a very strange fact that those notions should prevail almost as much between societies as between private persons—strange because whatever one society can take from another may be equally useful to both. And another point: If public good were the sole measure and foundation of property and of peoples’ rights, this would follow:

Innocent beings don’t have a right to exemption from misery; it is morally all right to make them miserable if their misery—whether great or small—would give rise to some good that outweighed it, however slightly.

Indeed, any number of innocent beings might be put into a state of absolute and eternal misery, provided that this was made up for by producing at the same time a greater number of beings in a greater degree happy. [The next part of the paragraph is hard to follow closely. In it Price credits his present opponent—the balance-of-happiness-over-misery theorist—with being committed to the following: There is no morally significant difference between these two:

(i) giving a man a quantity K of happiness and no misery,

(ii) giving a man a quantity J of misery and a quantity J+K of happiness,

because in each case what counts is the amount of uncancelled happiness [not Price’s phrase], which is K each time. And, says Price, the opponent is also committed to saying that there is no morally significant difference between these two:

(ii) getting a surplus of happiness in the manner of (ii) above by giving some misery but more happiness to one person,

(iii) getting a surplus of happiness by making a large number of people totally miserable while making a large number of other people happy to an even greater degree.

Price continues with a comment on (iii):] The procedure in (iii) is clearly wrong and unjust, especially if we suppose the sufferings of the unhappy people to be in some way part of the means to greater happiness for the rest. Is a man x, whatever his relations (e.g. of friendship, benefaction etc.) are to another man y, unable to be wronged by y through any actions that aren’t harmful to the public? Is it all right for a man to ruin any number of his fellow-creatures (doing this innocently, i.e. not wanting to ruin them), provided he causes the good of others in a greater degree? Such consequences are plainly shocking to our natural sentiments, but I don’t know how to avoid them on the principles I am examining, ·i.e. on the thesis that public utility is the only criterion of right and wrong·. It is indeed hard to determine what degree of superior good would make up for the irreparable and undeserved ruin of one person, i.e. what overbalance of happiness would be great enough to justify the absolute misery of one innocent being. [In a footnote here, Price

77

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

quotes Cicero as saying that ‘some actions are so foul that a good man would not do them to save his country’, and adds details.] Be these things as they may, the points I have made are at least enough to show that public happiness cannot be the sole standard and measure of justice and injustice. But I could set those arguments aside and let the whole issue rest on the answer that any impartial person will find he has to give to the following question:

Concerning an object that can’t be divided or enjoyed in common by two persons, and would be equally advantageous to both of them: Isn’t it fitting—setting aside all distant consequences—that the person who possessed it first, or the one whose skill and labour had produced it, should have the use and enjoyment of it rather than the other person?

The affirmative in this case is very obvious; and anyone who gives that answer has to think that the origin of property is something like what I have said it is.

What may have helped to mislead some writers is the visible general connection between •injustice and •cruelty; but even if •these were more inseparable than they are, we would still have no reason for running them together. A little reflection will show an unbiased person that the notion of an action’s being unjust is different from that of its being cruel, inhuman, or unkind. If they weren’t different, how could the guilt of a •cruel action always appear to be made worse by its also being •unjust? Someone may reply: ‘The injustice of an act of cruelty adds to the private damage it does a damage also to the public, and that makes it appear more cruel and therefore more wrong.’ But how could anyone think that possible harms to the public in the distant future (many of which are not immediately discovered ·even· by those who search for them) are always thought of by the bulk of men? If they were, that would make simple and illiterate people in some cases better judges of what is just and unjust than those who are learned and studious!....

[In two short paragraphs, Price (i) repeats his earlier point about settling ownership disputes by ‘frivolous’ differences if there are no weightier ones, and (ii) reminds us of the ‘intelligible’ view that someone who owns something is free to give it to anyone else he chooses. In a third paragraph he (iii) writes about two situations in which x and y are quite relaxed about which of them owns z—in one of them •x and y are good friends or close relatives, in the other •z is something such as air or water, that is easily and plentifully available. He says that these aspects of property pose no problem for his account of property and justice, and he silently implies that they are problematic for the theory that the concept of justice (and therefore the concept of property) is definable purely in terms of public utility.]

The particular rules of justice are various, and in many cases it’s hard to determine what justice requires. There’s no need for me to go into all that. But I do want to say this: although I can’t allow •public good to be the sole source of justice, •it undoubtedly has a great influence on it, and is one important factor in many of its maxims. •It gives to the rights of men a considerable additional force, and in some cases •it entirely creates those rights.—It is utterly obvious that the happiness of the world and the existence of society require that possessions be stable, and property sacred, and not liable to be violated except on very extraordinary occasions. When we are considering what the common interest requires in regard to some proposed action, we have to take into account not only •the immediate effects of the action, but also what its longer-term consequences are likely to be—what it opens the way to, and what would actually happen if everyone acted in this way. If it is morally all right for me to take a man’s property....on the grounds

78

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

that I am poorer than he is, or he doesn’t need it, or I plan to give it to someone worthier than he is, then it is all right for anyone to act in this way in similar circumstances; and if that happened, the boundaries of property would be overthrown and the door opened to general anarchy, distrust and savageness.—But it is far from true that considerations of this kind are the sole guides to men in their sentiments about property and justice; indeed (I repeat) men usually don’t think about such things at all....

These then are the main types of virtue. There may be particular cases that don’t cleanly belong to any of the types. We judge what is or isn’t to be done by attending to •people’s different relations, circumstances, and qualifications, and to •the natures and tendencies [here = ‘causal powers’] of objects—in short by examining the whole truth of the case we are considering. The universal law of rectitude considered in the abstract is always invariably the same, but what it demands continually changes from case to case because there’s so much variety in the cases—the situations of agents and objects are always changing.

However different from one another the types of virtue that I have listed are, the very notion of them as types of virtue implies that they all involve one general idea and should be regarded only as different specifications of one basic all-governing law. In all these virtues it is the same authority that commands, the same truth and right that oblige, the same eternal reason that instructs. Virtue thus considered is necessarily one thing. No part of it can be separated from any other.

This shows us what a defective and inconsistent thing partial virtue is—·e.g. for someone to have all the virtues except piety·. The same law that requires piety also requires benevolence, veracity, temperance, justice, gratitude, and so on. All these rest on the same foundation, and are alike our indispensable duty. So someone who generally neglects some one of them is a rebel against reason and a deserter from the cause of righteousness and order, just as if he had neglected them all. The law’s authority on one point is not different from its authority on another, and on all points. To break the law on one point (I mean: to do so habitually and wilfully) is therefore to throw off one’s allegiance and to trample on the whole authority of the law. True and genuine virtue must be uniform and universal. Nothing short of an entire good character can help us to be accepted ·by God on the day of judgment·. As long as we retain any evil habit we can’t be counted as loyal subjects of the divine government, we continue under the curse of guilt, slaves to vice, and not qualified for bliss. I’ll have occasion to say more about this later.

Something else that helps to unite the types of virtue I have listed is that they often agree in requiring the same actions. An act of justice may be also an act of gratitude and bene-ficence, and any act of any of these kinds is also required for the virtue of piety towards God. If injustice, fraud, falsehood, and a neglect of private good were universally prevalent, what a dreadful state the world would be in! and how thoroughly the ends of benevolence would be defeated!—There are many virtues, but annihilating any one of them has the most pernicious consequences for all the others. This ·unity of the virtues· can be seen in good measure in how things go in •the present state of things, but in •the final issue of things ·in the after-life· the harmony between them will be found to be much more strict. Whatever exceptions may now happen ·in our present life·, if we look forwards to the whole of our existence we’ll find that the three great principlesc of the love of God, the love of man, and true self-love will always draw us the same way; and we have the strongest reason to assure ourselves that eventually no-one

79

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

will be able to say that he has prospered because of some unjust action, or that although he has been less scrupulous than others he has been more successful and happy.

But although the types of virtue I have listed agree in often requiring the same course of action, it is also true that they often interfere with one another....in particular cases.—This perhaps hasn’t been sufficiently attended to, so I shall emphasize it.

The difficulty of determining what is morally right or wrong in particular cases is created mainly by this interference between the different general principles of virtue.—The pursuit of the happiness of others is a duty, and so is the pursuit of one’s own happiness; on the whole these two duties are inseparably connected, but in many particular instances one of them can’t be pursued without giving up the other. When the public happiness is very great and the self-interest very inconsiderable, there is no problem.... But when the public happiness ·that is at stake· is lessened, and the private self-interest is increased to a certain degree, doubt arises and makes us entirely incapable of determining which we ought to choose. We have the most satisfactory perception that we ought to care for our own good, and within certain limits prefer it to that of anyone else; but where exactly are those limits? Who can tell us in all cases of opposition between the two types of duty where the boundaries are of right, of wrong, and of indifference [= ‘neither required nor forbidden’] are to be found? [Price continues with other examples: the duty to seek one’s own and the public good may clash with duties having to do with friendship, gratitude, justice, and so on. Different bases for ownership may clash. Such conflicts as these confront us with difficulties that we often lack the skill to overcome. There’s nothing remarkable about this, Price says; in non-moral matters also we are sometimes ‘at a loss to know what is true, when the arguments for and against a proposition appear nearly equal’.]

Bear in mind that the principles themselves are selfevident. It is very unreasonable to argue thus:

•Because in many individual cases the principles clash and create obscurity, therefore they aren’t selfevident (or: therefore there are no moral distinctions).

That inference is like these:

•In some circumstances we can’t judge the distances and sizes of bodies by their appearance to the eye; therefore we never can.

•·Undeniable· principles can be used in proving particular doctrines and in opposing them; therefore these principles are not undeniable.

•In some cases it isn’t easy to determine what the effect will be of different forces variously combined and acting contrary to each other; therefore we can’t be sure about what any force acting separately will produce (or: therefore we can’t know that there is any such thing as force).

[Price elaborates that a little in a footnote, that ends:] The weakness of our discerning faculties cannot in any case affect truth. Things themselves continue invariably the same, however different our opinions of them may be, or whatever doubts or difficulties may perplex us.

These remarks may be useful in helping us to determine how far and in what sense morality is capable of demonstration [= ‘logically rigorous proof’]. There are certainly many moral principles and maxims that need only to be understood to be assented to. I don’t see why such propositions as these,

•Gratitude is due to benefactors,

•Reverence is due to our Creator,

•It is right to care for our own happiness,

•An innocent being ought not to be absolutely miser-

80

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

able,

•It is wrong to take from someone the fruit of his labour,

and others of that kind may not be laid down and used as axioms, the truth of which appears as irresistibly as the truth of the basic propositions of geometry. But the picture changes when we come to consider particular effects. When people speak of ‘demonstrating morality’ they must mean relating these particular cases to the general self-evident principles of morality, showing with certainty how they relate to them. It would be happy for us if this were always possible! We would then •be relieved of many painful doubts, •know universally and infallibly what we should do and what we should avoid, and •have nothing to attend to except making our behaviour conform to our knowledge. Everyone must see how impracticable this is. Even if benevolence were the only virtuous principle—·so that we had no clash-of-principles difficulties·—we would still be far from being able to apply it always, with no danger of mistake, to particular actions. Why? Because we can’t be more sure in a particular case that doing A would be an instance of beneficence than we are of the likely consequences of doing A. [And the same point could be made (Price continues) if self-love were the only principle of virtue. Applying the principle to individual cases would require knowledge, which we often don’t have, about likely consequences of doing A or doing B. Similarly with •duty to God, •the properties and rights of others, and •gratitude: if any one of those were the whole of virtue, we would still have daunting difficulties in many particular cases. All this is offered as evidence against the thesis that ‘morality can be demonstrated’ in the sense Price adopted early in this paragraph.]

A second source of insuperable difficulties ·for the thesis in question· comes to the surface when we remember that in order to discover what is right in a particular case we ought to extend our views to all the different types of virtue, to examine how relevant each of them is to the case in hand, and to compare their respective influence and demands—not to mention the fact that they often interfere with one another. To know that we ought to do A, it isn’t enough to know that doing A will bring good to others; we must also take into account how it affects ourselves, what justice has to say about it, and so on; all this must be taken in and weighed if we want to form a true judgment about the rightness of doing A on this occasion. The truth of the matter is this:

•To be capable of deducing—demonstrably, accurately and in particular detail—the whole rule of right as it applies in every case, we must have universal and unerring knowledge.

And no finite understanding is equipped to have such knowledge. Only he who knows all truth is acquainted with the whole law of truth in all its importance, perfection and extent.

These considerations may help us to form a judgment about the different sentiments and practices, in several areas of morality, that have held sway in different countries and ages. All men at all times have agreed in accepting the general principles that I have listed ·on the preceding page·. It can’t be shown that there have ever been human beings with no ideas of property and justice, or of the rightness of veracity, gratitude, benevolence, prudence, and religious worship. The only disagreements have concerned particular usages and practices; and it is inevitable that different people will have different ideas about these, according to their various opinions •about how these practices relate to the universally acknowledged moral principles, or •about their purposes, connections, and consequences.—Those who plead for passive obedience and non-resistance—·holding that it is never right to resist the power of the king·—think

81

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

that divine command or public good requires something that others, with more reason, think to be a reproach to human nature and destructive of the very purpose of magistracy and government.—-The nations where people accepted the customs of exposing children and aged persons—·leaving them out in the wilds to die of starvation or cold or animal predation·—approved of these customs because they believed them to be •conducive to the general advantage and •friendly to the sufferers themselves.—Self-murder [Price’s term] among some of the ancients was justified and applauded because they thought of it as a method of extricating themselves from misery, one that only brave men could use, rather than seeing it as what it truly is, namely an act of very criminal discontent and unwillingness to put up with suffering, a desertion of the place assigned to us by Providence, and a cowardly flight from the duties and difficulties of life.—As far as anyone has ever approved persecution, it could only have been because they thought they were serving God, inflicting his wrath upon his enemies, justly punishing obstinacy and impiety, and....preventing the propagation of anything that tends to subvert true religion and ruin the souls of men.—The most superstitious practices and ridiculous rites of worship have gained credit and support merely because they were thought to be •pleasing to God, •means of procuring his favour, and •proper expressions of homage and adoration.

[In the next sentence and some later ones, the line between ‘speuclative’ and ‘practical’ can be equated with the line between ‘not having to do with morality’ and ‘having to do with morality’. In this early modern sense of the word, ‘speculative’ doesn’t mean anything about guess-work, as ‘speculate’ does today.] In these and countless other instances of the same sort, men’s practical errors have clearly arisen from their speculative errors—mistaking facts, or not knowing all the relevant facts—which has the result that they often think to be right practices that they would unavoidably condemn if they had sounder beliefs on matters of fact. The rules by which to judge are universally the same; those who approve and those who disapprove are applying the same principles, and differ only in how they apply them. When they are in error, the error consists in thinking that something belongs to a particular species of virtue when really it doesn’t. It is just as reasonable to expect disagreement •here as in •the application of agreed principles of knowledge and assent in general. The inference

•Men are diverse in their speculative opinions; therefore they don’t have speculative reason,

is no more extravagant than this:

•Men are diverse in their opinions about the fitness or unfitness, lawfulness or unlawfulness, of particular practices; therefore they have no powers of moral perception (or: therefore there is no fixed standard of morality).

Until men can be •raised to the level of not having any defective knowledge, and •secured against partial and inadequate views, they will go on being apt to •believe cases and facts and the tendencies of actions to be otherwise than they really are, and consequently to •form false judgments about right and wrong....

[In Price’s day ‘education’ had a somewhat broader meaning than it does today, so that it could often be replaced by ‘upbringing’.] Bear in mind also some questions that arise about the influence of custom, education, and example. •To what extent can they alter our natural sentiments? To what extent can they give us an undue attachment to some qualities, and vivacity to some ideas above others? •How much depravity and blindness can they introduce into our moral and intellectual powers? ·Reflecting a little on the third question·: through the influence of custom etc. the most stupid notions may come to be rooted in our minds beyond the possibility of

82

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 7: What are the main kinds of virtue?

being eradicated, we may be made hostile to things that are naturally very agreeable, and our very sensations may be perverted.

Some writers have been disposed to infer from this that all we are is derived from •education and habit; that we can never know when we are free from •their influence and forming our beliefs on the basis of sound evidence; or that there are no natural sensations and desires at all, and no principles of truth that are in themselves certain and invariable, and compelling everyone’s assent. This inference is unreasonable. Education and habit can’t give us any new ideas. The power they have presupposes something natural as their foundation. If it weren’t for the natural powers by which we perceive pleasure and pain, good and evil, beauty and ugliness, the ideas of them could never be aroused in us ·by education etc. or in any other way·, any more than the ideas of colour can be aroused in persons born blind.... If the ideas of proportion, similarity, existence, identity, and so on weren’t essential to our understandings, we would lose all capacity for knowledge and judgment, so that we couldn’t possibly be misled....by wrong biases! If we had no natural ideas of virtue and vice, we wouldn’t be capable of approval or disapproval—love or hatred—of actions and characters, except on the basis of their being advantageous or disadvantageous to us. Custom and education can only alter the direction of natural sentiments and ideas, connecting them with wrong objects.—The part of our moral constitution that is chiefly liable to being ruined by these causes is the part that depends on instinct. Our outright horror at vice and our attachment to virtue may be impaired, the conscience deadened, the nature of particular practices mistaken, the sense of shame weakened, the judgment darkened, the voice of reason stifled, and self-deception practised, to the most lamentable and fatal degree. Yet the grand lines and primary principles of morality are so deeply worked into our hearts, so integral to our minds, that they will always be legible ·there·. The general approval of certain virtues and dislike of their contraries must always remain, and can’t be erased except through the destruction of all intellectual perception. The most depraved people never sink so low as to lose all moral discernment, all ideas of right and wrong, justice and injustice, honour and dishonour. This is clear enough from •the judgments they pass on the actions of others, from •the resentment they show whenever they are ill-treated, and from •the inner uneasiness and remorse that they can’t help feeling and are sometimes severely tormented by. All the satisfaction and peace within themselves that they are capable of enjoying comes largely from their taking care not to think about themselves, and from their having learned to disguise their vices under the appearance—·the appearance to themselves·—of some virtuous or innocent qualities, which shows that vice is still so foul and frightful to them that they can’t bear the direct view of it in themselves. [Price winds this up by saying that even if everything he has said about these ‘most depraved’ people is wrong, they can safely be ignored by those who care about moral truth and the truth about human nature.]

The sources of error and disagreement that I have been discussing would produce very considerable effects even if all the particulars of duty and rightness were in themselves plain and easy to discover. Something that was so plain that differences about it wouldn’t be caused by educations, temperaments, views, and degrees of wisdom as different as those of mankind, or by inattention, prejudices, and corruptions as great as those that prevail among men—that would have to be very plain indeed!—But if we remember the things I have said about interference between the principles of morality, and about the impossibility of a complete and

83

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

scientific deduction of what we ought to do and what we ought to avoid in particular circumstances, we’ll accept that the subject itself is often wrapped in real darkness and accompanied by insurmountable difficulties that produce even greater and more unavoidable disagreements. What I have said •seems to account well enough for the diversity of men’s sentiments concerning moral matters, and •makes it reasonable to expect that they should be no less various than their sentiments concerning anything else.

One last point: Even if all men in all cases judged rightly what is virtue and right behaviour, the moral practices in different ages and countries would still vary considerably. The reason is obvious. In different ages and circumstances of the world, the same practices don’t always have the same connections, tendencies, and effects. The state of human affairs is perpetually changing, and is very different in different nations at the same period of time. Amidst this variety the subject-matter of virtue couldn’t possibly continue precisely the same. When new connections are established, and new customs, laws, and political constitutions are introduced, it is inevitable that new obligations arise and changes occur in what behaviour is morally proper. Practices that are justifiable and proper •under one form of government, or •when a community is first established, or •among people with a particular cast of mind that leads to their having particular regulations and opinions, may be quite wrong in another state of things or among people of other characters and customs. The ancient Spartans, we are told, accepted theft as a practice. They didn’t care much about wealth, and that fact together with many circumstances in the state of their affairs might rightly relax their ideas of ownership, and make each instance of taking from someone something that he owned different from what it is now among us. Some virtues or accomplishments may be more useful and more difficult—and therefore deserving of more applause—in some countries than in others....

Chapter 8

The nature and essentials of virtue in practice as distinct from absolute virtue.

From what principlec or motive does a virtuous agent act?

Before starting on the main topic of this chapter, I must give you a clear account of the distinction between abstract or absolute virtue and practical or relative virtue. I mentioned this earlier, but now it will be the basis for what I shall have to say on the main topic.

I expect to show clearly that there is a sound basis for this distinction. If we don’t attend to it we shan’t be able to •have an accurate view of the nature of virtue, or •avoid getting into many tangles in our enquiries into it.

The phrase ‘abstract virtue’, when used properly, stands

84

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

for a quality of an external action or event. It stands for a property that an action can have independently of what the agent thinks about it. An abstractly virtuous action is one that is right, in itself and absolutely, for the agent to perform; it is what such-and-such an agent in such-and-such circumstances should do—what he would judge, if he judged truly, that he ought to do. Practical virtue, on the other hand, is essentially tied to what the agent thinks about his actions. It signifies what he ought to do given that he has such-and-such sentiments.—A distinction something like this is the line some writers have drawn between materially good actions and formally good actions [This distinction is mentioned again on page 95].—Moral agents are apt to •be mistaken about the circumstances they are in, and thus to •form wrong judgments about their own obligations. This presupposes that these obligations do really exist independently of their judgments. But when they are in any way mistaken, it doesn’t follow that then nothing remains obligatory, because there is a sense in which the following is true:

What a person in the sincerity of his heart thinks he ought to do is what he indeed ·practically· ought to do; and he would be at fault if he didn’t do it, even if it is contradictory to what is his duty in the former ·abstract· sense.

—If anyone objects that ‘this implies that an action can be both right and wrong at the same time’, that is mere trifling because it overlooks that fact that two different views of the action are at work here. Take the following case:

A magistrate gives a judgment awarding an estate to person x rather than to person y because there is overwhelming evidence that x and not y is entitled to it. It later turns out that the estate really does belong to y.

The magistrate has certainly done what is right in one sense, though it is just as certainly wrong in another sense—·it is practically right, abstractly wrong·.

If we reject this distinction ·by dropping the notion of ‘abstract virtue’ and having ‘practical virtue’ as our only moral notion·, we’ll be committed to ·some intolerable consequences·: •things really are whatever we think they are, •there is no sense in which someone can ‘act wrongly’ without incurring guilt and blame, •while we follow our judgments, we cannot err in our conduct, •if through an involuntary mistake a man

breaks the most important engagements, hurts his best friends, or bestows his bounty on the most worthless objects,

if through religious zeal and blind superstition he

commits the most shocking barbarities, thinking that in this way he is serving God,

and if through a belief in their lawfulness he

engages in violence and deceit,

there is no sense in which his conduct ‘contradicts rectitude’, or in which it can be truly said that ‘he acts wrongly’. Thus the difference between an enlightened conscience and an erroneous one would vanish, no moral mistake would be possible, all the fancies of men concerning their duty would be equally sound, and the most ignorant people would be as well informed about the subject-matter of virtue as the most knowing!—But there’s really no need for me to go on about this—the point is obvious....

From knowledge of •a person’s nature and capacities, •his relations, connections, and dependencies, and •the consequences of his actions, it is possible for us to work out the whole of what he ought to do in the first sense—·i.e. as a matter of abstract virtue·—without paying the least attention to his private judgment. But to decide what he ought to do in the second sense—·i.e. as a matter of practical

85

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

virtue·—we do have to know about his judgment, what he actually thinks about what he is doing at the time of doing it; and that is the only thing we have to take into account. Abstract virtue requires a great variety of circumstances to be taken into account, and we can’t possibly know it for sure on every occasion, any more than we can always know for sure the whole truth about anything else. Practical virtue, on the other hand, involves few difficulties. The greatest degree of doubt about the abstract morality of an action may leave us with no hesitation at all about its practical morality. Our rule is to take care to inform •our consciences in the best manner we can, and then to follow •them steadily and faithfully; and when in doubt to take the safer option, i.e.

•not to risk doing anything about which we have doubts, when we know that there can’t be anything wrong with not doing it,

and, on the other hand,

•not to omit to do anything about which we have doubts, when we know there can’t be anything wrong with doing it.

Now consider a case where we think it may be wrong to do A, and also think that it may be wrong not to do A, and where our doubts ·or uncertainties· on the two sides are equal. In such a case it becomes practically indifferent which way we act. When the doubts on one side outweigh the doubts on the other, it’s obvious that we ought to take the option in which there seems to us the least danger of going astray.—It’s a fortunate thing for us that our entitlement to count as ‘virtuous’ beings depends not on the correctness of our opinions, or the constant objective [= ‘abstract’] rightness of everything we do, but on the conformity of our actions to the sincere conviction of our minds. If we came to suspect that that is not the standard for ‘virtuous person’, the results of that would be very bad: it would cause us to distrust our only guide (·conscience·), and would throw us into a permanent state of bewilderment....

I have applied the adjectives ‘real’ and ‘absolute’ to the first kind of virtue, for an obvious reason, but don’t get the idea that the second kind isn’t also in a different sense ‘real’ virtue. It is ·really and· truly and absolutely right that a person should do what the reason of his mind—his perhaps misinformed mind—requires of him, or what according to his best judgment he is convinced is the will of God. If he doesn’t do this he will necessarily and justly come to dislike himself, and will forfeit all claims to integrity. [At this point Price has a long footnote which is here raised into the main text.]
·START OF THE LONG FOOTNOTE·
So all the claims to dominion over conscience—how absurd they are! What those who have pleaded for such dominion have been trying to get is a power or right to oblige people to act against their private judgment—i.e. a right to oblige people to act wrongly. Every man ought to be left to follow his own conscience, because it’s only then that he acts virtuously. Where the plea of conscience is real (and who but God can judge how far in general it is or isn’t so?), it is wicked to put restraints on it. For that is violating the rights of what is above all things sacred [Price’s phrase], trying to turn men into hypocrites and knaves, establishing human authority on the ruins of divine authority.—The only interference with anyone’s conscience that is ever right is necessary self-defence when some men’s consciences lead them to hurt others, to take away their liberty, or to subvert the public.—It flies in the face of common sense, as well as being impious, for any men to claim a power to oblige their fellow-men to worship God in any manner other than the one that is most agreeable to their consciences....—The civil magistrate goes out of his domain when he intervenes in religious differences. His role is only to secure the liberties

86

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

and properties of those under his jurisdiction, to protect all good subjects, to preserve the peace amongst conflicting sects, and to block them from encroaching on one another.

Forgive me if I work in an extra point here. It is the fact that we have something very close to a demonstration [= ‘a logically rigorous proof’] that God will not and cannot (a) grant to any particular man or set of men a power to direct the faith and practices of others in religious matters without at the same time (b) making them infallible and impeccable. For if he did (a) without (b), what would the (a) amount to? It would be simply a grant of power to mislead and deceive! We know what errors, what corruptions, what desolation have been actually produced when (a) this power has been claimed by men who did not have (b) those qualifications!—It is a part of the special good fortune of this nation that principles of this kind have been so well explained here and are now so widely accepted here. May they be still more widely accepted and better understood, and may our constitution and laws, already the best in the world, grow to a perfect conformity to them! As for those who favour giving up their liberty and independence and submitting to human authority in religious matters, may their number continually decrease. and may the joyful time soon come when all slavish principles are detested and held in contempt by everyone!
·END OF THE LONG FOOTNOTE·
These different kinds of rectitude have such an affinity that we are very apt to confuse them with one another in our thoughts and talk, and we have to attend carefully if we are to know which of them we are talking about. It is hardly possible in writing on morality to avoid blending them in our language, often talking about both even in the same sentence. But I have said enough to enable an attentive person to see when and how this is done, and to prepare the way for the explanation of the nature and essentials of practical virtue that I now embark on. ·My discussion will have three main episodes·.

1. Practical virtue presupposes liberty. Whether or not everyone will agree about this, it can’t be omitted.

[Price is about to make heavy use of ‘determine’ and its cognates. Its uses can be seen as having two strands: (i) In the phrase ‘acting and determining’, it means something like ‘deciding’, but not in the sense of ‘deciding to do A next week’. To say that I ‘determine to do A’ is to say that I actively set myself to do A right now; an act of determining was sometimes called ‘an act of the will’ or ‘a volition’. (ii) In the phrase ‘not necessarily determined’, it means something like ‘caused’. The common meaning that ran through both uses was that of ‘settle’, ‘fix’, ‘pin down’ or the like. If I determine to do A I settle the question of what I am about to do. If an explosion determines the outbreak of a fire, it settles the question of whether there will soon be a fire. So there was no outright ambiguity in ‘determine’; and for Price and some others there weren’t even two clearly separate strands in its use, because in their view when you actively set yourself to do something—i.e. when you determine to do it—you do literally cause yourself to do it.]

The liberty I am talking about here is the power of acting and determining; and it is self-evident that if anyone lacked that power he could have no moral capacities. When someone acts he must himself be the cause of the action, and therefore not necessarily determined to act. Let anyone try to find for the expressions ‘I will’, ‘I act’, a sense that is consistent with supposing that the volition or action does not come from myself. [In that sentence, ‘I will’ means ‘I perform an act of the will’; it is present-tense, not an auxiliary verb in the future tense as in ‘I will visit you tomorrow’.] Virtue presupposes determination, and determination presupposes a determiner, and ‘a determiner who doesn’t determine himself’ is an obvious contradiction. Determination requires a cause. If this cause is the person himself, that’s all I ask for. If not, then it is no longer his determination, i.e. the determiner

87

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

is no longer him but rather the motive—or whatever else anyone will say is the cause of the determination. When you are told that a certain person did A, to ask ‘What brought about the determination to do A?’ is to ask ‘Who did A?’ Surely everyone can feel the absurdity of saying that my volitions are produced by an outside cause, i.e. are not mine; or saying that I determine voluntarily and yet necessarily! ·And such denials of liberty, as well as being absurd, fly in the face of experience·.—We have a constant and necessary awareness of ·our· liberty, on a par with our awareness that we think, choose, will, or even exist. Whatever anyone may say to the contrary, no-one can possibly •think in earnest that he has no active, self-moving powers and isn’t the cause of his own volitions, or •fail to ascribe to himself things that he must be aware of thinking and doing.

This question about liberty has been enormously much darkened by fallacious reasonings, and creates much danger of falling into a confusion of ideas; and I don’t want to go much further into all that. I merely point out that it is hard to say what virtue and vice, commendation and blame, mean if they don’t presuppose agency, free choice, and an absolute dominion over our decisions.—It has always been the general sense of mankind....that they can’t be accountable for anything that they have no power to avoid. Applauding or reproaching ourselves for events that we didn’t cause any more than we caused our own existence, and that we couldn’t have prevented any more than we could prevent the returns of the seasons or the revolutions of the planets—nothing can be more glaringly absurd than that! The whole language of men, all their practical sentiments and schemes, and the whole structure and order of human affairs, are based on the notion of liberty and are utterly inconsistent with the supposition that....our purposes and determinations are not subject to our own command, but are rather the result of physical laws that can’t be resisted. [That’s Price’s first use of ‘physical’ in this work. (Previous occurrences in this version are all tagged as editorial.) At his time and earlier, ‘physical’ bore traces of its origin in the ancient Greek trilogy—Logic/Ethics/Physics, what-must-be/what-ought-to-be/what-is. Thus, ‘physical laws’ are just causal laws governing what goes on in the world, what actually happens; with no implied restriction to matter or body.]

If any of the advocates of the doctrine of necessity should find that what they mean by ‘necessity’ is consistent with the ideas of agency and self-determination, there won’t be much left to argue about: the liberty that I insist on as essential to morality will be admitted, and we won’t have to pay much attention to any difficulties relating to the nature of that influence we commonly ascribe to motives.^22

2. Intelligence—·i.e. the ability to think·—is also required for practical morality. Some degree of this is necessary for the perception of moral good and evil, and without this perception there can be no moral agency. Doesn’t liberty include or imply the ability to think? No! All the lower orders of beings possess true liberty. Self-motion and

^22 ·Not that these ‘difficulties’ amount to much·. When we say that someone’s motives ‘determine him’, all we mean is that he •chooses to follow his judgment and desires, or that he •actually does what he is inclined to do. There is not much mystery in that! In saying this, we don’t mean that the man’s motives are involved in causing his determination, or that his judgment and views are physically connected with the actions consequent upon them. It would be absurd to say that our inclinations act on us, or compel us, that our desires and fears put us into motion or produce our volitions, i.e. are agents! But it is perfectly conceivable that they may be the occasions of our putting ourselves into motion.—There’s no need for me to prove that the idea of an •efficient cause—·a cause that makes something happen·—is essentially and totally different from an •explanation (Price’s word is ‘account’) or •occasion. If ball x strikes y, the location of y on the billiard table is the occasion or explanation of the collision—·i.e. it is a background condition, and is part of the explanation of the collision·—but it’s senseless to say that y’s location is the efficient cause of its motion....

88

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

activity of some kind are essential to every conscious living being. There seems to be no difference between •having no spontaneity and •being entirely inanimate. [At Price’s time ‘animate’ often meant not ‘living’ but, more narrowly, ‘breathing’; so plants were ‘inanimate’.]—But though liberty doesn’t presuppose intelligence, yet intelligence plainly presupposes liberty. For what I have just said about all creatures that can feel is much more strictly true of creatures that can think. A thinking, designing, reasoning being that has no liberty, no inward, spontaneous, active, self-directing principlec, is something that no-one can form any idea of. That’s a measure of how unreasonable are all objections to the making of free creatures, and how absurd it is to ask why men were made free. But,

3. The main point now to be insisted on is that an agent can’t be rightly called ‘virtuous’ unless he acts •from a consciousness of rectitude, and •with a regard to it as his rule and purpose. This seems to me to be undoubtedly true and of great importance, but I know that there are many who’ll be hard to convince of it; so I should make a special point of trying to explain and prove it.

Liberty and reason constitute the ability to be virtuous; what makes a person’s character actually virtuous is the intention with which he acts.—Don’t forget the distinction that I drew at the start of this chapter. To mere theoretical virtue—i.e. the abstract reasons and fitnesses of things—praiseworthiness is not applicable. The object of our praise and esteem is the actual conformity of moral agents’ wills to what they see or believe to be the fitnesses of things. We could reasonably label one of these as ‘the virtue of the action’ and the other as ‘the virtue of the agent’. No particular intention is required for virtue of the action, because what is objectively right can be done from any motive, good or bad; so someone’s doing something objectively right doesn’t confer any merit on him—indeed, it is consistent with the greatest guilt. On the other hand, in assessing the virtue of the agent the most essential thing is the agent’s intention. When the intention is good, that confers virtue on the agent, whatever is the objective moral status of the action, for it often happens that an agent is entitled to commendation for some objectively wrong action that he performs.

It may help us to think more clearly about this matter if we take the position that very strictly speaking the only thing that an agent does is what he intends to do. What happens beyond his intention or contrary to it, even if it happens through a chain of natural causes that has his determination on it, shouldn’t be imputed to him. Our own determinations are, strictly speaking, our only actions. They are all that we have absolute power over and are responsible for....—It seems indeed to be utterly obvious that there are two views or senses in which we commonly speak of ‘actions’. Sometimes we mean by a person’s ‘action’ his determination or volition, of which his intention is an essential part. And sometimes we mean the real event, the effect produced in the outer world. For a being who has infinite knowledge and power, these two always coincide: what such a being designs and determines to do is always the same as the actual event produced. But we have no reason to think this true of any inferior beings.

In further explaining and proving the thesis that I am working towards, it will be proper to show that (1) someone’s perception of right and wrong does stimulate [Price’s word is ‘excite’] him to act, and (2) that it is the only sufficient principlec of action. With these two points established, we’ll be better prepared to judge how far there can be practical virtue without it, ·i.e. without a perception of right and wrong·.

89

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

(1) If we attentively consult our experience and our reason, we’ll soon be satisfied about the first of these two points. All men continually feel that the perception of right and wrong stimulates them to action, feeling this so naturally and strongly that most of them would be puzzled at anyone’s questioning whether it is so. There are many supposable cases where it is impossible to assign any other reason for action. [Price sketches some of these—cases where someone keeps a promise, refrains from stealing, obeys and honours God, and so on and so on, asking in each case: Why would would the man act in that way if not because of his perception that it was the right way to act?]

In addition to all that, it seems extremely evident that stimulation [Price: ‘excitement’] belongs to the very ideas of moral right and wrong, and is essentially inseparable from the thought of them. My account of obligation in chapter 6 is enough to show this.—When we are aware that an action is fit to be done, or that it ought to be done, it isn’t conceivable that we can remain uninfluenced, or have no motive to action. It wouldn’t be much use arguing with someone who denies this and maintains that the fitness or reasonableness of an action is no reason for doing it, and that the immorality or unreasonableness of an action is no reason against doing it. A •liking for or •inclination toward rectitude can’t be separated from the •perception of it. The knowledge of what is right, without any approval of it or concern to do it, isn’t conceivable or possible. And this knowledge will certainly be followed by corresponding actual •behaviour whenever there is nothing to oppose •it.

•Why does a reasonable being act reasonably?

•Why does he have a disposition to follow reason, and some aversion to doing wrong? Why does he choose to do what he knows he should do?

•Why does he think it matters whether he abstains from conduct that he knows to be evil and criminal?

These questions need not be answered. They don’t deserve to be answered.

So, as I pointed out earlier, instincts aren’t needed for the choice of ends. The nature of any being that can think is its own law. It has within itself a spur to action and a guide of action that it can’t suppress or reject. Rectitude is itself an end, an ultimate end, an end superior to all other ends; it governs directs and limits all the other ends, and its existence and influence don’t depend on anything arbitrary [see note on page 4]. It presides over everything. Every appetite and faculty, every instinct and will, and all nature are subjected to it. To act from •affection for rectitude is to act with light, conviction, and knowledge, whereas acting from •instinct is acting in the dark and following a blind guide. Instinct •drives and precipitates, but reason •commands. We can resist the impulses of instinct without doing violence to ourselves. Our highest merit and perfection often consist in doing just that. But we can never contradict the dictates of reason without a sense of shame, and without giving to our beings a wound in their most essential and sensitive part. Our experience of the operations of instincts ·in us· is evidence of our imperfection, and meanness, and low rank. The perception of rectitude prevails most in the higher ranks of beings. God’s chief glory is that he is removed infinitely from the possibility of any other principlec of action.

(2) With two things now made clear—that •our judgment concerning the nature of actions as morally good or bad prompts a motive to do or avoid them; and that •this judgment (although it often doesn’t prevail) is always the first, the proper, and the most natural and intimate spur and guide of the actions of reasonable beings—let us now explore a further question. Is a reasonable being’s judgment about right and wrong the only spur to his action that can

90

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

qualify him as morally good and worthy? Is such a judgment the only principlec from which flow all the actions that lead us to esteem the agents? In short, is virtue itself the thing that a virtuous agent aims at?

Remember that the only things that are strictly done by an agent are things that he designs to do, and that something that wasn’t in any way an object of his design is not strictly his, or at least can’t give him any claim to merit or praise. It follows from this that someone can’t be properly said to practise virtue if he doesn’t design to practise it, if it is of no importance to him, or if he doesn’t think about it at all. It seems utterly evident that an action that is under no influence or direction from a moral judgment can’t be ‘moral’ in the practical sense, i.e. that when virtue isn’t pursued or intended there is no virtue in the agent: morally good intention, without any idea of moral good, is a contradiction. To act virtuously is to obey or follow reason—and you can’t do that without knowing and intending it!

I know that according to the account of virtue that some writers have given, virtue presupposes that the agent has some intention other than the intention to be virtuous. That is because on their account of virtue...
how Price finished this sentence: it denotes only the emotion arising in us on observing actions flowing from certain motives and affections, and, in the original constitution of natures, is applicable alike to actions flowing from any motives.
what he seems to have meant: •when we call an action ‘virtuous’, all we mean is that when we observe the action and the motives and feelings that produced it, we experience a certain emotion in ourselves; and •the basic constitution of our minds doesn’t restrict this kind of emotion to any special subset of motives.
If this account were true, it would be a gross blunder to suppose that how a person acts is influenced by his sense of virtue and duty, or by any respect for moral good. But those of us who reject the underlying theory of virtue needn’t be troubled by this consequence of it; indeed the theory’s having this consequence is a large part of the case against it.

If a person can be virtuous and praiseworthy although he never thinks about virtue and isn’t ever motivated by it, then intelligence [still = ‘the ability to think’] certainly isn’t required for moral agency, and the lower animals are just as capable of virtue and moral merit as we are.—By this standard, couldn’t a person be regarded as ‘public spirited’ just because he makes a discovery that enriches his country, even if he did this accidentally and without any view to public good? Mightn’t a course of behaviour count as ‘ambitious’ even if it didn’t arise from the love of honour and power? or as ‘selfish’ even if it didn’t aim at private interest? or as ‘friendly’ even if it wasn’t associated with any friendly intention?

[Price’s next paragraph consists mainly in some quotations from Lord Shaftesbury’s book Characteristics of Men, Manners, Opinions, Times, which present the view of virtue that Price has been defending. Such quotations continue in a long footnote; but there Price writes less favourably about Shaftesbury’s performance in another of his works, thus:] Shaftesbury’s account of virtue in his Inquiry concerning Virtue or Merit is extremely deficient in several ways, especially in its limiting virtue so much....to the cultivation of natural affection and benevolence, and overlooking entirely....the authority belonging to virtue and to the principlec of reflection. Still, Lord Shaftesbury has said many excellent things about virtue and providence, and about life and manners; and it’s a very sad thing that his works are stained by his prejudices against Christianity, which have contributed so much to depriving his insights of their good

91

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

effects.

You may ask: ‘Isn’t benevolence a virtuous principlec? And don’t we approve all actions that come from it?’ I answer by repeating my earlier point [pages 32 and 39] that benevolence is of two kinds, rational and instinctive. Rational benevolence entirely coincides with rectitude, and the actions coming from it coincide with actions coming from a concern for rectitude. And the same is to be said of all those feelings and desires that would arise in a thinking nature just because it was capable of thought. Could it ever be the case that efforts to achieve an end which we as reasonable beings can’t help loving and choosing were not approved by reason? Could it be the case that something that is necessarily desirable to all beings is not also something that it is necessarily right to pursue? No, neither of those is possible!

But instinctive benevolence is not a principlec of virtue, and actions motivated by it alone are not virtuous. To the extent that you are influenced by instinctive benevolence, you are influenced by something other than reason and goodness, and that detracts from the moral worth of your action and of your character. This observation agrees perfectly with how ordinary people commonly think and feel and decide. When we know that a person’s conduct comes from mere natural temperament or inclination, we may indeed love the person—as we commonly love lower animals that we find to be gentle and easily managed—but we won’t have any tendency to regard to him as a virtuous agent. A soft and simple-minded man, however compliant, generous and good-tempered he is, never stands high in our esteem because we see his character as coming less from any influence of reason and moral good than from an agreeable instinct and turn of temperament that he was born with. Similarly, the tenderness of parents for their offspring, a fond mother’s risking her life to save her child, and all actions motivated by the nearer attachments of nature, seem to have their moral value lessened in proportion as they •come more from natural instinct and •are less accompanied by reflection on their reasonableness and fitness. In the absence of this reflection, it makes no moral difference what sort of feeling an action comes from....—But bear in mind that such reflection will usually accompany friendly and benevolent actions, and is certain to have some part in producing them—you can’t experience or think about such actions without approving of them. And, ·more generally·, some ideas of right and wrong are always present with all men, and must have some influence on almost everything they do. We have an inescapable awareness of rightness in relieving misery, in promoting happiness, and in every service of love and good-will towards others. This is what consecrates kindness and humanity, elevating them to the level of virtues.

Think about your attitude to

(i) actions motivated by universal, calm, and dispassionate benevolence,

and to

(ii) actions producing as much good as those, or even more, directed toward people to whom nature has closely linked us, and arising from kind impulses in our minds that are narrower (·not universal·) and more urgent (·not calm and dispassionate·).

Everyone regards the actions in (i) as more virtuous and amiable than the actions in (ii). Why? Because in (i) the operations of instinct have less effect and are more subdued, and the attention to what is morally good and right is more open and forceful. If we were prompted to the acts of universal benevolence in the same ·heated and urgent· way that parents are prompted to the care of their children, that

92

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

wouldn’t lead us to think of those acts as more virtuous. These facts can’t be explained consistently with the theory that virtue consists in

acting from kind feelings that can’t be derived from thinking, and can’t be influenced by it in their immediate exercise.

If that theory were right, why couldn’t it be the case that the virtue is greatest where the kind impulse is strongest? How could we explain the fact that when all use of reason is excluded, and only the force of instinct is at work, the virtue is the least and tends to vanish entirely? And why, especially, should we regard

resisting our strongest instincts, and steadily following the deliverances of cool unbiased reason against our instincts

as the highest virtue? Those who defend this theory would probably give it up, and accept the position I am defending, if they could be convinced that benevolence is essential to intelligence—·essential to thinking·—and not merely an implanted principlec or instinct.

These remarks are also applicable to self-love. Reasonable and calm self-love, as well as the reasonable and calm love of mankind, is an entirely virtuous principlec. They are both parts of the idea of virtue. Where virtue is greatest there will be the most ardent and active benevolence, and likewise the greatest degree of true prudence, i.e. the highest concern about bettering ourselves to the utmost, and the most effective and constant pursuit of private happiness and perfection, in opposition to whatever hindrances and temptations to neglect them may be thrown in our way.

Our natural desires carrying us to our own self-interest are very strong, and our •pursuit of our own interests is more likely to arise from these desires without any rational reflection or help from moral judgment than is our •pursuit of public good; and that is one reason why the former pursuit is not considered as virtue to the extent that the latter is. Avoiding a present danger or securing a present good for ourselves isn’t often regarded as at all virtuous; but the same can’t be said of trying to prevent a future danger or to secure a future good. The reason for this is that we are drawn towards what is present with a greater degree of instinctive desire^23 ·and therefore with less input from moral thinking·. The present makes itself felt more strongly than the future does, and strikes our minds more forcibly. Yet, in some circumstances where particular passions are opposed to reason, and where different pleasures compete with one another, it can be really virtuous to act with the motive of securing some present good. And quite generally, the more

^23 This is a very wise and necessary disposition of our natures. If the prospect of distant good aroused our desires with the same urgency as our desires for present good, think how distracted we would be in our pursuits! How inattentive to what is present, how impatient, how miserable it would make us! ·There is also a bad consequence of the way we are constituted·. Because we are more strongly drawn to present good than to future good, there is a danger that we will choose and settle for the one and neglect the other. But this drawback (which it is the business of reason and a principal part of virtue to prevent) is much less than the opposite drawbacks that would have come with a different constitution of our natures.—If you look at the situation coolly, it may seem very strange that someone who is acting solely from a concern for his own private good will knowingly choose a lesser good rather than a greater one, a present good rather than a much more important future one. If on such occasions we were determined by nothing but the simple and calm thought of good as such, this fact would indeed be entirely inexplicable. But when we attend to the fact that we have a stronger instinctive determination to present good than to future good, the difficulty mostly vanishes. The fact in question won’t be harder to explain than the fact that sometimes in other contexts a man will follow his passions and instincts in opposition to •his own happiness and to •all the reasons that can be put to him....

93

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

remote a good is, and the more temptations we have to resist in order to get it, the greater is our virtue in staying focused on it. These are cases where •reason is more needed to interpose and decide, •our passions are less in agreement with its dictates, and •our determinations are more derived from its authority. There are some kinds of future good the pursuit of which always proves virtue. Others are so agreeable to the lower parts of our natures, and so connected with strong instinctive desires, that actions produced by the prospect of getting them provide little if any evidence of virtue, even when reason approves of our choosing them. But when reason condemns certain gratifications, when lower pleasures stand in competition with higher ones, or when for any reason intrinsically innocent pleasures ought to be forgone—in these cases guilt and blame become the consequences of pursuing those pleasures.

This gives us a clear view of how far hope and fear can be virtuous principlesc, and why (for example) it isn’t virtuous to do something so as to escape an ignominious death or to obtain a valuable promotion, although it is often virtuous to refrain from gratifications that we know are harmful to us, or to give up a debauched way of life—to which passion and habit strongly urge us—because we think it will have a bad effect on our health and fortune.

These facts (and there are many more of the same kind) are all very strong evidence for the truth of the conclusion I am trying to establish, namely that the virtue of an agent is always less in proportion to the degree to which •his natural temperament and inclinations fall in with his actions, •instinctive principlesc operate, and •rational reflection on what it is right to do is lacking.

Something else that should be noticed: what I have said about self-love and the actions flowing from it shows us clearly what truth there is in this:

Conduct based on religious principles, and influenced by thoughts of the rewards and punishments that will follow virtue and vice in the after-life, can be fairly said to have no moral goodness.

·Specifically, what it shows is that there is no truth in this·! It is indeed surprising that anyone should ever have had anything negative to say about conduct in which we extend our care to the whole of our existence, act with a view to our final welfare, and elevate our minds above this-worldly objects because of our concern for a blessed immortality. If anything gives dignity to a character and raises one man above another, this does. If anything is virtue, this is. Especially given that virtue is the very reward that is expected -

•the highest degrees of moral improvement,

•a close resemblance to God,

•opportunities for the most extensive beneficence, and

•admission into a state into which no defilement can enter, and the love and hope of which imply the love of goodness.

—In short, if it is always virtuous to engage in a reasonable and steady pursuit of one’s own private happiness amidst temptations to forgo it through passion and present gratifications, it isn’t hard to work out what opinion we ought to have of the pursuit of the very special happiness that virtuous men are taught to expect in another world!....

Returning now to the main topic of this chapter: What I have said about virtuous actions can easily be applied to vicious actions. [See note on ‘vicious’ on page 21.] Someone’s performing a vicious action doesn’t imply that he is vicious, unless he knew or could have known that his action is vicious.... One way—and perhaps a good way—of putting the point is to say that the viciousness in an action isn’t the agent’s any more than the vicious action is his, and no more

94

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

of the vicious action is his than was included in his intention. (I said this earlier about the virtue of the action and of the agent.)

When we learn that a person had no suspicion of wrong in an action of his, and that he certainly wouldn’t have performed it if he had had such a suspicion, it would be utterly unjust to charge him with guilt and ill-desert on account of this action. It’s true that his lack of suspicion ·that his action is vicious· may be an effect of criminal •error and •carelessness, but in that case the agent’s guilt comes from •them and not from the resulting action that he performs in the belief that it is innocent. Every single action that a person performs has in it some precise and fixed degree of guilt, innocence or virtue, which depends only on his perceptions, views, and state of mind at the time of doing it, and can’t be increased or decreased by anything that happened before the action was performed or by anything that happens afterwards. What has been once true of an event must always remain true of it. The real exact character of an action at the time of performance—I mean its status as commendable or blameworthy—must for ever remain its character without alteration.—If it turns out to have pernicious consequences, they increase its guilt to the extent that the agent, at the time of acting, foresaw or suspected that such consequences would ensue, or had some awareness that he ought to be taking greater care about the possible effects of his conduct. A series of evil actions may give rise to other evil actions; if these are only materially [see page 85] evil, they may themselves be a very severe punishment of former wickedness, but they can’t increase the agent’s guilt or make him liable to further punishment.... If we accepted that one faulty step can taint all the actions that it may unfortunately have led to, whatever our present sense of them may be,....our condition would be deplorable! ·It would require impossible skill in looking forward·: who can ever know all the effects that will result from his actions? And in many cases ·it would require impossible skill in looking back·: who can be sure that the beliefs that he is now acting on didn’t have, anywhere in the thought-sequence that led to them, some influence from undue bias?....

Don’t think that what I am saying here has a tendency to excuse men for being negligent in their enquiries. [Price wrote ‘... a tendency to render men negligent in their enquiries’, but this was presumably a slip.] Though a crazy or drunken man may not be immediately to blame for performing many actions that are in themselves very evil, it is extremely wicked for a man to put himself into a state in which he knows he will be likely to perform such actions. •Doing what we foresee may cause us to do something evil blindly and unknowingly is not very different, ·morally speaking·, from •doing the evil deliberately.

This shows us, how inexcusable voluntary ignorance is, and how important it is that we avoid all unfairness in forming our beliefs. No upright person can be indifferent about this. Indeed we never have more scope for virtue, or better opportunities for exercising some of the mind’s noblest dispositions, than when we are enquiring after truth and duty. Considering •the dismal evils that can arise from dishonesty about this, and •what a sad thing it is to have darkness as our inner light, and •what mazes of error, superstition and destructive conduct we can be led into by a misguided judgment, we can’t be too diligent in working to get our consciences rightly informed, too anxious about acquiring sound beliefs and freeing ourselves from the power of whatever prejudices or passions tend to warp our minds and are inconsistent with the coolness, honesty, and impartiality that are absolutely essential for anyone trying to

95

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 8: A virtuous agent’s motives

discover what is true and right.

Thus I have given what I think to be the true account of the nature of practical virtue. I started with the thesis that practical virtue requires liberty and the ability to think. But what I have mainly emphasized is that we don’t regard as ‘virtuous’ any actions flowing merely from instinctive desires or from any other principlec except a concern for virtue itself. I have tried to show that what a virtuous agent cares about most is just being virtuous.—Virtue, if I have argued rightly, must be desired, loved, and practised on its own account. Nothing is an exercise of virtue unless it comes from an inward liking and respect for virtue for its own sake.—And I hope I have explained well enough how benevolence and self-love, and the actions to which they prompt us, are morally good and praiseworthy only to the extent that they are derived from this source. Some may say that

A respect for God’s will is a principlec of virtuous conduct that isn’t reducible to the desire for virtue.

Nothing could be more unreasonable than that! Why do virtuous agents obey the will of God? Isn’t it from a sense of duty? What merit would there be in obeying God’s will out of blind awe or servile dread, with no knowledge that this conduct is fit and appropriate?.... Here, as everywhere else, the ultimate spring of virtuous practice in reasonable beings is the reasonable faculty itself, the consideration of duty or the perception of right.

96

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

Chapter 9:

What does it mean to say that some actions and characters are more virtuous than others? How do we judge this?

Difficulties in the practice of virtue, the use of trial and discipline in getting reasonable beings to be virtuous,

and the essentials of a good and bad character

Throughout this work I have considered virtue generally and abstractly—its nature, foundation, obligation, and principal types—until in chapter 8 I considered it more particularly in relation to actual practice, and the capacities and wills of moral agents. I am now going to continue with that, explaining the various degrees of virtue in different actions and characters, and showing •how we calculate them, •how far the temperament should be formed by virtue, and •how the faculty that perceives virtue is related to our other powers.

As I showed in chapter 8, what makes us virtuous and deserving of reward is our reflection on the fitness of what we are about to do and the right of the case [Price’s phrase] concerning it. It’s the intention to act virtuously, and the influence that a concern for virtue has on our resolutions, that makes us objects of moral praise and esteem; and the greater this influence is, the greater we must judge the virtue to be and the more we must admire the action. Our judgment about the degree of moral good and evil in actions, then, is based on the degree of regard or disregard, of attachment or lack of attachment, to truth and rectitude that the actions display. External actions are to be considered as signs of the motives and views of agents. We can usually infer the motives from the actions with sufficient certainty; and when this happens to be impracticable, that prevents us from making any judgment about the merit or demerit of actions.

Here are some facts that provide good enough support for the thesis I have been presenting.

There isn’t much virtue in performing a good action that the agent has little temptation to omit: someone who isn’t drawn by virtue to perform a good action that •won’t cost him much trouble or expense, and •doesn’t noticeably get in the way of any of his natural desires, must have a very low level of virtue!—When secular interests, love of fame, curiosity, resentment, or any of our individual attitudes work together with virtue in prompting an action, the action is virtuous just to the extent that it was influenced by the agent’s thought of its rightness; and that influence can’t be great if the action is known to be in line with the agent’s non-moral way of thinking and with the current of his passions.—When difficulties occur, and secular interest, humour, vanity, or any of our inferior powers clash with virtue, the degree of virtue is proportional to the difficulties—or the number and violence of the passions—that are overcome.—When a given action would fulfill several different virtues, the performance of the action gives less strong evidence for virtue than it would if it had been motivated by a concern for just one of those virtues. A right action that was hard to perform

97

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

and was motivated •purely by gratitude is more virtuous than the same action, equally difficult and performed with an equal effect, when motivated •by gratitude, public and private interest, justice and veracity. So the virtue must be greatest when

•any single type of it,

•every view of what is decent and fit,

•every decision of our practical judgments,

is sufficient to determine us in opposition to all temptations, when we are ready to follow wherever virtue leads us and have a moral sensibility that makes us shrink from every appearance of wrong, and a horror at guilt that makes us afraid even to move towards it.

What about vicious actions? Well, the same circumstances that lessen the virtue of an action increase the vice in omitting it, and vice versa. If A is an evil act that I am not much tempted to perform, I don’t have to be very virtuous not to perform it; but if I do perform it that is very criminal because it shows very great weakness of the moral principlec.—When someone performs an evil action without having any thought of its being evil, he isn’t displaying a disregard for virtue and so he isn’t guilty.—When the agent does think of his action as evil, but his motives for committing it are very strong and pressing, the guilt of the action is lessened and all that can be inferred is (not the absolute but) the comparative weakness of the agent’s virtuous principlec, i.e. its being weaker than some other principlesc.—The more deliberately a wrong action is done, the more wicked it appears to us. That’s because in this case reason and conscience have time to marshal their forces and exert their utmost strength, and yet are conquered. That is why a single deliberate and willful act of vice may be the strongest proof of ·the agent’s· bad moral state and a sufficient indication of his whole moral character; and this can’t be said of any spur-of-the-moment faults that the agent is rushed into by the violence of sudden passions. In a word, with respect to an action that a man performs,

•the more evil it is,

•the more it contradicts his instinctive desires as well as his ideas of rectitude,

•the greater number of the different types of moral obligation it violates,

•the clearer his perception is of wrong in it,

•the longer his time for reflection is, and the fewer and weaker his temptations,

the greater is the vice he can be accused of and the more flagrant is his guilt. On the other hand, it is evident that the degree of guilt in an evil action is lessened if the number and strength of temptations is increased, and the time for reflection and the sense of wrong is shortened; and these factors may bring the guilt-level so low that all disapproval of the agent vanishes. From these observations we may draw the following ·four· inferences.

(1) [Price says that an agent can be thoroughly virtuous even if in his right actions he doesn’t have to overcome difficulties aand temptations. His virtue is secured by the facts about how he would behave if he were in such difficulties. Price continues:] Difficulties and drawbacks that get in the way of virtue are the means for showing to others what our moral temperament is. And they also have the following effects on ourselves. They awaken our attention to righteousness and goodness, they call forth the moral principlec to exert itself in a manner not otherwise possible, and thus become the means of producing stronger virtuous efforts, and of increasing the force and dominion of reason within us, and improving and confirming virtuous habits.—These are the uses of the difficulties and temptations that are met with in virtuous conduct, but it must

98

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

be accepted that in some respects they are also the causes of very great evils. They ·often· improve virtue, but they also ·sometimes· overwhelm and ruin it. They give rise to moral discipline, but they also obstruct it, producing moral depravity and generating all the corruptions and vices of the world. It isn’t part of my present plan to explain this fact, but I can’t resist going off-course so far as to raise a question about ·the moral education of· beings like ourselves, who grow up gradually to the use of reason, and on the way to it need •to acquire some habits or other and •to be guided by instinctive principlesc. Among such beings, how far might the evils I have mentioned have been prevented? We can’t answer this with certainty. Can virtue be disciplined and tested without being endangered? or endangered without sometimes being lost? Can we acquire any security or confirmation in virtue until we are habituated to it? And before the habit is acquired, and in the dawn of reason, won’t there inevitably be a risk of moral degeneration?

It may be thought that there could be beings who were so constituted that:

When they come into existence their constitutions and circunstances are such that while they are advancing towards maturity of reason, and acquiring sufficient views of the nature and excellence of virtue to keep them steady in the practice of it, their inclinations and desires always coincide with •their duty, and they don’t acquire habits that are unfavourable to •it.

For all I know, this is possible. And that is just one of many reasons why we have to admit that there’s much in the present state of mankind that we can’t explain. In fact, given where we stand in the universe and given the limitedness of our intellects, it would be very strange if we could explain all the facts about any object in nature, let alone the nature of mankind!—Be this as it may, it can’t be wrong to make this point: Given the natures and circumstances of men as they now are, if our desires and our duty always coincided we might have spent years behaving in an objectively virtuous manner without becoming truly virtuous in a grounded way; it could happen that ·during all those years of struggle-free virtuous behaviour· the moral principlec was lying dormant in us, so that if the slightest temptation turned up we would have gone astray. ·As things are with mankind·, difficulties in doing our duty and particular desires drawing us away from it ·do us a good service: they· force us to exercise virtue in a more wary, attentive, and constant manner, which accelerates our progress in it and grounds our respect for it. Although early on the virtuous principlec may be scarcely able to turn the balance in its own favour, every repeated instance, in which the inward spring of virtue thus exerts its utmost force and overcomes opposition, gives it new power. It has often actually happened that virtuous men have

•through a course of virtuous struggles and long practice of self-denial,

•through being accustomed to repelling temptations, restraining appetites and disregarding sufferings that their duty forced on them,

gradually strengthened the virtuous principlec and established the sovereignty of conscience in themselves to such an extent that difficulties have in a manner vanished, and virtue has become easy and delightful. And bear in mind that although this is the period when the difficulties of such a person are least, it is also the period when his virtue is greatest. So the truth of the matter is that the difficulties a virtuous agent meets with are in general evidence only of the defects of his virtue. If he had a sufficient degree of virtue he wouldn’t meet with any difficulties; and the more •virtue he has,

99

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

•the less effect any given degree of temptation has in turning him aside from virtue or disturbing his resolutions,

•the more he is master of every inclination within him,

•the less reluctance he feels in the discharge of his duty, and

•the more pleasure and eagerness he has in sticking to his duty.

How unreasonable it is, then, to •assert that human virtue exceeds that of angels because of the opposition it encounters, or to •think that the question ‘Would the excellence of God’s moral character be increased if he had within him some dispositions contrary to goodness?’ is hard to answer!—Can the very facts that are evidence for imperfection in virtue also add to its merit? [Price answers ‘No’, both regarding angels and regarding God. He is especially emphatic about God—‘His moral excellence consists in a degree of purity or holiness that makes him incapable of being tempted to evil.’ In the course of his long and unnecessary paragraph developing this line of thought, Price adds two footnotes:] (i) What I am saying here can be illustrated by substituting •power for •virtue.... The power of a being is the same, whether or not it meets with opposition. The difficulties that the being finds in overcoming opposition only serve to show its weakness: the greater the power it has, the less difficulty it must find in producing any given effect; and when the power is supposed to be infinite, as God’s is, the very notion of difficulty and opposition becomes a contradiction. (ii) The way I am talking about God is suitable to our common ways of conceiving of his perfections, but it isn’t strictly proper. In fact, it is in general hardly possible to speak about God otherwise than improperly....

This discussion shows that what I said about the extenuation of guilt by the strength of temptations must be understood with some restrictions. The strength of someone’s temptations may show only that his power of resistance is weak, that the spring of virtue (the contrary force in our minds that should repel temptations) is unwound or broken. ‘My temptations were strong’ is often pleaded as an excuse for vice—but what a wretched excuse it is! Temptations commonly owe their strength to strong evil habits that the guilty person has acquired and to the low and slack state of his moral powers. How absurd it is to make the lack of virtue an excuse for the lack of virtue, and to justify guilt by guilt!—However,....we can conceive of temptations so strong that no human virtue could overcome them. Although it’s only because our virtue is imperfect that we are vulnerable to being overcome by any temptations,....being overcome by some temptations may show much less defect of virtue than being overcome by some others. That is all that is meant by the plea of temptation as extenuating guilt. No-one, for instance, will say that a crime committed through fear of immediate tortures and death implies as much guilt as the same crime committed to avoid a slight inconvenience. [That completes (1), which began on page 98.]

(2) This discussion of degrees of virtue and vice has little or no relation to the question of whether there are any different degrees of objective right and wrong in actions, and doesn’t imply anything concerning it. Even if there were no different degrees of right and wrong, so that the only way to apply them was in judgments of the form ‘This action is absolutely and totally right’ and ‘This action is absolutely and totally wrong’, there would still be just as much room for countless degrees of virtue and vice, of merit and guilt in agents, and also in actions considered (not in the absolute and abstract way, but) in relation to the intentions and views

100

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

of •the agents or as signs and effects of •their respect for absolute virtue.

That is how we most commonly consider •actions, and it is the true source and meaning of the different degrees of commendation and blame, of praise and censure, that we bestow on •them, and of the various words and phrases by which these are signified....

(3) [Price now criticises Hutcheson’s formula for computing the morality of actions. He thinks it is along the right lines except for its fundamental assumption that—in Price’s words—‘benevolence is the whole of virtue’.]

(4) It is sometimes said that some good actions are more amiable [see note on page 29] than others because they are more free; but that cannot be right. It is very improper to speak of degrees of natural liberty and necessity. There seems to be no conceivable intermediate case between being the cause of an effect and not being its cause, between determining ourselves and not determining ourselves, between agency and its contrary. Every act of the will that I am conscious of—if it really is my act—must be entirely mine, and can’t be more or less mine. You may want to object: ‘But two or three or any number of causes may work together to produce one single effect.’ But that doesn’t hold as an objection, because in the case you have envisaged each cause has its own individual share of the effect to produce, which this cause alone produces, and it would be absurd to say that this cause was ‘helped’ to produce that share.—Besides, voluntary determination is a simple effect, not a complex and compounded one; so it doesn’t admit of more than one cause or principlec, because it’s a contradiction to suppose that the determination of a being may be partly his and partly another’s.

Setting that aside, let us turn our thoughts to the more intelligible suggestion that what is being said to lessen the merit of good actions must be not •natural necessity (which would take away the whole idea of action and will) but •moral necessity. This is the ‘necessity’ that arises from the influence on the mind of motives and feelings; it is said to be present when, given that the agent has such-and-such views, circumstances, and principlesc, it is certain that he will decide to do so-and-so. Now, it is undeniable that the very greatest necessity of this sort is consistent with—indeed it is implied by—the idea of the most perfect and meritorious virtue, so that it can’t possibly lessen it!^24

The more confident we can be that a man will perform an action when he is convinced of its propriety, whatever obstacles may lie in his way—i.e. the more effective and unconquerable the influence of conscience is within him—the more amiable we must think him.—Similarly, the most abandoned and detestable state of wickedness implies the greatest necessity of sinning and the greatest degree of moral impotence. The most vicious man is the one who is most enslaved by evil habits, or in whom appetite has gained the upper hand, and the respect for virtue and duty is weakened, to such an extent that we can always foretell with certainty that he will do evil when tempted to it.—Arising from that, let me ·refer back to the issue of liberty discussed earlier. I want to· remark in passing that an idea of liberty must be very erroneous if it •makes liberty inconsistent with the most zxabsolute and complete certainty—i.e. with the

^24 When someone says that a virtuous action is more amiable the less ‘necessary’ it is, if he means that the action is more amiable the less the agent is urged to it by....any motives other than virtuous ones, this will be very true. But in that case what increases the virtue of the action is not the mere circumstance of its being less ‘necessary’ but its coming more from the influence of love of virtue; and that fits with what I said at the beginning of this chapter.

101

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

kind of ‘necessity’ I have been discussing—or if it •supposes necessity to overthrow all steadiness of character and conduct. The greatest influence of motives that can rationally be conceived can in no way affect liberty (taking it that a rational account of motives doesn’t involve the obvious and intolerable absurdity of treating motives as though they were physical causes—·pushes in an almost literal sense·). It is surely very surprising that anyone should imagine that....when a man does something with the full consent of his will, with the least reluctance and the greatest desire and resolution, he should for this very reason be suspected of not doing ·it· freely, i.e. not doing at all.

My account of the various degrees of virtue and merit in actions, and of how we estimate them, enables us to understand why it is that

•when we judge calmly and impartially, we form much the same judgment of good actions affecting strangers as we do of good actions affecting ourselves or friends,

and also why

•if an agent has no opportunities to exercise his virtue, or if his good endeavours produce effects contrary to the ones he designed, our esteem for him is not lessened.

There’s no way to explain these facts if virtue is (as it must be if our ideas of it come from an implanted sense) merely a particular kind of agreeable feeling or sensation. There can be no doubt that our feelings of pleasure are lessened if the beneficiary of a good action is remote from us, or if well-intentioned conduct fails to have a good effect; so our assignments of virtue will also differ, if it’s true that virtue is merely an agreeable feeling. In contrast with this, the account of virtue that I have presented provides us with a stable and fixed rule of judgment, and shows us that the object of such judgments—·namely the merit or virtue of actions and characters·—is real and determinate in itself, unchangeably the same through all changes in our opinions or points of view. But the other notion of virtue that I have been criticising provides no basis for any rational estimate of virtue, leaves no fixed standard for it, and implies that all thoughts about it are equally sound because no-one can be mistaken about the morality or immorality of a particular action or character if all he is doing is to say what he feels about it.^25 It’s true that he can err regarding how much good is produced, or regarding how exactly the agent felt when acting; but these are not the same as virtue according to the theory I am now criticizing....

I added the restriction ‘when we judge calmly and impartially’ because it is perfectly obvious that the causes I have mentioned do often pervert and mislead our judgments. [Price devotes a page to elaborating this point. We are likely to give more moral credit to someone who succeeds in doing good to us than to someone who does good to people we don’t know or who tries but fails to do good to anyone. But we should guard against this ‘bias’.]

Having thus explained the general foundation of the different degrees of virtue and vice in actions, and stated the principles and rules by which we judge them, it will be useful next to get a clear view of what it takes for an agent to qualify as virtuous, i.e. for his character to be rightly labelled ‘virtuous’ rather than the contrary.

Anyone who has any idea of moral good must have an affection for it that can’t fail to have some influence on

^25 ‘The distinction of moral good and evil is founded on the pleasure or unpleasure that results from encountering or thinking about the sentiment or character in question; and that pleasure or unpleasure has to be known to the person who feels it; from which it follows that there is just so much virtue or vice in any character as everyone places in it, and that we can’t possibly be mistaken about this.’ Hume, Treatise of Human Nature, III.ii.8.

102

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

his actions and temperament.—It isn’t conceivable that a creature who is capable of reasoning should (i) have no respect for reason and its dictates, having no notion of the distinction that we express when we say ‘This is to be done’ and ‘That isn’t to be done’. A perception of that distinction is essential to our nature, and so is always present with us; and it’s not conceivable that this perception should ever become wholly ineffective in someone.—Nor, strictly speaking, can a being who is capable of reasoning (ii) have any tendencies within him that are contrary to rectitude. I mean: he can’t dislike rectitude as such, or be inclined to do wrong because it is wrong.—To suppose (i) is to suppose the entire destruction of the being’s powers of thought; and the very idea of (ii) is self-contradictory. There can’t be a being so corrupt that the unreasonableness of an action—i.e. his seeing reason against it—will be for him a reason for doing it or not a reason against doing it....

So (i) and (ii) aren’t possible, and don’t make any part of the idea of an evil character. This reminds us that the sources of all vice are our lower propensities and appetites. They are in themselves natural, innocent, and useful; but with us in our present state it is inevitable that they often interfere with reason and take over from it as influences on us—as much when they can’t be lawfully gratified as when they can. [Our ‘present state’ is meant to distinguish us as we now are with what we might come to be like in the after-life.] That is how it comes about that •we often actually deviate ·from the path of rectitude·, and that •how men differ in

•the strength of the reflecting principlec in them

is not in any way correlated with how they differ in

•the strength of their instinctive powers and desires.

The rightful place of the reflecting principlec in the mind is that of superiority to all these powers and desires, and of absolute dominion over them. As Butler has pointed out, it is in the nature of that principlec that

•it always has the role of examining, judging, deciding, directing, commanding, and forbidding, that

•it shouldn’t ever let anything push it aside, that

•it ought to model and superintend our whole lives, and that

•every motion and thought, every affection and desire, should be subjected constantly and wholly to its inspection and influence.

Reason is so intimately built into men that a deliberate decision not to be governed by it is scarcely possible, and that even when men are urged by passion and appetite they can seldom openly contradict it, or ever break loose from its guidance, without the help of tricks and sophistry, without many painful blinkings at the light and hard struggles to escape the force of conviction, without earnestly searching for excuses and palliatives, and thus trying to throw a cloud before their own eyes, to reconcile themselves to the wrong they are doing, hide its ugliness, and deceive themselves into thinking that in their circumstances it isn’t wrong after all. This shows plainly •how great the force of reason is, •how sovereign and unsurmountable it is in its nature, •how it clings to us when we are trying to cast it off, and •what effect it will have in our minds, somehow, however much we do to obscure, abuse, or subvert it.

This essential pre-eminence of the reasoning faculty is what ought chiefly to be considered in settling the true idea of human nature. [At this place Price has a footnote, which is here raised into the main text.]
·START OF PRICE’S FOOTNOTE·

The human mind would apparently have little order or consistency if it were only a system of passions and feelings that are continually drawing us different ways, without anything at the head of them to govern them, with the strongest

103

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

of them at any given moment necessarily determining our conduct. But this is far from being the mind’s real state. It has a faculty that is essential to it, to which every ·other· power within it is subjected; the special task assigned to this faculty is to reconcile the differences amongst all our particular feelings, to point out to us when and how far each one of them shall or shall not be gratified, and in all cases of competition to settle which is to give way. This faculty is our moral faculty; and what gives us the true idea of human nature is the subservience of all within us to this faculty. Its supremacy, I have remarked, is implied in the idea of it, but we have also a demonstration of it from fact. The least violation of this faculty at the behest of all our other powers in combination gives us pain and shame; whereas the greatest violation of our other powers at the behest of •the moral faculty is approved by us; indeed, the more we contradict our other powers in compliance with •it, and the greater sacrifice we make of their enjoyments and gratifications to •it, the more pleased we are with ourselves, and the higher inward satisfaction and triumph we feel. [The footnote adds a reference to Butler as agreeing with this, and to Hutcheson. Price says that it is hard to reconcile Hutcheson’s correct views on this matter with his other views about virtue, and continues at enormous length to explain why.]
·END OF FOOTNOTE·
It proves to us quite certainly that the basic, proper, and sound state of our natures is the state in which this faculty—our natures’ distinguishing part—is indeed pre-eminent, and all the other powers and principlesc are obedient to it.—Goodness in mankind is this state restored and established. It is the power of reflection raised to its proper position of direction and sovereignty in the mind, conscience fixed and kept on the throne and governing all our passions. The least it implies is some predominance of good feelings, and superiority of virtuous principlesc above all others.—Wickedness, on other hand, is the subversion of this basic and natural state of the mind, or the prevalence of the lower powers in opposition to the authority of reason. It implies that good principlesc are inferior to some others within us, gives us a greater attachment to some particular objects than to truth and righteousness, or makes our attitude to virtue so defective that it is consistent with knowingly acting wrongly. It is the violent and unnatural state of the mind, the deposition of reason, and the exaltation of appetite, the death of the man, and the triumph of the brute, slavery in opposition to liberty, sickness in opposition to health, and uproar and anarchy in opposition to order and peace. [That last sentence is verbatim Price.]

Thus, if we want to know our own characters, to find out which class of men we belong to, the good or the bad, we must compare

•our concern for everlasting truth and righteousness with our concern for friends, credit, pleasure, and life,

•our love of God and moral excellence with our love of inferior objects, and

•the dominion of reason ·over us· with the force of appetite,

and find which prevail. Until the rational part gets the victory over the animal part and the heart is mainly turned towards virtue, until the principlesc of piety and goodness obtain in some degree the supremacy and the passions are compelled to give up their usurped power, we are within the confines of vice and misery.—There’s reason to believe that many people deceive themselves into thinking that since they have many valuable qualities and feel the workings ·within them· of good principlesc, since they love virtue and hate vice and do good in their roles or positions in life, they have little reason to distrust their characters. What they are overlooking is

104

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

the point I have been emphasizing, namely that they ought chiefly to attend to the place and degree of these principlesc in comparison with others. The people who are truly virtuous and worthy are not those who hate vice but those who hate it above pain, dishonour, or anything whatever; not those who love virtue but those who have a supreme concern for virtue, putting it ahead of anything that can compete with it. It is often said that it is the ruling passion that determines how someone’s character should be described. The ruling love of power, fame, and distinction qualifies a man as ‘ambitious’, the ruling love of pleasure makes him ‘a man of pleasure’, the ruling love of money makes him a ‘covetous’ man. Well, similarly, the ruling love of God, of our fellow-creatures, and of rectitude and truth is what makes a man qualify as ‘virtuous’.

‘How can I know that the love of virtue is predominant in me? What are the marks and effects of the superiority of good feelings that you have said are essential to a good character?’ This is a natural question to raise.

(1) The •predominant passion always pulls the thoughts after it, gives them their principal employment, and gives a touch of •itself to all our studies and deliberations. What we most love is what we think about oftenest and attend to the most. If we want to know whether virtue and conscience rule within us, therefore, we must examine which way the main current of our thoughts runs, what objects show up in them most frequently and unavoidably, what lies on them with the greatest weight, and what we dwell on most and take into consideration most when we are planning and deciding what to do.

Specifically, when you are deliberating about some project that you might undertake, do you think not so much about how it will affect your credit, fortune, or ease, as about what, all things considered, reason and right require of you, what you would expect anyone else to do in the same circumstances, what good it may produce, how it will appear to you in retrospect, what effect it will have on God’s favour to you, how well it fits with your interests on the whole, and how well it suits the dignity of a being with your faculties, your relationships, and your expectations? But,

(2) This predominance will mainly show up in actual practice, in how we live our lives. Our actions always show what stands foremost in our thoughts and feelings. The strength of inner feelings is always proportional to their effects on external conduct. When the intellectual and moral principlec is the reigning one, therefore, it excludes everything irregular and immoral from the behaviour, all unreasonable courses of action are dropped, the whole of duty is faithfully attended to and carried out, no bad habits are spared, no wrong dispositions are given free rein, no known obligation is deliberately and openly neglected. [That sentence contains the first of several occurrences of a cognate of ‘regular’ used in a moral sense. On the basis of the word’s etymology (Latin regula = ‘rule’), conduct is ‘irregular’ if it breaks the moral rules, i.e. if it is morally wrong. Cognates of ‘regular’ in our everyday sense of it occur quite often up to page 34. On page 121 it seems to be used a couple of times in both senses at once.]

To qualify as having good characters we must—above all—have virtue that is not partial; we must act in conformity with every relation in which we stand, however it is made known to us; we must attend not to one duty or one kind of right conduct to the neglect of others, but be equally concerned about every type of duty and the whole of moral rectitude. Someone who is just, kind, meek, and humble, but also an habitual drunkard, has no claim to genuine virtue. The same is true of •anyone who is sober and temperate but will deceive and cheat; of •anyone who prays and fasts, is exact in all the external parts of religion, and is zealous for

105

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

truth and piety, but lacks honesty, gentleness, meekness, veracity, and charity; of •anyone who is chaste, generous, friendly, and faithful, but lacks piety.... I gave part of the reason for this in chapter 7, and here I shall add one more: it is that someone who habitually breaks one divine law, or retains one cherished vice, demonstrates that if he had equal temptations to transgress in all other parts of virtue he would do it, and become totally abandoned. As long as any ·one· passion holds sway over us and remains rebellious and lawless, there’s plainly something within us stronger than virtue, something that masters and subdues it; God and conscience don’t have the throne; the mind still doesn’t have the right balance, and its order and health are not recovered. Until we have an equal and entire affection for goodness, we don’t have any affection for it that is truly acceptable or that can be of much account and value. [Price develops this line of thought in the language of love for a woman, ending with:] Her nature is such that she can’t admit of any rival. He who doesn’t love her above everything else doesn’t love her at all.—A partial concern with rectitude is inconsistent and absurd.... If you want to be genuinely good, you must be consistently and thoroughly good..... If you aren’t, then give up all claim to true virtue, and give up all hope of the happiness in reserve for it.

You’ll see that I am not saying that we must be perfect. We are indeed quite incapable of that.... Some infirmities will cling to the best people, and it is impossible at present [= ‘in this earthly life’] always to discipline our passions so strictly that they never surprise or hurry us into doing something that our hearts will disapprove of. But whenever this happens, it is essential to the character of a good man that this ·moral failure· is his greatest trouble, and that it makes him even more vigilant in future. His settled prevailing commitment in heart and life is to truth, piety, and goodness, though unfortunately he may sometimes be misled. Conscience is uppermost, the sovereignty of reason is established, and bad habits are suppressed—though not so thoroughly that he will never be in danger of deviating. The enemies of his virtue will never find him off his guard.

(3) In order to discover whether the love of •virtue is predominant in us we should investsigate what degree of delight we have in •it. Anything that gives to the soul its prevailing tone and direction and generates its chief pursuit will be agreeable to it. All acts arising from established habits are free, unconstrained and cheerful. What our hearts are most set on will make the principal part of our happiness. What we love most, or have the greatest esteem and liking for, must be the source of our greatest pleasures.—So a man should suspect himself of bad character if he finds that virtuous actions, the duties of piety, and the various exercises of love and goodness to which he may be called, are distasteful and burdensome to him. For every virtuous man,

•virtue is what chiefly gives him contentment,

•exercising virtue is his chief delight, and

•his consciousness of ·his own· virtue gives him his highest joy.

He ought always to be ready to do whatever it requires from him, never reluctant to do what he is convinced is his duty, and never more satisfied or happy than when he is doing it.

You may want to ask: ‘These pleasures that are inseparable from virtue, especially the pleasures of the higher degrees of it—don’t they tend to make virtue that much more selfinterested and thus to lower its value?’ I answer that this may indeed be the consequence, insofar as the pleasure that merely accompanies virtue can be the motive for virtuous conduct. But it is scarcely in our power (whatever we may think)....really to deceive ourselves in this manner.

106

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

[Price explains how self-deception comes into this. If you are to do A in order to get pleasure from the thought of having acted virtuously, you must be planning •to do A for that pleasure-seeking reason and •to deceive yourself into thinking that you have done A for a motive that makes this virtuous.]

(4) One further criterion of a good character must not be overlooked, namely the constant endeavour to improve. True goodness must be a growing thing. All habits gain strength through time and exercise. There can’t be any question of someone’s having sound principlesc of virtue in him if he isn’t concerned about strengthening them to the utmost and ·thereby· getting a total victory over all the enemies of his happiness and perfection. Whoever has tasted the joys of benevolence and righteousness hopes to get more of them, and is grieved by the remains of moral imperfection in his character. ·If all he wanted was· to keep within the bounds of what is innocent or lawful, ·he might fully achieve his aim; but· he can’t have so little zeal that that is all he wants! A person who thinks himself ‘good enough’ can be sure that he isn’t good at all. When the love of virtue becomes the reigning affection ·in us·, it won’t be possible for us to be satisfied with any degrees of it that we can acquire.—We find an analogue of this when any of our lower affections takes charge. Every passion, when it becomes uppermost, constantly urges us to provide new gratifications for it. A man whose prevailing passion is the love of power, or of money, or of fame, seldom thinks (however much he has) that he has acquired enough, but is continually grasping at more and working to add to his glory and treasures.—This fact about the passions, namely that when they pass their natural boundaries they can’t be satisfied, •is a sad perversion of a disposition that is truly noble, and often •leads to unbearable misery.... One of the most pitiable spectacles in nature is a covetous, ambitious or voluptuous person who, not contented with what he has, loses all the enjoyment it could give him and is tortured perpetually on the rack of wild and restless desire. But consider the good man who can’t be satisfied with his present level of goodness, who is driven by the high and sacred ambition to grow wiser and better, to become more like God, and to move steadily towards perfection—how desirable and happy his state is!

....The understanding has two branches, •moral and •speculative [see note on page 82]. Our speculative understanding is evidently capable of infinite improvement, so our moral understanding must be so as well. Why? Because these are the same faculty applied to different subject-matters, so they must be inseparably connected, and it’s inconceivable that they don’t influence each other. In a good person

•every improvement in his speculative knowledge,

•every advance he makes in the discovery of truth,

•every addition to the strength of his reason, and the extent and clarity of its perceptions,

must be accompanied by perceptions of •moral good that are correspondingly more extensive, with a clearer and better acquaintance with •its nature, importance and excellence, and consequently with more scope for practising •it and a more invariable direction of the will towards •it. This ·improvement of the understanding·, combined with the growing effects of habit and of constant exercise of the man’s virtue, can gradually strengthen and exalt the practical principlec of rectitude to such an extent that it absorbs every other principlec in him, and annihilates every contrary tendency. In moral or intellectual improvement there is no point beyond which we can’t go through hard work, attention, correct cultivation of our minds, and the help of proper advantages and opportunities. [Can •vice intensify without limit, as •virtue can? Price’s answer has a puzzling

107

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

No-Yes-No form, but we can work out what his position is. A limitless diminution in the strength of the moral principlec in someone leads to its being completely wiped out, and then—Price seems to say—he is throwing out reason and is no longer a being to whom moral categories apply. But short of that limit there is room for endless variety in how thoroughly the vicious man’s moral principlec is out-gunned by his other desires and passions.]

[Price offers an exclamatory page about the many moral frailties of human beings and the correspondingly many opportunities for moral improvement. Then:]

One question more on this subject can properly be raised here: ‘In our idea of a good character should we include not only •the subordination to the faculty of reason of all our other powers but also •a correct ordering of those lower powers in relation to one another?’ A sufficient answer to this ·can be given briefly; it· is that the subordination to reason of the lower powers implies their due state, measure, and proportion in relation to one another. It may happen that some of them are stronger than they ought to be in comparison with others; but if reason is in charge the irregularity that would otherwise follow will be prevented, and the right balance will be gradually restored; the moral principlec will strengthen the side that is too weak and restrain the one that is too strong.—I have remarked that when we increase the force of reason we correspondingly lessen the occasion for appetite and instinct. So there can’t possibly be any drawbacks in any reduction of instinct if reason is correspondingly raised. But we men aren’t in fact capable of improving our reason as much as that, so that in fact great evils would arise from taking away •our instincts and passions. •They were wisely, kindly given to us....

•to be our only guides until reason becomes capable of taking over as our director,

and after that

•to enforce reason’s dictates, and aid us in obeying them,

•to give vigour and spirit to our pursuits, and

•to be the sail and wind (so to speak) for the vessel of life.

What we should be concerned about, then, is not eradicating our passions (which would be a wicked thing to do, if it were possible) but keeping reason vigilant and immovable at the helm, and making the passions more easily governable by it....

The character and temperament of a man who naturally has the passion of resentment in a strong form, with little compassion to counter-balance it, will certainly degenerate into malice and cruelty if he is guided solely by instinctive principlesc. But if is guided by reason and virtue, the excessiveness of his resentment will be checked; all that is hard, unfair, injurious, revengeful, or unkind will be excluded from his conduct; his temperament will be softened and humanized; the miseries of others will be duly regarded, and all that is proper will be done to ease their burdens and increase their joys. The same thing holds for someone whose self-love and desire for distinction are naturally too high in relation to his benevolence, and who will become proud, selfish, and ambitious unless he is governed by reason. And similarly with all other cases of passions that aren’t properly strength-related to one another.—A man’s being virtuous rules out his allowing any excess in his feelings or any internal disorder that he is aware of or that he could discover and rectify. Neither anger, nor self-love, nor the desire for fame can be so powerful....as to make him envious, gloomy, covetous, cowardly, self-neglectful, mean-spirited, or slothful. •Piety and •virtue consist in the proper regulation of the passions—no better definition can be given of •them. They

108

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 9: Degrees of vice and virtue

signify nothing more than

excluding whatever is inconsistent with true worth and integrity,
making those who claim to have them better in every aspect of life, and
making iritable people good-natured,
making fierce and overbearing people gentle,
making obstinate people compliant,
making haughty people humble,
making narrow and selfish people open and generous,
making sensual people temperate, and
making false and deceitful people faithful and sincere.

Reason is inconsistent with every kind of unreasonableness and irregularity. It is essential to it that as far as its command extends it directs the passions to their proper objects, confines them to their proper functions, and prevents them from disturbing our own peace or that of the world....

[Price now writes ecstatically about the ‘tranquility and bliss’ that comes with great virtue, and the ‘contempt as well as pity’ that we must feel for ‘those who prefer shadows and tinsel to this first and highest good’.]

To conclude this chapter, let me remark that my account of the requirements for having a good character gives us a melancholy view of the condition of mankind. If my account is right, true goodness is by no means as common as we could wish, and the indifference and carelessness that we see in a great part of mankind is utterly inconsistent with it.—Many of the people who have good reputations, and whose behaviour is in the main decent and regular, may owe this more to •the particular favourableness of their natural temperament and circumstances, or to •their never having had much opportunity or temptation to be otherwise, than to •any genuine and sound principlesc of virtue established within them and governing their hearts. Most people are not grossly wicked or eminently good—these two extremes are almost equally scarce—but they are as far from being truly good as they are from being very bad; they are lazy and unthinking, neglecters of God and immortality, wearers of the form of piety without the reality of it. They are, in short, blameworthy and guilty not so much because of what they do as because of what they do not do.

So we all have the greatest reason for being careful of ourselves, and for closely watching and examining our hearts and lives.—I suspect that it’s much too common for men to think that their duties are less onerous than they really are, and to expect....that they may rise to bliss under the divine government as a matter of course, and without working at it very hard.—There isn’t indeed anything more necessary than to call on men to consider seriously the nature of the present state, the precariousness of their situation, and the danger they are in of remaining destitute of the virtuous character and temperament that are necessary qualifications for bliss. More than anything else, they need to be warned to save themselves from the evil of the world, and to be reminded, often, that if they want to escape future condemnation they must exercise vigilance, attention and zeal, and try to be better than mankind in general are.

109

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

Chapter 10

Using my account of morality to explain and support some of the principal doctrines of natural religion, particularly God’s moral attributes, his moral government, and a future state of rewards and punishments

Before I embark on the announced topics of this chapter, bear with me while I recapitulate part of what I have already said in this work, and try to give you a clear, unified, over-all view of the state of the controversy about the foundation of virtue.

It is discouraging to think of the confusion that arises in most debates and enquiries from the ambiguous senses of words. If we could •understand one another’s meaning precisely, •see in detail how our views differ, and •communicate our naked and genuine opinions to one another without risking their being more or less mistaken because of the imperfections of language, we would find that there are few if any points on which we disagree as much as we seem to. Many questions have been fiercely debated about down the centuries although the disputants on both sides have all along really meant pretty much the same, and been nearly agreed—as far as they had ideas. I say ‘as far as they had ideas’ because men in general lack ideas as much as they lack anything; and a controversy can become very tedious and voluminous while neither party have any definite opinions about the subject of it and both are zealously and quarreling over a set of phrases....

Our present topic has suffered from a great many of the tangles caused by the ambiguity of words; and it seems that the word ‘foundation’, especially, can have various senses which, if they aren’t attended to, are bound to produce endless disputes. For how could we agree on a view about what the foundation of virtue is if we give different meanings to ‘foundation’ and therefore have different ideas about what the question is?

Let us, then, consider in careful detail what we mean when we investigate the ‘foundation of virtue’. And let us stipulate that by ‘virtue’ we mean ‘absolute virtue’ or the rightness, propriety or fitness of certain actions; everyone attributes this to some actions, and the only way I can explain it is to ask you to reflect on what you are conscious of when you experience or think about those actions.

(1) When now we ask ‘What is the foundation of virtue?’, using ‘virtue in the sense I have just explained,we may mean ‘What is the true explanation or reason that such-and-such actions are right, or appear to us under the notion of right?’ And only two explanations of this can possibly be given. It may be said (i) that right is a species of sensation, like taste or colour, and therefore ‘right’ doesn’t stand for anything absolutely true of the actions to which we apply it. This answer places the foundation of right entirely in God’s will and good pleasure. It may instead be said (ii) that ‘right’ stands for a real characteristic of actions, something true of them, something necessary and unchangeable and independent of our perceptions, like equality, difference, proportion, or connection; so that there’s nothing to be said about why such-and-such actions are right, any more than

110

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

about why the natures of things are what they are—e.g. why the opposite angles made by the intersection of two straight lines are equal, or why it is impossible that anything should exist without a cause.—It would be extremely unreasonable for anyone to demand more than this, asking ‘What is the foundation of truth?’ When we have traced a subject back to the natures of things we are always completely satisfied, and it is trifling and silly to want any further explanation. If someone seriously asked ‘Why is the whole greater than a part?’ or ‘Why is two different from twenty?’, would he deserve an answer? Wouldn’t we think he was out of his mind? It has been said that the will of God is the foundation of truth, but no-one can understand this. It is sacrificing all the divine perfections to the single attribute of will, and even—while seeming to magnify God’s will—subverting it, making it impossible. For what is it founded on? Can there be power without possibles, or will without objects, i.e. without anything to be willed? ·God’s will is his •power to actualize various •possibilties; in exercising it he •wills that •something-or-other be the case·. The will presupposes these ·possibilities and objects of the will·; are they nevertheless dependent on the will and derived from it?—Perhaps some people will think as I do that because •truth has a reference to •mind, •necessary truth and the eternal natures of things imply a •necessary and eternal mind, and force us to acknowledge the unoriginated, incomprehensible wisdom and intelligence of God.

(2) Again, when we ask ‘What is the foundation of virtue?’we may mean ‘What....are the considerations that imply obligation in particular cases and make particular actions right?’ If I ask ‘Why ought this person to act in that way in those circumstances?’, it would be proper to reply ‘Because he has received benefits from others’ or ‘Because it will make him happy’ or ‘Because God commands it’. And there will be as many ‘foundations’ of virtue (in this sense) as there are first principles of it. Those who say that the only foundation of virtue is private happiness are probably using ‘foundation’ in this sense. That is, they probably mean that nothing obliges, nothing ever makes an action fit to be performed, except some prospect of the agent’s obtaining happiness and avoiding misery. If we ask these people ‘What makes it right for us to promote our own good? How are we to explain its being the ·proper· object of our desires and efforts?’, they probably wouldn’t mind appealing to truth and the natures of things; and in that case they and I would be in agreement about ‘the foundation of virtue’ in the former sense of ‘foundation’, and would differ only about the subject-matter of virtue (as I called it when discussing it in chapter 7).—This must be what is meant by those who contend that virtue and obligation are created purely by the will of God (unless they are also claiming that God’s will is the only thing that makes truth). If they think carefully about the question ‘Why ought we to do the will of God?’....they will find that they must either •treat this as a necessary self-evident truth or •explain it in terms of the power of God to make us happy (or miserable) if we obey (or disobey) him; the latter of those would turn their theory into the one that bases all virtue and obligation on self-love, and is vulnerable to my criticisms of that.

[In the third edition Price added an end-note, linked to this point in the text. It is a pained report on and criticism of some of the views expressed in William Paley’s Principles of Moral and Political Philosophy.]

(3) Or the phrase ‘the foundation of virtue’ may mean ‘the motives and reasons that lead us to virtue and support the practice of virtue in the world’. This must be what is meant by those who want to unite the different theories and represent •God’s will, •self-interest, •the reasons of things,

111

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

and •the moral sense as distinct but coinciding ‘foundations of virtue’. It is indeed undeniable the joint force of these carries us to virtue. But if we are using ‘foundation’ only in its first sense, we’ll find that only the last two of that quartet can be the true ‘foundation of virtue’.

If you want to get a more detailed and precise view of this subject, and to avoid puzzles and confusion as much as possible, you should attend also to the various common meanings of the words ‘action’ and ‘virtue’. What I have called ‘the virtue of the agent’ or ‘practical virtue’ is to be understood quite differently from absolute virtue. But I think I said enough about that distinction in chapter 8.

My remaining task is to make some general remarks about the whole position that I have been defending in this treatise.

The most important thing is to point out how my account of morality helps us in our enquiries into the nature and character of ·God as· the first cause, and in explaining and proving the facts of Natural Religion.

If it were certain that the origin of our moral perceptions is an implanted sense [see page 4], it wouldn’t follow from our having such perceptions that God has them too, any more than such conclusions could be drawn from other facts about our likes and dislikes or about our sensations of sight and hearing. If there were nothing in the natures and reasons of things to be a ground of a moral and righteous disposition in God’s mind, enabling us to say why he prefers happiness to misery, and approves of goodness, truth, and fairness rather than their contraries, it would be much harder than it is to learn about his will and character; indeed, I think it would be utterly inconceivable to us how he could have any moral character at all.—This is supported by my reasoning in chapter 1, section iii, and also by the following reasoning.

If in respect of intrinsic worth and goodness all rules and standards of conduct are alike, if no goal can appeal to God’s choice more than other goals because of something in it, if

in particular there is nothing in the natures of things to be the ground of his preference for happiness over misery, or his approval of goodness rather than cruelty, then his nature must be essentially indifferent alike to all goals; it was always as possible that he should be malevolent as that he should be benevolent; there is no explanation to be given of why he is one of these rather than the other; and therefore he can’t have any determinate character. It’s quite certain that whatever God is he is necessarily. The suggestion that there is something in his nature that he might have lacked, or that he could lose, is self contradictory.

[Price offers to ‘illustrate’ his reasoning with the example of a universe containing only one body, which is moving in a certain direction. The illustration isn’t well presented, and anyway doesn’t help much. After moving out of it, Price returns to his real topic:] It is absurd, among many states of will and character that are in themselves indifferent and equally possible, to suppose that some one of them is actual without some cause that makes it so.

I should add that if no rule of conduct for thinking beings follows from the natures of things, and is necessary, then there is necessarily no rule—the whole notion of such a rule is contradictory.

The distinction between necessary and contingent existence is the main foundation of all that we believe regarding the first cause. We perceive this distinction intuitively—·i.e. we see it at a glance, and don’t have to be argued into grasping it·. The objects of thought that suggest it to us force the idea of it onto our minds. Some things present themselves to us as self-evidently effects, unstable and arbitrary in their

112

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

natures, indifferent as between existence and non-existence, and capable of existing in any one of an infinity of different ways. So we know for sure that these things are derived, dependent, and produced ·by causes·. Examples of this include: •matter and •motion, the •form and order of the world, and all •particular things that we can perceive through the senses. These items—and in general all imperfect and limited existents—are effects, and require a cause; and we see this as clearly as we see that there is such a thing as ·causation· or productive power or dependence of one thing on another. In short, if it is conceivable that x doesn’t exist then it is possible for x not to exist; and anything that could not-exist must, if in fact it does exist, have been caused to do so.—On the other hand, there are some things that we see intuitively not to be effects, not to need a cause, to be underived, self-existent, and unchangeable. We can see that to suppose any of them to be possibly non-existent is to suppose a contradiction.... Examples of this include •space and •duration and all •abstract truths and possibilities.

[Now a brief paragraph in which Price repeats things that (as he admits) he has already said in chapter 5. Then:]

Reasonings of this kind plainly tend to show us that if the distinctions of right and wrong, and moral good and evil, are nothing in the natures of things, God cannot have any character. And this conclusion is contradicted by known facts: God’s having some dispositions, some principlec of action, some character, is clearly shown to us by the fact that he creates at all, and even more clearly by the purposes indicated by his acting with the uniformity and wisdom that we see in the constitution of nature. So the whole course of things—·the world and everything that happens in it·—shows the falsity of the premise that good and evil are not inherent in the intrinsic natures of things.

But although •effects thus prove that God has some character (which is enough to refute the theory of morality I have been attacking), it may be doubted whether •effects alone provide us with any undeniable proofs of God’s having the particular character of goodness; because it seems not to be impossible to explain the effects on other suppositions. An unthinking agent cannot produce •order and •regularity; so wherever •these appear they demonstrate design and wisdom in the cause. But it can’t be said, in a parallel way, that happiness couldn’t be caused by a selfish or capricious or even malicious agent; so the appearance of happiness in an effect can’t be claimed to demonstrate the goodness of the cause. It has to be granted that •good is greatly prevalent in what we see of the works of God, that •everything we perceive of the world shows kind design, and that •the primary direction of every law and regulation of nature is towards happiness; but still someone might say:

‘Who knows what different scenes may have existed at earlier times, or may now exist in other districts of the universe? An evil being may sometimes cause good, just as a good being may sometimes cause suffering and pain. We see so little of nature! From what we observe •at a point and •in a moment what conclusions can we securely draw regarding •the whole universe •through all eternity? Concerning a plan of boundless extent, designed and carried out by an incomprehensible being, what can be learned from such a superficial and incomplete observation as we can make of a vanishingly small part of it? Can it be right to base a general conclusion on a single experiment, or to determine the character and views of a being that we have no independent experience of, from a few acts that can be interpreted in many different ways? If we had only effects to go by, and

113

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

nothing in necessary truth and reason to argue from, wouldn’t it be natural to wonder, anxiously, about •whether great changes will happen in the world later on, •whether the principlec of action in the first Cause is not goodness but caprice or a love of variety, or •whether the world as we now see and feel it was designed to give a keener edge to future disappointment, the ultimate aim being universal misery?’

I leave it to you to decide what respect you think these objections deserve. I am far from thinking that they succeed in showing that effects, independently of all arguments from moral fitness [Price’s seven-word phrase], can’t provide us with sufficient arguments for the goodness of God.

When we first reflect that undoubtedly God has some will and character, and that it is inherently as possible and as credible that he should be good as that he should have any other character, our subsequent thoughts about the obvious marks of kindness and love that we see in his works inevitably incline us to think that he is good.When we have no more evidence for a proposition than against it, any •circumstance that tips the balance in its favour ought to determine our understandings and draw our assent ·to the proposition· with a level of confidence proportional to •its apparent weight. As for the objections and suspicions expressed above, it can fairly be said that we should judge concerning what we don’t see by what we do see, and not vice versa! Thus, as long as the over-all appearance of what we experience of God’s works, though comparatively little, is clearly as if happiness were their end, we’re entitled to conclude that this is indeed the truth. ·And the point about what a tiny proportion of the universe we know anything about cancels out·. We are considering the thesis that some principlec other than goodness influences the Author of the universe, so that on the whole the universe doesn’t look as though goodness were behind it. Well, the more extensive we suppose the universe to be, the more improbable it was that we would be dropped into the ‘·vanishingly small·’ part of it where goodness is so much exerted.—But some writers (especially those who have a dismal idea of human life as being on the whole unhappy) are unlikely....to be much influenced by this argument. This leads to questions of considerable importance that have often been well discussed: What are we to make of the appearances of evil in the world? Given those appearances, and the greater degrees of happiness that we think we see might have been given to us, don’t we have reason to suspect that goodness is not the spring of action in the Deity?—In thinking about this, we should especially note •that the natural state of a being is always his sound and good and happy state, •that all the corruptions and disorders we observe are plainly unnatural deviations and excesses, and •that there are no examples in which ill as such [Price’s phrase] is the genuine causal upshot of the basic constitution of things.^26

If, while the voice of all nature (as far as we hear it) is providing us with these arguments, it appears to us that

•for a thinking being all ends are not the same, and

•that there is something intrinsically better in goodness, veracity, and justice than in their contraries, something morally different in their natures,

our confidence about God’s moral attributes will be increased

^26 It might have been objected here that the most we can infer from effects is the present disposition of the Deity, and that even if they showed this to be benevolent we still have no evidence to prove the stability of God’s character, i.e. that he always has been and always will between good. The full reply to such objections may be learnt from the observations on the necessary existence of the Deity that will be found at the end of this treatise. [This refers to a ten-page ‘dissertation’ that Price tacked onto to this work in its third edition; it is not included in this version.]

114

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

in the same degree that we think we have reason to believe this. And if it appears to us clear and certain that

•intellect implies the approval of beneficence, that

•the understanding is the power that judges concerning moral differences, and that

•the natures of things make it necessary that goodness rather than malice constitutes the disposition and end of every mind in proportion to the degree of its knowledge and perfection,

our confidence about the present point will become equally clear and certain.

But if we reject these principles, and accept instead that all our ideas of worth and virtue, of morality and excellence, have no foundation in truth and reality, we’ll have to settle for much inferior evidence on very important points.—If •our approval of goodness comes from intellectual perception, it demonstratively [= ‘rigorously’] implies the goodness of God; but if •it comes solely from an arbitrary structure of our minds, all it shows is that....the plan of the universe, whatever it is, required that what is here and now should carry the appearance of benevolence....

Indeed, on the principles I have defended in this treatise it is very easy to establish the moral perfections of the Deity.—As I showed in chapter 3, the true explanation for why we want and prefer our own private happiness is •the nature of happiness. This leads to the inevitable conclusion that •this is also the true explanation for why we want and prefer public happiness. And if that is right then we immediately see that God must be benevolent.—In short, if

there is a rule of right •arising from the differences and relations of things and •extending as far as all the possible effects of power, a rule which (to the degree that it is known) compels the respect and affection of all reasonable beings, and which ·in· its own nature constitutes the proper, supreme, and eternal guide and measure of all the decisions those beings make,

it follows rigorously that the first Intellect—i.e. God—must be under the direction of this rule more than any other being is. How much more? As much more as his understanding is higher than theirs and his knowledge more perfect. He is in fact the living independent spring of this rule. He can’t contradict •it without contradicting •himself. It is a part of the idea of reason, so it must be absolutely sovereign in the self-existent infinite reason, ·i.e. in God·.

So there’s no difficulty about discovering the principlec of action in the Deity. It is obvious that the seat of •infinite power must be the seat of •infinite knowledge, and this makes it equally evident that it must be also the seat of •absolute rectitude; and these qualities—thus implying one another and being essentially ·not three but· one—constitute the idea of Deity, and exhibit the Deity to us in the most awe-inspiring and glorious light. Among the various possible schemes of creation and ways of ordering the series of events there is a best one, and this is the rule and goal of God’s conduct, and it isn’t possible that he should deviate from it, given that he sees it to be his rule and that he doesn’t have any difficulty about ·abiding by it or about· doing anything....

[Price goes on about that at some length: God isn’t subject to any of the factors that might lead someone to act wrongly—ignorance, error, passion, and so on. Before all that, he has remarked on our good fortune in living in a universe governed by a wise, good Deity—‘as certainly as God exists, all is well’.]

Before we leave this topic I should say—so as to prevent a misunderstanding—that whenever I say that what explains God’s rectitude is neceessity, or speak of goodness as essential to him, I am talking about the principlec of rectitude, not

115

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

the exercise of it. It would be absurd to suppose that God •acts by the same kind of necessity by which he •exists, or that •his uses of his power are necessary in the same sense ·of ‘necessary’· as •his power is.... All voluntary action is free—that’s part of what ‘voluntary’ means—and this implies the physical possibility of not performing the action [see note on ‘physical’ on page 88]. What this ‘possibility’ means is not in the least inconsistent with its being utterly certain that the action will be performed, or with the impossibility—in another sense of ‘impossibility’—that the action should be omitted. Consider these two:

(i) God will never do wrong.

(ii) The wisest created being won’t do something that is destructive to him without being even slightly tempted to do it.

Of course we can depend on the truth of (ii); well, can depend infinitely more on the truth of (i). And now consider these:

(i) He who is the abstract of all perfection will deviate into imperfection in his conduct.

(ii) Infinite reason will act unreasonably.

(iii) Eternal righteousness will act unrighteously. benum(iv) Infinite knowledge will make a mistake.

(v) Infinite power will be conquered.

(vi) Something that exists necessarily will cease to exist.

These are equally impossible; but what rules out (i)–(iii) is a different kind of impossibility from the one that (iv)-(vi) have.—It may be really impossible for someone in his right mind and to drink poison when he no motive to do so, and really impossible that he won’t die if he does drink the poison; but can’t everyone see that these ‘impossibilities’ are totally different in meaning? What good reason can there be against calling the one a ‘moral impossibility’ and the other a ‘natural impossibility’?

Many people are unwilling to acknowledge this distinction, but I think it is of great importance. Perhaps the following illustration will help.

[In what follows, the original doesn’t mention particular numbers; they are added for clarity, and don’t affect the points that are being made.] Suppose that we have a die with a million faces, and that I, who have no special skill, and want on my first throw to bring up the number 397,515; we’ll say that it is certain that I’ll fail; we often use ‘certain’ for things that are less sure than that! How about my throwing 397,515 on each of my first one million throws? Most people would say that that’s impossible. This impossibility, however, is plainly very different from absolute physical impossibility; for if it is ·physically· possible to succeed on the first throw (as it undoubtedly is), then it’s just as possible (·physically·) to succeed on the second, the third, and all the subsequent throws; and therefore it is, in this sense of ‘possible’, as possible to throw that number a million times in a row as to throw it the first time.—[Price now expands the example: a million dice, each having a million faces, are each thrown a million times and each throw with each of them comes up 745,001. This will strike people as even more ‘impossible’, but it is perfectly naturally or physically possible that this should happen. He continues:] If you still don’t see the distinction, compare that last outcome with this: throwing a six with a die that has no numbers stamped on it!

To push on further with this example: Remember that the improbability of throwing any particular face of a die is always proportional to how many faces the die has; so when the number of faces is infinite the improbability of the outcome—·say, the improbability of throwing the number that is equal to 498,053,999,145,011^9855, or throwing the number 7·—is infinite; and we describe something that is infinitely improbable as being ‘impossible’, in a sense of

116

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

that word like the sense that is involved when we say ‘It is impossible that a wise man should, knowingly and without temptation, do something that will destroy him’. But some number has to come up, and each number has the same chance of being thrown as any other; so it is possible that this number may be thrown, in the sense in which ·it is possible that a wise man will etc., etc., meaning that· he has it in his power to etc., etc. [At this point Price switches from •the improbability that x will happen to the •certainty that x won’t happen. We’ll follow him in this; but it’s just a stylistic variation and doesn’t affect the argument.] The certainty C2 that a particular face of an infinite die won’t be thrown twice in a row is infinitely greater than the certainty C1 that it won’t be thrown the first time; and the certainty Cx that in an infinity of throws of this die that number won’t come up every time is greater than C1 in the same proportion that infinity raised to the infiniteth power is greater than infinity. But we mustn’t lose sight of the fact that the impossibility of that outcome is still not a physical impossibility. But there is more excuse for confusing these two kinds of impossibility (or necessity) •in this context than there would be for confusing them •when comparing the outcomes of free choices with the outcomes of the operation of blind and unthinking causes. The former kind of ‘impossibility’ is a matter of degree, while the latter kind is not. The necessity by which twice two is not twenty, or a mass of matter doesn’t stay still when pushed by another, is always the same, and can’t be even slightly increased or lessened.

·Connecting the die-throwing illlustration with what I was saying about the different kinds of necessity, or senses of ‘necessary’, that are involved in ‘Necessarily God always acts well’ and ‘Necessarily God exists and is perfectly good’·: The necessity of the eternal conformity of all God’s actions to the rules of wisdom and righteousness is comparable with the certainty that an infinite number of dice, each with an infinite number of faces and thrown all together an infinite number of times, would not always bring up the number equal to 659,555,816,451,11079443. The latter outcome, though it’s infallibly true that it won’t happen, nevertheless ‘could’ happen, in a sense not very unlike that in which God ‘could’ deviate from rectitude, e.g. creating a miserable world, or destroying the world after promising not to—namely, the sense in which it means that God has the power to do such things.^27

That is enough of that subject. Let us now take the account I have given in this treatise of the nature and subject-matter of morality, and apply it to another question of considerable importance regarding the Deity. I mean the question ‘Are all God’s moral attributes reducible to benevolence? Does his benevolence include the whole of his character?’ [Price’s discussion of this seems to equate benevolence with goodness. There are hints of that elsewhere in the work, and also hints that point the other way.]

I have shown that the answer No is correct for inferior beings, and in general that virtue is by no means reducible to benevolence. If I have been right about that, our present question is immediately answered. Absolute and eternal rectitude (i.e. a concern for what is in all cases most fit and righteous) is properly the ultimate principlec of God’s conduct, and the sole guide of his power. The first and chief component in this is goodness; but goodness and rectitude, however much they may •coincide, are far from

^27 If you don’t like the word ‘infinite’ as used here, replace it by ‘indefinite’, which serves my purpose just as well. The die-throwing analogy that I have presented here gives me a way of making my points with great exactness; so I hope you’ll forgive me if it strikes you as containing anything unsuitable to the dignity of the subject to which it is applied.

117

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

being •identical.... So, faced with the question

‘If there were ever some kind of conflict between rectitude and goodness in a particular case, which of the two would stand first in God’s mind and which would give way?’,

one would think that there couldn’t be any controversy about the answer. Would anyone say that it is not because it is right that God promotes the happiness of his creatures? Or that he would promote such happiness in cases where—or in a manner in which—it would be wrong to promote it?....

[Price develops this line of thought through four bookpages [= two in the format of this version] whose main content—as he admits—has already been provided in earlier chapters. A few notable episodes from this material are given in the present paragraph.] Happiness is an object of essential and eternal value. It was because it was right to confer happiness that God created the universe in the first place. It was for this that the world was produced, and for this it is continued and governed.... But while we find it necessary to conclude that goodness is the principlec from which God created, we ought....never to forget that this principlec is founded in reason and guided by reason.... It would be a very dangerous error to consider goodness in God as not being exercised under the direction of justice. Divine benevolence is a disposition to bring happiness to the faithful, the pious, the upright—not to make everyone indiscriminately happy in every possible way.... There is nothing unreasonable in believing that falsehood and deceit could often be as likely to produce happiness as truth and faithfulness are. Supposing that such a case occurred in the world, it is surely beyond doubt that God would prefer the latter—·the route to happiness through truth and faithfulness·. If this is denied, if it is indeed true that there’s nothing right in one or wrong in the other apart from their consequences, what can we depend on? How are we to know that God hasn’t actually chosen the methods of falsehood and general deception? We are in a very bewildered state if we have •to wait for a satisfactory solution of such doubts, •to wait until we discover that the circumstances of our state and of the world are such that it can never be equally advantageous to us to deceive us—especially given our experience of countless cases where a given end can be achieved, often most quickly and efficiently, by deviating from truth!—Although we are to conceive of God as just and true as well as good, it’s clear that •justice and •truth could never lead him to create. •They presuppose that there already exist beings who have reason and moral capacities; •they are a certain manner of acting towards such beings.... I think you’ll see that I am not guilty of an inconsistency when I say •that the moral attributes of God are not all resolvable into benevolence and also •that happiness is the goal—and probably the only goal—for which he created and governs the world.—Happiness is the goal of his government, but (I repeat) it is happiness in subordination to rectitude; it is the happiness of the virtuous and worthy rather than of others; it is happiness obtained consistently with justice and veracity....

One last point: Although it is proper, and often unavoidable, to speak of goodness, justice, and veracity as different attributes of the Deity, they are different only as •different views, effects, or manifestations of •one supreme principle, which includes the whole of moral perfection, namely everlasting rectitude or reason. That complete what I have to say about the character of the Deity.

I shall now proceed in the same manner to examine the other principles and facts of natural religion, and to point out the special evidence for them that comes from my account of the nature and foundation of morals.

118

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

[The three book-pages on the topic of God’s ‘moral government’ consist mainly of variants on the argument that the absolute rectitude of God’s character, and his perfect knowledge of moral truth, make it stand to reason that rectitude will be at the heart of his government of the world. For example: ‘It is self-evident that virtue ought to be happier than vice, and we can be very confident that if something ought to be, the universal governing mind will ensure that it will be.’ Given the difference between virtue and vice, we can be sure of God’s attitude to virtuous people and vicious ones, namely ‘that God is for the one and against the other, i.e. that the administration of the world is strictly moral and righteous’. On this note, Price modulates into his next topic:]

If it should appear that in the present world virtue and vice are not distinguished in the manner that these observations require, the unavoidable consequence must be that there is a future state. Let us look carefully into the question of how this matter stands, and what the force is of this inference. [In this context, Price talks about our life on earth as mortals using the expressions ‘(at) present’, ‘this present state’, ‘now’, ‘this life’, ‘this scene’, ‘here’, ‘here below’ and ‘temporal’ (Price sometimes says ‘temporary’, in a now obsolete sense of that word). The underlying thought was that God doesn’t exist in time, and that in our life after death we won’t be in time either; so it’s a special feature of our ‘present’ life that it is temporal.]

On the one hand, it must be granted that in general virtue is the present good of men, and vice the present ill of men, and that we see enough in our present state, without needing any abstract arguments, to •convince us that God favours the virtuous, and to •point out to us the beginnings of a moral government.—But it is equally evident that we now perceive only the beginnings of such a government, and that it is nowhere near as thorough as we have reason to expect.

Virtue tends to produce much greater happiness than it now actually produces, and vice to produce much greater misery. These contrary tendencies don’t and couldn’t ever produce their full effects during the short period of this life, and they are often prevented from taking the effect that they could and generally do take, by many obstacles arising from the wickedness of mankind and other causes of a plainly temporal kind that can’t be regarded as natural or necessary. We can reasonably presume that tendencies thus interrupted and opposed, though they are inseparable from virtue and vice and essential to the constitution of things, will at some time or other lead to their genuine effects. They clearly tell us of the purpose of him who made the world what it is. Can we think that this purpose will be defeated?

Though virtue always tends to happiness, and though it is the nature of it to advance our happiness and to better our condition, in proportion to the degree in which we possess it, yet such is the state of things here below that the event sometimes proves otherwise. It is impossible to survey the world, or to recollect the history of it, without being convinced of this. There is not the least probability that all men are constantly and invariably more or less happy, as they are more or less conscientious and upright. So often virtue has been oppressed and persecuted while vice has prospered and flourished. Good men may (1) get themselves into •tangles because they are so rigid about moral correctness, or into •lowness of spirits and melancholy, and in consequence of this may be rendered ignorant of their own characters, and live in perpetual distrust and terror; or they may (2) have false notions of religion and the Deity, which give them great trouble and rid them of many of the joys that would otherwise have come with their integrity. And then there are men who, perhaps through faults of their parents or of their upbringing, (3) have diseased bodies, and spend

119

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

their lives burdened by pain and sickness, and ones who (4) are harrassed and defamed because of their virtue, driven away from all that is dear to them and compelled to spend their days in poverty or in an inquisition [Price’s phrase, perhaps meaning ‘spend their days being investigated’]. These ·four kinds of· people are less happy than many others have been spared such hardships without being more vituous. Indeed, they are less happy than many vicious people who

•swim with the current of the world and comply with its customs,

•deny themselves nothing that they ·want and· can get without hurting their reputations,

•are born into wealth and privilege,

•enjoy health and vigour of body, and naturally easy and gay temperaments,

•never give a thought to what may happen to them hereafter, or have opinions that fill them with false hopes about this, and at last

•die without concern or remorse.

[From here on Price will refer often to the life we shall have after our biological death, using such expressions as ‘future’, ‘hereafter’ or ‘beyond this world’.] Of course there have been instances of this kind! It certainly happens sometimes that the very honesty of people subjects them to special difficulties and drawbacks, while lying and dishonesty help them on their way to ease, and honour, and plenty!

Indeed, all things considered, this world seems to be more like a school for developing virtue than a position of honour for it; the course of human affairs is favourable to virtue more by •exercising it than by •rewarding it! Other things being equal, virtue always has a great advantage over vice, and is alone sufficient to outweigh many large drawbacks; but it would be very extravagant to claim •that it is at present always completely its own happiness, •that it is sufficient on its own to outweigh all possible evils of body, mind, and financial condition, or •that (for example)

a man who has become wealthy by vicious but private methods, and afterwards enjoys his wealth for many years with discretion and a good reputation

has less pleasure than

a man whose benevolence or integrity has brought him to a dungeon or to the stake, or who lives in perplexity, labour, self-denial, torture of body, and melancholy of mind.

It is indeed true that virtue even in the most distressed circumstances is preferable to vice in the most prosperous circumstances, and that being burned to death ought to be chosen rather than the greatest wages of iniquity.^28 This doesn’t mean that in distressed circumstances virtue is more profitable than vice (i.e. accompanied by more pleasure), but that it •is intrinsically excellent and obligatory, •is to be chosen for itself independently of its utility, and •remains more desirable and amiable than anything else we could aim at, even when it is stripped of every reward and is in the greatest degree afflicted and oppressed.

[Price now embarks on two book-pages developing the theme that a person who is fairly virtuous but has some elements of vice in his make-up, or a vicious person who is starting to reform himself, is likely to suffer more than someone who is thoroughly virtuous and more than someone who is ‘thoroughly wicked’. This is woven in with some other points about ways in which ‘in the present world’ virtue

^28 Anyone who thinks this assertion to be in any degree inconsistent or extravagant must be someone who holds that virtue is good and eligible and obligatory only as a means to private pleasure, and that nothing but pleasure can be an object of desire and preference. With that view as a basis, the very notion of parting with life (or giving up an enjoyment) for the sake of virtue implies a contradiction....

120

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

sometimes leads one into suffering that could otherwise have been avoided. Then:]

[The ensuing questions are really disguised assertions, but in this case the interrogative device works well enough for us, and is therefore allowed to stand. See example and note on page 2.] Don’t such observations point out to us a future state, and prove that this life is connected with another—·a life after our animal death·? Rather than accepting this conclusion, shall we retreat to atheism and deny that a perfectly reasonable being governs all things? Or must we maintain that his being righteous himself doesn’t imply that he approves of righteousness and will support it, distinguishing those who do his will and imitate his goodness from those who do not? If •nothing is to be expected beyond this world, •no suitable provision is made for many differences in how men are constituted, •no remarkable evidence is seen of the divine holiness, and •the noblest and best of all objects (that on which the welfare of the creation depends, and which raises beings to the nearest resemblance to God) seems to be left without any adequate support—is this possible under the Divine government? Can it be conceived that the wisdom and fairness of providence should fail in just this one respect, i.e. in respect of virtue?.... But if we accept that this scene is related to a future more important one, all is clear, every difficulty is removed, and every irregularity vanishes. We are now presented with a plain explanation of all the strange phenomena in human life. It’s not important how much virtue suffers and vice triumphs •here, if •hereafter there will be a just distinction between them and all the inequalities will be set right. Indeed, it may sometimes be right that a vicious man is permitted to enjoy the world, and also that a good man is made to struggle with difficulties....

A moral plan of government must be implemented gradually and slowly, through a series of steps and stages. Before retribution there must be probation and discipline. Before anyone receives reward (or punishment), he must be given sufficient opportunities to deserve reward (or punishment)—to form and display his character—and during that time there have to be many occasions when the person’s choice of virtue or vice will make no difference to the immediate outcome. If every single action were immediately followed by its proper reward or punishment,.... •the characters of men couldn’t be formed, •virtue would be become ·self·-interested and mercenary, •some of the most important branches of virtue couldn’t be practised at all, •adversity (which is often its best friend) would never have access to it, and •there wouldn’t be any of the trials that are needed to train virtue up to maturity and perfection. This would disturb the regular [here = ‘orderly and morally correct’; see note on page 105] process of a moral government, and defeat its purposes. And so the very facts that are regarded ·by some· as objections to ·the thesis that there is such a moral government· turn out to be required for such government, given how mankind are now constituted.....

If we accidentally discovered a a piece of workmanship—a product of skill—that was entirely new to us, no-one would doubt that it was made to be used in a particular way, if its design and structure were plainly appropriate for such a use, and the supposition of this use of it •explained everything in it that would otherwise be disproportioned and inexplicable, and •made it appear regular and beautiful throughout. Think how perverse it would be to •deny obstinately that it was intended for such a use, and in consequence of this to •ignore the undeniable marks of the most masterly hand in various parts of it, and •maintain it to be the work of some bungling craftsman who lacked either the knowledge or the power needed to make it more perfect!

121

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

Another example: We find a particular passage in a book that at first seems strange to us, but then we see an obvious and natural sense of it that fits with the phrasing of the passage itself and also makes it fit in with •the wisdom apparent in other parts of the book, and with •what previously we had the best reason to believe concerning the character and abilities of the author. Given all of this, how unreasonable it would be to insist that the passage is nonsense or blasphemy!

I thought I needed to make these points as an aid to those who don’t want to allow anything irregular in the present distribution of happiness and misery, because they are afraid that such an admission would imply that we don’t have sufficient evidence for a perfect order in nature, and for the wisdom and fairness of providence.^29

It would indeed hardly be possible to avoid atheism if the assertions of some writers on this subject were true. We say:

From the view that we have of the constitution and order of the divine government, why can’t we infer what will take place hereafter under that government? In many other cases we infer what is unknown from what is known, e.g. inferring the whole meaning of what someone said from hearing only a part of it.

There are those who would reply to us as follows:

In that last case our inference is based on a previous acquaintance with the speaker, with language, and with the general manner in which men use it to express their sentiments. If we didn’t have such acquaintance, even if we understood the meanings of the particular words we heard we couldn’t infer anything from them beyond the ideas that they immediately conveyed, or see the least reason to suspect any further intention in the speaker. Similarly, because we have no previous acquaintance with the divine nature and government, we can’t know anything about them beyond what is directly signified to us by the state of things around us; we can have no reason to think that the created world has any order greater than what we at the present moment observe, or to conclude that the First Cause has any powers and qualities in a higher degree than they are actually exhibited to us in the world as we experience it. It may be further argued that because this visible universe is an object wholly singular to us—·not one instance of a kind of which we have experienced other instances·—we can’t draw any conclusions from it, or determine anything about the nature, designs, and properties of its cause, or even know that it has a cause. Trying to reach such conclusions from the basis that we have is like trying to work out what the speaker means when we haven’t had the experiences needed to let us have any idea

^29 By ‘anything irregular’ I mean anything that would be irregular if this life were not related to another life ·after death·. Something that is perfectly right and just when considered in its relations to the whole to which it belongs can look quite unjust when it is considered by itself, detached from the rest. How strange it is that anyone should overlook this obvious truth!
Bear in mind that the points I have been making here don’t show anything about the nature of the future state, except that that in it the rewards and punishments begun in this life will be made adequate. But it’s perfectly obvious that this could happen and yet all mankind eventually perish, ·so that in these arguments there is no promise of eternal life·. Reason, therefore, leaves us much in the dark on this subject. All we are sure of is that the after-life will on the whole be better or worse for each person in proportion as he has been morally better or worse in his conduct and character. [The footnote continues at considerable length, making two points. •Any virtuous person must have a good enough sense of his own unworthiness to feel that he doesn’t deserve any notable reward in the after-life. •The Christian revelation offers the prospect of ‘a new life of complete happiness that will never end’.]

122

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price 10: Natural religion

of what any words mean, so that for us the speaker’s words are just noises. [Price refers to one of Hume’s essays as a source for some of this line of thought, but his posthumously published Dialogues concerning Natural Religion are better.]

....This line of thought can have no effect on anyone who is sure, ·as I am·, that these difficulties are based on a wrong account of how our minds operate. However much the human understanding is •preceded by sense-experience, and •supplied by it with its first opportunities to exert itself, it is a faculty infinitely superior to all the powers of sense, and a most important source of our ideas. Our understanding enables us, independently of experience, to demonstrate countless truths concerning many items of which we otherwise could never have known anything.—It is the special advantage of the principles I have maintained that they provide us with direct and demonstrative proofs of the truths of natural religion, and particularly of God’s righteousness and goodness, at the same time that they aid and support all reasonings from experience. [Because ‘demonstrative’ means ‘logically rigorous’, Price is here making a very strong claim. In this work he seldom claims to (be able to) ‘demonstrate’ significant philosophical results. The clearest cases where he does are both about demonstrating what the moral structure of the after-life will be. The other is back on page 44 (‘prove with the evidentness of a demonstration what supreme reason will do’).]

[Price closes the chapter with an emotionally colourful account, supposedly drawn from his conclusions in this book, of the wonderfulness of virtue and the dreafulness of vice. He writes of virtue as something we can carry with us into the after-life and that will ‘make God our friend’, but he doesn’t openly say anything about divine rewards for virtue. He concludes the virtue part of this by saying: ‘Secure this, and you secure everything. Lose this, and all is lost.’ In the vice part, Price depicts the havoc caused in the world by vice, and also hammers away at ‘what it is to set up our own wills against Reason and the Divine will’. One gets the impression that in this context the divine will is uppermost in his mind. This is how the chapter ends:] The effects of vice in the present world, however shocking, may be nothing compared with those that may take place hereafter, when •the evil and the good will no longer be blended, when •the natural tendencies of things will no longer be interrupted in their operation, when •the moral constitution of the universe will be perfected, and when •everyone will get what he deserves. It may be impossible for us to imagine what the punishment will be that will then overtake vice. When we seriously consider what vice is and what it can do, our ideas about the dreadful loss we may suffer through it can hardly be exaggerated, and we can’t be too concerned to remove all the remains of it from our temperaments and to put as much distance as possible between ourselves and the danger with which it threatens us.

123

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price Conclusion

Conclusion

Having completed my design in this work, I will close by offering an argument for the practice of virtue. I think it deserves to be considered by everyone, and especially by people who are disposed to scepticism and infidelity.

In chapter 10 I have presented some proofs of the principal facts of natural religion, especially of •a perfect moral government in nature and •a future state of rewards and punishments. There is a great deal of other evidence that wasn’t on the path I was following. Above all, the Christian revelation confirms for us everything we can learn through reason on these subjects, and promises to the virtuous eternal life—a happy immortality.

But I am now going to suppose that the whole of this evidence is so insufficient that it creates only a chance, overbalanced by contrary chances, for such a reward for virtue; and I shall argue on that basis that our obligations will still be the same, and that not practising virtue—indeed not sacrificing to it all present advantages and gratifications—is utterly foolish.—·To get started on the argument·, consider what any given chance for such a good must be worth.

An even chance for any given stake is worth one half of that stake; if the chance is only a third (or a tenth) of all the chances, its value will be a third (or a tenth) of the whole stake, and so on. So if the good that is at stake is the future reward of virtue, and its value is reckoned to be •equal to the value of all present good, •not more than that, then it will be right to sacrifice for it a half (a third, a tenth) of all present good, according as the chances for obtaining it are a half (a third, a tenth) of all the chances for and against obtaining it.

If the value of the future reward of virtue is supposed greater than the value of all present good, it will be right to give up for it a proportionally greater part of present good; and the future good might be so great as to make any chance for it worth more than all that can be enjoyed in this life.—The same is true of the value of any means of avoiding a future evil. Though we suppose the evil to be enormously improbable, its nature and duration and intensity may be so great that something that saves us from the tiny danger of it may be worth more than anything we can sacrifice in order to get it.

In other words: Any given chance for a given good is worth something. The same chance for a greater good is worth more, and consequently when the good is infinite the value of any chance for it must be likewise infinite. Given that the future good that is promised to virtue is infinite, and the loss of it with which vice threatens us is therefore an infinite evil, it follows that any suspicion that religion may be true, or the bare possibility that virtue and vice will have the consequences that Christianity has taught us to expect, has the same implications for practice as if we were sure of its truth.

Even if we think that (through some strange confusion in the affairs of the world, or an extravagant mercy in God) vice also gives us a chance of happiness hereafter, if we accept that virtue is to any degree more likely to lead to happiness than vice is, it will still be mad not to adhere to virtue and avoid vice, at all costs. What is the value of a small increase in the chance of obtaining a good? Obviously, its value depends on the value of the good; and if the good is infinite then any increase in the chance of getting it has an infinite value.

124

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price Conclusion

I don’t think anyone can escape this conclusion unless he asserts that it is certain that

Christianity is false and there is no future state, or if there is such a state virtue gives no better chance for happiness in it than vice does.

It would be inconsistent for a sceptic to assert this, and surely no man in his right mind will assert it. However, let us consider the situation of someone who does assert it. It would still be prudent of him to be sufficiently unsure of his atheism to take the precaution of living in such a way that he has nothing to fear if the worst were to happen and his confidence were to turn out to be wrong. [That is, if Christianity were to turn out to be true, this being ‘the worst’ from the point of view of the atheist.] But someone whose disbelief in Christianity falls short of this extreme certainty is guilty ·not of mere •imprudence but· of •unspeakable folly if he is loose and careless in his life, or ever consents to any wrong action or omission in the interests of getting some benefit in this world.

Indeed, anyone who fairly examines the evidence for religion must see that it deserves great regard.—Someone who thinks about how reasonable it is to presume that

•infinite goodness will communicate infinite happiness, that

•the creator of everything designs his creatures for such a happiness by allowing those who are qualified for this to live for ever, improving under his eye and care, and that

•virtuous men, if there are any, have most reason to expect to be favoured in this way;

someone who reflects on

•the many ways in which our minds have been shaped in favour of virtue,

•the accountableness of our natures,

•our unavoidable fears and hopes regarding the afterlife,

•the malignant and detestable nature of vice,

•the views of mankind in general concerning a future state and reckoning [here = ‘rewards and punishments’], and

•the spotless holiness of the Deity, which the sacred writings assert and display, and some conviction of which naturally forces itself on everyone,

—that person really can’t avoid having uneasy suspicions about what may happen in the after-life, and be led to consider with deep concern

•how awful the future displays of divine justice may turn out to be,

•how greatly we may be involved in the incomprehensible scheme of providence,

•how much may depend on what we now are, and

•how necessary it is for us to do everything we possibly can to keep ourselves safe.

—We have a great deal of reason to believe that at some time or other present inequalities will be set right, and a greater difference than we now see between what comes to the virtuous and what comes to the vicious. As for what kind or degree of difference the counsels and ends of the divine government may require—who can be sure about that? We see enough in the present state of things, and sufficiently experience what can happen given how this world is run, to alarm our fears and start us giving serious thought to what greater differences between human beings than we now observe are likely in a future state, and what greater happiness or misery than we now feel—or can have any ideas of—may await us in the future endless duration through which it is at least credible that we are going to exist.

125

Principal Questions in Morals Richard Price Conclusion

And however little respect some people may have for such considerations, it must be past dispute among impartial people who have enquiring minds that the arguments that have been used to prove natural and revealed religion, when taken all together, produce some degree of real evidence—and if that’s so, those arguments lay a sufficient foundation for the above reasoning.

What makes it all the more appropriate for us to attend to this reasoning is the fact that it’s a kind of reasoning that we are continually using in the common course of life, and because it explains to us the principles and reasons that we act on in almost all our temporal concerns. Sceptical people ought to be forced to think about the fact that our nature and condition are such that they make us, in the daily course of life, act on evidence much lower than what is commonly called ‘probable’, and that there are countless instances in everyday life where a man would be regarded as in a literal sense distracted if he refused to act, and with great application too, on something for which the probability was greatly against his succeeding [‘... in a literal sense distracted’—colloquially ‘he is out of his mind’, literally ‘he has lost his way’].

Men will often take great precautions against dangers that are remote and imaginary, but they neglect an easy and reasonable precaution against the worst and greatest of all dangers! They become eager and restless adventurers, taking great trouble and running great risks where there’s any prospect of getting money, power, or fame—these being objects with little intrinsic value, objects that it would be our greatest dignity and happiness to despise! Yet they are unwilling to take any trouble or run any risks in order to obtain blessings of incalculable value and to secure a chance for eternal bliss.... By living as virtue and piety require, we can in general lose nothing and may gain infinitely; by a careless ill-spent life we can get nothing, or at best (come what may) next to nothing and may lose infinitely? When will these indisputable truths that imply so much about our interests sink deeply enough into our hearts?It would be very unfair to my argument if I didn’t make this last point. You will have noticed that the argument has been based on the supposition that •there is a very great probability against religion and future retribution, and that •virtue requires us to sacrifice to it all our present enjoyments. The reverse of both these suppositions appears in reality to be the truth. There is not only an even chance but a great probability for the truth of religion. There is nothing to be got by vice, and the best part of present good is commonly lost by it. What virtue requires us to give up is not the happiness of life but our follies, diseases, and miseries. Given that this is how things stand, how foolish is a vicious choice! How shocking is the infatuation that makes us capable of it!

126